<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2846</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">openvetj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Veterinary Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2226-4485</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2218-6050</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tripoli</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11018439</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11018439.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11018439</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11018439</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38633167</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/OVJ.2024.v14.i1.31</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OVJ-14-341</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Immunological studies on the effects of toltrazuril and neem extract in broiler chickens suffering from coccidiosis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kairy</surname><given-names initials="MH">Mohamed H.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fadel</surname><given-names initials="HAE">Hosny Abd El</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aleim</surname><given-names initials="AEAFAE">Abd El Aleim F. Abd El</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gad</surname><given-names initials="GN">Gehan N.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Youssef</surname><given-names initials="FEZA">Fatma El Zahra A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names initials="AM">Amira M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>SaadEldin</surname><given-names initials="WF">Walaa F.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Pharmacology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Zagazig University, Zagazig, Egypt</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Biochemistry, Toxicology and Nutritional Deficiencies, Animal Health Research Institute (AHRI), Agriculture Research Center (ARC), Zagazig, Egypt</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Educational Veterinary Hospital, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Zagazig University, Zagazig, Egypt</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Department of Biochemistry, Toxicology and Nutritional Deficiencies, Animal Health Research Institute (AHRI), Agriculture Research Center (ARC), Zagazig, Egypt. <email>karimsalama63@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">460065</issue-id><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>17</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-04-24 20:25:32.927"><day>24</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-341.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>The prevalence of avian coccidiosis in the poultry industry has grown, resulting in substantial financial losses from high mortality, stunted growth, reduced productivity, and expensive medical expenses.</p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>The purpose of the current study was to assess the immunological effects of neem leaf extract and toltrazuril on broilers that had contracted coccidiosis.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>In this investigation, 100 one-day-old Cobb broiler chicks without sexes were employed. The chicks were divided into five equal groups, with 20 birds in each. On the 14<sup>th</sup> day of life, the birds in groups 2, 3, 4, and 5 received an oral inoculation with 1 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup> sporulated oocysts of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria tenella</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic>) (field isolate). The first group (Gp), which consists of 20 healthy broilers, served as a negative control. Gp (2) contains experimentally infected broilers and nontreated (served as a positive control). Gp (3) contains experimentally infected broilers treated with toltrazuril (1 ml/l drinking water) for two consecutive days. Gp (4) contains experimentally infected broilers treated with neem leaf extract 4% (50 ml/l drinking water) for 5 successive days, and Gp (5) contains experimentally infected broilers treated with toltrazuril (1 ml/l drinking water) and a half dose of neem leaves extract 4% (25 ml/l drinking water) for 5 successive days. For the purpose of estimating body weight growth and feed conversion ratio, each broiler was weighed separately at the start of the trial and again on the 1st and 10th day after treatment. In addition to obtaining intestinal samples for immunohistochemistry, blood samples were also obtained for immunological examination.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>As compared to the negative control group, the experimentally infested broilers with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> showed significant decreases in serum nitric oxide, lysosome, phagocytic percent, and phagocytic index, along with significant increases in white blood cells (WBCs), lymphocyte, heterophilis, eosinophilis, basophilis, monocyte, serum total protein, &#947; globulin, fibrinogen, and haptoglobin. When compared to the control positive group, experimentally infested broilers treated with either neem or toltrazuril alone or in combination demonstrated significant increases in serum total protein, nitric oxide, lysozyme, phagocytic percent, and phagocytic index, but significant decreases in WBCs, lymphocytes, heterophile, eosinophile, basophile, and monocyte. The intestinal peroxidase stain of broilers infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> exhibited a significant positive expression for CD4, but the infected broilers treated with toltrazuril and half a dosage of neem displayed a negative expression for CD4, identical to the negative control.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>The broiler chickens infested with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> may have a variety of negative impacts on their immune systems and immunohistopathological findings. Nonetheless, toltrazuril and neem extract, either separately or in combination, function as anticoccidial medications that may enhance the broiler chicks&#8217; immune state.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Immunity</kwd><kwd>Neem extract</kwd><kwd>Broiler chicks</kwd><kwd>Coccidiosis</kwd><kwd>Toltrazuril</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Infestations of parasites pose a major risk to health and reduce productivity (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Nazmiye, 2008</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria spp.</italic>, are the culprits behind coccidiosis, which is acknowledged as a significant protozoal illness affecting birds (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Kitandu and Juranov&#225;, 2006</xref>). Due to two factors&#8212;confined host rearing circumstances and resistance to chemoprophylaxis&#8212;avian coccidiosis has grown more common in the poultry sector (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">Stephen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>). Due to high mortality, poor growth, decreased output, and high medical costs, the disease has a substantial financial impact on the chicken business (<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">Williams, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Abd El-Maksoud <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>).</p><p>The amount of coccidians that complete their life cycles should be limited by the ideal anticoccidial (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Jain, 1986</xref>). According to <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Doumas <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (1981</xref>) and <xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">Mathis <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2004</xref>), toltrazuril is a triazinone medication with broad-spectrum anticoccidial and antiprotozoal activity. By preventing the nuclear division of schizonts, macrogametes, and the wall-forming bodies of macrogaments, toltrazuril is effective against all species of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> and against all intracellular developmental phases, including schizogony and gametogony (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">Said <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>).</p><p>Herbal extracts are an alternative and safe anticoccidial medication because they do not leave tissue residue or produce drug resistance (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Ghafouri <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2023</xref>). Due to their low toxicity and low cost of manufacturing, herbal plants and their byproducts may be used as treatments for coccidiosis (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Abbas <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Nimbidin, sodium nimbolide, gedunin, azadirachtin, mahmoodin, epicatechin and catechin, margalone, margolonone and isomargolonone, cyclic trisulphides, polysaccharides GIa, GIIa, GIIIa, GIb, NB-II, and peptidoglycon are among the active components found in neem (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Biswas <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>). Immunomodulatory, anti-inflammatory, antihyperglycemic, antimalarial, antifungal, antioxidant, antimutagenic, and anticarcinogenic qualities have been shown for neem leaves and their constituents (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">Subapriya and Nagini, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Gaurav <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>).</p><p>Investigating the impact of <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic>, toltrazuril, and neem leaf extract on certain immunological and immunohistochemical alterations in broilers was the goal of the current study.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Drugs</title><p>A: 2.5% toltrazuril (Baycox)<sup>&#174;</sup> acquired from Bayer Comp. 25 mg/kg bw for two consecutive days is the suggested therapeutic dose, which is equivalent to 1 ml/1 litre of drinking water (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">Mathis <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>).</p><p>B. Aqueous neem extract: Leaves were harvested from medium-aged green trees in the agricultural orchards of the Faculty of Agriculture, Zagazig University, Egypt. They were then dried for 24 hours at 37&#176;C in an oven and then pulverized using a metal grinder. Weigh out 40 g of the dried ground leaves, and then transfer them to a nonmetallic container. The method described by <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Leila (1977</xref>) was used to prepare an extract (4%) by pouring 1 l of boiling distilled water over it and letting it sit at room temperature for 5&#8211;8 hours.</p></sec><sec><title>The Eimeria strain</title><p>It was kindly acquired from the Parasitology Department, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Zagazig University, Egypt.</p></sec><sec><title>Birds</title><p>One hundred unsexed broiler chicks of a commercial breed (Cobb breed) were employed; they were 1 day old and appeared to be in good health. El-wady Poultry Company supplied them. Following a comprehensive washing and disinfection process, the chicks were kept in a consistently clean and hygienic environment and fed on a specially prepared diet devoid of chemical additives, antibiotics, and anti-coccidial medications. Throughout the 5 weeks of the trial, tap water was available at all times. The chicks were raised on the floor in individual units, with bedding made up of two inches of freshly shredded wood litter. After being adjusted to 32&#176;C for the first week, the temperature was lowered by 2&#176;C each week after that. For the duration of the experiment, ideal light conditions were met every day. The use of routine preventive medication and immunization campaigns against viral and bacterial infections was made.</p><p>The chicks were divided into five primary groups. Group 1 consisted of 20 healthy broilers (-ve Control). On the 14th day of life, the birds in groups 2&#8211;5 received an oral inoculation with 1 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup> sporulated oocysts of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria tenella</italic> (field isolate). Experimentally infested broilers in Gp (2) are not treated (+ve control), while experimentally infested broilers in Gp (3) are treated with toltrazuril (1 ml/l drinking water) for 2 days in a row. In Gp (4), experimentally infested broilers are given a 4% neem leaf extract (50 ml per l of drinking water) for 5 days (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Durrani <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). In Gp (5), experimentally infested broilers are given a half-dose of 4% neem leaf extract (25 ml/l drinking water) and toltrazuril (1 ml/l drinking water) for five consecutive days.</p></sec><sec><title>Growth performance</title><p>To estimate body weight increase and feed conversion ratio (FCR), each broiler was weighed separately at the start of the research and on the first and 10th day after treatment.</p></sec><sec><title>Blood samples</title><p>Three blood samples were collected from each chick on the first day following therapy.</p><p>To estimate leukograms, the initial sample was taken on a tube containing EDTA as an anticoagulant (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Feldman <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). For the purpose of estimating serum total protein (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Doumas <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1981</xref>), serum protein fractionation using cellulose acetate electrophoresis (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Henry <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1974</xref>), lysozyme (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">Schltz, 1987</xref>), nitric oxide (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Rajarman <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>), the second blood sample was collected in a clean centrifuge tube without anticoagulant and centrifuged at 3,000 rpm for 15 minutes.</p><p>In accordance with (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Lucy and Larry, 1982</xref>), the third sample was collected on a tube containing heparin as an anticoagulant for the measurement of phagocytic activity (phagocytic % and phagocytic index).</p><p>The determination of inflammatory markers including hepatoglobulin (PIT54) and fibrogen (FGB) was done according to Tomas Marques (2017).</p></sec><sec><title>Tissue specimens</title><p>On the first day following treatment, broilers were sacrificed and intestinal tissues were collected for immunohistochemical examination (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Kim <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The automated SPSS program version 16 was used to evaluate the data that was obtained.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>The authors affirm that this work adheres to the highest ethical standards. The authors have ensured the originality of the content, obtained necessary permissions for data and materials used, and followed ethical guidelines for research and publication.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Results</title><p>When compared to the -ve control, broilers that were experimentally infested with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> exhibited a substantial decrease in weight gain, FC, and FCR on the 1st and 10th day post infection. However, when compared to +ve control, experimentally infested broilers treated with toltrazuril or neem leaf extract, either alone or in a combination, significantly enhanced weight gain and FCR (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Effect of toltrazuril and neem leaves extract 4% on body performances of infected broilers with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic>.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial BWt</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">First day</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Tenth day</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(g)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">BW(g)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">BWG(g)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">FC</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">FCR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">BW(g)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">BWG(g)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">FC</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">FCR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">774.50 &#177; 3.65<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,310.32 &#177; 3.56<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">557.20 &#177; 1.65<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">670</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 &#177; 0.09<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,980.00 &#177; 1.67<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">660.12 &#177; 2.69<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,150</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.72 &#177; 0.19<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">760.50 &#177; 2.76<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">957.30 &#177; 3.69<sup>bc</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200.10 &#177; 1.34<sup>d</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">620</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10 &#177; 0.15<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,364.0 &#177; 3.31<sup>e</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">454.0 &#177; 2.98<sup>e</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">950</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25 &#177; 6.16<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">751.50 &#177; 4.68<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,132.30 &#177; 2.95<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">370.40 &#177; 1.56<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">675</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85 &#177; 0.26<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,924.0 &#177; 2.68<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">831.10 &#177; 4.55<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,050</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26 &#177; 0.11<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">773.17 &#177; 4.59<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,115.73 &#177; 2.89<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">342.56 &#177; 3.36<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">651</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90 &#177; 0.83<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,838.97 &#177; 2.84<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">723.20 &#177; 2.89<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41 &#177; 0.32b</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">765.29 &#177; 5.89<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,125.14 &#177; 4.75<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">359.85 &#177; 3.73<sup>bc</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">663</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.84 &#177; 0.59<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,890.32 &#177; 3.86<sup>d</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">765.18 &#177; 3.87<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32 &#177; 0.14<sup>b</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Means that carry different superscripts in the same column are significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). </p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>When broilers were experimentally infested with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic>, their white blood cell (WBC), lymphocytes, heterophiles, eosinophils, basophils, and monocytes were compared with the (-ve control) significantly increased (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). However, when broilers were experimentally infested and treated with either toltrazuril or neem leaf extract alone or in combination, their WBCs, lymphocytes, heterophiles, eosinophiles, basophiles, and monocytes were significantly decreased when compared with the +ve control.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Effect of toltrazuril and neem extract 4% on total and differential leukocytic count in infected broilers with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella.</italic></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters (p)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBCs &#215;10<sup>3</sup> cmm</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterophil %</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymphocyte %</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Esinoophil %</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basophile %</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monocyte %</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.69 &#177; 0.68<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.12 &#177; 0.56<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00 &#177; 0.56<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 &#177; 0.21<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21 &#177; 0.07<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.36 &#177; 0.23<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.73 &#177; 0.89<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.35 &#177; 0.38<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.50 &#177; 0.98<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25 &#177; 0.08<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16 &#177; 0.04<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.77 &#177; 0.34<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.95 &#177; 0.64<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.27 &#177; 0.38<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.05 &#177; 0.98<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 &#177; 0.09<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26 &#177; 0.07<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05 &#177; 0.68<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.20 &#177; 0.66<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50 &#177; 0.38<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.30 &#177; 0.98<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27 &#177; 0.07<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 &#177; 0.04<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.56 &#177; 0.52<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.97 &#177; 0.96<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.54 &#177; 0.38<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.37 &#177; 0.98<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24 &#177; 0.08<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 &#177; 0.07<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25 &#177; 0.54<sup>b</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Means that carry different superscripts in the same column are significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). </p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>When compared to the -ve control, broilers that were experimentally infested had significant decreases in serum total protein and &#947; globulin, but only marginal decreases in albumin, &#945;, &#946;, total globulin, and A/G ratio. In addition to a negligible rise in albumin, &#945;, &#946;, &#947;, total globulin, and A/G ratio as compared to +ve control broilers, experimentally infected broilers treated with toltrazuril or neem alone or in combination showed significant increases in serum total protein (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><p>When compared to healthy broilers (-ve control), experimentally infested broilers with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> showed significant decreases in serum nitric oxide, lysozyme, phagocytic percent, and phagocytic index. However, when compared to +ve control broilers, broilers treated with toltrazuril or neem extract individually showed significant increases in nitric oxide, lysozyme, phagocytic percent, and phagocytic index (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Effect of toltrazuril and neem extract 4% on protein profile in infested broilers with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella.</italic></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">T. protein gm/dl</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Albumin gm/dl</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Globulin gm/dl</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">A/G Ratio</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#913;</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#914;</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#915;</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total globulin</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.40 &#177; 0.68<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90 &#177; 0.20<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 &#177; 0.18<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 &#177; 0.30<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60 &#177; 0.25<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50 &#177; 0.60<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 &#177; 0.09<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.94 &#177; 0.89<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57 &#177; 0.22<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 &#177; 0.28<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 &#177; 0.27<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 &#177; 0.19<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.02 &#177; 0.26<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 &#177; 0.08<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.29 &#177; 0.56<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59 &#177; 0.86<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 &#177; 0.09<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 &#177; 0.12<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 &#177; 0.21<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40 &#177; 0.89<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44 &#177; 0.06<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.97 &#177; 1.57<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 &#177; 0.95<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 &#177; 0.51<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 &#177; 0.28<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24 &#177; 0.32<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.55 &#177; 0.89<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 &#177; 0.06<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.35 &#177; 1.32<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82 &#177; 0.23<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 &#177; 0.53<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21 &#177; 0.23<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34 &#177; 0.48<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48 &#177; 0.57<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44 &#177; 0.09<sup>a</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Means that carry different superscripts in the same column are significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). </p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><title>Effect of toltrazuril and neem extract 4% on nitric oxide, lysosome, phagocytic %, and phagocytic index of infected broilers with<italic toggle="yes"> E. tenella.</italic></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Nitric oxide</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Lysosome</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Phagocytic %</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Phagocytic index</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">First day</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tenth days</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">First day</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tenth day</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">First day</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tenth days</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">First day</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tenth days</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.26 &#177; 2.87<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.60 &#177; 2.96<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.85 &#177; 0.98<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.22 &#177; 0.77<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.20 &#177; 2.21<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.50 &#177; 2.83<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.93 &#177; 0.76<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.13 &#177; 0.21<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.14 &#177; 1.59<sup>d</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.60 &#177; 2.54<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 &#177; 0.08<sup>d</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.41 &#177; 1.08<sup>d</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.10 &#177; 1.53<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.09 &#177; 1.55<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54 &#177; 0.43<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83 &#177; 0.18<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.87 &#177; 1.98<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.80 &#177; 1.56<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.76 &#177; 0.56<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.70 &#177; 0.97<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.11 &#177; 1.43<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.13 &#177; 1.94<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60 &#177; 0.86<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.98 &#177; 0.21<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.28 &#177; 2.59<sup>d</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.00 &#177; 2.62<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.17 &#177; 0.97<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.71 &#177; 0.89<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.09 &#177; 1.78<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.12 &#177; 1.32<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.17 &#177; 0.32<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.92 &#177; 0.28<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.74 &#177; 1.87<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.10 &#177; 1.97<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.30 &#177; 0.89<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.15 &#177; 0.69<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.43 &#177; 2.53<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.32 &#177; 1.43<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.89 &#177; 0.32<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.08 &#177; 1.43<sup>a</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Means that carry different superscripts in the same column are significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). </p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><title>Effect of toltrazuril and neem extract on the inflammatory markers (FGB and hepatoglobin) in infected broilers with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella.</italic></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Group</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Fibrinogen (g/l)</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Haptoglobin (g/l)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">First day</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tenth day</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">First day</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tenth day</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 &#177; 0.20<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 &#177; 0.36<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 &#177; 0.18<sup>d</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 &#177; 0.24<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.12 &#177; 3.21<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10 &#177; 0.09<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.55 &#177; 1.88<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.45 &#177; 1.92<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.17 &#177; 2.83<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 &#177; 0.12<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.13 &#177; 2.95<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.19 &#177; 0.73<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.26 &#177; 1.89<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 &#177; 0.40<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.54 &#177; 1.93<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 &#177; 0.03<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gp (5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.31 &#177; 1.74<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 &#177; 0.51<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.85 &#177; 0.85<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07 &#177; 0.01<sup>e</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Means that carry different superscripts in the same column are significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). </p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Experimentally infected broilers with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> exhibited a significant increase in fibrinogen and haptoglobin. However, when toltrazuril or neem extract is administered to the broilers, either separately or in combination, the levels of fibrinogen and haptoglobin significantly decrease (<xref rid="tab5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).</p><p>A healthy broiler&#8217;s intestinal peroxidase-stained section revealed -ve expression of CD4. Infested broiler intestines stained with peroxidase demonstrated high positive expression of CD4. The intestinal peroxidase-stained tissue of infested broilers treated with toltrazuril exhibited a moderate positive expression of CD4. Infested broilers treated with neem showed nearly significant +ve expression for CD4 in their peroxidase-stained gut. Peroxidase-stained intestinal tissue of infested broilers given a half-dose of neem and toltrazuril demonstrates -ve expression for CD4 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p> The data gathered demonstrated that in comparison to healthy broilers, broilers afflicted with coccidiosis showed a significant reduction in body weight increase, the elevation of feed conversion rate, and feed consumption. The findings of <xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">Walk <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2011</xref>), who reported that coccidiosis causes intestinal disruption that reduces nutrient absorption and feed utilization efficiency and is associated with decreased body weight, weight gain, feed intake, and increased feed conversion rate, corroborated our findings. Besides, <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">El-Banna <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2005</xref>), noted that broilers with coccidiosis exhibit a decrease in body weight gain and an increase in FCR. The data of the current study is also consistent with that published by <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">James <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2022</xref>), who reported that broiler coccidiosis resulted in decreased FCR and weight increase.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>Peroxidase-stained intestine of A) healthy broilers showing -ve expression of CD4. B) Infested broilers with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> showed strong +ve expression of CD4. C) Broilers infested with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> treated with toltrazuril showed moderate +ve expression of CD4. D) Infested broilers treated with neem showed almost strong +ve expression of CD4. E) Infested broilers treated with toltrazuril +half dose of neem showed -ve expression of CD4 (&#215;400).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-341-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>The current study found that, as compared to the artificially infected and untreated group (+ve control), broilers with coccidiosis treated with toltrazuril or neem leaf extract, either alone or in combination, showed improvements in body weight, weight gain, and FCR. Toltrazuril&#8217;s anticoccidial action could be the cause of these improvements in body weight growth (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Rachid <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Our findings align with those published by <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">El-Banna <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2005</xref>), who discovered that toltrazuril effectively treats coccidiosis in broilers and enhances their physical performance. The same outcomes were seen earlier by <xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">Soko&#322; <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2014</xref>), who reported that toltrazuril enhanced bodily functions and was beneficial in treating quail coccidiosis. In a similar vein, Onyiche <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2021) reported that neem extract improves body weight, weight increase, and FCR and is effective against <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic>. When compared to healthy, noninfected broiler chickens, the current study found that <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> significantly increased the levels of WBC, lymphocytes, heterophil, eosinophil, basophil, and monocyte in broiler chickens. Our findings corroborated <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Coles&#8217;s (1997</xref>) observation that avian coccidiosis was associated with an increase in eosinophil count. <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Feldman <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2000</xref>) previously reported on these results, stating that eosinophilia was seen in birds with coccidiosis. This result was in good agreement with the findings by <xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Razzaq <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2003</xref>), who found that quail with coccidiosis had a markedly higher WBC count than healthy, noninfected birds. The same findings were published by <xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">Seddik and El-Bealawy (2007</xref>), who claimed that enteritis brought on by coccidiosis in chicken causes a notable rise in WBCs. Furthermore, according to <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Chapman (2008</xref>), turkey with coccidiosis exhibits elevated WBC, heterophile, and lymphocyte levels. Increased concentrations of heterophils and eosinophils in response to parasite infestation are the cause of elevated WBCs (<xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">Wakenell, 2010</xref>). This result was consistent with results from <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Melkamu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2018</xref>), who found that, in comparison to healthy, noninfested broilers, broilers infected with coccidiosis had elevated levels of WBCs and heterophil. When compared to infested nontreated broilers (+ve control), experimentally infested broilers treated with toltrazuril or neem leaf extract, either alone or in combination, showed significant decreases in WBCs, lymphocyte, heterophile, eosinophile, basophile, and monocyte. Comparing broilers infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> treated with toltrazuril to those infected without treatment, <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Allam <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2008</xref>) reported similar outcomes, stating that there was a substantial drop in WBCs. The findings of the present study corroborated those of <xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">Soko&#322; <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2014</xref>), who found that toltrazuril effectively treated quail coccidiosis and increased the number of WBCs. Toltrazuril treatment for coccidiosis in broiler chickens resulted in a nonsignificant drop in WBCs, lymphocytes, heterophils, eosinophils, and basophils (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Rehab, 2017</xref>). <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">El-Ghoneimy and El-Shahawy (2017</xref>) noted the same alterations in leukograms in broilers with coccidiosis. Comparing broilers infested with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> to those treated with toltrazuril or neem leaf suspension, either separately or in combination, showed improved total leukocyte counts. Similar findings were reported by <xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Roy <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2019</xref>). Furthermore, in comparison to infected broilers that were not treated for coccidiosis, broilers treated with toltrazuril exhibited noticeably better WBCs, according to <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Shahira <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2021</xref>). The same results were observed by Onyiche <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2021) who mentioned that neem extract contains natural antioxidants in biological systems against parasites and ameliorative detrimental effects in total and differential leukocytic count. When compared to healthy, noninfected broilers, broilers infested with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> showed substantial decreases in serum total protein, &#947; globulin, and albumin. There was also an insignificant decrease in &#945;, &#946;, &#947;, total globulin, and A/G ratio. Our results are confirmed with those reported by <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">El-Banna <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2005</xref>) who mentioned that coccidiosis in broiler chicks generates a considerable decrease in total protein, &#947; globulin insignificant decrease in albumin, &#945;, &#946;, &#947;, globulin, and A/G ratio. Our findings are consistent with those of <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">El-Dakhly <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2006</xref>), who found that, in comparison to healthy, noninfected broilers, coccidiosis causes a decrease in protein picture. The findings of <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Patra <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2010</xref>), who suggested that liver abnormalities and impaired nutritional absorption from the inflamed gut may be the cause of hypoproteinemia and hypoalbuminemia in broiler hens infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic>, corroborated our findings. This result was in good agreement with earlier research conducted by <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Abd El-Aziz <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2011</xref>), who reported that chicken cecal coccidiosis causes a considerable reduction in the protein picture. The same findings were published by <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Abd El-Maksoud <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2014</xref>), who showed that the serum total protein, albumen, globulin level, and A/G ratio of broilers infested with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> decreased. When compared to a broiler infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> that was not treated (+ ve control broiler), infested broilers treated with toltrazuril or neem leaves extract, either separately or in combination, showed nonsignificant increases in serum total protein along with insignificant increases in serum albumin, &#945;, &#946;, &#947;, total globulin, and A/G ratio. Toltrazuril treatment for coccidiosis in broiler hens results in nonsignificant reductions in blood total protein, albumin, and globulin levels (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Rehab, 2017</xref>). When compared to broilers experimentally infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> that were not treated, broilers suffering from coccidiosis treated with toltrazuril exhibited improvement in protein picture producing nonsignificant decreases in serum total protein, albumin, &#945;, &#946;, &#947;, globulin, and A/G ratio (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Mona <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). The same findings were noted by <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Shahira <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2021</xref>), who reported that toltrazuril improves serum protein, albumin, and globulin levels and is useful in the treatment of coccidiosis. The serum total proteins, albumin, and globulin levels of broilers given neem extract improved (<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Vanessa <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>). The same outcomes were noted by Onyiche <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2021), who reported that neem extract has a protective impact on protein images and acts as a natural antioxidant in biological systems against parasites.</p><p>According to the current study, when compared to noninfested (healthy) broilers, broiler chickens with coccidiosis showed significantly lower serum levels of lysozyme, nitric oxide, phagocytic percent, and phagocytic index. The same results were reported by coccidiosis (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Allen, 1997</xref>) who indicated that broiler chickens suffering from coccidia showed declines in serum nitric oxide and lysozyme.</p><p>According to <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">El-Sayed (2002</xref>), coccidiosis in broilers causes a considerable drop in phagocytic percentage and phagocytic index. Our findings corroborated those of <xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2008</xref>), who found that coccidiosis significantly reduced lysosome and nitric oxide levels. Our findings are consistent with those of <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Nasr <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2014</xref>), who reported that broilers infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> exhibited a noteworthy reduction in both phagocytic percentage and phagocytic index. The findings were in line with those of <xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">Mohamed <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2018</xref>), who found that coccidiosis significantly reduced serum nitric oxide, lysosome, phagocytic percentage, and phagocytic index.</p><p>In comparison to infested broilers that were not treated, broilers that were experimentally infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> and treated with either toltrazuril or neem extract alone showed a substantial increase in nitric oxide, lysozyme, phagocytic %, and phagocytic index. ThankGod <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2021) reported similar outcomes, stating that neem watery extract contains natural antioxidants in biological systems against parasites and ameliorates negative effects in lysosome phagocytic activity and nitric oxide. The current study has demonstrated that, in comparison to healthy, noninfested broilers, broilers afflicted with coccidiosis have a substantial rise in fibrinogen and haptoglobin. The same findings were reported by <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">Richrds and Augustine (1988</xref>), who found that haptoglobin and fibrinogen levels were higher in broilers with coccidiosis. The same findings were reported by <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Allen (1997</xref>), who noted that haptoglobin and fibrinogen levels significantly increased in broiler chicks with coccidiosis. Our findings concurred with those of <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Georgieva <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2010</xref>), who reported that an <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> infection in broilers causes an increase in the inflammatory markers fibrinogen and haptoglobin in the plasma. This conclusion was consistent with the findings of <xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2008</xref>), who reported that coccidiosis causes a considerable rise in fibrinogen and haptoglobin and a significant decrease in nitric oxide and lysosome. These findings concur with those of <xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">Mohamed <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2018</xref>), who found that in addition to a notable increase in fibrinogen and haptoglobin, coccidiosis also causes a drop in serum nitric oxide and lysosome levels.</p><p>When compared to experimentally infected broilers that were not treated, broilers that were treated with either toltrazuril or neem alone or in combination had a large rise in nitric oxide and lysozyme along with a significant decrease in fibrinogen and haptoglobin. The same outcomes were noted by Onyiche <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2021), who reported that neem watery extract, had a beneficial effect on lysosomes and nitric oxide levels in biological systems by acting as natural antioxidants against parasites. Furthermore, <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Liza <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2021</xref>) report that neem extract-treated coccidiosis-affected rabbits have decreased levels of (haptoglobin and fibrinogen). The intestinal peroxidase stain of a healthy broiler demonstrated -ve expression for CD4, while the intestinal peroxidase of broilers infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> showed strong positive expression for CD4. The intestinal peroxidase of broilers infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> treated with toltrazuril demonstrated moderate positive expression for CD4, and the intestinal peroxidase of infected broilers treated with neem displayed nearly strong positive expression for CD4, while the intestinal peroxidase-stained intestine of infested broilers treated with toltrazuril +half dose of neem displayed -ve expression for CD4. Broiler infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> exhibit positive CD4 in their intestines (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">Rothwell <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>). <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Carbonnel <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (1999</xref>) observed the same alteration in intestinal tissue treated with peroxidase dye.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Although broiler hens infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> have numerous negative effects on immunity and immunohistopathological picture, toltrazuril and neem leaf extract, either separately or in combination, function as anticoccidial drugs that enhance broiler immunity.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>The authors would like to thank all people who supported the experimental work.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>No conflict of interest is to be declared.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data will be made available upon reasonable request.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>Fatma El Zahra Abdel-Hamid Youssef did the experimental work, data analysis, and drafted the manuscript. Amira M. Ibrahim and Walaa Fathy SaadEldin supported the experimental part, sampling, and financial support, Hosny Abd El Fadel, Abd El Aleim F. Abd El Aleim, Gehan N. Gad proposed the research theme, supervised the work, and revised the final manuscript.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saleemi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anticoccidial drug resistance in fowl coccidia: the state of play revisited</article-title><source>World&#8217;s. Poult. Sci. J</source><year>2012</year><volume>67</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>350</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd El-Aziz</surname><given-names>M.I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Shazly</surname><given-names>K.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Sherbeney</surname><given-names>E.M.E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effet of diaclazuril or maduramicin alone or together in ontroling cecal occidosiss in chickens</article-title><source>Kafrelsheikh. Vet. Med. J</source><year>2011</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>187</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd El-Maksoud</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Afaf</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Badry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical effect of coccidia infestation in laying hen</article-title><source>Benha. Vet. Med. J</source><year>2014</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>133</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allam</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayoumie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seham</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of toltrazuril and amprolium plus in broiler chickensinfected with coccidiosis</article-title><source>Assuit. Vet. Med. J</source><year>2008</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide production during <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria tenella</italic> infections in chickens</article-title><year>1997</year><volume>76</volume><publisher-loc>Beltsville, MD</publisher-loc><publisher-name>SDA, Agricultural Research Service</publisher-name><fpage>810</fpage><lpage>813</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ps/76.6.810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9181612</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chattopadhyay</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banarjee</surname><given-names>R.K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological activities and medicinal properties of neem (<italic toggle="yes">Azadirachta indica</italic>)</article-title><source>Curr. Sci. Rev</source><year>2002</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>336</fpage><lpage>345</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carbonnel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavergne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matuchansky</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brouet</surname><given-names>J.C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sigaux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beaugerie</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemeth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>CoYn</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cosnes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gendre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rambaud</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The clinicopathological features of extensive small intestinal CD4 T cell in&#64257;ltration</article-title><source>Gut</source><year>1999</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>662</fpage><lpage>667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10517900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/gut.45.5.662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1727728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coccidiosis in the turkey</article-title><source>Avian. Pathol</source><year>2008</year><volume>37</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18568647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/03079450802050689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Avian medicine and surgery</article-title><year>1997</year><edition>2nd</edition><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doumas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Certor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaflr</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A candidate reference method for determination of total protein in serum</article-title><source>Clin. Chem</source><year>1981</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6169466</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Durrani</surname><given-names>F.R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chand</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sultan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Durrani</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akhtar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunomodulatory and growth promoting effects of neem leaves infusion in broiler chicks</article-title><source>Sarhad. J. Agric</source><year>2008</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>655</fpage><lpage>659</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Banna</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Zorba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Hady</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anticocci-dial efficacy of drinking water soluble diclazuril on experimental and field coccidiosis in broiler chickens</article-title><source>J. Vet. Med. A. Physiol. Path. Clin. Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16050910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1439-0442.2005.00727.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Dakhly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shalaby</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Nesr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The efficacy of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic> and/or diclazuril for inhibition and control of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria tenella</italic> infection in balady chicks</article-title><source>Kafer El-Sheik. Vet. Med. J</source><year>2006</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Ghoneimy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Shahawy</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of amprolium and toltrazuril efficacy in controlling natural intestinal rabbit coccidiosis</article-title><source>Iran. J. Vet. Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29163644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5674438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><element-citation publication-type="thesis"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Sayed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of diclazuril and semduramicin as prophylactic or thera-peutic treatments n broilers infected with <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria tenella</italic></article-title><year>2002</year><comment>Thesis (Pharmacology), Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Tanta University, Tanta, Egypt</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zinki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Schalms veterinary hematology</article-title><year>2000</year><edition>5th</edition><publisher-loc>Philadelp-hia, PA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Lippincott Williams and Wilkins</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaurav</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pramanik</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukesh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandeep</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manoj</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaswant</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of neem (<italic toggle="yes">Azadirachta indica</italic>) leaves powder against Coccodia in commercial broiler chickens</article-title><source>J. Pharm. Phytochem</source><year>2018</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1S</issue><fpage>991</fpage><lpage>993</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Georgieva</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koinarski</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urumova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marutsov</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikolov</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaprazov</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walshe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Georgiev</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koinarski</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> infection and <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria tenella</italic> invasion on blood concentrations of some positive acute phase proteins (haptoglobin (PIT 54), fibrinogen and ceruloplasmin) in chickens</article-title><source>Rev. M&#233;d. V&#233;t</source><year>2010</year><volume>161</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>89</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghafouri</surname><given-names>S.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghaniei</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tavanaee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadr</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charbgoo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghiassi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abuali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of therapeutic effects of an herbal mixture (<italic toggle="yes">Echinacea purpurea</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Glycyrrhiza glabra</italic>) for treatment of clinical coccidiosis in broilers</article-title><source>Vet. Med. Sci</source><year>2023</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>829</fpage><lpage>836</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36253639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/vms3.971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10029886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winkelman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical chemistry: principals and techniques</article-title><year>1974</year><publisher-loc>Hagerstown, MD</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Harper and Row</publisher-name><fpage>437</fpage><lpage>440</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>N.C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Schalm&#8217;s veterinary hematology, 4th ed</article-title><year>1986</year><publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Lee and Febiger</publisher-name><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>96</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Micah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oriel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aliyu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>David</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Field study in the effect of neem aqueous leav extracts in broilers coccidiosis</article-title><source>Poult. Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>658</fpage><lpage>664</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunohistochemistry for pathologists: protocols, pitfalls, and tips</article-title><source>J. Pathol. Transl. Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>50</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>418</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27809448</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4132/jptm.2016.08.08</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5122731</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitandu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juranov&#225;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Progress in control measures for chicken coccidiosis</article-title><source>Acta. Vet. Brno</source><year>2006</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>276</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leila</surname><given-names>S.F.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A manual on some Philippine medicinal plants (Preparation of drug materials)</article-title><source>Bot. Soc. U. P</source><year>1977</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>82</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liza</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amany</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ameliorative effect of neem leaf and pomegranate peel extracts in coccidial infections in New Zealand and V-line rabbits: performance, intestinal health, oocyst shedding, carcass traits, and effect on economic measures</article-title><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ani11082441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8388781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34438898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larry</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ontageny and line difference in mitogenic responses of chicken lymphocyte</article-title><source>Poult. Sci</source><year>1982</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3382/ps.0620579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6866896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathis</surname><given-names>G.F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Froyman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Irion</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coccidiosis control with toltrazuril in conjugation with anticoccidial medicated or non-medicated feed</article-title><source>Avian. Dis</source><year>2003</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>463</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12887207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1637/0005-2086(2003)047[0463:CCWTIC]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Froyman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coccidiosis control by toltrazuril in the drinking water for a 2-day period</article-title><source>Vet. Parasitol</source><year>2004</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15110398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vetpar.2004.02.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Melkamu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mersha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asrat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Haematological changes caused by coccidiosis in infected chickens</article-title><source>Int. J. Adv. Res. Biol. Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>196</fpage><lpage>202</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mosaad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nahed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asmaa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of high dietary level of some amino acids and coccidial infection on growth performance and health status of broiler chicken</article-title><source>Alexandria. J. Vet. Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>58</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>165</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mona</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd-El Alim</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of phytobiotics, probiotics and toltrazuril on chicken coccidiosis</article-title><source>Zag. Vet. J</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>214</fpage><lpage>223</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasr</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reda</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> oocyst whole antigen vaccine and the enhancive effect of probiotic on broilers</article-title><source>Int. J. Basic. Appl. Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>362</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nazmiye</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parasitic zoonotic diseases in Turkey</article-title><source>Vet. Ital</source><year>2008</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>646</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20411490</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Onyiche</surname><given-names>T.E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gotep</surname><given-names>J.G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanko</surname><given-names>J.T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ochigbo</surname><given-names>G.O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozoani</surname><given-names>H.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Viyoff</surname><given-names>V.Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dogonyaro</surname><given-names>B.B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Makoshi</surname><given-names>M.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinjir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thekisoe</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atiku</surname><given-names>A.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shamaki</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muraina</surname><given-names>I.A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Azadirachta indica</italic> aqueous leaf extracts ameliorates coccidiosis in broiler chickens experimentally infected with <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> oocysts</article-title><source>Sci. Afr</source><volume>132</volume><fpage>658</fpage><lpage>664</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayoub</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chanu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joy</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pravo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dvel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis of <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> infection in chicken</article-title><source>Int. J. Poult. Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>813</fpage><lpage>818</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rachid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akbar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Araby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ismae</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashmi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative efficacy of different toltrazuril doses against coccidiosis in broiler chickens</article-title><source>Mansoura. Vet. Med. J</source><year>2009</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>184</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajarman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nonnecke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horst</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of vitamins E on nitric oxide prod-uction by blood mononuclear leukocytes from neonatal calves fed milk replacer</article-title><source>J. Dairy. Sci</source><year>1998</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(98)75892-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9891273</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Razzaq</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashmi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamran</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical and haematological effects of coccidiosis and its prophylactic control in quails</article-title><source>Pak. J. Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><element-citation publication-type="thesis"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehab</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of toltrazuril as anticoccidial drug in broilers</article-title><year>2017</year><comment>M. Sc Thesis, Submitted to Faculty of Veterinary Medicine (Pharmacology Department), Zagazig University, Zagazig, Egypt</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richrds</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Augustine</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serum and liver zinc, copper, and iron in chicks infected with <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria acervulina</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria tenella</italic></article-title><source>Biol. Trace. Elem. Res</source><year>1988</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2484359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF02795457</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothwell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gramzinski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Avian coccidiosis: changes in intestinal lymphocyte populations associated with the development of immunity to <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria maxima</italic></article-title><source>Parasite. Immunol</source><year>1995</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8587790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-3024.1995.tb00883.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>M.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>F.B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative study of neem leaf (<italic toggle="yes">Azadirachta indica</italic>) suspension and toltrazuril against coccidiosis in Sonali chicken</article-title><source>Bangladesh. J. Vet. Med</source><year>2019</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>105</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Said</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khairy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel Alim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zainab</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Compatibility of toltrazuril and probiotic in chickens</article-title><source>Zag. Vet. J</source><year>2010</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>81</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schltz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methods in clinical chemistry</article-title><year>1987</year><publisher-loc>St. Louis, MO</publisher-loc><publisher-name>C. V. Mosby Co</publisher-name><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>46</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seddik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Bealawy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of probiotic in broiler chickens infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. maxima</italic></article-title><source>Zag. Vet. J</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>201</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahira</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mervat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gehan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rania</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative biochemical and pathological studies between toltrazuril and garlic supplementation in chickens infected with coccidiosis</article-title><source>Egy. J. Anim. Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>80</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soko&#322;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gesek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norynska</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michalczyk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toltrazuril treatment coccidiosis caused by <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria </italic>sp</article-title><source>in Japanese quails. Polish. J. Vet. Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>17</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>468</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2478/pjvs-2014-0067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25286655</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rommel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daugschies</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haberkorn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies of resistance to anticoccidials in <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria </italic>field isolates and pure <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> strains</article-title><source>Vet. Parasitol</source><year>1997</year><volume>69</volume><issue>1&#8211;2</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9187026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0304-4017(96)01096-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Subapriya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medicinal properties of neem leaves</article-title><source>Curr. Med. Chem. Rev</source><year>2005</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2174/1568011053174828</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15777222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanessa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jean</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kissel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of graded levels of <italic toggle="yes">Azadirachta indica</italic> seed oil on growth performance and biochemical profiles of broiler chickens</article-title><source>Vet. Med. Sci</source><year>2019</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>442</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30828990</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/vms3.162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6682791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wakenell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>D.J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wardrop</surname><given-names>K.J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Haematology of chickens and Turkeys</article-title><source>In Vet haematology</source><year>2010</year><edition>6th</edition><publisher-loc>Ames, IA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>John Wiley&amp; Sons</publisher-name><fpage>957</fpage><lpage>967</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cowieson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Remus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McElroy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of dietary enzymes on performance and intestinal goblet cell number of broilers exposed to a live coccidia oocyst vaccine</article-title><source>Poult. Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21177448</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3382/ps.2010-00760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of grape seed proanthocyanidin extract in broiler chickens: effect on chicken coccidiosis and antioxidant status</article-title><source>Poult. Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>2273</fpage><lpage>2280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18931178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3382/ps.2008-00077</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>R.B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiological aspects of the use of live anticoccidial vaccines for chickens</article-title><source>Int. J. Prasitol</source><year>1998</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1089</fpage><lpage>1098</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0020-7519(98)00066-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9724880</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>