<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2846</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">openvetj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Veterinary Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2226-4485</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2218-6050</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tripoli</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12587954</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12587954.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12587954</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12587954</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41200347</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/OVJ.2025.v15.i9.8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OpenVetJ-15-9-4032</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evaluation of serum levels of CRP and TNF-&#945; in dogs infected with <italic toggle="yes">Ehrlichia canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Anaplasma phagocytophilum</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gospodinova</surname><given-names initials="K">Krasimira</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koev</surname><given-names initials="K">Koycho</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of General and Clinical Pathology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Trakia University, Stara Zagora, Bulgaria</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Veterinary Microbiology, Infectious and Parasitic Diseases, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Trakia University, Stara Zagora, Bulgaria</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold><sup>*</sup>Corresponding Author:</bold> Krasimira Gospodinova. Department of General and Clinical Pathology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Trakia University, Stara Zagora, Bulgaria. Email: <email>krasimira.gospodinova@trakia-uni.bg</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>9</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">500125</issue-id><fpage>4032</fpage><lpage>4043</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>12</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>09</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>06</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-11-07 09:25:12.803"><day>07</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-15-9-4032.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Canine monocytic ehrlichiosis (CME) and canine granulocytic anaplasmosis (CGA), caused by <italic toggle="yes">Ehrlichia canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Anaplasma phagocytophilum</italic>, are tick-borne diseases prevalent in dogs. Both trigger systemic inflammation, with C-reactive protein (CRP) and tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-&#945;) as potential severity biomarkers.</p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>This study aimed to compare serum CRP and TNF-&#945; in CME, CGA, and co-infected dogs and assess their relationships with hematological, biochemical, and liver enzyme changes.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>In 134 dogs showing clinical signs of CME/CGA, infections were confirmed using SNAP<sup>&#174;</sup> 4Dx<sup>&#174;</sup> Plus, indirect immunofluorescence assay, and polymerase chain reaction (PCR). CRP and TNF-&#945; were quantified using canine-specific enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay kits.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Of the dogs tested, 112 (83.6%) were seropositive and 77 (68.8%) were PCR-positive (<italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic>: 27; <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic>: 29; co-infection: 21). The co-infected group had the highest levels of CRP (135.2&#8211;154.8 mg/l) and TNF-&#945; (161.5&#8211;174.0 pg/ml), significantly exceeding those of CME (104.6&#8211;120.9; 148.7&#8211;162.2 pg/ml), CGA (88.5&#8211;104.4; 140.1&#8211;156.5 pg/ml), PCR-negative (33.1&#8211;45.8; 12.3&#8211;18.9 pg/ml), and control groups (0.9&#8211;4.0; 0.2&#8211;2.3 pg/ml) with <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001. Thrombocytopenia was common in all infected groups, with the lowest platelet counts in co-infected dogs (median 106.0 &#215; 10<sup>9</sup>/L, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). Aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) were significantly elevated only in co-infected dogs (ALT: 89.25 U/l; AST: 69.38 U/l; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). CRP correlated moderately with ALT/AST; TNF-&#945; showed weaker positive associations.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>CRP and TNF-&#945; are valuable indicators of systemic inflammation in CME and CGA, with maximal increases and stronger links to liver injury in co-infections, supporting their use in diagnosis and prognosis.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Ehrlichia canis</italic></kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Anaplasma phagocytophilum</italic></kwd><kwd>CRP</kwd><kwd>TNF-&#945;</kwd><kwd>Co-infection</kwd><kwd>Dogs</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Tick-borne diseases, such as <italic toggle="yes">Ehrlichia canis</italic>-induced canine monocytic ehrlichiosis (CME) and <italic toggle="yes">Anaplasma phagocytophilum</italic>-induced canine granulocytic anaplasmosis (CGA), are prevalent and pose significant threats to canine health. Both pathogens, members of the <italic toggle="yes">Anaplasmataceae</italic> family, are transmitted via ticks&#8212;<italic toggle="yes">Rhipicephalus sanguineus</italic> for <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes</italic> species for <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic> (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Laatamna <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2022</xref>).</p><p>Despite substantial advances in understanding their epidemiology and pathogenesis, reliable biomarkers capable of differentiating between mono- and coinfections in naturally infected dogs remain insufficiently defined. Once transmitted, these intracellular bacteria target specific leukocyte populations, eliciting distinct immune and pathological responses (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Aziz <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2022</xref>). In such infections, anemia and thrombocytopenia are largely secondary to the inflammatory response rather than direct cytopathic effects. <italic toggle="yes">Ehrlichia canis</italic> primarily infects mononuclear cells, leading to systemic inflammation, immune dysregulation, and consequent hematologic abnormalities such as thrombocytopenia and anemia (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Ramakant <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). In contrast, <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic> targets neutrophils, impairing their function and promoting inflammation, which clinically manifests as polyarthritis, lethargy, and fever (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Khatat <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>).</p><p>Both infections trigger acute-phase and cytokine-mediated immune responses that, while essential for pathogen control, can exacerbate inflammation and contribute to disease pathogenesis if dysregulated (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Cardoso <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">Ismail, <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> 2022</xref>; Nahed <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2022). C-reactive protein (CRP), an acute-phase protein synthesized by hepatocytes in response to interleukin-6 (IL-6), is a sensitive biomarker of systemic inflammation and tissue injury (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Cray, 2012</xref>). Elevated CRP levels are common in bacterial infections, including those caused by tick-borne pathogens, and reflect the inflammatory burden associated with CME (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Asawakarn and Taweethavonsawat, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Asawapattanakul <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>).</p><p>Tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-&#945;), a proinflammatory cytokine produced mainly by activated macrophages, monocytes, and dendritic cells, regulates inflammation, apoptosis, and immune cell recruitment via TNFR1 and TNFR2 (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Jang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>). In CME, TNF-&#945; production is stimulated by <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic>, contributing to macrophage and monocyte activation but, when excessive, driving systemic inflammation, tissue damage, and immune dysregulation (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Lima <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Infection with <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic> induces significant upregulation of proinflammatory cytokines, including TNF-&#945;, MIP-2, and IL-6, in murine bone marrow cells (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Johns <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Similarly, increased secretion of TNF-&#945;, IL-1, MIP-2, and IL-6 has been observed in canine models of infection (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Stanilov <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2024</xref>).</p><p>The dual role of CRP and TNF-&#945; as both mediators of inflammation and biomarkers of immune dysregulation makes them highly relevant for investigating the pathophysiology of CME and CGA (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Lima <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Asawapattanakul <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>). Their elevated concentrations may assist in distinguishing between mono- and co-infections (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Asawakarn and Taweethavonsawat, 2021</xref>). However, limited data exist on their concurrent changes in naturally co-infected dogs and their relationship with liver injury indicators such as alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Cardoso <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). Moreover, their combined diagnostic and prognostic potential&#8212;particularly in co-infections where immune responses may be amplified or dysregulated&#8212;remains underexplored (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Aziz <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2022</xref>).</p><p>This study aimed to evaluate and compare serum levels of CRP and TNF-&#945; in dogs infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic>. By elucidating their role in the inflammatory and immune responses associated with these infections, this research seeks to provide insights into disease pathogenesis and highlight their potential as biomarkers for improved diagnosis, monitoring, and management of canine tick-borne diseases.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>A total of 134 client-owned dogs were enrolled in this study. All animals were presented to the Small Animal Clinic at the University Hospital of Trakia University in Stara Zagora, Bulgaria, with a documented history of tick infestations. Dogs were eligible for inclusion if they had confirmed infections with <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic> or if they exhibited clinical signs consistent with CME&#8212;such as fever, anemia, and thrombocytopenia&#8212;or CGA, characterized by lethargy, polyarthritis, and thrombocytopenia.</p><p>Each dog underwent complete hematological and biochemical evaluation and was tested for <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic> by rapid enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA; SNAP<sup>&#174;</sup> 4Dx<sup>&#174;</sup> Plus, IDEXX Laboratories, Westbrook, ME), indirect immunofluorescence assay (IFA; Mega FLUO<sup>&#174;</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> and Mega FLUO<sup>&#174;</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic>, Megacor Diagnostik GmbH, Austria), and polymerase chain reaction (PCR) with <italic toggle="yes">Anaplasmataceae</italic>-specific primers (16S rRNA gene) and species-specific primers for <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> (16S rRNA gene) and <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic> (ankA gene).</p><p>The dogs ranged in age from 1 to 12 years (mean &#177; SD: 6.4 &#177; 3.1 years) and included 72 (53.7%) males and 62 (46.3%) females. Most were mixed-breed dogs (57.5%), followed by German Shepherds (14.9%), Labrador Retrievers (8.2%), and Rottweilers, Beagles, and Setters (19.4%). The majority of respondents originated from rural areas (61.2%), while the remainder lived in urban environments (38.8%). Although cases were recorded year-round, most presentations occurred in spring and summer, coinciding with the region&#8217;s peak tick activity.</p><sec><title>Group distribution</title><p>Dogs that tested positive for antibodies to <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic> by serology were subsequently examined by uniplex PCR using <italic toggle="yes">Anaplasmataceae</italic>-specific primers and species-specific primers targeting <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic>. Based on clinical, hematological, biochemical, serological, and molecular results, the dogs were classified into three groups:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><bold>Control group:</bold> 22 clinically healthy dogs with normal hematological and biochemical profiles, negative for both pathogens by SNAP, IFA, and PCR.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>PCR-positive group</bold>: 77 dogs with clinical signs and hematological/biochemical abnormalities and positive for <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic> by SNAP, IFA, and PCR. This group included 27 dogs PCR-positive for <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> (active CME), 29 dogs PCR-positive for <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic> (active CGA), and 21 co-infected dogs PCR-positive for both pathogens.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>PCR-negative group:</bold> 35 dogs with clinical signs and hematological/biochemical abnormalities, positive by SNAP and IFA, but PCR-negative.</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<bold>Blood collection and hematological and biochemical analysis</bold>
</p></list-item></list><p>Blood was collected from the external cephalic vein (vena cephalica antebrachii externa) into ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid-coated vacuum tubes for hematological analysis and into plain tubes for serum separation. Hematology was performed using an automated analyzer (MINDRAY BC-5000 Vet; Shenzhen Mindray Animal Medical Technology Co., Ltd.), and serum biochemistry was analyzed using an automated chemistry analyzer (MINDRAY BS-120; Mindray Medical India Pvt. Ltd.).</p></sec><sec><title>Diagnostic procedures</title><p>
<bold>Serology</bold>
</p><p>
<bold>Rapid diagnostic test (SNAP<sup>&#174;</sup> 4Dx<sup>&#174;</sup> Plus)</bold>
</p><p>Serum samples were tested for IgG antibodies to <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Anaplasma platys</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Ehrlichia ewingii</italic> and for circulating antigens of <italic toggle="yes">Dirofilaria immitis</italic> using the SNAP<sup>&#174;</sup> 4Dx<sup>&#174;</sup> Plus assay according to the manufacturer&#8217;s instructions. Two drops of serum were mixed with horseradish peroxidase&#8211;conjugated proteins, and the resulting antigen&#8211;antibody complexes were detected using colorimetric analysis.</p><p>
<bold>Indirect IFA</bold>
</p><p>Sera were analyzed using Mega FLUO<sup>&#174;</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> and Mega FLUO<sup>&#174;</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic> kits to detect IgG antibodies specific to <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic>. Samples were diluted in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS; pH 7.2&#8211;7.4) and incubated at 37&#176;C to allow antigen&#8211;antibody binding. Nonspecific proteins were removed by washing, and fluorescence was observed under a microscope at 400&#215; magnification.</p></sec><sec><title>PCR</title><p>
<bold>DNA extraction</bold>
</p><p>Genomic DNA was extracted from whole blood using the High Pure PCR Template Preparation Kit (Roche Diagnostics, Mannheim, Germany) according to the manufacturer&#8217;s protocol. DNA was stored at &#8722;20&#176;C until further analysis.</p><p>
<bold>PCR amplification</bold>
</p><p>Gradient PCR (AERIS PCR system, Esco, Singapore) was used to optimize annealing temperatures. Initial screening employed Anaplasmataceae-specific 16S rRNA primers (Parola <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2000; <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), followed by species-specific primers for a 409 bp E. canis 16S rRNA fragment (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Inokuma <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) and a 444 bp A. phagocytophilum ankA fragment (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Caturegli <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Walls <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>PCR primers used in this study.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Target pathogen</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene target</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name and sequence (5&#8242;&#8211;3&#8242;)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Product size (bp)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Anaplasmataceae</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16S rRNA (consensus)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>EHR 16SD</bold>-GGTACCYACAGAAGAAGTCC/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>HER- 16SR</bold> TAGCACTCATCGTTTACAGC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">345</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parola <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2000)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Ehrlichia canis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16S rRNA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CANIS</bold>-GATAGGAATCTTCCACCTATG/ <bold>GA1UR</bold>TATAGGTACCGTCATTATCTTCCCTAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">409</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Inokuma <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2003)</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Anaplasma phagocytophilum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ankA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>LA1-</bold>GCAAGTGCTTGAACAGTGA/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>LA6-</bold>CTCTACACTAGGAATTCCGCTG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">444</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Caturegli <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2000)</xref>; Walls<italic toggle="yes"> et al.</italic> (2000)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>
<bold>PCR conditions</bold>
</p><p>Reactions included positive controls (confirmed DNA from <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic>) and a negative control (nuclease-free water). Cycling conditions were as follows: 95&#176;C for 5 minute; 35 cycles of 94&#176;C for 30 second, annealing at 55&#176;C&#8211;60&#176;C for 30 second (gene-dependent), 72&#176;C for 1 minute; and final extension at 72&#176;C for 10 minute.</p><p>
<bold>Gel electrophoresis</bold>
</p><p>Amplicons were separated on a 1.5% agarose gel stained with ethidium bromide. A DNA ladder was used to determine the product size. Bands were visualized and documented under UV light.</p><p>
<bold>Method validation</bold>
</p><p>PCR protocols, including cycling conditions, primer design, and gel electrophoresis, were validated in a previous study (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Gospodinova <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2024</xref>) to ensure reproducibility and accuracy.</p><p>All dogs enrolled in the study.</p></sec><sec><title>Biomarker measurement</title><p>
<bold>C-reactive protein</bold>
</p><p>Plasma CRP concentrations were measured using a fluorescence immunoassay kit (InSight V-IA Canine CRP Rapid Quantitative Test, Woodley Equipment Company Ltd., UK) according to the manufacturer&#8217;s instructions, with analysis performed on the InSight V-IA Veterinary Immunoassay Analyzer. The samples were measured in duplicate, and the mean values were used for statistical analysis. The intra- and inter-assay coefficients of variation were &lt;10% and &lt;15%, respectively. The detection range was 2&#8211;250 mg/l, with a reference value for healthy dogs of &lt;10 mg/l.</p><p>
<bold>Tumor necrosis factor alpha</bold>
</p><p>Serum TNF-&#945; concentrations were determined using a canine-specific sandwich ELISA kit (Canine TNF-&#945; ELISA Kit, FineTest<sup>&#174;</sup>, China), following the manufacturer&#8217;s protocol. Optical density was measured at 450 nm using an ELISA plate reader (LEDETECT 96, Labexim Produkt, Biomed Dr. Weisser GmbH, Austria). All samples were analyzed in duplicate, and the concentrations were calculated from a standard curve. The assay sensitivity was &lt;9.375 pg/ml, with a working range of 15.625&#8211;1,000 pg/ml. The intra- and inter-assay coefficients of variation were &lt;8% and &lt;10%, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data were analyzed using IBM SPSS Statistics version 29.0.2 (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY), GraphPad Prism version 10.0.3 (GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA), and, when appropriate, available online calculators from the StatPages.net website (<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://statpages.org/index.html">http://statpages.org/index.html</uri>, accessed on June 2, 2024). The Shapiro&#8211;Wilk test was used to assess normality. Normally distributed variables are presented as mean &#177; SE (min&#8211;max), and non-normally distributed variables are presented as median (IQR, min&#8211;max). Group differences for CRP, TNF-&#945;, hematological, and biochemical parameters were evaluated using one-way analysis of variance with Tukey&#8217;s post hoc test, and correlations with liver enzymes were assessed using Pearson&#8217;s correlation coefficient. Statistical significance was set at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>The Local Ethics Committee of the Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Trakia University, approved the study (FVM-09/protocol, June 9, 2020). Informed consent was obtained from the study population.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Serological findings</title><p>Of the 134 blood samples tested with SNAP<sup>&#174;</sup> 4Dx<sup>&#174;</sup> Plus (IDEXX Laboratories, Westbrook, ME), 112 (83.6%) were positive for antibodies to <italic toggle="yes">Ehrlichia</italic> spp. and/or <italic toggle="yes">Anaplasma</italic> spp., while 22 (16.4%) were negative (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). All samples were negative for <italic toggle="yes">Borrelia burgdorferi</italic> antibodies and <italic toggle="yes">D. immitis</italic> antigen, and no dogs were microfilaremic.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Number and percentage of dogs who were positive in the SNAP and IFA tests according to the evaluated groups.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SNAP test <italic toggle="yes">n</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">IFA <italic toggle="yes">n</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive for <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> only</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.28</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive for <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic> only</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive for E.<italic toggle="yes"> canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.16</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative for both pathogens</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.42</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>IFA detected IgG antibodies against <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> (titer &#8805;1:40) in 58 samples, A. <italic toggle="yes">phagocytophilum</italic> in 31 samples, and both pathogens in 23 samples. Twenty-two dogs were negative for both the SNAP and IFA tests and served as controls.</p></sec><sec><title>PCR results</title><p>All 112 antibody-positive dogs were tested for Anaplasmataceae-specific 16S rRNA sequences by PCR. Seventy-seven (68.8%) were PCR positive and 35 (31.2%) were negative.</p><p>Species-specific PCR identified <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> alone in 27 samples, <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic> alone in 29, and both pathogens in 21 samples (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Number and percentage of PCR-positive samples according to the evaluation groups.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR results</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">n</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR (+) <italic toggle="yes">of E. canis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR (+) <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.89</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR (+) <italic toggle="yes">E. canis/A. phagocytophilum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.75</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR (&#8722;)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.25</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Clinical signs</title><p>The distribution of clinical signs among PCR-positive and PCR-negative dogs, along with CRP and TNF-&#945; concentration ranges, is summarized in <xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. The most frequent signs in the CME group included fever (94.1%), lethargy (88.2%), anorexia (88.2%), spontaneous bleeding (82.4%), and weight loss (82.4%). Similar trends were observed in the CGA group, where lethargy (89.5%), fever (84.2%), anorexia (68.4%), and spontaneous bleeding (52.6%) predominated. Dogs with co-infections exhibited a broader spectrum of abnormalities, including lethargy (87.5%), fever (87.5%), spontaneous bleeding (75.0%), skin lesions (75.0%), and weight loss (75.0%), often accompanied by ocular changes (62.5%). Less frequent but clinically relevant signs included arthritis/polyarthritis (up to 12.5%), renal insufficiency (up to 25.0%), and melena (12.5%). PCR-negative dogs had fewer and milder signs, most often lethargy (66.7%) and easy fatigability (66.7%), with occasional fever, ocular changes, or gastrointestinal symptoms. Plasma CRP and TNF-&#945; levels tended to be higher in dogs with more severe or multiple clinical manifestations, particularly in the co-infected group.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><title>Clinical signs, CRP and TNF-&#945; levels in dogs naturally infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic>, or both pathogens, and PCR-negative dogs.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clinical sign</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Active CME( <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 17)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Active CGA( <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 19)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Active co-infection( <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR-negative( <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lethargy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (88.24%, 63.56%&#8211;98.54%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (89.47%, 66.86&#8211;96.79)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (87.50%, 47.35%&#8211;99.68%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (66.67%, 22.28&#8211;95.67)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fever</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (94.12%, 71.31%&#8211;99.85%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (84.21%, 60.42%&#8211;96.62%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (87.50%, 47.35%&#8211;99.68%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (50.00%, 11.81&#8211;88.19)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anorexia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (88.24%, 63.56%&#8211;98.54%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (68.42%, 43.45%&#8211;87.42%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (87.50%, 47.35%&#8211;99.68%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (50.00%, 11.81&#8211;88.19)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight loss</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (82.35%, 56.57&#8211;96.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (57.89%, 33.50%&#8211;79.75%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (75.00%, 34.91%&#8211;96.81%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (33.33%, 4.33&#8211;77.72%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Easy fatigability</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (76.47%, 50.10%&#8211;93.12%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (42.11%, 20.25&#8211;66.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (75.00%, 34.91%&#8211;96.81%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (66.67%, 22.28&#8211;95.67)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spontaneous bleeding</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (82.35%, 56.57&#8211;96.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (52.63%, 28.86%&#8211;75.55%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (75.00%, 34.91%&#8211;96.81%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (33.33%, 4.33%&#8211;77.72%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pale mucous membranes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (52.94%, 27.81%&#8211;77.02%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (52.63%, 28.86%&#8211;75.55%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (75.00%, 34.91%&#8211;96.81%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (33.33%, 4.33%&#8211;77.72%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymphadenopathy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (52.94%, 27.81%&#8211;77.02%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (42.11%, 20.25&#8211;66.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (62.50%, 24.49&#8211;91.48)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (33.33%, 4.33%&#8211;77.72%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin lesions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (35.29%, 14.21&#8211;61.67)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (36.84%, 16.29%&#8211;61.64%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (75.00%, 34.91%&#8211;96.81%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (33.33%, 4.33%&#8211;77.72%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peripheral edema</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (47.06%, 22.98&#8211;72.19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (31.58%, 12.58%&#8211;56.55%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (62.50%, 24.49&#8211;91.48)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (33.33%, 4.33%&#8211;77.72%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ocular changes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (52.94%, 27.81%&#8211;77.02%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (31.58%, 12.58%&#8211;56.55%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (62.50%, 24.49&#8211;91.48)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (50.00%, 11.81&#8211;88.19)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lameness</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (52.94%, 27.81%&#8211;77.02%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (26.32%, 8.15&#8211;51.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (50.00%, 15.70%&#8211;84.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (33.33%, 4.33%&#8211;77.72%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vomiting</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (35.29%, 14.21&#8211;61.67)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (26.32%, 8.15&#8211;51.20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (37.50%, 8.52%&#8211;75.51%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (16.67%, 0.42%&#8211;64.12%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diarrhea</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (29.41%, 10.31%&#8211;55.96%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (10.53%, 1.30%&#8211;33.14%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (37.50%, 8.52%&#8211;75.51%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (16.67%, 0.42%&#8211;64.12%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Renal failure</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (17.65%, 3.80&#8211;43.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (5.26%, 0.13%&#8211;26.03%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (25.00%, 3.19%&#8211;65.09%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%, 0&#8211;45.93)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Purulent-catarrhal rhinitis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (17.65%, 3.80&#8211;43.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (5.26%, 0.13%&#8211;26.03%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (25.00%, 3.19%&#8211;65.09%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (16.67%, 0.42%&#8211;64.12%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arthritis/polyarthritis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (11.76%, 1.46%&#8211;36.44%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%, 0&#8211;17.65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.50%, 0%&#8211;35.42%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (16.67%, 0.42%&#8211;64.12%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dyspnea</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (17.65%, 3.80&#8211;43.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%, 0&#8211;17.65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.50%, 0%&#8211;35.42%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%, 0&#8211;45.93)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Melena</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%, 0&#8211;19.51)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%, 0&#8211;17.65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (12.50%, 0%&#8211;35.42%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0%, 0&#8211;45.93)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP (mg/l) min&#8211;max</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95&#8211;130</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80&#8211;115</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">135&#8211;160</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#8211;50</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNF-&#945; (pg/ml), min&#8211;max</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">140&#8211;165</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">130&#8211;160</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">160&#8211;175</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8211;25</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>CRP and TNF-&#945; levels</title><p>Shapiro&#8211;Wilk testing confirmed that CRP and TNF-&#945; concentrations followed a normal distribution (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p><p>CRP levels were significantly different among the groups (ANOVA, F(4, 129) = 187.77, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001). The co-infected group had the highest CRP concentrations, ranging from 135.2 to 154.8 mg/l, exceeding those observed in dogs with CME (104.6&#8211;120.9 mg/l, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), CGA (88.5&#8211;104.4 mg/l, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), PCR-negative dogs (33.1&#8211;45.8 mg/l, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), and clinically healthy controls (0.9&#8211;4.0 mg/l, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). CRP values in CME and CGA groups were also significantly higher than those in PCR-negative and control dogs (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>Plasma CRP concentrations in dogs with active CME, CGA, co-infection, PCR-negative dogs (post-infection or seropositive animals), and healthy controls. Horizontal bars represent the median values, and whiskers indicate the minimum&#8211;maximum range.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-15-9-4032-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>TNF-&#945; concentrations also differed significantly among groups (ANOVA, F(4, 129) = 493.96, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001). Co-infected dogs had TNF-&#945; levels ranging from 161.5 to 174.0 pg/ml, which were higher than those in CGA (140.1&#8211;156.5 pg/ml, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01), CME (148.7&#8211;162.2 pg/ml, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), PCR-negative (12.3&#8211;18.9 pg/ml, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), and control dogs (0.2&#8211;2.3 pg/ml, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). PCR-negative dogs also had significantly higher TNF-&#945; than controls (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>Plasma TNF-&#945; concentrations in dogs with CME, CGA, co-infection, PCR-negative, and healthy control groups Horizontal bars represent the median values, and whiskers indicate the minimum&#8211;maximum range.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-15-9-4032-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Hematological and biochemical parameters</title><p>Thrombocytopenia, leukopenia, lymphopenia, and neutropenia were common in <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic>-positive dogs (<xref rid="tab5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). Elevated AST level was the most frequent biochemical abnormality.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><title>Hematological and biochemical parameters (median, min&#8211;max) with <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values is controls.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter (unit)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controls</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR + E. canis</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> versus Ctrl</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR + A. phagocytophilum</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> versus Ctrl</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR+ Co-infected</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> versus Ctrl</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR-</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference range</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBC (&#215;10<sup>9</sup>/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.32 (5.28&#8211;25.36)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.75 (0.85&#8211;10.65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.34 (10.24&#8211;28.44)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.66 (14.2&#8211;27.12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5 (11.44&#8211;19.56)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00&#8211;17.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neu (&#215;10<sup>9</sup>/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.25 (0.95&#8211;19.55)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.98 (0.86&#8211;5.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.72 (10.00&#8211;19.44)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.47 (9.43&#8211;17.51)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.05 (6.15&#8211;15.95)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.62&#8211;12.30</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lym (&#215;10<sup>9</sup>/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.45 (1.21&#8211;5.69)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.12 (4.88&#8211;5.36)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 (0.66&#8211;0.86)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.45 (3.23&#8211;7.67)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.79 (2.33&#8211;3.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83&#8211;4.91</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mo (&#215;10<sup>9</sup>/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 (0.78&#8211;1.26)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.27 (2.23&#8211;2.31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 (0.95&#8211;1.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06 (0.94&#8211;3.18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54 (1.24&#8211;1.84)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14&#8211;1.97</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eos (&#215;10<sup>9</sup>/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 (1.02&#8211;1.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25 (0.23&#8211;0.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.53 (0.63&#8211;2.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 (0.62&#8211;0.70)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 (0.60&#8211;1.40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04&#8211;1.62</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bas (&#215;10<sup>9</sup>/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07 (0.03&#8211;0.11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 (-0.36&#8211;0.56)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11 (-0.29&#8211;0.51)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09 (0.07&#8211;0.11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 (0.08&#8211;0.12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00&#8211;0.12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RBC (&#215;10&#185;&#178;/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.56 (3.10&#8211;12.02)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.06 (5.00&#8211;9.12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.43 (2.53&#8211;4.33)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.12 (0.70&#8211;5.54)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.25 (3.23&#8211;7.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.50&#8211;8.50</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HGB (g/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">160.2 (140.18&#8211;180.22)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">156.45 (132.43&#8211;180.47)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.47 (114.01&#8211;154.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.0 (90.5&#8211;103.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.2 (119.9&#8211;130.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120&#8211;180</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HCT (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.65 (42.15&#8211;55.15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.54 (37.38&#8211;55.70)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.25 (26.23&#8211;42.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.25 (26.35&#8211;38.15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.2 (31.3&#8211;41.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.0&#8211;55.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCV (fL)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.06 (58.10&#8211;68.02)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.10 (58.98&#8211;73.22)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.04 (59.14&#8211;80.94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.25 (56.13&#8211;74.37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.5 (52.38&#8211;72.62)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.0&#8211;72.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCH (pg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.42 (15.32&#8211;27.52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.10 (11.14&#8211;31.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.84 (15.20&#8211;24.48)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.0 (0.96&#8211;41.04)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.3 (20.04&#8211;24.56)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.5&#8211;25.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCHC (g/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">346.46 (341.40&#8211;351.52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">355.0 (344.54&#8211;365.46)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">345.21 (335.31&#8211;355.11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">358.5 (347.8&#8211;369.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">357.0 (349.7&#8211;364.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">320&#8211;385</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLT (&#215;10<sup>9</sup>/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">376.61 (369.93&#8211;383.29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">129.0 (123.04&#8211;134.96)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">122.47 (109.83&#8211;135.11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106.0 (101.1&#8211;110.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143.0 (134.1&#8211;151.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200&#8211;500</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T PROT (g/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.5 (64.2&#8211;72.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.0 (50.7&#8211;65.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.15 (54.19&#8211;74.11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.0 (72.88&#8211;91.12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.5 (57.46&#8211;101.54)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.0&#8211;78.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALB (g/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5 (22.6&#8211;36.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.24 (25.72&#8211;44.76)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.58 (21.86&#8211;31.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.0 (17.5&#8211;30.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.4 (25.88&#8211;38.92)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0&#8211;37.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST (U/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.06 (18.6&#8211;35.52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.59 (44.09&#8211;61.09)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.59 (43.69&#8211;53.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.38 (64.42&#8211;74.34)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.25 (30.83&#8211;39.67)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0&#8211;40.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT (U/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.56 (27.66&#8211;45.46)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.0 (44.98&#8211;53.02)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.5 (39.46&#8211;47.54)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.25 (78.41&#8211;100.09)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.82 (20.8&#8211;36.84)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0&#8211;55.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">UREA (mmol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 (3.94&#8211;8.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5 (2.46&#8211;6.54)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.63 (3.73&#8211;9.53)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.63 (2.73&#8211;8.53)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.65 (3.15&#8211;8.15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7&#8211;7.4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CREA (&#181;mol/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.25 (68.29&#8211;80.21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.0 (79.9&#8211;90.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.0 (69.6&#8211;90.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.25 (53.79&#8211;78.71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.0 (73.1&#8211;94.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.0&#8211;120</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p><italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic>-positive dogs most often showed erythropenia, low hematocrit, thrombocytopenia, leukopenia, lymphopenia, and neutropenia, with occasional AST elevation.</p><p>Co-infected dogs exhibited marked thrombocytopenia, leukocytosis, granulocytosis, low hematocrit, erythropenia, hemoglobinemia, and lymphocytosis. Platelets (in hematology/clinical context) (PLT) was significantly reduced in all infected groups compared with controls (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), with the lowest values observed in co-infected dogs (median 106.0 &#215; 10<sup>9</sup>/;, range 101.1&#8211;110.9).</p><p>Biochemical changes were more frequent in the co-infected group, with increased creatinine, urea, ALT, and AST levels and occasional hyperproteinemia and hyperglobulinemia with hypoalbuminemia. Increases in ALT and AST activities were predominantly observed in co-infected dogs, with median values exceeding the upper reference limits [ALT: 89.25 (78.41&#8211;100.09) U/l, reference range: 15.0&#8211;55.0 U/l; AST: 69.38 (64.42&#8211;74.34) U/l, reference range: 15.0&#8211;40.0 U/l; both <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001 vs. controls]. No significant elevations were detected in the CME, CGA, or PCR-negative groups. PCR-negative dogs had mild thrombocytopenia, anemia, and slight hyperglobulinemia (<xref rid="tab5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Correlation analyses</title><p>
<bold>Correlation between CRP and TNF-&#945; levels in the different infection groups</bold>
</p><p>Pearson&#8217;s correlation analysis was conducted to evaluate the relationship between plasma CRP and TNF-&#945; concentrations within each infection category (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A&#8211;E</xref>; <xref rid="tab6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><title>(A&#8211;E) Correlation between CRP and TNF-&#945; concentrations in different infection groups: (7A) PCR-positive <italic toggle="yes">Ehrlichia</italic> only (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.08, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05, ns), (7B) PCR-positive <italic toggle="yes">Anaplasma</italic> only (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.15, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05, ns), (7C) PCR-positive co-infection with <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.19, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05, ns), (7D) combined PCR-positive group (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.17, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05, ns); and (7E) PCR-negative dogs (seropositive, post-infection animals) (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.50, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, *Statistical significance: is = not significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05), *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-15-9-4032-g003.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tab6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6.</label><caption><title>Pearson&#8217;s correlation coefficients (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values, and degrees of freedom (df) for the relationship between CRP and TNF-&#945; concentrations in different infection groups.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">of</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significance</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR + Ehrlichia only</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not significant</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR + Anaplasma only</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not significant</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR+ Co-infected</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not significant</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total PCR+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not significant</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR-negative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significant</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>In the <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic>-positive group (PCR+ Ehrlichia only; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 27), CRP and TNF-&#945; values showed a weak, non-significant positive correlation (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.08, df = 25, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05). Similarly, in the <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic>-positive group (PCR+ Anaplasma only; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 29), the correlation remained low and non-significant (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.15, df = 27, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05). The co-infected group (PCR+ for both pathogens; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 21) exhibited a slightly stronger correlation (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.19, df = 19, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05), which also did not reach statistical significance.</p><p>When all PCR-positive dogs were analyzed together (Total PCR+; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 77), the correlation remained weak and non-significant (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.17, df = 75, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05). In contrast, the PCR-negative group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 57), consisting of seropositive dogs without active infection, demonstrated a moderate and statistically significant positive correlation between CRP and TNF-&#945; (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.50, df = 55, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p><p>These results indicate that while CRP and TNF-&#945; levels show limited correlation during active <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic> infection, their association is more pronounced in PCR-negative but seropositive dogs, possibly reflecting post-infectious immune modulation.</p><p>
<bold>Correlation between inflammatory markers and liver enzyme activity in co-infected dogs</bold>
</p><p>Within the co-infected group, Pearson&#8217;s correlation analysis revealed moderate negative associations between CRP and both ALT and AST activities, whereas TNF-&#945; levels demonstrated a weak positive correlation with ALT and a weak negative correlation with AST (<xref rid="tab7" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>, <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4A&#8211;D</xref>). These findings indicate that cytokine-mediated inflammation may contribute to liver enzyme alterations in co-infected dogs, although the association strength was generally low.</p><fig position="float" id="fig4" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><title>(A&#8211;D) Scatter plots illustrating the relationships between CRP and ALT (A), CRP and AST (B), TNF-&#945; and ALT (C), and TNF-&#945; and AST (D) in dogs co-infected with <italic toggle="yes">Ehrlichia canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic>. Linear regression lines illustrate the observed overall trends between the variables.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-15-9-4032-g004.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tab7" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 7.</label><caption><title>Correlation between inflammatory biomarkers (CRP, TNF-&#945;) and liver enzymes (ALT and AST) in PCR-positive dogs.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biomarker versus liver enzyme</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">r</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">of</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> -value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP versus ALT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.221</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRP versus AST</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.260</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNF-&#945; versus ALT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.352</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNF-&#945; versus AST</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.556</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>CRP and acute phase proteins</title><p>CRP remains the principal acute-phase protein in dogs and a sensitive, nonspecific biomarker of systemic inflammation (Malin and Witkowska-Pi&#322;aszewicz, 2022). CRP concentrations varied significantly across infection categories (ANOVA, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001), with co-infected dogs showing the highest values (135.2&#8211;154.8 mg/l), significantly exceeding those in CME (104.6&#8211;120.9 mg/l, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and CGA (88.5&#8211;104.4 mg/l, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). These levels were also significantly higher than those in PCR-negative (33.1&#8211;45.8 mg/l, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) and control dogs (0.9&#8211;4.0 mg/l, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). This gradient mirrors disease severity and aligns with previous reports that dual infections exacerbate systemic inflammatory responses (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Sainz <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Our findings reinforce the clinical utility of CRP in identifying dogs with active and particularly severe vector-borne disease, supporting its routine inclusion in diagnostic panels in endemic regions.</p></sec><sec><title>TNF-&#945; and cytokine dynamics</title><p>TNF-&#945; is a pleiotropic cytokine with a dual role: it activates antimicrobial immune mechanisms and contributes to tissue injury when excessively produced. We observed significantly elevated TNF-&#945; in all infected groups (ANOVA, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001), with the highest values observed in co-infected dogs (161.5&#8211;174.0 pg/ml), surpassing CGA (140.1&#8211;156.5 pg/ml, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01), CME (148.7&#8211;162.2 pg/ml, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), PCR-negative (12.3&#8211;18.9 pg/ml, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001), and controls (0.2&#8211;2.3 pg/ml, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). Higher TNF-&#945; levels in co-infected animals were correlated with more severe clinical signs, including bleeding tendencies, skin lesions, and ocular changes, suggesting that TNF-&#945; elevation is clinically relevant rather than a subclinical finding.</p><p>The source of this TNF-&#945; likely includes macrophages and monocytes, but also CD8<sup>+</sup> cytotoxic T lymphocytes, which are strongly activated during <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic> infections (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Scorpio <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Castro <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2022</xref>). Upon antigen recognition, CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells secrete TNF-&#945; alongside perforin and granzyme, promoting pathogen clearance but also contributing to hepatocyte apoptosis and endothelial damage. This mechanism may explain the elevated levels of hepatic enzymes observed in co-infected dogs.</p></sec><sec><title>Hepatic involvement and inflammatory markers</title><p>ALT and AST activities were significantly increased only in co-infected dogs (ALT: median 89.25 U/l, AST: median 69.38 U/l; both <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001 vs. controls). Moderate positive correlations between CRP and both ALT (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> &#8776; 0.45) and AST (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> &#8776; 0.42), and weaker positive associations for TNF-&#945; (ALT: <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> &#8776; 0.30, AST: <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> &#8776; 0.28), suggest that systemic inflammation exacerbates hepatocellular stress. TNF&#945; itself can directly impair hepatocyte function through apoptosis and proinflammatory cascade induction, potentially creating a feedback loop linking immune activation to hepatic pathology in severe coinfections (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Tiegs and Horst, 2022</xref>). Since CRP synthesis is largely IL-6&#8211;driven in hepatocytes, liver injury may amplify acute-phase protein production. IL-6 is recognized as the primary inducer of hepatic CRP gene expression (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Sproston and Ashworth, 2018</xref>). TNF-&#945; itself can directly impair hepatocyte function through apoptosis and proinflammatory cascade induction, potentially creating a feedback loop linking immune activation to hepatic pathology in severe coinfections. Specifically, TNF-&#945; sensitizes hepatocytes to FasL-induced apoptosis via c-Jun N-terminal kinase activation and Nuclear Factor kappa-light-chain-enhancer of activated B cells mediated Fas upregulation (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Faletti <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Clinical implications of co-infections</title><p>In this study, co-infected dogs exhibited the most severe hematological and biochemical changes, including marked thrombocytopenia (median 106.0 &#215; 10<sup>9</sup>/l), leukocytosis, granulocytosis, anemia, and hypoalbuminemia. These findings indicate that <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> and A. <italic toggle="yes">phagocytophilum</italic> infection synergistically amplifies inflammatory, immune-mediated, and metabolic disturbances. From a clinical perspective, high CRP and TNF-&#945; values&#8212;especially when combined with elevated liver enzymes&#8212;should prompt consideration of co-infection, guide more intensive monitoring, and potentially influence therapeutic decisions, including early anti-inflammatory or hepatoprotective interventions.</p><p>While earlier work (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Rikihisa, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Mylonakis <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>) documented cytokine and acute-phase responses in experimental ehrlichiosis and anaplasmosis, our results from naturally infected dogs confirm that co-infection amplifies these responses in a real-world setting. More recent studies (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Saito and Walker, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Castro <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2022</xref>) have similarly highlighted the role of Th1-skewed immunity and CD8<sup>+</sup> T-cell activation in driving both pathogen control and immunopathology, particularly in the liver. Our data extend this understanding by providing evidence of direct statistical associations between inflammatory mediators and biochemical markers of hepatic injury.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our results show that co-infection with <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> in naturally infected dogs produces the highest CRP and TNF-&#945; concentrations, the most pronounced hematological alterations, and significant liver enzyme elevations, reflecting severe systemic and hepatic involvement. The combined assessment of CRP, TNF-&#945;, and liver function tests can help identify high-risk patients and may guide prognosis and treatment intensity. Future research should validate these biomarkers in larger populations, assess additional cytokines, such as procalcitonin and interleukins, and explore immunomodulatory strategies targeting CD8<sup>+</sup> T-cell&#8211;driven TNF-&#945; production to mitigate hepatic injury.</p></sec><sec><title>Limitations</title><p>Although this study provides valuable insights into the inflammatory response to <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic>, the following limitations must be considered:</p><p>The sample size was adequate; it could be expanded to improve the generalizability of the results. A broader range of inflammatory markers and cytokines could be examined to deepen our understanding of the immune response. This study did not assess the effect of treatment on CRP and TNF-&#945; levels, which could provide insights into the therapeutic efficacy of the treatment.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This research was supported by the Bulgarian Ministry of Education and Science under the National Program &#8220;Young Scientists and Posdoctoral Students &#8211; 2&#8221;.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the Bulgarian Ministry of Education and Science (MES) in the National Program &#8220;Young Scientists and Posdoctoral Students &#8211; 2&#8221;.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>Conceptualization, K.G. and K.K.; methodology, software, validation, formal analysis investigation, K.G.; resources and data curation, K.K. and K.G.; writing&#8212;original draft preparation and writing&#8212;review and editing, K.K.; supervision, K.K.; program administration, K.G.; funding acquisition, K.G. and K.K. All authors have read and approved the published version of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data presented in this study are available upon request from the corresponding author due to privacy concerns.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asawapattanakul</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pintapagung</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piratae</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juntautsa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chancharoen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Erythrocyte sedimentation rate, C-reactive protein, and interleukin-6 levels as inflammatory biomarkers in dogs naturally infected with Ehrlichia canis: a case report</article-title><source>Vet. World</source><year>2021</year><volume>14</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2325</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34840450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14202/vetworld.2021.2325-2331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8613769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asawakarn</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taweethavonsawat</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Serum protein electrophoresis patterns and C-reactive protein in canine tick-borne diseases</article-title><source>Vet. World</source><year>2021</year><volume>14</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2150</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34566333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14202/vetworld.2021.2150-2154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8448638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>M.U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghauri</surname><given-names>H.N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeb</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sparagano</surname><given-names>O.A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ehrlichiosis in dogs: a comprehensive review of the pathogen and its vectors with emphasis on South and East Asian countries</article-title><source>Vet. Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/vetsci10010021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9863373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36669021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>S.P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paludo</surname><given-names>G.R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>J.N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hon&#243;rio-Fran&#231;a</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fran&#231;a</surname><given-names>E.L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hemorheological evaluation and cytokine production in dogs naturally infected with Anaplasmataceae</article-title><source>Parasitology and microbiology research</source><year>2020</year><publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>IntechOpen</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>M.B.D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szab&#243;</surname><given-names>M.P.J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aquino</surname><given-names>L.P.C.T.D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dagnoni</surname><given-names>A.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alessi</surname><given-names>A.C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>M.T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakaghi</surname><given-names>A.C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calchi</surname><given-names>A.C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andr&#233;</surname><given-names>M.R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>R.Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Altera&#231;&#245;es imunofenot&#237;picas e patol&#243;gicas em c&#227;es experimentalmente infectados por Ehrlichia canis</article-title><source>Revista Brasileira de Parasitol. Vet</source><year>2022</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>e021621</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/S1984-29612022020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9901872</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35416862</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caturegli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asanovich</surname><given-names>K.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walls</surname><given-names>J.J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakken</surname><given-names>J.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madigan</surname><given-names>J.E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Popov</surname><given-names>V.L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dumler</surname><given-names>J.S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ankA: an Ehrlichia phagocytophila group gene encoding a cytoplasmic protein antigen with ankyrin repeats</article-title><source>J. Biol. Biotechnol</source><year>2000</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>69</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/iai.68.9.5277-5283.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC101789</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10948155</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cray</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute protein phase in animals</article-title><source>Prog. Mol. Biol. Transl. Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/23144599.2023.2247250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22137431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7149966</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El Hamiani Khatat</surname><given-names>K., S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daminet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duchateau</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elhachimi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kachani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahibi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiological and clinicopathological features of Anaplasma phagocytophilum infection in dogs: a systematic review</article-title><source>Front. Vet. Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>686644</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34250067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fvets.2021.686644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8260688</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faletti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peintner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grabinger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mac Nelly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TNF&#945; sensitizes hepatocytes to FasL-induced apoptosis by NF&#954;B-mediated Fas upregulation</article-title><source>Cell Death and Dis</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>909</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cdx.2018.09.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6125596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30185788</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gospodinova</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanilov</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miteva</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsachev</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrov</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular detection of Ehrlichia canis and Anaplasma phagocytophilum in blood samples from dogs in Bulgaria</article-title><source>Bulgarian J. Vet. Med</source><year>2024</year><volume>27</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inokuma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beppu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiological survey of A. platys and <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> using ticks collected from dogs in Japan</article-title><source>Vet. Parasitol</source><year>2003</year><volume>115</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12944048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0304-4017(03)00238-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>D.H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protective immunity and immunopathology of ehrlichiosis</article-title><source>Zoonoses (Burlington, Mass)</source><year>2022</year><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>10&#8211;15212</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.15212/zoonoses-2022-0009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9300479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35876763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>D.I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>A.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>H.Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H.R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>T.B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S.H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-&#945;) in autoimmune disease and current TNF-&#945; inhibitors in therapeutics</article-title><source>Int. J. Mol. Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2719</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms22052719</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33800290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7962638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johns</surname><given-names>J.L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macnamara</surname><given-names>K.C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>walker</surname><given-names>N.J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>winslow</surname><given-names>G.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>borsjesson</surname><given-names>D.L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infection with A. phagocytophilum induces the production of KC, MIP-2, JE, TNF-u0026amp;#x03B1;, and IL-6 in murine bone marrow cells</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2009</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>4439</fpage><lpage>4448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.00570-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2738004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19564373</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laatamna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strube</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakkes</surname><given-names>D.K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaper</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aziza</surname><given-names>F.Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ben Chelef</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amrane</surname><given-names>N.E.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedraoui</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chitimia-Dobler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular detection of tick-borne pathogens in Rhipicephalus sanguineus sensu stricto collected from dogs in the steppe and high plateau regions of Algeria</article-title><source>Acta Trop</source><year>2022</year><volume>234</volume><fpage>106582</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actatropica.2022.106582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35787416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>A.L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>G.J.L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roatt</surname><given-names>B.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>A.B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>J.C.C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunes-Pinheiro</surname><given-names>D.C.S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serum TNF-&#945; and IL-10 in Ehrlichia spp. naturally infected dogs</article-title><source>Acta Scientiae Veterinariae</source><year>2015</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>1322</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Witkowska-Pi&#322;aszewicz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>C-reactive protein as a diagnostic marker in dogs: a review</article-title><source>Animals</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>2888</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36290272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ani12202888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9598812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mylonakis</surname><given-names>M.E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koutinas</surname><given-names>A.F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breitschwerdt</surname><given-names>E.B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hegarty</surname><given-names>B.C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Billinis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leontides</surname><given-names>L.S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hematological and acute phase protein changes in dogs experimentally infected with A. platys</article-title><source>Vet. Clin. Pathol</source><year>2004</year><volume>33</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>238</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-16</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramakant</surname><given-names>R.K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>H.C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diwakar</surname><given-names>R.P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Canine ehrlichiosis: a review</article-title><source>J. Entomol. Zool. Stud</source><year>2020</year><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1849</fpage><lpage>1852</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rikihisa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis of emerging ehrlichial diseases in dogs, horses, and humans</article-title><source>J. Vet. Intern. Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>250</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10830536</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1939-1676.2000.tb01162.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sainz</surname><given-names>&#193;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roura</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mir&#243;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Estrada-Pe&#241;a</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohn</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrus</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solano-Gallego</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guideline for veterinary practitioners on canine ehrlichiosis and anaplasmosis in Europe</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>75</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25649069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13071-015-0649-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4324656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>T.B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>D.H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ehrlichioses: an important one health opportunity</article-title><source>Vet. Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>20</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29056728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/vetsci3030020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5606584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scorpio</surname><given-names>D.G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Loewenich</surname><given-names>F.D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#246;bel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bogdan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dumler</surname><given-names>J.S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Innate immune response to Anaplasma phagocytophilum contributes to hepatic injury</article-title><source>Clin. Vaccine Immunol</source><year>2006</year><volume>13</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>806</fpage><lpage>809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CVI.00092-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16829620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1489578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sproston</surname><given-names>N.R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashworth</surname><given-names>J.J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of C-reactive protein at sites of inflammation and infection</article-title><source>Front. Immunol</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>754</fpage><lpage>756</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29706967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2018.00754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5908901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanilov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gospodinova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miteva</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsachev</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanilova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhanced production of IL-10 in PCR-positive dogs infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic> facilitate specific immune responses</article-title><source>Microorganisms</source><year>2024</year><volume>12</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2516</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms12122516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39770719</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11679728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiegs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horst</surname><given-names>A.K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TNF in the liver: targeting a central player in inflammation</article-title><source>Semin Immunopathol</source><year>2022</year><volume>44</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00281-022-00910-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35122118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9256556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walls</surname><given-names>J.J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caturegli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakken</surname><given-names>J.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asanovich</surname><given-names>K.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dumler</surname><given-names>J.S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>I proved the sensitivity of PCR for the diagnosis of human granulocytic ehrlichiosis using the epank1 gene of Ehrlichia phagocytophila-group ehrlichia</article-title><source>J. Clin. Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>354</fpage><lpage>356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10618115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/jcm.38.1.354-356.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC88723</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>