<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2846</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">openvetj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Veterinary Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2226-4485</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2218-6050</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tripoli</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11682755</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11682755.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11682755</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11682755</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39737033</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/OVJ.2024.v14.i11.11</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OVJ-14-2827</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Investigating the effect of quail egg supplementation enriched with marine macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">Eucheuma spinosum</italic> on hematological indices, lipid profile parameters, and blood glucose level of Sprague Dawley rats during lactation and offspring growth</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Basri</surname><given-names initials="H">Hasan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Widiyanto</surname><given-names initials="S">Slamet</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saragih</surname><given-names initials="HTSSG">Hendry T. S. S. G.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuprizal</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zuprizal</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Biology Doctoral Study Program, Faculty of Biology, Universitas Gadjah Mada, Yogyakarta, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Biology Study Program, Faculty of Mathematics and Natural Sciences, Universitas Islam Al-Azhar, Mataram, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Animal Physiology, Faculty of Biology, Universitas Gadjah Mada, Yogyakarta, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Laboratory of Animal Development Structure, Faculty of Biology, Universitas Gadjah Mada, Yogyakarta, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Animal Nutrition and Feed Science, Faculty of Animal Science, Universitas Gadjah Mada, Yogyakarta, Indonesia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Slamet Widiyanto. Department of Animal Physiology, Faculty of Biology, Universitas Gadjah Mada, Yogyakarta, Indonesia. <email>slametbio@ugm.ac.id</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>11</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">477914</issue-id><fpage>2827</fpage><lpage>2836</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-12-31 15:25:20.740"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2827.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>The lactation period is a crucial period where the nutritional status and the mother&#8217;s environment influence milk production, impacting organ differentiation, function, and structure in the baby&#8217;s body.</p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>The study aimed to determine the impact of providing lactating rats with quail egg supplements enriched with marine macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">Eucheuma</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">spinosum</italic> on their physiological condition (blood cells, lipids, blood glucose, antioxidant activity, and prolactin hormone levels) and the growth of their offspring.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods:</title><p>The study involved 25 lactating Sprague Dawley white rats aged 3 months old and weighing approximately 200 g divided into five treatment groups thus; T0 as the control, T1 with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed, T2 with quail eggs enriched with 3% of marine macroalgae, T3 with quail eggs enriched with 4% of marine macroalgae, and T4 with quail eggs enriched with 5% of marine macroalgae, which received one quail egg for 21 days. At the end of the study period, the following parameters were assayed: vitamin A, iodine, weight and body length of rat pups, red blood cell count, hemoglobin levels, hematocrit, mean corpuscular volume, mean corpuscular hemoglobin, mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration, white blood cell count, lymphocytes, neutrophils, red blood cell distribution width, platelet distribution width, and mean platelet volume. Also, cholesterol levels, high-density lipoprotein, low-density lipoprotein, blood glucose levels, prolactin hormone, antioxidant activity with SOD and MDA.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>The study result found that adding marine macroalgae to the quail feed significantly increased the vitamin A and iodine content in the quail egg yolks. Furthermore, the weight and body length of the rat pups in the supplemented groups significantly increased (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) compared to the control group. However, it did not have a significant impact (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05) on the rats&#8217; blood parameters, cholesterol, blood glucose, antioxidant activity, and prolactin hormone levels.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>In conclusion, providing lactating rats with quail eggs enriched with marine macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic> support the growth and development of the rat offspring without negatively impacting the rats&#8217; overall health parameters.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Marine macroalgae</kwd><kwd>Quail eggs</kwd><kwd>Lactation</kwd><kwd>Haematological</kwd><kwd>Antioxidant activity</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Lactation is a crucial period where the nutritional status and the mother's environment influence milk production, impacting organ differentiation, function, and structure in the baby's body (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Marshall <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Carretero-Krug <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). The lactation period begins with milk secretion and includes all changes in the mammary glands from the beginning of pregnancy to the breastfeeding period (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Neville <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). During lactation, nutritional needs increase compared to normal conditions. These nutrients are utilized to increase blood volume, as well as the growth of mammary glands in preparation for breastfeeding and to increase body metabolism. Inadequate nutrition during lactation can lead to decreased milk production, complications for the mother and baby, an increased risk of cardiovascular disease (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Crozier <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Dos <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Biberoglu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2016</xref>), and causes oxidative stress due to excessive metabolic load during lactation (<xref rid="ref61" ref-type="bibr">Toy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Berchieri-Ronchi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2011</xref>). These nutritional needs must be maintained from pregnancy to lactation. Complete nutrition is essential for recovery after childbirth and preparation for milk production. The nutritional requirements for milk formation are particularly high because breast milk is the sole source of nutrition for children's growth and development (<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">Prawitasari <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). Under normal conditions, breast milk provides all the nutritional needs for growth, development, and the child's immunological response (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Lokossou <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). The calories expended during lactation by the mother must be balanced with nutritional intake for the energy obtained from food to be used for milk production (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Kim and Yi, 2020</xref>).</p><p>Balanced energy and protein supplementation can increase fetal growth and reduce the risk of fetal mortality at birth, low birth weight, and delivery at early gestational age, particularly in pregnant and lactating mothers who are malnourished (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Imdad and Bhutta, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">Salmuth <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). Furthermore, various important micronutrients are necessary for achieving nutritional needs during breastfeeding, including folic acid, calcium, iron, zinc, iodine, and vitamins (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Delange, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">Mousa <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). Most nutritional needs are provided through the food consumed by the parent. Quail eggs known for their high nutritional content, are a readily available functional food source that can be further enriched through the feed provided, offering essential nutrients for the growth and development of the fetal (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">Miranda <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">Jeke <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>). The nutritional content of quail eggs includes fat, protein, carbohydrates, fiber, essential fatty acids, vitamins, minerals, lipids, and bioactive compounds as antioxidants (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Basri <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). The nutritional value of quail eggs can be enhanced by using appropriate feed additives, such as macroalgae. Macroalgae can be used as a valuable source of feed additives due to their abundant availability and easy access of the resource. Furthermore, the nutritional composition of macroalgae comprises carbohydrates, protein, lipids, minerals, dietary fiber, amino acids, and bioactive compounds, all of which are potentially suitable for inclusion in quail feed (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">&#216;verland <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Kulshreshtha <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>)<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> Macroalgae can be used as feed additives to improve health, productivity, and the overall quality of meat and eggs (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Hajati and Zaghari, 2019</xref>)<bold>.</bold> Previous studies on the addition of macroalgae, specifically <italic toggle="yes">Macrocystis</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">pyrifera</italic> flour, has been found to increase the nutritional content of chicken eggs (<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">Rend&#243;n <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2003</xref>).</p><p>Limited research has been conducted on the impact of quail eggs enriched with marine macroalgae as a nutritional supplement during lactation. Previous studies have found that consuming chicken eggs and milk during lactation can significantly increase breastmilk production (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Achalapong, 2016</xref>). Similarly, studies on administering egg protein have indicated a significant increase in the weight and body length of rat pups (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">Naeem <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). Furthermore, a study involving the supplementation of one organic quail egg per day to hematology showed no significant differences in results; however, it was observed that organic quail egg supplementation could maintain the hematological status of erythrocytes, hemoglobin (Hb), and blood pH in lactating white rats (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Basri <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>). Based on these findings, the objective of this study is to investigate the effects of quail eggs enriched with <italic toggle="yes">Eucheuma spinosum</italic> on the physiological condition of lactating rats including hematological indicies, lipid profile parameters, blood glucose, antioxidant activity, and the hormone prolactin, the weight and body length of rat pups.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Study area</title><p>The research was conducted at the Integrated Research and Testing Laboratory, Tropical Livestock Research Center Laboratory, Faculty of Animal Husbandry, Gadjah Mada University.</p></sec><sec><title>Procedures</title><p>Female Sprague Dawley rats were used in the study. The rats were housed at 26&#176;C with 70% humidity under artificial lighting (12 hours light and 12 hours dark) (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Gopalakrishnan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>). They were fed for 15 hours (17:00&#8211;07:00), a 9-hour fasting period (08:00&#8211;16:00), and ad libitum access to feed and drinking water. The rats were given standard feed (Rat Bio) produced by PT. Citra Ina Feed Mill contains 60% carbohydrates, 20% protein, 4% fat, 4% crude fiber, 12% calcium, and 0.7% phosphorus. The study treatment involved quail eggs enriched with marine macroalgae of the <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic> (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). Each rat was given one quail egg per day for 21 days, with the eggs boiled for 2 minutes and then cut into small pieces before being given to the rats every day at 16:00 (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Basri <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Research design</title><p>This is an experimental study with a completely randomized design. The study used 25 lactating white Sprague-Dawley rats aged 3 months old and weighing around 200 g. The rats were divided into 5 treatments:</p><p>T0: control treatment</p><p>T1: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed</p><p>T2: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed + 3% marine macroalgae</p><p>T3: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed + 4% marine macroalgae</p><p>T4: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed + 5% marine macroalgae.</p><p>Each treatment group consisted of 5 replications, with each replication including 1 lactating white rat. At the end of the lactation period, blood sampling was performed. Blood samples were collected from the orbital sinus of the eye after prior anesthesia using ketamine and xylazine. A 1 ml blood sample was collected using microcapillary hematocrit and placed in an ethylen diamine tetra acetic acid vacutainer tube. The blood samples were then centrifuged at 3,000 rpm speed for 5&#8211;15 minutes.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>Marine macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic>.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2827-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>The mating process of the rats</title><p>The mating process of white rats commences by placing male and female rats in separate cages with transparent bases for 1 day. The initial step involves placing three female white rats, which have undergone the estrus phase, along with one male white rat in a cage measuring 37 &#215; 30 &#215; 20 cm. The mating process typically takes place during nighttime and extends over a period of 5 days.</p></sec><sec><title>Sample analysis method</title><p>The UV-Vis Spectrophotometer method was used to analyze the Vitamin A content (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">Nielsen, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">Nisa <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017</xref>). Additionally, the iodine concentration in egg yolk was determined using the spectrophotometer method at 440 nm (<xref rid="ref60" ref-type="bibr">Sumaiya <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2016</xref>). A complete blood analysis, including RBC, HGB, hematocrit, mean corpuscular volume, mean corpuscular hemoglobin, white blood cell, lymphocytes, neutrophils, red blood cell distribution width, platelet distribution width, and mean platelet volume, was conducted using the hematology analyzer method (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Binev, 2023</xref>). Cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein (HDL), and low-density lipoprotein (LDL) levels were analyzed using the CHOD-PAP method. Blood glucose was measured using the GOD-PAP method, using UV-Vis spectrophotometry (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Apriyanto <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>).</p><p>SOD, MDA, and prolactin hormone levels were measured using an ELISA kit from the Bioassay Technology Laboratory (Shanghai, China). The CAT numbers of each kit were: SOD CAT No. E0168Ra, MDA CAT No. E0156Ra, Prolactine CAT No. E0190Ra. The development of rat pups was observed, including body weight gain measured using a digital scale with an accuracy of 0.01 g and body length observed using a caliper (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Mahmood <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">Iwansyah <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Data analysis</title><p>The data obtained were analyzed using variance, and if a significant difference was found, the Duncan test was conducted at a 95% significance level. The analysis was performed using SPSS 22 for Windows software.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>The study was carried out with approval from the Ethical Clearance Commission of the Integrated Research and Testing Laboratory (LPPT) at Gadjah Mada University, with the number 00026/04/LPPT/VIII/2023.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The vitamin A and iodine content in quail eggs significantly increased (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the T1, T2, and T3 groups compared to the control group (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The highest increase in vitamin A content was observed in the T2 group. This increase in vitamin A levels was attributed to the addition of <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic> to the quail feed. The vitamin A content in <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic> was 31.56 &#181;g/100 g, and it increased the highest vitamin A content to 87.12 &#177; 1.71 &#181;g/100 g in quail-fed 4% marine macroalgae. The marine macroalgae species <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic> contains 57.77 ppm of iodine. Quail eggs supplemented with 4% marine macroalgae feed have the highest iodine content at 12.01 &#177; 0.1 ppm (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>The body weight and body length of the rat pups were measured every week to determine the effects of the treatments (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Results of the body weight and body length of the rat pups on days 7, 14, and 21 showed a significant increase (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) compared to the control group (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The administration of quail eggs to groups T1, T2, T3, and T4 significantly increased the body weight and body length of the rat pups compared to treatment T0. The highest increase in body weight and body length of the rat pups was found in group T4, while the lowest values were found in the control group.</p><p>Providing lactating rats with quail egg supplements enriched with marine macroalgae did not result in any significant changes in the levels of various hematological parameters compared to the control group (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The lipid components examined in this study were cholesterol, HDL, LDL, blood glucose, SOD, MDA and prolactin hormone. According to the results, cholesterol, HDL, LDL, blood glucose, SOD, MDA, and prolactin hormone levels did not show significant changes compared to the control group (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Vitamin A and iodine content</title><p>The concentration of vitamin A in egg yolk is closely linked to the concentration of vitamin A in the feed consumed by poultry (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Lima and Souza, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">Mel&#233;ndez-Mart&#237;nez, 2019</xref>). Previous studies have shown that providing macroalgal extract can increase the vitamin A content in broilers egg (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Ivarsson <italic toggle="yes">et al.,</italic> 2023</xref>). It is important to note that vitamins are required in small amounts but play a critical role in primary biological functions such as growth, embryonic development, epithelial cell differentiation, and immune function. Vitamin A deficiency can lead to various disorders, including lack of appetite, decreased development and immunity, and increased disease susceptibility (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">Khan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). The process of transferring vitamin A from the feed to quail eggs involves the absorption of vitamin A from the feed consumed by the quail, which is then stored in the egg yolk. Since vitamin A is fat-soluble, it is absorbed along with the fat in the feed and carried to the liver. During egg formation, vitamin A is transferred through the bloodstream to the ovaries for the synthesis of egg yolk precursors (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">Khan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>).</p><p>The high level of iodine in the quail eggs is due to the high transfer of iodine from the feed to the eggs. Previous research has shown that feed containing 13 ppm iodine can increase the iodine content in chicken egg yolks (<xref rid="ref60" ref-type="bibr">Sumaiya <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2016</xref>). Similarly, other studies have indicated a linear correlation between the iodine content in feed mixtures of up to 5 mg/kg and the iodine content in egg yolks (<xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">S&#322;upczynska <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). The iodine in feed is absorbed through the digestive tract and transported via the bloodstream to various tissues and organs, including the ovaries (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Andersson and Braegger, 2022</xref>). The developing egg follicle (ovum) accumulates iodine in the ovary. As the mature egg follicle moves to the oviduct, where the shell and egg white are formed, iodine accumulates in the egg components. Iodine is a micronutrient necessary to produce thyroid hormones, which are essential for regulating metabolism, growth, and development (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Andersson and Braegger, 2022</xref>). Sufficient iodine concentration in breast milk is crucial for providing optimal neonatal thyroid hormones and preventing impaired neurological development in breastfed babies (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Azizi and Smyth, 2009</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Vitamin A (&#181;g/100 g) and iodine (ppm) content in quail eggs enriched with macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic>.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T0</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vitamin A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.57 &#177; 1.88<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.48 &#177; 1.35<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.12 &#177; 1.71<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.03 &#177; 1.21<sup>bc</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iodine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.66 &#177; 0.36<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.29 &#177; 0.67<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.01 &#177; 0.61<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.46 &#177; 0.57<sup>b</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: Different superscripts on the same line indicate significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p </italic>&lt; 0.05). T0: given commercial feed; T1: fed commercial feed + 3% marine macroalgae; T2: fed commercial feed + 4% marine macroalgae; T3: fed commercial feed + 5% marine macroalgae.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Body weight (g) and length (mm) of rat pups supplemented with quail eggs enriched with <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic>.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T0</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Weight</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#8211;7 day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.64 &#177; 0.92<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.60 &#177; 1.40<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.21 &#177; 1.44<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.55 &#177; 0.56<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.69 &#177; 0.51<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8&#8211;14 day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.13 &#177; 1.11<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.04 &#177; 2.78<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.22 &#177; 2.78<sup>bc</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.46 &#177; 0.84<sup>bc</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.03 &#177; 1.18<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8211;21 day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.56 &#177; 2.00<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.38 &#177; 2.75<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.90 &#177; 2.93<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.44 &#177; 2.37<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.35 &#177; 2.62<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Length</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#8211;7 day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.98 &#177; 4.51<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.32 &#177; 2.85<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.95 &#177; 0.53<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.63 &#177; 0.96<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.67 &#177; 0.76<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8&#8211;14 day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.01 &#177; 2.49<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.57 &#177; 5.37<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.10 &#177; 3.84<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.36 &#177; 0.90<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.29 &#177; 1.49<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8211;21 day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.83 &#177; 1.54<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.74 &#177; 3.35<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.23 &#177; 2.75<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.01 &#177; 2.87<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.28 &#177; 3.78<sup>b</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: Different superscripts on the same line indicate significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p </italic>&lt; 0.05). T0: control treatment; T1: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed; T2: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed + 3% marine macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic>; T3: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed + 4% marine macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic>; T4: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed + 5% marine macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum.</italic></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Hematology profile of lactating rats given quail eggs supplementation enriched with macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic>.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T0</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RBC (&#215;10 <sup>6 </sup>/&#181;l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.22 &#177; 0.30<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.09 &#177; 0.28<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.19 &#177; 0.30<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.28 &#177; 0.21<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.37 &#177; 0.23<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hb (g/dl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.22 &#177; 0.20<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.06 &#177; 0.27<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.18 &#177; 0.42<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.64 &#177; 0.35<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.46 &#177; 0.44<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HCT (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.06 &#177; 0.96<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.68 &#177; 7.63<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.76 &#177; 1.12<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.80 &#177; 1.53<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.04 &#177; 1.44<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCV (fl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.60 &#177; 1.25<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.97 &#177; 1.69<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.52 &#177; 1.24<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.57 &#177; 0.73<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.27 &#177; 0.25<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCH (pg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.52 &#177; 0.53<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.92 &#177; 0.72<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.87 &#177; 0.78<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.95 &#177; 0.24<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.67 &#177; 0.17<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCHC (g/dl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.66 &#177; 0.87<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.90 &#177; 0.38<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.96 &#177; 0.67<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.22 &#177; 0.68<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.60 &#177; 0.25<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBC &#215;10 <sup>3 </sup>/&#181;l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.22 &#177; 0.69<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.08 &#177; 1.21<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.10 &#177; 1.07<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.04 &#177; 0.65<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.12 &#177; 0.86<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LYM (&#215;10 <sup>3 </sup>/&#181;l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60 &#177; 0.48<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.92 &#177; 1.10<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.44 &#177; 0.62<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.60 &#177; 0.60<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42 &#177; 0.25<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NEUT (&#215;10 <sup>3 </sup>/&#181;l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62 &#177; 0.31<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16 &#177; 0.50<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66 &#177; 0.74<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44 &#177; 0.29<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70 &#177; 0.68<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RDW (fl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.22 &#177; 0.82<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.32 &#177; 5.67<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.86 &#177; 1.60<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.62 &#177; 1.28<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.18 &#177; 1.79<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDW (fl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.08 &#177; 0.27<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.54 &#177; 0.62<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.18 &#177; 0.47<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.74 &#177; 0.35<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.32 &#177; 0.61<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPV(fl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.20 &#177; 0.14<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.50 &#177; 0.31<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.24 &#177; 0.13<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48 &#177; 0.19<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.32 &#177; 0.34<sup>a</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: The same superscript on the same line shows that it is not significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">p </italic>&#707; 0.05). T0: control treatment; T1: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed; T2: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed + 3% marine macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic>; T3: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed + 4% marine macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic>; T4: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed + 5% marine macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum.</italic></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><title>Serum biochemistry, oxidative stress status and prolactin hormone in lactating rats supplemented with quail egg enriched with macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T0</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cholesterol (mg/dl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.25 &#177; 14.00<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.50 &#177; 7.97<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.97 &#177; 2.96<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.27 &#177; 10.16<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.45 &#177; 17.10<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL (mg/dl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.57 &#177; 2.76<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.83 &#177; 2.35<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.67 &#177; 0.93<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.23 &#177; 1.35<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.87 &#177; 4.10<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL (mg/dl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.47 &#177; 4.71<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.63 &#177; 9.62<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.23 &#177; 1.40<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.67 &#177; 3.08<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.90 &#177; 8.46<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose (mg/dl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.93 &#177; 3.07<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.80 &#177; 7.97<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.57 &#177; 10.60<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.17 &#177; 15.47<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.40 &#177; 2.14<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDA (<bold>nmol/ml)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37 &#177; 0.10<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26 &#177; 0.06<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 &#177; 0.64<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 &#177; 0.47<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27 &#177; 0.05<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOD <bold>(ng/ml)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25 &#177; 0.15<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93 &#177; 0.38<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87 &#177; 0.23<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06 &#177; 0.18<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01 &#177; 0.20<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prolactin Hormone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.69 &#177; 5.49<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.87 &#177; 10.60<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.75 &#177; 6.30<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.95 &#177; 7.56<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.96 &#177; 5.92<sup>a</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: The same superscript on the same line shows that it is not significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">p </italic>&#707; 0.05). T0: control treatment; T1: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed; T2: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed + 3% marine macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic>; T3: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed + 4% marine macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic>; T4: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed + 5% marine macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum.</italic></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Body weight and length of rat pups</title><p>There was a linear increase in the body weight and body length of the rat pups starting on days 7, 14, and 21 in the groups given quail egg supplementation. The highest increase in body weight and body length of the rat pups was found in group T4, while the lowest values were found in the control group. Based on these results, it was found that supplementation of quail eggs enriched with <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic> was able to increase the body weight and body length of the rat pups (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).</p><p>Quail eggs enriched with <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic> contain high levels of nutrients, particularly protein. Body length and weight are crucial parameters that need to be measured to understand the impact of high protein intake on the growth of the offspring (<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Pastuszewska <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). Previous research has also reported that providing egg protein to mothers significantly increased the body weight and length of rat pups compared to the control group (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">Naeem <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). Consistent with the previous statement, a high correlation was found between body length and weight with high protein consumption (<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Pastuszewska <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). Another study reported that providing one egg per day for 6 months to children in Ecuador resulted in a 47% reduction in stunting prevalence and a 74% reduction in underweight, thus helping the offspring achieve normal growth (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Iannotti <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>Rat pups aged 21 days after being given treatment, including: T0: control treatment; T1: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed; T2: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed + 3% marine macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic>; T3: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed + 4% marine macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic>; T4: treatment with quail eggs enriched with commercial feed + 5% marine macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">E. Spinosum</italic>.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2827-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Hematological indicies</title><p>Hematological examination is valuable for diagnosing and monitoring metabolic diseases (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Dunlea <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). Hematological status is a useful indicator for assessing health conditions during lactation (<xref rid="ref64" ref-type="bibr">Wrzeci&#324;ska <italic toggle="yes">et al.,</italic> 2023</xref>). Concerning the levels of various hematological parameters, the study results showed that there are no significant changes in the treatment groups compared to the control. <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Basri <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., (2018)</xref> found that there is no impact on red blood cell and Hb levels in lactating white rats when given organic quail eggs and suggested that supplementing lactating rats with quail eggs enriched with marine macroalgae can help maintain their hematological condition and prevent physiological disorders during the lactation period. Normal hematological levels indicate the absence of metabolic disorders, diseases, organ damage, drug influence, or stress in rats (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">Lager and Jordan, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Kuhn <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Gwozdzinski <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Serum biochemistry, oxidative stress status, and prolactin hormone</title><p>This study showed a similar result to the previous research that providing organic quail egg supplements during the lactation period had no impact on the lipid profile parameters such as total cholesterol, LDL, HDL, and triglycerides (<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">Purba <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>). The lack of effect on increasing plasma lipid levels during lactation is attributed to increased distribution of lipids to the placenta and mammary glands to meet the lipid needs of rat offspring (<xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017</xref>). Additionally, the similar feed consumed may have caused the lack of effect of quail egg supplementation on cholesterol, LDL, and HDL levels in lactating rats. The cholesterol content influences cholesterol levels synthesized in the liver and small intestine in the diet (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Caponio <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). The body has a specific mechanism for managing excess cholesterol from food intake, involving reducing endogenous absorption and synthesis, and increasing cholesterol excretion through bile (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Fernandez and Murillo, 2022</xref>). Excess cholesterol in cells inhibits HMG-CoA activity (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Altmann <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>), thus causing the body to maintain a balance in plasma cholesterol levels (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Fernandez and Murillo, 2022</xref>). Cholesterol is crucial for the development of brain tissue, nerve myelination, and serves as a fundamental ingredient for many enzymes (<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Lawrence and Lawrence, 2011</xref>).</p><p>The research on the effect of quail eggs on blood glucose levels revealed no significant difference compared to the control group. However, in group T3, glucose levels decreased, possibly due to metabolic changes (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Hussein, 2013</xref>). Metabolic changes indicate an increase in the rat's nutritional requirements for the growth of her offspring (<xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">Zhu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2015</xref>). Giving quail eggs may not significantly impact blood glucose levels. A homeostasis process occurred in groups T1, T2, and T4, maintaining normal blood glucose levels. Homeostasis is achieved when glucose enters the liver. The small intestine and liver absorb glucose, and excess glucose is converted into glycogen and stored in the liver and muscles, with a small amount stored in the brain (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Kanungo <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>).</p><p>Findings from this investigation of MDA's lipid peroxidation indicate no significant increase compared to the control, and there was no decrease in SOD levels across all treatments. Throughout the study, SOD and MDA levels remained constant, indicating the absence of significant oxidative stress. MDA and SOD levels fluctuate in response to physiological imbalances during the lactation period. Previous research also supports the observation that MDA levels in lactating rats do not significantly increase compared to controls (<xref rid="ref66" ref-type="bibr">Zheng <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2015</xref>). This absence of oxidative stress in lactating rats may be attributed to the direct energy metabolism to the offspring via milk (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Garratt <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2011</xref>). The physiological regulation of antioxidant systems plays a crucial role in maintaining the oxidant-antioxidant balance, thus preventing oxidative damage to macromolecules (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Garratt <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2011</xref>). The data suggests that antioxidants are physiologically regulated in response to reactive oxygen species (ROS) in various tissues of lactating rats, contributing to oxidant-antioxidant balance during peak lactation (<xref rid="ref66" ref-type="bibr">Zheng <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2015</xref>). The increase in metabolic rate during lactation leads to a rise in the production of ROS, potentially disrupting macromolecules, which can be mitigated by antioxidants (<xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">Selman <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">Salmon <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Dowling and Simmons, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Garratt <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr">Xu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>).</p><p>According to the research findings, the treatment group given quail eggs did not show a significant increase in prolactin hormone levels compared to the control. This contrasts with previous research, suggesting that high-protein foods can significantly stimulate prolactin secretion (<xref rid="ref62" ref-type="bibr">Vel&#225;zquez-Villegas <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2015</xref>). In rats, the lactation period lasts for 21 days after birth (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Grases-Pint&#243; <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). The levels of secreted prolactin are influenced by various factors, including the frequency and duration of offspring breastfeeding (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">Cregan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="ref63" ref-type="bibr">Wati <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>), maternal psychology (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">Nagel <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>), and the length of the lactation period. Prolactin hormone levels naturally decrease over time (<xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">Powe <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). Given that blood sampling in this study was conducted at the end of the third week, which also marks the end of the lactation period, no increase in prolactin hormone levels would likely be observed in the blood samples.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The research results indicate that the addition of 4% of marine macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic> to quail feed can effectively increase vitamin A and iodine levels in quail egg yolks. Furthermore, the T4 treatment, which involves enriching quail eggs with 5% marine macroalgae, is shown to increase the weight and body length of rat pups. However, this treatment did not have a significant impact on hematological levels, lipids, antioxidant activity, and the hormone prolactin compared to the control treatment. Overall, the study suggests that incorporation of quail eggs enriched with marine macroalgae <italic toggle="yes">E. spinosum</italic> support the growth and development of the rats offspring without negatively impact the health of the rats. Further research is needed to explore the potential beneficial effects of quail eggs enriched with marine macroalgae on other health parameters in lactating rats.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Aknowledgments</title><p>The authors acknowledge the scholarship provided by Indonesia Endowment Funds for Education (LPDP) and Center for Higher Education Funding (BPPT) in 2022.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors have declared no conflicts of interest.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>The study was funded by the Centre for Higher Education Funding (BPPT) and the Indonesia Endowment Fund for Education (LPDP).</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>HB and SM concept and design, HB analisis/interpretasi data and drafting manuscript, SM HG ZZ critical revision of manuscript, HB HG statistical analysis, HB admin, technical or material support, SH HG ZZ Supervision and final approval.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data from this study are provided in the manuscript.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Achalapong, J. 2016. Effect of egg and milk supplement on breast milk volume at 48 and 72 hours postpartum: a randomized-controlled trial. Thai. J. Obstet. Gynaecol<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> 24(1), 20&#8211;25.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Altmann, S.W., Davis, H.R., Zhu, L.J., Yao, X., Hoos, L.M., Tetzloff, G., Iyer, S.P., Maguire, M., Golovko, A., Zeng M., Wang, L., Murgolo, N. and Graziano, M.P. 2004. Niemann-pick C1 Like 1 protein is critical for intestinal cholesterol absorption. Science. 303(5661), 1201&#8211;1204.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1126/science.1093131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14976318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Andersson, M. and Braegger, C.P. 2022. The role of iodine for thyroid function in lactating women and infants. Endocr. Rev. 43(3), 469&#8211;506.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1210/endrev/bnab029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9113141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35552681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Apriyanto, Y.S., Iriyanti, N. and Tugiyanti, E. 2021. The effect of supplementation of avocado seed flour (<italic toggle="yes">Persea americana</italic> Mill.) in feed on blood lipids profile and egg yolk cholesterol of japanese Quail (<italic toggle="yes">Corturnix-corturnix japonica</italic>). Anim. Prod. 23(1), 10&#8211;17.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Azizi, F and Smyth, P. 2009. Breastfeeding and maternal and infant iodine nutrition. Clin. Endocrinol. (Oxf). 70(5), 803&#8211;809.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2265.2008.03442.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19178515</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Basri, H., Saraswati, T.R. and Isdadiyanto, S. 2018. Hematological status of rats (<italic toggle="yes">Ratt2us</italic><italic toggle="yes">norvegicus</italic> L.) in the lactation period after giving supplements organic quail eggs. IJBR. 6(1), 1&#8211;4.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Berchieri-Ronchi, C.B., Kim, S.W., Zhao, Y., Correa, C.R., Yeum, K.L. and Ferreira, A.L. 2011. Oxidative stress status of highly prolific sows during gestation and lactation. Animal. 5(11), 1774&#8211;1779.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/S1751731111000772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22440418</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Biberoglu, E., Biberoglu, K., Kirbas, A., Daglar, K., Genc, M. and Avci, A. 2016. Circulating and myometrial markers of oxidative stress in pregnant women with fetal growth restriction. J. Obstet. Gynaecol. Res. 42(1), 29&#8211;35</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jog.12857</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26555027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Binev, R. 2023. Investigations on some indicators in the blood of cattle with orosthenic activity tongue rolling. J. Adv. Vet. Anim. Res. 10(2), 336&#8211;341.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5455/javar.2023.j685</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10390672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37534076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Caponio, G.R., Wang, D.Q., Ciaula, A.D., Angelis, M.D. and Portincasa, P. 2020. Regulation of cholesterol metabolism by bioactive components of soy proteins: novel translational evidence. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 22(1), 227.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms22010227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7794713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33379362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Carretero-Krug. A., Montero-Bravo, A., Morais-Moreno, C., Puga, A.M., Samaniego-Vaesken, M.L., Partearroyo, TG. and Varela-Moreiras, L. 2024. Nutritional status of breastfeeding mothers and impact of diet and dietary supplementation: a narrative review. Nutrients. 16(2), 301.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/nu16020301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10818638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38276540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Cregan, M.D., Mitoulas, L.R. and Hartmann, P.E. 2002. Milk prolactin, feed volume and duration between feeds in women breastfeeding their full-term infants over a 24 h period. Exp. Physiol. 87(2), 207&#8211;214.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1113/eph8702327</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11856965</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Crozier, S.R., Robinson, S.M., Godfrey, K.M., Cooper, C. and Inskip, H.M. 2009. Women's dietary patterns change little from before to during pregnancy. J. Nutr. 139(10), 1956&#8211;1963.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3945/jn.109.109579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3113465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19710161</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Delange, F. 2007. Iodine requirements during pregnancy, lactation and the neonatal period and indicators of optimal iodine nutrition. Public Health Nutr. 10(12a), 1571&#8211;1580.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/S1368980007360941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18053281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Dos, Q. Santos, R., Sichieri, Marchioni, D.M. and Verly Junior E. 2014. Brazilian pregnant and lactating women do not change their food intake to meet nutritional goals. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth. 14(186), 1&#8211;7.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2393-14-186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4049461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24890188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Dowling, D.K and Simmons, L.W. 2009. Reactive oxygen species as universal constraints in life-history evolution. Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences, 276(1663), 1737&#8211;1745.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1098/rspb.2008.1791</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2674489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19324792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Dunlea, E., Crushell, E., Cotter, M., Blau, N. and Ferreira, C.R. 2023. Clinical and biochemical footprints of inherited metabolic disease. XVI. Hematological abnormalities, Mol. Genet. Metab. 140(4), 107735</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ymgme.2023.107735</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11752282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37989003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Fernandez, M.L and Murillo, A.G. 2022. Is there a correlation between dietary and blood cholesterol? evidence from epidemiological data and clinical interventions. Nutrients. 14(10), 2168.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/nu14102168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9143438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35631308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Garratt, M., Vasilaki, A., Stockley, P., McArdle, F., Jackson, M. and Hurst, J.L. 2011. Is oxidative stress a physiological cost of reproduction? An experimental test in house mice. Proc. Biol. Sci. 278(1708), 1098&#8211;1106.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1098/rspb.2010.1818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3049035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20926440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Gopalakrishnan, K., Teitelbaum, S.L., Wetmur, J., Manservisi, F., Falcioni, L., Panzacchi, S., Gnudi, F., Belpoggi, F. and Chen, J. 2018. Histology and transcriptome profiles of the mammary gland across critical windows of development in sprague dawley rats. J. Mammary Gland Biol. Neoplasia. 23(3), 149&#8211;163.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10911-018-9401-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6103804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29956080</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Grases-Pint&#243;, B., Abril-Gil, M., Torres-Castro, P., Castell, M., Rodr&#237;guez-Lagunas, M.J., P&#233;rez-Cano, F.J. and Franch, A. 2021. Rat milk and plasma immunological profile throughout lactation. Nutrients. 13(4), 1257.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/nu13041257</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8070501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33920419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Gwozdzinski, K., Pieniazek, A. and Gwozdzinski, L. 2021. Reactive oxygen species and their involvement in red blood cell damage in chronic kidney disease. Oxid. Med. Cell Longev. 2021, 1&#8211;19.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2021/6639199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7932781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33708334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Hajati, H. and Zaghari, M. 2019. Spirulina in Poultry Nutrition. Cambridge Scholars Publishing, Cambridge, UK.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Hussein, E. 2013. Biochemical and histopathologichal studies on the liver of rats administrated with different concentrations of aqueous extrack of <italic toggle="yes">Glycyrrhiza glaborus</italic>. Glob. Vet. 10(5), 491&#8211;495.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Iannotti, L.L., Lutter, C.K., Stewart, C.P., Gallegos Riofr&#237;o, C.A., Malo, C., Reinhart, G ., Palacios, A., Karp, C., Chapnick, M., Cox, K. and Waters, W.F. 2017. Eggs in early complementary feeding and child growth: a randomized controlled trial. Pediatrics.140(1), 2016&#8211;3459.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1542/peds.2016-3459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28588101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Imdad, A and Bhutta, Z.A. 2011. Effect of balanced protein energy supplementation during pregnancy on birth outcomes. BMC Public Health. 11(Suppl. 3), S17.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1471-2458-11-S3-S17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3231890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21501434</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Ivarsson, E., Wall, H., Boyner, M., Cervin, G., Pavia, H. and Wattrang, E. 2023. Effects of algal supplementation in feed to broiler breeders on transfer of nutrients and antibodies to chicks and quality of hatchlings. Animal. 17(12), 101020.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.animal.2023.101020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37988995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Iwansyah, A.C., Damanik, M.R.M., Kustiyah, L. and Hanafi, M. 2017. Potensi fraksi etil asetat daun <italic toggle="yes">Coleus amboinicus</italic> L. dalam meningkatkan produksi susu, berat badan tikus dan anaknya. J. Gizi. Pangan. 2(1), 61&#8211;68.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Jeke, A., Phiri, C., Chitindingu, K. and Taru, P. 2018. Ethnomedicinal use and pharmacological potential of Japanese quail (<italic toggle="yes">Coturnix coturnix japonica</italic>) birds meat and eggs, and its potential implications on wild quail conservation in Zimbabwe: A review. Cogent. Food Agric. 4(1), 1507305</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Kanungo, S., Wells, K., Tribett, T. and El-Gharbawy, A. 2018. Glycogen metabolism and glycogen storage disorders. Ann. Transl. Med. 6(24), 474.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.21037/atm.2018.10.59</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6331362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30740405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Khan, R.U., Khan, A., Naz, S., Ullah, Q., Puva&#711;ca N.,, Laudadio, V., Mazzei, D., Seidavi, A., Ayasan, T. and Tufarelli, V. 2023. Pros and cons of dietary vitamin a and its precursors in poultry health and production: a comprehensive review. Antioxidants, 12(5), 1131.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antiox12051131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10215127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37237998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Kuhn, V., Diederich, L., Keller, T.C.S., Kramer, C.M., L&#252;ckst&#228;dt, W. and Panknin, C. 2017. Red blood cell function and dysfunction: redox regulation, nitric oxide metabolism, anemia. Antioxid. Redox. Signal. 26(13), 718&#8211;742.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/ars.2016.6954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5421513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27889956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Kulshreshtha, G., Hincke, M.T., Prithiviraj, B. and Critchley, A. 2020. A review of the varied uses of macroalgae as dietary supplements in selected poultry with special reference to laying hen and broiler chickens. J. Mar. Sci. Eng. 8(7), 536.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Kim, S.Y. and Yi, D.Y. 2020. Components of human breast milk: from macronutrient to microbiome and microRNA. Clin. Exp. Pediatr. 63(8), 301&#8211;309.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3345/cep.2020.00059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7402982</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32252145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Lager, K and Jordan, E. The metabolic profile for the modern transition dairy cow. The Mid-South Ruminant Nutrition Conference, 2012, pp 9&#8211;16.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Lawrence, R.A and Lawrence, R.M. 2011. Breastfeeding: a guide for the medical profession, 7th Ed. Philadelphia, PA: Saunders Elsevier.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Lima, H. J.D. and Souza, L.A.Z. 2018. Vitamin A in the diet of laying hens: enrichment of table eggs to prevent nutritional deficiencies in humans. World Poult. Sci. J. 74(4), 619&#8211;626.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Liu, Y., Song, M., Bai, H., Wang, C., Wang, F. and Yuan, Q.. 2024. Curcumin improves the egg quality, antioxidant activity, and intestinal microbiota of quails during the late laying period. Poult. Sci. 103(1), 103233.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.psj.2023.103233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10685021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37980738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Lokossou, G. A. Kouakanou, G,L., Schumacher, A. and Zenclussen, A.C. 2022. Human breast milk: from food to active immune response with disease protection in infants and mothers. Front. Immunol. 13, 849012.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2022.849012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9016618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35450064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Mahmood, A., Omar, M.N. and Ngah, N. 2012. Galactagogue effects of Musa x paradisiaca flower extract on lactating rats. Asian Pac. J. Trop. Med. 5(11), 882&#8211;886.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S1995-7645(12)60164-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23146802</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Mel&#233;ndez-Mart&#237;nez, A.J. 2019. An overview of carotenoids, apocarotenoids, and vitamin A in agro-food, nutrition, health, and disease. Mol. Nutr. Food Res. 63(15), e1801045.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/mnfr.201801045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31189216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Miranda, J., Anton, X., Redondo-Valbuena, C., Roca-Saavedra, P., Rodriguez, J. and Lamas, A.. 2015. Egg and egg-derived foods: effects on human health and use as functional foods. Nutrients. 7(1), 706&#8211;729.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/nu7010706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4303863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25608941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Marshall, N.E., Abrams, B., Barbour, L.A., Catalano, P., Christian, P., Friedman, J.E., Hay, W.W., Jr, Hernandez, T.L., Krebs, N.F., Oken, E., Purnell, J.Q., Roberts, J.M., Soltani, H., Wallace, J. and Thornburg, K.L. 2022. The importance of nutrition in pregnancy and lactation: lifelong consequences. Am. J. Obstet. Gynecol. 226(5), 607&#8211;632.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajog.2021.12.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9182711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34968458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Mousa, A., Naqash, A. and Lim, S. 2019. Macronutrient and micronutrient intake during pregnancy: an overview of recent evidence. Nutrients. 11(2), 443.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/nu11020443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6413112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30791647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Nagel, E.M., Howland, M.A., Pando, C., Stang, J., Mason, S.M., Fields, D.A. and Demerath, E.W. 2022. Maternal Psychological Distress And Lactation And Breastfeeding Outcomes: A Narrative Review. Clin. Ther. 44(2), 215&#8211;227.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.clinthera.2021.11.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8960332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34937662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Naeem, M., Rahim, M.A., Nisa, M.U., Khalid, K., Ahmad, N. and Khalid, N. and Awuchi, C.G. 2023. Digestibility, intake, and growth performance of egg protein replaced with vegetable protein in weaning food. Cogent Food and Agriculture. 9(1), 2258800.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Neville, M.C., Demerath, E.W., Hahn-Holbrook, J., Hovey, R.C., Martin-Carli, J., McGuire, M.A., Newton, E.R., Rasmussen, K.M., Rudolph, M.C. and Raiten, D.J. 2023. Parental factors that impact the ecology of human mammary development, milk secretion, and milk composition-a report from "breastmilk ecology: genesis of infant nutrition (BEGIN)" Working Group 1. Am. J. Clin. Nutr. 117 (Suppl. 1), S11&#8211;S27.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ajcnut.2022.11.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10232333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37173058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Nielsen, S.S. 2010. Food Analysis. 4th Edition, Food Science Text Series, Newyork, NY: Springer, pp: 602.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Nisa, R.K., Saraswati dan, T.R., Yuniwarti, E.Y.W. 2017. Kadar kolesterol dan vitamin A pada telur itik pengging, itik tegal dan itik magelang. <italic toggle="yes">Buletin Anatomi dan Fisiologi, 2</italic>(2), 114&#8211;119.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>&#216;verland, M., Mydland, L.T. and Skrede, A. 2019. Marine macroalgae as sources of protein and bioactive compounds in feed for monogastric animals. J. Sci. Food. Agric. 99(1), 13&#8211;24.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jsfa.9143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6585948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29797494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Pastuszewska, B., Taciak, M., Ochtabi&#324;ska, A., Tu&#347;nio, A., Misztal, T., Romanowicz, K. and Morawski, A. 2008. Nutritional value and physiological effects of soya-free diets fed to rats during growth and reproduction. J. Anim. Physiol. Anim. Nutr. (Berl). 92(1), 63&#8211;74.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1439-0396.2007.00711.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18184381</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Powe, C. E., Allen, M., Puopolo, K.M., Merewood, A., Worden, S., Johnson, J.C., Fleischman, A. and Welt, C.K. 2010. Recombinant human prolactin for the treatment of lactation insufficiency. Clin. Endocrinol. (Oxf). 73(5), 645&#8211;653.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2265.2010.03850.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6488522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20718766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Prawitasari, S., Saraswati, T.R. and Tana, S. 2019. Liver histological structure of rats (<italic toggle="yes">Rattus norvegicus</italic>) in the lactation period after supplemented with organic quail eggs. <italic toggle="yes">J. Phys.: Conf. Ser.</italic>, pp: 1217.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Purba, S.L., Saraswati, R.T. and Isdadiyanto, S.. 2018. The effect of organic quail egg supplementation on the blood lipid profile of white mice (<italic toggle="yes">Rattus Norvegicus</italic> L.) during the lactation period. <italic toggle="yes">J. Phys.: Conf. Ser.,</italic> pp: 1025.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Rend&#243;n, U., Carrillo, S., Arellano, L.G., Casas, M.M., P&#233;rez, F. and Avila, E. 2003. Chemical composition of the residue of alginates (<italic toggle="yes">Macrocystis pyrifera</italic>) extraction. Its utilization in laying hens feeding. Cuban J. Agricult. Sci. 37, 287&#8211;293.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Salmon, A.B., Marx, D.B. and Harshman, L.G. 2001. A cost of reproduction in <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila melanogaster</italic>: stress susceptibility. Evolution, 55(8), 1600&#8211;1608.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.0014-3820.2001.tb00679.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11580019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Salmuth, V.V., Brennan, E., Kerac, M. and McGrath, M. 2021. Frison S, Lelijveld N. Maternal-focused interventions to improve infant growth and nutritional status in low-middle income countries: a systematic review of reviews. PLoS One. 16(8), e0256188.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0256188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8372927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34407128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Selman, C., McLaren, J.S., Himanka, M.J. and Speakman, J.R. 2000. Effect of longterm cold exposure on antioxidant enzyme activities in a small mammal. Free Radic. Biol. Med. 28(8), 1279&#8211;1285.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0891-5849(00)00263-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10889458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>S&#322;upczynska, M., Jamroz, D., Orda, J. and Wiliczkiewicz, A. 2014. Effect of various sources and levels of iodine, as well as the kind of diet, on the performance of young laying hens, iodine accumulation in eggs, egg characteristics, and morphotic and biochemical indices in blood. Poult. Sci. 93(10), 2536&#8211;2547.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3382/ps.2014-03959</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25071224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Sumaiya, S., ,Nayak, S., Baghel, R.P., Nayak, A., Malapure, C.D. and Kumar, R. 2016. Effect of dietary iodine on production of iodine enriched eggs. Vet. World. 9(6), 55&#8211;558.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14202/vetworld.2016.554-558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4937043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27397975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Toy, H., Camuzcuoglu, H., Arioz, D.T., Kurt, S., Celik, H. and Aksoy, N. 2009. Serum prolidase activity and oxidative stress markers in pregnancies with intrauterine growth restricted infants. J. Obstet. Gynaecol. Res. 35(6), 1047&#8211;1053.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1447-0756.2009.01063.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20144170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Vel&#225;zquez-Villegas, L.A., L&#243;pez-Barradas, A.M., Torres, N., Hern&#225;ndez-Pando, R., Le&#243;n-Contreras, J.C. and Granados, O. 2015. Prolactin and the dietary protein/carbohydrate ratio regulate the expression of SNAT2 amino acid transporter in the mammary gland during lactation. Biochim. Biophys. Acta. 1848(5), 1157&#8211;1164.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bbamem.2015.02.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25701231</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Wati, L.R., Sargowo, D., Nurseta, T. and Zuhriyah, L. 2023. The role of protein intake on the total milk protein in lead-exposed lactating mothers. <italic toggle="yes">Nutrients,</italic> 15(11), 2584.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/nu15112584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10255346</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37299547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Wrzeci&#324;ska, M., Kowalczyk, A., Czerniawska-Pi&#261;tkowska, E., Kordan, W. and Araujo, J.P. Examination of the haematological profile of pregnant Polish Holstein-Friesian black-and-white cattle in the early stage. J. Vet. Res. 67(3), 415&#8211;425.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2478/jvetres-2023-0043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10541671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37786841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Xu, Y.C., Yang, D.B., Speakman, J.R. and Wang, D.H. 2014. Oxidative stress in response to natural and experimentally elevated reproductive effort is tissue dependent. Funct. Ecol. 28(2), 402&#8211;410.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Zheng, G.X., Lin, J.T., Zheng, W.H., Cao, J. and Zhao, Z.J. 2015. Energy intake, oxidative stress and antioxidant in mice during lactation. Dongwuxue Yanjiu. 36(2), 95&#8211;102.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.13918/j.issn.2095-8137.2015.2.95</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4790255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25855228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Zhang, Y., Kallenberg, C., Hyatt, H.W., Kavazis, A.N. and Hood, W.R. 2017. Change in the lipid transport capacity of the liver and blood during reproduction in rats. Front. Physiol. 8, 517.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fphys.2017.00517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5527701</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28798692</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Zhang, X., Yang, S. Chen, J. and Su, Z. 2019. Unraveling the regulation of hepatic gluconeogenesis. Front. Endocrinol. (Lausanne). 9, 802.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fendo.2018.00802</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6353800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30733709</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Zhu, W., Mu, Y., Liu, J. and Wang, Z.. 2015. Energy requirements during lactation in female <italic toggle="yes">Apodemus chevrieri</italic> (Mammalia: Rodentia: Muridae) in the Hengduan Mountain Region. Italian J. Zool. 82(2), 165&#8211;171.</comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>