<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2846</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">openvetj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Veterinary Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2226-4485</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2218-6050</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tripoli</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11682779</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11682779.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11682779</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11682779</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39737013</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/OVJ.2024.v14.i11.27</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OVJ-14-2989</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ultrastructural morphology of second and third-stage larvae of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara cati</italic> inside paratenic host tissue</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Theja</surname><given-names initials="LA">Letitia Amanda</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kusnoto</surname><given-names initials="K">Kusnoto</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tacharina</surname><given-names initials="MR">Martia Rani</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suwanti</surname><given-names initials="LT">Lucia Tri</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mufasirin</surname><given-names initials="M">Mufasirin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastutiek</surname><given-names initials="P">Poedji</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aryaloka</surname><given-names initials="S">Suhita</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khairullah</surname><given-names initials="AR">Aswin Rafif</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moses</surname><given-names initials="IB">Ikechukwu Benjamin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raissa</surname><given-names initials="R">Ricadonna</given-names></name><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mulyaningrum</surname><given-names initials="PW">Putri Wahyu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yanestria</surname><given-names initials="SM">Sheila Marty</given-names></name><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riwu</surname><given-names initials="KHP">Katty Hendriana Priscilia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff9" ref-type="aff">
<sup>9</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Profession Program in Veterinary Medicine, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Airlangga, Surabaya, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Division of Veterinary Parasitology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Airlangga, Surabaya, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Division of Veterinary Microbiology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Airlangga, Surabaya, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Master Program of Veterinary Agribusiness, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Airlangga, Surabaya, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Research Center for Veterinary Science, National Research and Innovation Agency (BRIN), Bogor, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Applied Microbiology, Faculty of Science, Ebonyi State University, Abakaliki, Nigeria</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label>Department of Pharmacology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Brawijaya, Malang, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff8"><label>8</label>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Wijaya Kusuma Surabaya, Surabaya, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff9"><label>9</label>Department of Veterinary Public Health, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Pendidikan Mandalika, Mataram, Indonesia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Kusnoto Kusnoto. Division of Veterinary Parasitology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Airlangga, Surabaya, Indonesia. <email>kusnoto@fkh.unair.ac.id</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>11</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">477914</issue-id><fpage>2989</fpage><lpage>2994</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-12-31 15:25:20.740"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2989.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Toxocara cati</italic> is a known cause of a zoonotic infectious illness called toxocariasis. Parathenic hosts are important as they can transmit larvae 2 (L<sub>2</sub>) through direct transmission. Scanning electron microscope (SEM) techniques are needed to provide a three-dimensional image of each stage of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> larvae.</p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>The aim of this study was to determine the morphology of L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> in parathenic host tissue for etiological diagnosis using SEM.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods:</title><p>Mice were used as suitable paratenic hosts for this experiment. A total of 786 embryonated eggs (16 eggs/gram body weight) containing L<sub>2</sub> were inoculated into pregnant mice at day 11&#8211;13 of its gestation period. After delivery, L<sub>2</sub> was transmitted to the off-spring. After 14 days, L<sub>2</sub> was collected from mice, and L<sub>3</sub> was collected from its off-spring. Data were analyzed descriptively based on ultrastructure examination using SEM.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>SEM examination results indicate that the size of L<sub>2</sub> is smaller than L<sub>3</sub>. Results also showed differences between L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> based on middle and posterior observations. In the middle of the larval body, the number of L<sub>2</sub> body rings was observed to be narrower and more than that of L<sub>3</sub>. In addition, the distance between L<sub>2</sub> body rings was much larger than that of L<sub>3</sub>. Posteriorly, the tail tip of L<sub>3</sub> was more curved than L<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Ultrastructural examination using SEM has the ability to show differences in L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> body rings of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> by observing the middle and posterior parts of its larvae.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Toxocara cati</italic></kwd><kwd>Larvae</kwd><kwd>Scanning electron microscopy</kwd><kwd>Zoonosis</kwd><kwd>Parathenic host</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Toxocariasis is a zoonotic infectious illness that can be transmitted from animals to humans. It is a term for diseases caused by <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. One form of toxocariasis is <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara cati</italic> infection which is transmitted from definitive or paratenic hosts to humans (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>). In order to treat toxocariasis properly, an appropriate diagnostic method is needed. Diagnosis can be made through etiological diagnosis by observing the developmental morphology of each stage of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> larvae (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Magnaval <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). Observing the morphology of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> larvae usually uses a light microscope, but this method cannot identify them clearly and precisely (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Oguz <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>). Some organs of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> larvae such as the cervical alae, body ring, and cuticle cannot be seen, so other methods are needed. Observation of larval morphology can be seen more clearly using a scanning electron microscope (SEM) (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Dos Santos <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>).</p><p>SEM techniques are needed to provide a three-dimensional image of each stage of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> larvae. Research on larvae 2 (L<sub>2</sub>) and larvae 3 (L<sub>3</sub>) of paratenic host tissue using SEM has not been carried out much because previous research only detected L<sub>3</sub> migration patterns in paratenic host tissue (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Raulf <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). Cats and kittens can be infected with <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic>, but the incidence of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> in kittens is higher than in adult cats (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Bonilla-Aldana <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). Cats can become infected with <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> by ingesting L<sub>2</sub> which then migrates down the portal vein to the liver and lungs. In female animals, L<sub>2</sub> does not reach the adult stage. L<sub>2</sub> is considered to be dormant in the muscles when the cat is pregnant. L<sub>2</sub> develops into L<sub>3</sub> when the cat gives birth to kittens, resulting in transmammary transmission or transmission through milk (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Castro and Sapp, 2020</xref>).</p><p>Toxocariasis in humans is most often caused by <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Bakhshani <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). Humans, especially children, can be infected with toxocariasis from the ingestion of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> embryonated eggs in the soil (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Noordin <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). Zoonotic transmission through soil (soil transmission) is important because according to <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Candra <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2020)</xref>, the highest number of worm eggs found is due to the huge percentage of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. eggs observed in the soil of Bangkalan, Madura. Another route of the zoonotic transmission of toxocariasis is through the ingesting of larvae in undercooked meat. In humans, it causes ocular larval migrans (OLMs) and visceral larval migrans (VLMs) (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Hare and Franco-Paredes, 2014</xref>). VLM has symptoms that vary from asymptomatic to severe pathological conditions that are potentially fatal. In severe pathological conditions, it can cause hepatomegaly, hypergammaglobuline, lung damage, and neurological disorders (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Zibaei <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). OLM can cause inflammation and granulomatous inflammation of the retina, resulting in loss of vision (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Morsy, 2020</xref>).</p><p>The migration path of larvae in paratenic hosts is similar to the migration path of definitive hosts. The embryonic larval eggs that are eaten by the paratenic host penetrate the intestinal wall and then migrate through the blood vessels to the liver and lungs (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Strube <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2013</xref>). The larvae lie dormant in organs and muscles; when the paratenic host is eaten by a cat, the larvae develop into adult worms (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">Maciag <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). Most researchers believe that <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> larvae are only transmitted via transmammary, but research from <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Okada <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2021)</xref> in which very large doses of embryonated eggs were inoculated into paratenic hosts showed transplancetal transmission. Knowledge of the differences in the ultrastructural morphology of L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> inside paratenic host tissue is necessary for diagnosis, so as to avoid misidentification of each stage of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> larvae.</p><p>Previous studies majorly focus on the detection and transmission of the L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> using light microscopy with very limited application of electron microscopy which would properly show their morphological structure in comprehensive detail for effective diagnosis of toxocariasis. This study was designed to explore the application of scanning electron microscopy to comprehensively understand the ultrastructural morphology and topography of second and third-stage larvae of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara cati</italic> for the accurate diagnosis of toxocariasis, using mice as paratenic hosts.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Study area and sample collection</title><p>The research was carried out from February 2024 to July 2024. The research samples used were L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> and two pregnant female BALB/C mice (<italic toggle="yes">Mus musculus</italic>). The mice were purchased and maintained in the Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Airlangga, Surabaya, Indonesia. L<sub>2</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> was obtained from embryonated eggs inoculated into mice while L<sub>3</sub> was obtained from mouse offspring whose mothers were inoculated with <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> embryonated eggs. Toxocariasis examination using stool samples that have been taken, fertilization of worm eggs, inoculation on mice, and examination using a light microscope with an optilab camera (Nikon Corporation, Japan) were carried out at the Parasitology Laboratory, Airlangga University. Scanning electron microscopy (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc, USA) examinations on L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> samples were carried out at the Institute of Life Sciences, Engineering and Engineering Laboratory, Airlangga University.</p><p>Worms were obtained from the feces of cats that were identified to have toxocariasis and thereafter stored in storage pots containing phosphate buffer saline (PBS) solution. Worms that have died were surgically removed from the posterior reproductive tract to extract their eggs. On the other hand, those still alive were transferred to Petri dishes containing PBS and 0.9% NaCl solution. The worms were then incubated at 37&#176;C to produce eggs. Eggs were maintained in PBS and NaCl media in a ratio of 1:1 (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Suroiyah <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Fertilizing worm eggs</title><p><italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> worm eggs were cultured with PBS media and the addition of 2&#8211;3 drops of 0.5% formalin to kill microorganisms and prevent the growth of egg-disturbing microorganisms. In the media, the eggs will develop into second-stage larvae (L<sub>2</sub>) (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Simarmata <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). Egg development was routinely observed with a microscope at 100x and 400x magnification. The egg fertilization process was carried out for 21&#8211;28 days at room temperature. After fertilizing the eggs, they were placed in another tube and washed using distilled water. Embryoated eggs were deposited for 3&#8211;4 hours, collected by removing the supernatant, and thereafter observed using a light microscope.</p></sec><sec><title>Examination of mouse organs</title><p>Adult mice were infected using embryonated eggs with second-stage larvae. The dose of infected eggs was 16 embryonated eggs/gram of body weight. Female mice that had given birth were allowed to breastfeed for 14 days and dissected at the end of the 14th day to obtain L<sub>2</sub> tissue. Mice pups that had been breastfeeding for 14 days were dissected to obtain L<sub>3</sub> tissue. Before surgery, adult mice were euthanized by neck dislocation, while child mice were euthanized by neck decapitation. The examination was carried out by placing the somatic muscles and viscera (lungs, liver, and digestive tract) in a 1% trypsin solution, and thereafter, leaving the organs in an incubator at 37&#176;C for 4 hours before observing the L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> obtained by each organ. The number of observed larvae was then counted for each organ.</p></sec><sec><title>Sample examination using a scanning electron microscope (SEM)</title><p>The sample preparation procedure was done by first fixing the sample in 3% glutaraldehyde for 3 hours at 4&#176;C, and then centrifuged at 1,200 rpm for 15 minutes. Each sample was washed with phosphate buffer (pH 7.4) at least 3 times for 5 minutes at 4&#176;C, and then centrifugation at 1,500 rpm for 15 minutes. Next, each sample was dehydrated using graded alcohol of 30%, 50%, and 70% for 15&#8211;20 minutes at 4&#176;C, then centrifuged at 1,500 rpm for 15 minutes. Dehydration was continued using 80% and 90% alcohol, and centrifuged at 1,500 rpm for 15 minutes. The next step was replacing the liquid with amyl acetate as a preserving liquid until drying time (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Pertiwi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>).</p><p>L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> tissue to be dried were pipetted and dropped onto a glass object that had been cleaned using 70% alcohol. Drying was carried out using a critical point drying tool, then coated with pure gold using a vacuum evaporator.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>This research received approval by Animal Care and Use Committee (ACUC), Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Airlangga, Surabaya. Certificate number: 1.KEH.118.09.2022.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>L<sub>2</sub> was found in the somatic muscles and viscera of female mice in a moving condition. The number of larvae found was 82, equivalent to 10.4% of the 786 embryonated eggs inoculated. Of all the organs examined, the highest amount of L<sub>2</sub> was in the liver.</p><p>The mice that were operated on were those that had been breastfeeding for 14 days. Of the 13 mice that were dissected, L<sub>3</sub> was found in the viscera and somatic muscles. The larvae found in the mice were in a moving condition. The number of larvae found in the young mice was 14, equivalent to 1.78% of the 786 embryonated eggs inoculated. Of all the organs examined, the highest number of L<sub>3</sub> was found in the viscera.</p><p>SEM provides a morphological image in three dimensions L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub>. The results show that there are differences in size and shape at each larval stage. Images of L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> using SEM are shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. The SEM image results were measured for each part (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>It was observed that L<sub>2</sub> had a length of around 338.66 &#181;m and L<sub>3</sub> of 408.43 &#181;m (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The width of L<sub>2</sub> is approximately 10.12 &#181;m, while the width of L<sub>3</sub> is 11.09 &#181;m (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). On the L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> sides of the body, there are elongated refractile lines called lateral alae. On all parts of the L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> body, there is a body ring formation in the form of smooth lines extending transversally (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).</p><p>L<sub>2</sub> has a relatively narrow distance between the rings (739.2 nm) compared to L<sub>3</sub> (810.92 nm). The body ring on L<sub>2</sub> looks faint and smooth compared to L<sub>3</sub> which looks clear and prominent. The lateral alae and body ring of L<sub>3</sub> can be seen in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>.</p><p>The anterior part of L<sub>3</sub> was not visible because the worm larvae were positioned facing other parts of the body. In the anterior part of L<sub>2</sub>, formations such as the dorsal lips, cuticle, and cervical alae which have not yet formed completely were observed. The anterior width of L<sub>2</sub> was around 4.28 &#181;m. The width of the right cervical alae was around 419.71 nm and the width of the left one was around 520.59 nm. Anterior observation of L<sub>2</sub> is shown in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> (1000x); (A) L<sub>3</sub> in mouse offspring; (B) L<sub>2</sub> in adult mice. A = Anterior, P = Posterior.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2989-g001.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Measurements of L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic>.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Stadiums larvae</th><th colspan="5" rowspan="1">Body size (&#181;m)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">width</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anterior</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterior</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distance between body rings</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">L<sub>2</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">338.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.739</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">L<sub>3</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">408.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.810</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>The middle part of L<sub>2</sub> of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> (20000x). LA = Lateral alae, BR = Body ring.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2989-g002.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><title>The middle part of the L<sub>3</sub> of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> (20,000x). LA = Lateral alae, BR = Body ring.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2989-g003.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig4" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><title>Anterior section of L<sub>2</sub> in adult mouse tissue (20,000x). CA = Cervical alae, DL = Dorsal lips, KT = Cuticle.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2989-g004.jpg"/></fig><p>The posterior length of L<sub>2</sub> was around 3.31 &#181;m while that of L<sub>3</sub> was around 5.31 &#181;m. In the posterior part, the tip of the L<sub>2</sub> tail looks sharp and straight while the tip of the L<sub>3</sub> tail looks pointed and curved. In L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub>, there was an anal pore formation around the terminal bulb. Precloacal papillae and postcloacal papillae could not be seen in SEM observations. The posterior observation showing body ring structures of both L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> are shown in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figures 5</xref> and <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>From the present results, the number of L<sub>2</sub> found was 82 from a total of 786 inoculated embryonated eggs (10.4%). In mice, L<sub>3</sub> tissue was found in somatic muscles and viscera. The number of L<sub>3</sub> tissues found was 14 from a total of 786 inoculated embryonated eggs (1.78%). Of all the organs examined, the highest amount of L<sub>2</sub> was in the liver, while L<sub>3</sub> was in the viscera. This showed that there is transmission of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> larvae from mother mice to their offspring. According to <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Bakshani <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2020)</xref> who studied the distribution of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> larvae in mice, they argued that the low number of larvae could be caused by not all embryonated eggs hatching in the mice&#8217;s bodies or the embryonic eggs being defeated by the immune system before they hatch.</p><p>Using SEM examination in the present study, the anterior part of L<sub>2</sub> was observed to be the lip formation. The anterior part of L<sub>3</sub> was not observed because the larva was facing other parts of the body. Interestingly, the tapered dorsal lips were clearly observed. This is different from what was found by <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Pertiwi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2019)</xref> who demonstrated that the dorsal lips were blunt in <italic toggle="yes">T. canis</italic>. A thickened cuticle was also observed at the bottom of the lips. This is in accordance with <xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Abou-El-Naga <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2022)</xref> who reported that the larvae will continue to thicken due to cuticle growth. The cuticle layer has been previously reported to line the mouth and esophagus (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Bowman <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1993</xref>). On the lateral side from the present work, there is a part of the cervical alae that has not developed completely. Cervical alae can be seen in second-stage larvae but do not develop completely. The cervical alae develop completely at the adult worm stage (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Mahdy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig5" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><title>Posterior section of L<sub>2</sub> in adult mouse tissue (10,000x). AP = Anal pore, BR = Body ring, TL = Tail.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2989-g005.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig6" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><title>Posterior section of L<sub>3</sub> in mouse tissue (20,000x). AP = Anal pore, BR = Body ring, TL = Tail.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2989-g006.jpg"/></fig><p>The present SEM examination revealed that L<sub>2</sub> has a smaller body size than L<sub>3</sub>. This may indicate that larvae grow in every stage. SEM showed that the posterior length of L<sub>2</sub> is smaller than L<sub>3.</sub> The posterior parts of L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> appear to taper to form a tail. The tail tip of L<sub>2</sub> appears flatter while the tail tip of L<sub>3</sub> appears curved. <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Raulf <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2021)</xref> previously reported that the L<sub>3</sub> somatic muscle was extended from the buccal capsule to the tail. This explains why the tails of L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> were different. Apart from that, there is an anal pore formation around the terminal bulb and a visible body ring. When observed using SEM, no precloacal papillae or postcloacal papillae were visible. <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Simarmata <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2019)</xref> found that there were papilla formations on L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic>. This happens because the papilla may peel off during the preparation process. <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Flay <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2022)</xref> found that the postfixing process using osmium tetroxide of <italic toggle="yes">Haemonchus contortus</italic> larvae had poor penetration in a short time. As a result, some parts of the larvae were not visible or missing in ultrastructural observations.</p><p>Ultrastructural observations of the middle part of the larvae can identify lateral alae and body rings at both L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> in the present study. The L<sub>2</sub> body ring tends to look faint compared to the L<sub>3</sub> body ring which looks prominent. The distance between the L<sub>2</sub> body rings tends to be narrower than L<sub>3</sub>. The body ring is a thickened cuticle that is visible throughout the larva&#8217;s body (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Ghorbanzadeh <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). An increase in the distance between the body ring and a decrease in the body ring can be caused by the loss of the outer layer of the cuticle which forms folds (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Radwan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2009</xref>). On the lateral side, there are lateral alae formations in the form of lines at L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub>. According to <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Zibaei (2017)</xref>, the lateral alae are visible as refractile lines along the larval body. The lateral alae usually disappear in the adult phase and the cervical alae will grow to a length of 45 mm (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Ziegler and Macpherson, 2019</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Mice infected with <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> embryonated eggs showed positive results in the presence of L<sub>2</sub> tissue and their offspring were positively infected in the presence of L<sub>3</sub>. Ultrastructural examination using SEM can also show differences in L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>3</sub> by observing the middle and posterior parts. In the middle of the larva&#8217;s body, it was observed that the distance between the body rings of L<sub>2</sub> was narrower than L<sub>3</sub>, while in the posterior section, the tail tip of L<sub>3</sub> was more curved than L<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors thanks to Universitas Airlangga.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>This research is funded by Rencana Kerja dan Anggaran Tahunan Skema Mandat year 2020 with grant number: 384/UN3.14/PT/2020.</p></sec><sec><title>Author&#8217;s contributions</title><p>LAT, PWM, and KK: Conceived, designed, and coordinated the study. MRT and LTS: Designed data collections tools, supervised the field sample and data collection, and laboratory work as well as data entry. MM, KHPR, and PH: Validation, supervision, and formal analysis. SA and ARK: Contributed reagents, materials, and analysis tools. IBM, SMY, and RR: Carried out the statistical analysis and interpretation and participated in the preparation of the manuscript. All authors have read, reviewed, and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data are available in the manuscript.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Abou-El-Naga, I.F., El-Nassery, S.M.F. and Sharaf, I.A. 2022. Immunochemical studies of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara canis</italic> proteases. Trop. Biomed. 39(3), 315&#8211;320.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.47665/tb.39.3.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36214429</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Bakhshani, A., Khodaverdi, M. and Borji, H. 2020. Distribution of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara cati</italic> larvae in experimentally infected BALB/c mice. Vet. Parasitol. 285(1), 109220.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vetpar.2020.109220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32950910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Bonilla-Aldana, J.L., Espinosa-Nu&#241;ez, A.C., Bonilla-Aldana, D.K. and Rodriguez-Morales, A.J. 2024. <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara cati</italic> infection in cats (Felis catus): a systematic review and meta-analysis. Animals 14(7), 1022.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ani14071022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11011152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38612261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Bowman, D.D., Oaks, J.A. and Grieve, R.B. 1993. Ultrastructure of the infective stage larva of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara canis</italic> (nematoda: ascaridoidea). Proc. Helminthol. Soc. Wash. 60(2), 183&#8211;204.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Candra, D.A., Lastuti, N.D.R., Hidayati, N., Kusnoto, Hastutiek, P. and Bijanti, R. 2020. Differential counting value and determining of leukocytes in chicken after infected with L2 <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara cati</italic>. J. Parasite Sci. 4(1), 11&#8211;16.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Castro, P.D.J. and Sapp, S.G. 2020. Role of cats in human toxocarosis. Companion Anim. 26(1), 1&#8211;8.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.12968/coan.2020.0104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9380441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35979067</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Chen, J., Liu, Q., Liu, G.H., Zheng, W.B., Hong, S.J., Sugiyama, H., Zhu, X.Q. and Elsheikha, H.M. 2018. Toxocariasis: a silent threat with a progressive public health impact. Infect. Dis. Poverty 7(1), 59.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s40249-018-0437-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5998503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29895324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Dos Santos, Q.M., Dzika, E. and Avenant-Oldewage, A. 2019. Using scanning electron microscopy (SEM) to study morphology and morphometry of the isolated haptoral sclerites of three distinct diplozoid species. PLoS One 14(1), e0211794.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0211794</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6389168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30802264</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Flay, K.J., Hill, F.I. and Muguiro, D.H. 2022. A Review: <italic toggle="yes">Haemonchus contortus</italic> infection in pasture-based sheep production systems, with a focus on the pathogenesis of anaemia and changes in haematological parameters. Animals (Basel) 12(10), 1238.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ani12101238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9137471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35625083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Ghorbanzadeh, B., Naem, S. and Farshid, A.A. 2021. Microscopic study of mechanoreceptors and chemoreceptors of anterior and posterior ends of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara Canis</italic> using scanning electron microscopy and light microscope. Arch. Razi Inst. 76(2), 311&#8211;322.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.22092/ari.2020.342252.1457</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8410181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34223730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Hare, A.Q. and Franco-Paredes, C. 2014. Ocular larva migrans: a severe manifestation of an unseen epidemic. Curr. Trop. Med. Rep. 1(1), 69&#8211;73.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Maciag, L., Morgan, E.R. and Holland, C. 2022. Toxocara: time to let cati &#8216;out of the bag&#8217;. Trends Parasitol. 38(4), 280&#8211;289.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pt.2021.12.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35058153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Magnaval, J.F., Bouhsira, E. and Fillaux, J. 2022. Therapy and prevention for human toxocariasis. Microorganisms 10(2), 241.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/microorganisms10020241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8875715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35208697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Mahdy, O.A., Mousa, W.M., Abdel-Maogood, S.Z., Nader, S.M. and Abdel-Radi, S. 2020. Molecular characterization and phylogenetic analysis of toxocara species in dogs, cattle and buffalo in Egypt. Helminthologia 57(2), 83&#8211;90.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2478/helm-2020-0013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7261022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32518484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Morsy, T.A. 2020. Toxocariasis: visceral and ocular larva migrans. J. Egypt. Soc. Parasitol. 50(1), 41&#8211;48.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Noordin, R., Yunus, M.H., Farrizam, S.N.T. and Arifin, N. 2020. Serodiagnostic methods for diagnosing larval toxocariasis. Adv. Parasitol. 109(1), 131&#8211;152.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/bs.apar.2020.01.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32381194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Oguz, B., Ozdal, N. and Deger, M.S. 2018. Genetic analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> Spp. in stray cats and dogs in van Province, Eastern Turkey. J. Vet. Res. 62(3), 291&#8211;295.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2478/jvetres-2018-0042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6296006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30584607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Okada, N., Ooi, H.K. and Taira, K. 2021. <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara cati</italic> larval migration to mouse fetuses through transplacental infection. Vet. Parasitol. 290(1), 109350.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vetpar.2021.109350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33453644</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Pertiwi, V.R., Kusnoto, Koesdarto, S., Lastuti, N.D.R., Suwanti, L.T. and Mufasirin. 2019. The differences between second stage larvaeand L2 <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara canis</italic> on mice tissueby using scanning electron microscopy. Indones. Vet. J. 20(3), 390&#8211;396.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Radwan, N.A., Khalil, A.I. and El Mahi, R.A. 2009. Morphology and occurrence of species of toxocara in wild mammal populations from Egypt. Comp. Parasitol. 76(1), 273&#8211;282.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Raulf, M.K., Lepenies, B. and Strube, C. 2021. <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara cati</italic> somatic and excretory-secretory antigens are recognised by C-type lectin receptors. Pathogens 10(3), 321.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/pathogens10030321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8001263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33803269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Simarmata, E.C., Kusnoto, K., Lazuardi, M., Koesdarto, S., Suprihati, E. and Santoso, K.P. 2019. Microscophy identification of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara cati</italic> first stage larvae and second stage larvae. J. Parasite Sci. 3(1), 1&#8211;4.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Strube, C., Heuer, L. and Janecek, E. 2013. <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. infections in paratenic hosts. Vet. Parasitol. 193(4), 375&#8211;389.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vetpar.2012.12.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23312872</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Suroiyah, F.A., Hastutiek, P., Yudhana, A., Sunarso, A. and Praja, R.N. 2018. Prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara cati</italic> infection on domestic cat in Banyuwangi district. J. Vet. Med. 1(3), 99&#8211;104.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Zibaei, M. 2017. Helminth infections and cardiovascular diseases: toxocara species is contributing to the disease. Curr. Cardiol. Rev. 13(1), 56&#8211;62.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2174/1573403X12666160803100436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5324319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27492228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Zibaei, M., Sadjjadi, S.M. and Uga, S. 2010. Experimental <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara cati</italic> infection in gerbils and rats. Korean J. Parasitol. 48(4), 331&#8211;333.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3347/kjp.2010.48.4.331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3018584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21234237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Ziegler, M.A. and Macpherson, C.N.L. 2019. Toxocara and its species. CAB Rev. 14(53), 1&#8211;27.</comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>