<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2846</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">openvetj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Veterinary Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2226-4485</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2218-6050</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tripoli</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12613167</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12613167.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12613167</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12613167</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41246398</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/OVJ.2025.v15.i10.58</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OpenVetJ-15-10-5400</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Spontaneous onset and resolution of gastroesophageal intussusception during contrast-enhanced computed tomography</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names initials="M">Mason</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lau</surname><given-names initials="M">Michelle</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Small Animal Specialist Hospital, North Ryde, Australia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold><sup>*</sup>Corresponding Author:</bold> Mason White. Small Animal Specialist Hospital, North Ryde, Australia. Email: <email>mwhite@sashvets.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>10</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">500573</issue-id><fpage>5400</fpage><lpage>5407</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>27</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>9</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-11-18 09:25:12.660"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.
</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-15-10-5400.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Gastroesophageal intussusception is a rare condition in dogs, most commonly presenting as an acute, life-threatening disease. In some dogs with chronic disease, intermittent intussusception is suspected to underlie clinical signs, although its relationship with other oesophageal disorders remains poorly understood. Transient intussusception has only been reported in one endoscopic study, where concurrent assessment of the oesophageal hiatus was not possible. To the best of the authors&#8217; knowledge, spontaneous reduction has never been definitively demonstrated tomographically.</p></sec><sec><title>Case Description:</title><p>A 10-year-old neutered male Australian Terrier presented to his local veterinarian after an episode of retching and collapse. He was referred to an internal medicine specialist and underwent computed tomography to look for possible underlying causes, as well as to investigate chronic, pre-existing respiratory disease. The gastric cardia and gastroesophageal junction herniated into the caudal thorax after contrast administration, before returning to a normal position on subsequent acquisitions, consistent with a sliding hiatal hernia. The patient was discharged for medical management and presented to a different referral hospital the following year for the evaluation of a sublumbar mass identified on abdominal ultrasound. Computed tomography revealed a mass arising from the right iliopsoas muscle, and a cytological diagnosis of hemangiosarcoma was made. The stomach was in its normal position on pre-contrast and delayed post-contrast images. However, on venous-phase images acquired between these time points, the gastric fundus was cranially herniated through the oesophageal hiatus into the caudal oesophageal lumen, with the gastroesophageal junction remaining appropriately positioned. These findings were consistent with self-resolving gastroesophageal intussusception. No treatment was pursued for the intussusception, and treatment for haemangiosarcoma was declined. A poor prognosis was given, and the patient died 5 days later without a postmortem examination.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>This is the first reported case of gastroesophageal intussusception in a dog that was tomographically determined to be self-resolving and the first case of gastroesophageal intussusception in association with an untreated hiatal hernia.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Chronic</kwd><kwd>Gastroesophageal</kwd><kwd>Intermittent</kwd><kwd>Intussusception</kwd><kwd>Transient</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Gastroesophageal intussusception (GEI) is a rare condition that typically affects young, large-breed dogs and presents as an acute, life-threatening condition that requires rapid recognition and treatment. It has also been thought to occur intermittently, resulting in chronic, sporadic gastrointestinal signs, though definitive tomographic identification of a spontaneously resolving intussusception has not been reported. Therefore, it was previously impossible to attribute clinical signs to intermittent intussusception rather than intermittent hiatal herniation or other oesophageal diseases. To the best of the authors&#8217; knowledge, this is the first case of true, spontaneously resolving GEI to be definitively documented tomographically, thereby demonstrating that a transient or intermittent form of the disease can occur. The pathophysiology of GEI is incompletely understood, and GEI may occur secondary to the gradual worsening of a pre-existing hiatal hernia over time. This case is the first report of GEI in a dog with a previously diagnosed, untreated hiatal hernia, demonstrating this theory to be plausible. Together, the findings in this case report demonstrate the feasibility of these theories that have previously been speculated but not definitively proven, providing insight into the pathophysiology of this poorly understood condition.</p></sec><sec><title>Case Details</title><p>A 10-year-old male neutered Australian Terrier presented to his regular primary care clinic after an episode of retching and collapse. He had reportedly been retching as though attempting to vomit, before slowly collapsing into dorsal recumbency and quickly returning to normal once picked up by his owner. The patient had a history of chronic lymphoplasmacytic rhinitis, keratoconjunctivitis sicca, and xeromycteria. The patient received several medications for the above-mentioned conditions, including antimicrobials, antihistamines, oral pilocarpine, topical ocular medications, and prednisolone or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs at different time points. The patient had a persistent biochemical hepatopathy that had been sonographically investigated and was thought to be associated with administration of the aforementioned medications. The initial physical examination revealed only mild left-sided, mucoid ocular discharge and left-sided mucopurulent nasal discharge. Routine hematology and serum biochemistry showed only mild, incidental changes, including an elevated alkaline phosphatase (ALP) (280 U/l). No specific treatment was pursued, and the patient was referred to an internal medicine specialist for assessment 2 weeks later.</p><p>Upon presentation to the referral hospital, the patient&#8217;s physical examination was unchanged; therefore, four days later, the patient underwent contrast-enhanced computed tomography (CECT) examination of the head, thorax, and abdomen under general anaesthesia to look for causes of collapse and assess his chronic, pre-existing nasal disease. The patient was premedicated with methadone (0.2 mg/kg IV) and medetomidine (5 &#181;g/kg IV). General anaesthesia was induced with alfaxalone (2 mg/kg IV to effect) and maintained with isoflurane delivered in oxygen. CECT (GE Healthcare Lightspeed CT, 16-slice CT, Illinois, United States) was performed with the patient in sternal recumbency. Iohexol 350 mg I/ml (Omnipaque<sup>&#174;</sup>, GE Healthcare Australia Pty Ltd, Australia) was administered at a dose of 2 ml/kg body weight over a 20-second injection period. Venous phase acquisitions of the abdomen and thorax were acquired 60 seconds after the injection. Venous-phase images of the abdomen revealed cranial displacement of the gastroesophageal junction and gastric cardia into the caudal mediastinum, while the stomach was positioned normally in the cranial abdomen on pre-contrast abdominal and post-contrast thoracic images acquired before and after this time point, respectively. These findings were consistent with a sliding hiatal hernia. A focal, strongly contrast-enhancing nodule was also seen arising from the bladder neck, consistent with a polyp or neoplasia. Other CT findings were incidental and consistent with bilateral non-destructive rhinitis, a dependent mineral-attenuating cholelith, and degenerative renal cysts and infarcts. Rhinoscopy immediately following computed tomography (CT) revealed bilateral mucus accumulation in the nasal cavities, and histopathological examination of mucosal biopsies was consistent with bilateral, chronic, proliferative neutrophilic and plasmacytic rhinitis. Oesophagoscopy was performed immediately after rhinoscopy and revealed an asymmetrical, ovoid (non-circular) oesophageal sphincter with a focal, puckered region and tendency to remain open. The patient had no history of chronic or intermittent gastrointestinal signs; however, a sliding hiatal hernia was considered a possible cause of retching and collapse. No specific treatment was pursued for the hiatal hernia, and the patient was discharged with an updated medical management plan for rhinitis. A fluoroscopic investigation to assess for gastroesophageal reflux was recommended but ultimately not performed.</p><p>The patient presented with a history of inappropriate urination, hyperglycemia, and glycosuria approximately 3 months later and was ultimately diagnosed with diabetes mellitus. Insulin therapy was initiated, and the following year, he underwent bilateral phacoemulsification and pseudophakia at a different referral hospital for treatment of diabetic cataracts. Right pelvic limb pain was noticed on a routine postoperative recheck examination approximately 3 months later, and the patient was referred to his local veterinarian for further investigation. Physical examination and pelvic limb radiographs with his local veterinarian raised concerns for acute exacerbation of degenerative osteoarthritis; however, the patient failed to improve with rest and pain relief. Severe muscle atrophy over the right hindquarters and pain on thoracolumbar and right pelvic limb palpation raised concerns for a neurogenic cause on follow-up examination. Routine haematology and biochemistry revealed mild leucocytosis (19.87 &#215; 10<sup>9</sup>/l) characterised by neutrophilia (17.25 &#215; 10<sup>9</sup>/l) and lymphopenia (0.98 &#215; 10<sup>9</sup>/l), as well as thrombocytopenia (93 &#215; 10<sup>9</sup>/l). Serum biochemistry revealed elevated ALT (921 U/l), elevated ALP (2210 U/l), mild hyperglycaemia (7.6 mmol/l), and hypokalaemia (3.5 mmol/l) with lipaemia and haemolysis. The next day, abdominal ultrasound was performed to investigate hepatic enzyme elevations. A large, irregular, heterogeneous, cystic mass was seen encircling the aorta at the level of the aortic trifurcation, with intraluminal echoes consistent with tumour thrombi extending cranially in the caudal vena cava from the mass to the level of the liver.</p><p>The patient was referred to the Oncology Department at the Small Animal Specialist Hospital in North Ryde 4 days later. Physical examination revealed moderate right pelvic limb lameness and a small, ulcerated area in the middle of the tongue. Repeat haematology and biochemistry revealed mild anaemia and haemoconcentration (PCV/TPP = 37/82), marginal hypocalcaemia (Ca = 1.24 mmol/l), marginal hypochloraemia (Cl = 107 mmol/l), and marked hyperglycaemia (Glucose = 24.1 mmol/l). To further characterise the sonographically identified lesion and look for evidence of potential metastases, CECT examination of the head, thorax, and abdomen was performed under general anaesthesia. The patient was premedicated with methadone (0.3 mg/kg, IV), and general anaesthesia was induced with intravenous administration of propofol (2.9 mg/kg total) and maintained with isoflurane delivered in oxygen. Contrast-enhanced computed tomography (GE Healthcare Revolution EVO CT, 128-slice CT, Illinois, United States) was performed with the patient in sternal recumbency and an intravenous catheter placed in the left cephalic vein. Pre-contrast acquisitions of the head, thorax, and abdomen were acquired. Iohexol 300 mg I/ml (Omnipaque<sup>&#174;</sup>, GE Healthcare Australia Pty Ltd, Australia) was then administered intravenously at a dose of 1.5 ml/kg body weight, with a fixed 20-second injection time. Bolus tracking was used to initiate scan acquisition, with the region of interest positioned over the caudal thoracic aorta and a trigger threshold of 100 Hounsfield units. Arterial-phase images were obtained 2 seconds after the trigger threshold was reached, followed by venous-phase images acquired 40 seconds later. A delayed-phase acquisition was performed 18 minutes after the initial trigger time based on a preliminary review of the earlier phases.</p><p>Pre-contrast acquisitions demonstrated a normally positioned stomach; however, the gastric fundus was cranially herniated through the oesophageal hiatus into the caudal esophageal lumen on the venous-phase post-contrast scan (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figs. 1</xref> and <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The distal oesophageal wall encircled part of the gastric fundus, creating a target-like appearance on transverse-plane images (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). The orad oesophagus contained a small-to-moderate amount of heterogeneous fluid-to-soft-tissue-attenuating material. Delayed post-contrast images showed the stomach had returned to its normal anatomical position.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>Transverse (A), sagittal (B) and dorsal (C) images from the venous-phase acquisition. Part of the gastric fundus (green arrow) has herniated cranially through the oesophageal hiatus into the caudal thoracic oesophagus (red arrow). The gastroesophageal junction (blue arrow) remains in a normal position. The more proximal thoracic oesophagus is mildly distended by a small volume of heterogeneous, intraluminal, fluid-and-soft-tissue-attenuating material. Findings are consistent with gastroesophageal intussusception.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-15-10-5400-g001.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>Dorsal reconstructions of the thorax and cranial abdomen acquired during pre-contrast (A), venous-phase (B), and delayed post-contrast (C) phases of the study. The stomach is appropriately positioned with minimal distension of the oesophagus in the pre-contrast (A) and delayed (C) acquisitions. Gastroesophageal intussusception is identified during the venous-phase acquisition (B) as outlined in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-15-10-5400-g002.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><title>Transverse-plane images of the thorax from the venous-phase acquisition at approximately the level of the T4 (A), T5 (B), T8 (C), T9 (D), and T10 (E) vertebrae. The gastric fundus (green arrow) has herniated cranially through the oesophageal hiatus into the caudal thoracic oesophagus (red arrow). Note that unlike in cases of hiatal herniation, the distal oesophageal walls are visualised surrounding part of the gastric fundus, creating a target-like appearance, indicative of intussusception.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-15-10-5400-g003.jpg"/></fig><p>An osteoaggressive, markedly vascular, and locally invasive caudal retroperitoneal mass was identified arising from the right iliopsoas muscle and extending ventral to the L4&#8211;L7 vertebrae. The caudal vena cava contained an extensive intraluminal, soft-tissue attenuating filling defect, and marked proximal right pelvic limb muscular atrophy was identified, indicating tumour thrombi and neurogenic atrophy, respectively. Other incidental computed tomography findings included hepatic/biliary cysts, chronic renal infarcts, cystic left hepatic lymphadenopathy, spondylosis deformans, shoulder and stifle osteoarthrosis, a left thyroid nodule, a small right thyroid, bronchial plugging indicative of chronic inflammatory disease, and nasal changes consistent with chronic inflammatory rhinitis.</p><p>Gastric changes were consistent with transient, self-resolving GEI. This may represent a one-time, spontaneous GEI, possibly triggered by iohexol-induced nausea (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Sanderson, 2005</xref>), anaesthesia-associated lower oesophageal sphincter laxity (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Van Geffen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>), or a combination thereof. Alternatively, the finding may reflect incidental capture of a chronic, intermittent GEI that is unrelated to intravenous contrast or anaesthetic administration. If this is the case, the intussusception could represent a progression or exacerbation of the previously documented hiatal hernia, or could represent a separate, concurrent, intermittently occurring disease entity.</p><p>The sublumbar mass arising from the iliopsoas was suggestive of malignant neoplasia. Differential diagnoses included haemangiosarcoma or a neuroendocrine tumour. Ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspirates were obtained. Cytological review was performed by a specialist veterinary pathologist, revealing individual and clustered, hyperchromic, pleomorphic spindle cells with moderately basophilic cytoplasm, variable punctate vacuolation, intracellular haemosiderin, scant mitotic figures, and large nuclei containing stippled chromatin and prominent nucleoli, consistent with a right iliopsoas haemangiosarcoma.</p><p>No treatments were considered necessary for the spontaneously resolved gastroesophageal intussusception because signs of gastrointestinal disease had not been reported. The sublumbar mass was deemed inappropriate for surgical resection due to its extent and invasiveness. A poor prognosis was given. Various chemotherapeutic options and palliative radiation therapy were discussed, but the patient&#8217;s owners declined further treatment. The patient was discharged the following morning to continue his ocular medications, insulin, appetite stimulants, antinausea medications, and ongoing pain relief. The patient&#8217;s owners reported a clinical deterioration in the form of whimpering, panting, hotness to the touch, and pelvic limb weakness when toileting 1 day after discharge. 3 days later, the patient presented to another 24-hour specialist facility having died at home. No postmortem investigations were conducted.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Gastroesophageal intussusception is defined as the retrograde translocation of all or part of the stomach into the thoracic oesophageal lumen (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Shibly <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). In some cases, other organs, including the duodenum, omentum, spleen, and pancreas, may invaginate alongside the stomach (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Rowland and Robinson, 1978</xref>; <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Roach and Hecht, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Emery <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Brady <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Grimes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). Importantly, in cases of GEI, the gastroesophageal sphincter maintains a normal position; this distinguishes it from axial or sliding hiatal hernias, in which the gastroesophageal junction is cranially malpositioned in the thorax, as outlined by Leib and Blass (cited in <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Grimes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>).</p><p>GEI has historically been considered to most commonly occur in young, large-breed dogs (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">von Werthern <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Rowland and Robinson, 1978</xref>; <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Moore, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Grimes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). Male German Shepherds are particularly over-represented and may be predisposed; A 2020 retrospective study found that dogs suffering from GEI had a median age of 13.2 months, were male in 72% of cases, and were German Shepherds in one-third (33%) of cases (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Grimes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). There are, however, reports of GEI in older dogs (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Pietra <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Kaewamatawong <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Brady <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Rohwedder &amp; Hellmuth, 2021</xref>), female dogs (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Greenfield <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">McGill <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Kaewamatawong <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>), cats (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Van Camp <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Van Geffen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Abbaszadeh Hasiri <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Martinez <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Tayler <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>) and a variety of other breeds, including Australian Shepherd (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Shibly <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>), Siberian Husky (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Greenfield <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">McGill <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Takeuchi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>), Briard (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Walker and Ryan, 2017</xref>), Pug (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Pietra <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>), Labrador (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Graham <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>), Golden Retriever (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Kaewamatawong <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>), Boxer (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Brincin <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2022</xref>), Doberman (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Sharma and A, 2005</xref>), Dalmatian (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">J&#228;rvinen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1995</xref>) and mixed breeds (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Rohwedder and Hellmuth, 2021</xref>), etc. This case report is the first to document the condition in an Australian Terrier.</p><p>Dogs with GEI most commonly present with gastrointestinal signs such as vomiting and regurgitation, and may suffer haematemesis, dyspnoea, and abdominal discomfort (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Shibly <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Grimes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). Acute-persistent and chronic-recurrent disease patterns have been described (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">von Werthern <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Shibly <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Grimes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>).</p><p>Acute, persistent GEI is the most commonly reported form in dogs (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Shibly <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Grimes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>) and is caused by herniation and entrapment of the stomach into the caudal oesophageal lumen, with or without other organs. The presenting clinical signs are caused by oesophageal obstruction and intra-thoracic mass effect, with or without secondary aspiration pneumonia (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">von Werthern <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">McGill <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Lockwood <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Shibly <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Displacement of the stomach into the caudal oesophagus impairs expansion of the caudal lung lobes and can result in respiratory distress (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">von Werthern <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Lockwood <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Compression of the pulmonary parenchyma, pulmonary vasculature, and caudal vena cava impedes venous return and leads to hypovolaemic shock, which is often the cause of rapid decline and death in these patients (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Lockwood <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Torad and Hassan, 2015</xref>). Additionally, compromised blood supply to the stomach and other prolapsed organs may lead to ischaemic necrosis and endotoxic shock (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">von Werthern <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Lockwood <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). The prognosis has traditionally been considered poor (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Lockwood <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>); rapid deterioration and death can occur without prompt diagnosis and aggressive treatment, and mortality rates of up to 95% have been reported by Leib and Blass, as cited by <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Martinez <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2001)</xref>. This might be attributed, at least in part, to a failure to recognise the condition and intervene before deterioration. A more recent study demonstrated a far better prognosis: 88% of dogs undergoing surgical intervention surviving to discharge, and 65% achieved long-term survival, though some chronic-form cases were included in this cohort (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Grimes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). Postoperative sequelae and complications, particularly megaoesophagus and secondary aspiration pneumonia, were common following GEI correction (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Grimes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>); the latter of which may contribute to respiratory signs (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Lockwood <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>).</p><p>Chronic or episodic forms of GEI have also been reported, typically resulting in intermittent gastrointestinal signs (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">von Werthern <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Greenfield <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Grimes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Shibly <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). This is the predominant form reported in cats (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Van Camp <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Van Geffen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Martinez <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Shibly <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>), although chronic disease has been associated with GEI in dogs, albeit less commonly (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Pietra <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Grimes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). One retrospective study of canine gastroesophageal intussusception noted that dogs with a chronic history were less likely to have previously been diagnosed with megaoesophagus than those with an acute history of clinical signs (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Grimes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). The authors of these cases proposed that GEI could have resulted from one of the following: a hiatal hernia that resulted in gastrointestinal signs until the stomach eventually invaginated into the oesophagus; undiagnosed megaoesophagus; or a lax lower oesophageal sphincter that allowed intermittent, self-correcting GEI.</p><p>To the best of the authors knowledge, there is only one report of spontaneous resolution of a GEI in a dog. This was identified endoscopically in an 8-week-old Husky with a 6-week history of regurgitation (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Greenfield <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>). In this case, the stomach was seen to intermittently intussuscept into the oesophagus, and although GEI had not been documented previously, the duration of clinical signs led the authors to consider chronically recurrent intussusception to be the likely cause of disease. However, the inability to assess concurrent hiatal abnormalities is a limitation of endoscopic evaluation of the oesophagus (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Walker and Ryan, 2017</xref>). A hiatal hernia is a key differential for GEI and may be a predisposing condition (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Grimes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). Computed tomography allows for differentiation between hiatal hernias and GEI (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Rohwedder and Hellmuth, 2021</xref>). To the best of the authors&#8217; knowledge, only one other report has described the computed tomographic features of GEI in dogs; however, that case involved acute-onset disease with immediate surgical intervention (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Rohwedder and Hellmuth, 2021</xref>), and spontaneous resolution was not observed.</p><p>Our case provides the first tomographic evidence that spontaneous resolution of a confirmed GEI can occur in dogs, lending plausibility to the theory that transient GEI can occur in dogs and that intermittent GEI may therefore underlie chronic clinical signs in some patients.</p><p>Oesophageal abnormalities, such as megaoesophagus, dysmotility, or oesophageal hiatus laxity, were speculated by Applewhite <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2002) to predispose affected animals to GEI, as cited by <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Grimes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2020)</xref>. <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Van Geffen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2006)</xref> also cited a 1984 review by Leib and Blass that found that the majority dogs with GEI had pre-existing oesophageal disease, most commonly megaoesophagus. Another retrospective study found that 36% of dogs with GEI were previously diagnosed with megaoesophagus (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Grimes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>), and pre-existing or concurrent megaoesophagus has also been reported in a number of cats with GEI (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Van Camp <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Martinez <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Van Geffen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).</p><p>The link between megaoesophagus and GEI is poorly understood. It is thought that megaoesophagus might lead to dilatation of the lower oesophageal sphincter and subsequent intussusception of the stomach into the oesophagus during episodes of regurgitation or vomiting (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Van Camp <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Grimes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). Unlike the previous case describing CT features of acute-onset GEI (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Rohwedder and Hellmuth, 2021</xref>), concurrent or pre-existing megaoesophagus was never documented in our patient. <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Grimes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2020)</xref> also reported that dogs with chronic clinical signs were less likely to have a prior diagnosis of megaoesophagus than those with acute presentations. This might imply different pathophysiologies between the acute persistent and chronic intermittent forms of the disease.</p><p>An alternative theory suggests that lower oesophageal sphincter dilation could occur with reflux oesophagitis secondary to recurrent regurgitation and vomiting caused by pre-existing gastrointestinal disease (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Rohwedder and Hellmuth, 2021</xref>). Hiatal hernias in particular have been proposed to cause chronic, intermittent gastrointestinal signs until the stomach eventually invaginates into the oesophagus (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Grimes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). A pre-existing hiatal hernia has been reported in a pug that subsequently developed GEI (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Pietra <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>); however, this dog had undergone surgical treatment of the hernia prior to the development of GEI, confounding the association. Our report is the first documented case of GEI in a patient with a history of untreated hiatal hernia. At the time of hiatal hernia diagnosis, oesophagoscopy revealed a subjectively puckered, dilated lower oesophageal sphincter, which might support the theory that gradual dilation can lead to eventual invagination of the stomach into the oesophagus. However, our patient did not suffer from chronic or recurrent gastrointestinal signs between the diagnosis of hiatal hernia and GEI. Although clinically-silent oesophageal reflux cannot be excluded, the oesophageal sphincter changes in this patient may have been incidental and unrelated to the tomographically identified sliding hernia or GEI. Therefore, although lower oesophageal sphincter laxity might be speculated in this single-animal case report, the associations between GEI and concurrent or pre-existing gastrointestinal disease must be interpreted with caution and should be the subject of future research.</p><p>This case report definitively demonstrates that GEI can exist as a transient, spontaneously resolving entity and is not synonymous with entrapment and strangulation. This lends plausibility to the notion that chronic-intermittent or transient forms of the disease might occur in dogs. However, it must be noted that the patient outlined in this case report did not have the typical history of chronic, intermittent gastrointestinal signs that have been attributed to supposedly intermittent GEI in the past, and that GEI was only definitively documented on one occasion. Although recurrent, intermittent, and clinically-silent episodes of GEI might occur, recurrent or intermittent GEI was not definitively identified in this case. Furthermore, the association between supposedly intermittent GEI and clinical signs has not been established; further research is required to determine whether intermittent GEI is the true cause of clinical signs when suspected. Both the hiatal hernia and self-resolving gastroesophageal intussusception occurred as transient abnormalities during contrast-enhanced CT studies. To the best of the authors&#8217; knowledge, this is the first case of GEI to be documented immediately after the administration of iodinated contrast media, and it is possible that both conditions occurred secondary to nausea induced by iohexol administration, with or without any association with other disease processes (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Sanderson, 2005</xref>). Therefore, this report lends credibility to multiple theories about the pathophysiology of GEI, and further research is required to better understand the potential associations with iodinated contrast administration.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, this case tomographically demonstrates for the first time that a self-resolving, non-entrapped, transient form of GEI can occur in dogs. Although recurrent, intermittent GEI was not directly observed in this case, these findings support the hypothesis that intermittent GEI may underlie chronic, episodic gastrointestinal signs in some patients, as has been previously proposed. Further research is required to definitively determine whether an association exists between intermittent intussusception and chronic or intermittent clinical signs. To the best of our knowledge, this is also the first reported case of GEI in a dog with a pre-existing, uncorrected hiatal hernia and the first to describe spontaneous onset of GEI following intravenous iodinated contrast administration. These observations support the possibility that such events could represent adverse reactions to contrast administration or anaesthesia. Further studies are needed to clarify the potential associations between transient GEI, general anaesthesia, iodinated contrast administration, hiatal herniation, and other disease processes.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>The authors declare that no financial support was received for the research, authorship, or publication of this article.</p></sec><sec><title>Author&#8217;s contribution</title><p>Dr. Mason White performed a literature review, drafted the manuscript, coordinated and included revisions, produced figures for publication, and approved the final manuscript.</p><p>Dr. Michelle Lau interpreted diagnostic imaging studies during clinical workup, contributed to manuscript revisions, and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are not openly available due to reasons of sensitivity and are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbaszadeh Hasiri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shojaee Tabrizi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahrari Khafi</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gastroesophageal intussusception in a domestic short-hair cat</article-title><source>IJVR</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>358</fpage><lpage>361</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biskup</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Latimer</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gastrooesophageal intussusception with splenic involvement in an adult dog</article-title><source>Vet. Rec. Case Rep</source><year>2017</year><fpage>4</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brincin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gastroesophageal intussusception secondary to induction of emesis with subsequent development of septic pericardial effusion after corrective surgery</article-title><source>J. Small Anim. Pract</source><year>2022</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34370318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jsap.13395</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biller</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nuth</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrasonographic Diagnosis of Gastroesophageal Intussusception in a 7 Week Old German Shepherd</article-title><source>Isr. J. Vet. Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>46</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buss</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhein</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbee</surname><given-names>D.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seitz</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gastroesophageal intussusception in a Labrador retriever</article-title><source>Can. Vet. J</source><year>1998</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>709</fpage><lpage>711</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9818138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1539471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greenfield</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coolman</surname><given-names>B.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bilateral incisional gastropexies for treatment of intermittent gastroesophageal intussusception in a puppy</article-title><source>J. Anim. Vet. Med. Assoc</source><year>1997</year><volume>211</volume><fpage>728</fpage><lpage>730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9301743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>B.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedlund</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tobias</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ham</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Repellin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sumner</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boudreau</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristics and long-term outcomes of dogs with gastroesophageal intussusception</article-title><source>J. Anim. Vet. Med. Assoc</source><year>2020</year><volume>256</volume><fpage>914</fpage><lpage>920</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2460/javma.256.8.914</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32223709</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>J&#228;rvinen</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saario</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andresen</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Happonen</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saari</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajam&#228;ki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lung Injury Leading to Respiratory Distress Syndrome in Young Dalmatian Dogs</article-title><source>J. Vet. Intern. Med</source><year>1995</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7674217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1939-1676.1995.tb03290.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaewamatawong</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banlunara</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wangrattanaparanee</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiertkrittikhoon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical, Radiographic and Pathological Features of Persistent Gastroesophageal Intussusception in an Adult Dog: a Case Report</article-title><source>Thai J. Vet. Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>225</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lockwood</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Radlinksy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crochik</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gastroesophageal intussusception in a German shepherd</article-title><source>Compend. Contin. Educ. Vet</source><year>2010</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>E1</fpage><lpage>E4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20957610</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Troy</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waldron</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intermittent gastroesophageal intussusception in a cat with idiopathic megaesophagus</article-title><source>J. Am. Anim. Hosp. Assoc</source><year>2001</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11361114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5326/15473317-37-3-234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGill</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lenard</surname><given-names>Z.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>See</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonsurgical Treatment of Gastroesophageal Intussusception in a Puppy</article-title><source>J. Am. Anim. Hosp. Assoc</source><year>2009</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19570902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5326/0450185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gastroesophageal intussusception</article-title><source>Small Animal Gastroenterology</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>Hannover, Germany</publisher-loc><publisher-name>J&#246;rg M Steiner Schl&#252;tersche</publisher-name><fpage>148</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pietra</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gentilini</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinna</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fracassi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Venturini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cipone</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intermittent Gastroesophageal Intussusception in a Dog: clinical Features, Radiographic and Endoscopic Findings, and Surgical Management</article-title><source>Vet. Res. Commun</source><year>2003</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14535521</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1023/b:verc.0000014271.98916.ff</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roach</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hecht</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What Is Your Diagnosis?</article-title><source>J. Anim. Vet. Med. Assoc</source><year>2007</year><volume>231</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2460/javma.231.3.381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17669038</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rohwedder</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hellmuth</surname><given-names>V.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gastroesophageal intussusception with complete herniation of the spleen in a 12 months old dog with idiopathic megaoesophagus</article-title><source>Vet. Rec. Case Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>15</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rowland</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gastro&#8211; oesophageal intussusception in an adult dog</article-title><source>J. Small Anim. Pract</source><year>1978</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">642469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1748-5827.1978.tb05464.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current Concepts for the Management of Chronic Renal Failure in the Dog and Cat--Early Diagnosis and Supportive Care</article-title><source>Proceedings of the World Small Animal Veterinary Association World Congress</source><year>2005</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gastroesophageal Intussusception in a Doberman Dog: a Rare Condition</article-title><source>Indian J. Vet. Pathol</source><year>2005</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>57</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shibly</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karl</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hittmair</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirt</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute gastroesophageal intussusception in a juvenile Australian shepherd dog: endoscopic treatment and long-term follow-up</article-title><source>BMC Vet. Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>109</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24885648</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1746-6148-10-109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4024095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosoya</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Itami</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okumura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postoperative improvement of megaesophagus and esophageal motility in a 19-day-old puppy with gastroesophageal intussusception</article-title><source>J. Vet. Med. Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>1740</fpage><lpage>1744</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34544935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1292/jvms.21-0384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8636889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tayler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mullowney</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lataretu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plested</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kathrani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gastroesophageal intussusception and extreme esophageal dilatation secondary to bilateral laryngeal paralysis in a cat</article-title><source>J. Vet. Intern. Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1088</fpage><lpage>1092</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33559171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jvim.16056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7995417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torad</surname><given-names>F.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gastroesophageal Intussusception in a 50-Day-Old German Shepherd Dog</article-title><source>Top. Companion Anim. Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26041593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/j.tcam.2015.02.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>von Werthern</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montavon</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fl&#252;ckiger</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gastroesophageal intussusception in a young German shepherd dog</article-title><source>J. Small Anim. Pract</source><year>1996</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8912243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1748-5827.1996.tb01750.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Camp</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Love</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumaresan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Radiographic Diagnosis&#8212;Gastroesophageal Intussusception in a Cat</article-title><source>Vet. Radiol. Ultrasound</source><year>1998</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9634185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1740-8261.1998.tb00338.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Geffen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandevelde</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Ham</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoybergs</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daminet</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Idiopathic megaoesophagus and intermittent gastro-oesophageal intussusception in a cat</article-title><source>J. Small Anim. Pract</source><year>2006</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16911118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1748-5827.2006.00024.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>J.J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gastro-oesophageal intussusception in a 25-week-old Briard</article-title><source>Vet. Rec. Case Rep</source><year>2017</year><fpage>5</fpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>