<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2846</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">openvetj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Veterinary Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2226-4485</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2218-6050</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tripoli</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11563613</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11563613.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11563613</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11563613</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39553753</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/OVJ.2024.v14.i9.30</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OVJ-14-2415</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Hematological profile of free-range Sunda porcupine (<italic toggle="yes">Hystrix javanica</italic>)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fibrianto</surname><given-names initials="YH">Yuda Heru</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larasati</surname><given-names initials="AD">Arinda Devi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Budipitojo</surname><given-names initials="T">Teguh</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wendo</surname><given-names initials="WD">Woro Danur</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Physiology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Gadjah Mada, Yogyakarta, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Anatomy, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Gadjah Mada, Yogyakarta, Indonesia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Arinda Devi Larasati. Department of Anatomy, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Gadjah Mada. Yogyakarta, Indonesia. <email>arinda.aja@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>9</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">475085</issue-id><fpage>2415</fpage><lpage>2420</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-11-18 15:25:24.860"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2415.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>The Sunda porcupine, or the Javan porcupine <italic toggle="yes">(Hystrix javanica</italic>), is a rodent native to Indonesia. Although information about its conservation status is available, the hematological profile is limited. The normal hematological profile of an animal is essential as a basic health indicator to determine the initial state of a pathological process of a disease. Since the hematological profile can provide significant evidence regarding the health status of the species, the Sunda Porcupine&#8217;s hematological profile can benefit conservation initiatives. Therefore, hematological evaluation of these porcupines can play a role in conservation initiatives, breeding strategies, and the prevention of zoonotic diseases.</p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>This research revealed the routine blood evaluation and white blood cell (WBC) morphological features of the free-ranging Sunda porcupine (<italic toggle="yes">H. javanica</italic>).</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>Blood samples from four free-range individuals captured Sunda porcupine (<italic toggle="yes">H. javanica</italic>) were obtained intracardially for routine hematological evaluation and WBC staining for morphological identification. The profiles were then analyzed descriptively.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Hematology profile averages were generally 4.04 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup>/Ul for RBC; Hemoglobin was in 12.83 g/dl; Hematocrit by 37.8%; MCV 107.1 fl; MCH 31.80 pg; MCHC 31.23 g/dl; while WBC and platelet (PLT) were at 9.67 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup>/&#956;l and 503.00 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup>/&#956;l, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>The morphology of red blood cells, WBCs, and the hematological profile of the Javan hedgehog is not much different from that of other mammals such as crested porcupines, ferrets, and guinea pigs. Until now, there has been limited research on the hematology of Sunda porcupines, which has led to a limited understanding of their health status. We anticipate that the findings of this study will serve as a diagnostic instrument for evaluating the health condition of Sunda porcupine and serve as a benchmark.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Sunda porcupine</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Hystrix javanica</italic></kwd><kwd>Hematology</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Indonesia is a country that has many resources in animal diversity, including porcupines. Sunda porcupine (<italic toggle="yes">Hystrix javanica</italic>), also known as Javan porcupine, is endemic to Java, Madura, Bali, Lombok, Sumbawa, and Flores islands in Indonesia, which is classified as &#8220;Least Concern&#8221; (LC) on the International Union for Conservation of Nature red list of threatened species (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Heinrich <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). This classification indicates that the species will not face a high risk of extinction shortly. However, despite its conservation status, illegal hunting and exploitation of the Sunda porcupine continue to increase, threatening the species sustainability (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Farida <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). According to recent reports, porcupines are among the most commonly seen animals in Asian markets that have been surveyed (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Cantlay <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017</xref>). People poached and hunted the porcupine for food, ethnomedicinal application, and commercial purposes. Porcupine meat has important nutritional and supplementary values as a source of protein and medicinal substance, including aphrodisiac potency (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Anita <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2015</xref>). Their visceral organs and gastrointestinal products, called bezoars, are used medicinally, while their hair and quills are employed as ornaments (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Duffin, 2013</xref>).</p><p>In conservation efforts regarding the Sunda porcupine, research has been done on the carbohydrate residue distribution in the testes for spermatid maturation, which can serve as foundational information in the breeding strategy (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Budipitojo <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020a</xref>). The placenta anatomy of Sunda porcupine has been identified which has a discoid shape and is classified as the hemochorial type (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Budipitojo <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, 2020b</xref>). Body measurements correlate with the body volume and body weight of the Sunda porcupine fetus, with a significant positive correlation found in horizontal body diameter, vertical body diameter, and head diameter (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Adi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, 2021</xref>). Ultrasonography measurements were performed to analyze the macroanatomy of the female reproductive in the Sunda porcupine without damaging the specimen (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Wahid <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). Evaluation of the results of radiographs of the front legs of the sunda porcupine in the lateral view and dorso-palmar view does not show any abnormalities (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Suparmin <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, 2018</xref>). Nevertheless, the data for determining the health status of <italic toggle="yes">H. javanica</italic> is rarely known due to the lack of research conducted. The most basic information to know about the health status of this animal is to have specific parameters regarding the hematological profile. Until now, there is no exact information on the normal hematological levels of the Sunda porcupine. However, hematological changes in the skin wound healing of Javan porcupine have been studied (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Agungpriyono <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>).</p><p>Knowledge of the hematological profile of blood can be a diagnostic and prognostic tool for porcupine&#8217;s health status. Hematological parameters and blood chemistry can be used to diagnose diseases, establish disease processes, and track disease development. Through hematological parameters, potential diseases can be identified to develop appropriate treatment strategies. Apart from that, hematological parameters also help monitor the prevalence of a disease so that disease spread can be prevented and effective disease management can be carried out (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Proverbio <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). These insights are crucial for implementing timely interventions and maintaining the health of porcupine populations. This is because the well-being of the wild <italic toggle="yes">H. javanica</italic> is starting to be threatened. Porcupines can occasionally be discovered dead or ill in their natural habitat without documentation of the incident. Moreover, zoonotic pathogen transmission also jeopardizes human health since porcupines are denoted as the new host of leptospira (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Cantlay <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017</xref>). Studies on the hematological profiles of other porcupine species, such as the crested porcupine (<italic toggle="yes">Hystrix cristata</italic>), can reveal important details about their current health and possible illnesses. As an illustration, elevated urea and creatinine levels in crested porcupines may signify renal impairment resulting from leptospira infection (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Coppola <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>).</p><p>The present study aimed to investigate the hematology in relation to the blood cell morphology of the Sunda porcupine (<italic toggle="yes">H. javanica</italic>). The current findings will serve as reference data for health assessment studies, epidemiology, and the conservation of this remarkable species in Indonesia. Additionally, these findings will enhance our understanding of the population processes, ecological relationships, geographical variations, and physiological conditions of the Sunda porcupine. Assessing the health status of the Sunda porcupine can improve conservation initiatives, breeding strategies, and the prevention of zoonotic diseases. Therefore, preliminary data from routine blood evaluations and white blood cell (WBC) morphological features of free-range Sunda porcupines may provide insight into their health status compared to other species. These data are expected to serve as a valuable parameter for health assessment and pathogenesis prediction in species protection management and a one health approach.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>This study used four Sunda porcupine blood samples (<italic toggle="yes">H. javanica</italic>) obtained from porcupine hunters in Tawangmangu subdistrict, Karanganyar Regency, Central Java. Blood collection can be done by taking blood from the neck, hands, feet, or from the heart. A blood sample of 3&#8211;5 ml is taken from the intracardiac with a 10 ml syringe after the porcupine is slaughtered and then placed in an EDTA tube (purple cap) in a vacutainer for the plasma sample, which will be used for the hematology examination process. This method refers to research from <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Coppola <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2020)</xref> Routine hematology examinations are carried out using the 5-Diff Vet Hematology Analyzer method. The hematological values analyzed included red blood cells (RBC), hemoglobin (Hgb), mean corpuscular volume (MCV), mean corpuscular Hgb (MCH), MCH concentration (MCHC), RBC distribution width (RDW), platelets (PLT), mean platelet volume (MPV), platelet distribution width (PDW), platelet crit (PCT), WBCs, lymphocytes, monocytes, granulocytes, and eosinophils. Blood smears were fixed using methanol, and they were stained with Giemsa.</p><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>For this research, ethical clearance (Number: 0129/EC-FKH/Int./2019) was obtained through the Research Ethics Commission of the Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Gadjah Mada, Yogyakarta.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The results of hematological level parameters consisting of RBCs and WBCs from Sunda hedgehogs were described in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><p><xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> describes the results of Hgb levels in Sunda porcupine obtained RBC levels with an average of 4.04 <italic toggle="yes">&#215;</italic> 10<sup>6</sup>/ul, Hgb 12.83 g/dl, hematocrit levels 41.03%, MCV levels 101.70 fl, MCH levels 31.80 pg, and MCHC levels 31.23 g/dl. The results of WBC measurements in Sunda porcupine WBC values of 9.67 <italic toggle="yes">&#215;</italic> 10<sup>3</sup>/ul, Neutrophils 62.68%, Basophils 0.80%, Eosinophils 2.90%, Lymphocytes 25.08%, Monocytes 8.55%, and Platelet levels 503 <italic toggle="yes">&#215;</italic> 10<sup>3</sup>/ul.</p><sec><title>Neutrophil</title><p>The shape of the neutrophil from Sunda porcupine was described in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. The shape of the neutrophil band found in this study corresponds to <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">Kuehnel (2003)</xref>, which is included in the criteria: a) Neutrophils with banded nuclei. b) Neutrophils with banded nuclei and visible nuclear segmentation. The cytoplasm is light pink and contains azurophilic granules with a diameter of about 0.5 &#956;m. c) Two neutrophils with segmented nuclei. Fine threads connect the three segments in each core. Coarse, highly colored chromatin bodies are located in the peripheral nuclear membrane. d) Neutrophils are over-segmented into five segments. The morphology of WBCs in Sunda porcupine blood smear preparations shows that neutrophils have a ribbon-like nucleus and are segmented. Compared with Neutrophils&#8217; morphology in other mammals (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Theml <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>), it does not show a significant difference.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Hematological results of Sunda porcupines. </title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Results of Sunda Porcupine</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Units</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RBC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<sup>6</sup>/ul</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hgb</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">g/dl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.55</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hematocrit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">fl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCHC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">g/dl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RDW-CV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.75</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<sup>3</sup>/ul</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.405</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutrophils %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.45</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutrophils #</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<sup>3</sup>/ul</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.865</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basophils %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basophils #</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<sup>3</sup>/ul</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.075</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eosinophils %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.65</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eosinophils #</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<sup>3</sup>/ul</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymphocytes %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.45</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymphocytes #</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<sup>3</sup>/ul</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.475</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monocytes %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.45</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monocytes #</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<sup>3</sup>/ul</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.815</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platelet count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<sup>3</sup>/ul</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">503.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">266</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">611</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">567.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MPV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">fl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.85</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDW</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.442</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5425</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>Sunda porcupine neutrophils. There are visible neutrophils containing granules (right), and some do not show granules; black arrows indicate platelets (scale bar = 10 &#956;m).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2415-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Lymphocytes</title><p>The shape of the lymphocytes from Sunda porcupine was described in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>. Lymphocytes in Sunda porcupine observed in this study are within the morphological description by <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Theml <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2004)</xref> range of normal lymphocytes (some adjacent to segmented neutrophilic granulocytes). Some larger lymphocytes with granules may occur in average persons. Occasionally, and without known triggers, the cytoplasm may expand. Lymphocytes are irregularly shaped, with different shapes from one monocyte to another. The cytoplasm is widened and narrowed to resemble the shape of the nucleus. The morphology of lymphocytes in other mammals (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Theml <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>) does not show a significant difference.</p><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>Sunda porcupine lymphocytes (scale bar = 10 &#956;m).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2415-g002.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><title>Sunda porcupine monocytes (scale bar = 10 &#956;m).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2415-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Monocytes</title><p>The shape of the monocytes from Sunda porcupine was described in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>. The monocytes observed in this study by <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Theml <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2004)</xref> range from images of monocyte types with lobes, nucleus, gray-blue cytoplasm, and fine granulations&#8212;to phagocytic monocytes with plasma vacuoles. Monocytes have rheophilic granules and nuclei resembling neutrophil bands, but their cytoplasm is usually gray&#8211;blue. The monocytes in the blood smear are seen to have gray lobes, nuclei, and cytoplasm with granulations. Compared with the morphology of monocytes in other mammals (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Theml <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>), it does not show a significant difference.</p></sec><sec><title>Eosinophil</title><p>The shape of the eosinophil from Sunda porcupine was described in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>. The results of observations on the morphology of Sunda porcupine eosinophil were observed by <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Theml <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2004)</xref> that Eosinophilic granulocytes with orange blood cell granules. In contrast, neutrophilic granulocyte granules are not round but bud-shaped&#8212;basophilic granulocytes. The granules are cell-shaped like eosinophilic granulocytes but dark blue to purple&#8212;very prominent large granules in basophilic granulocytes in chronic myeloproliferative disease (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Theml <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>). The Sunda porcupine eosinophil is seen to have lobes with granulations clustered around the nucleus. Compared with the morphology of eosinophils in other mammals (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Theml <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>), it does not show a significant difference.</p><fig position="float" id="fig4" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><title>Sunda porcupine eosinophil (scale bar = 10 &#956;m).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2415-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>There is a lack of information regarding the Sunda porcupine&#8217;s hematological profile. To confirm the hematological results of the Sunda porcupine, the comparison parameters in this study used the results from research using the crested porcupine by <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Coppola <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2020)</xref> using ten samples from the crested porcupine. The hematology results of the Sunda porcupine that we studied showed an average level of RBC (4.04 <italic toggle="yes">&#215;</italic> 10<sup>6</sup>/ul). <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Coppola <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2020)</xref> reported a higher value of 5.7 <italic toggle="yes">&#215;</italic> 10<sup>6</sup>/ul than this result. Sunda porcupine RBC is also lower on average compared to ferret RBC levels stated by <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Tilley <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2016)</xref> (6.60&#8211;12.18 <italic toggle="yes">&#215;</italic> 10<sup>6</sup>/ul), lower compared to Guinea pig (5.3&#8211;6.0 <italic toggle="yes">&#215;</italic> 10<sup>6</sup>/ul) (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Coleman <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>) and African hedgehog (5.01 <italic toggle="yes">&#215;</italic> 10<sup>6</sup>/ul) (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Okorie-Kanu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). Hgb levels in our Sunda porcupine showed an average level of 12.83 g/dl, not much different from Crested porcupines (13.6 g/dl), Guinea pigs (13&#8211;14.4 g/dl), and African hedgehogs (10.71&#8211;14.86 g/dl), and still within the normal range of Ferret (12.5&#8211;18.2 g/dL). The average hematocrit level of the Sunda porcupine (41.3%) was compared with that of the crested porcupine (34.8%) by <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Coppola <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2020)</xref>. The hematocrit results of the Sunda porcupine were higher than those of the crested porcupine, compared to ferrets (37.5%&#8211;59%) by <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Tilley <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2016)</xref> and guinea pigs (42&#8211;46 g/dl). Sunda porcupine hematocrit levels are almost identical. MCV and MCH levels in Sunda porcupines are much higher compared to crested porcupines (MCV: 77.3 fl; MCH: 23.8 pg), ferrets (MCV: 43.6&#8211;61.2 fl; MCH: 14.5&#8211;20.5 pg) (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Coppola <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Tilley <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2016</xref>), and guinea pigs (MCV: 75&#8211;79 fl; MCH: 24&#8211;24.5 pg) also African hedgehog (MCV: 76.34&#8211;9.78 fl; MCH: 22.47&#8211;31.44 pg) (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Okorie-Kanu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>, 2014</xref>). Sunda porcupine MCHC levels (31.2 g/dl) are in the same range as crested porcupine (30.1 g/dl), ferret (29.0&#8211;37.0 g/dl), guinea pig (30.9&#8211;31.4 g/dl), and African hedgehog (27.69&#8211;35.19 g/dl). From the parameters of the WBC component, the most different results from the Sunda porcupine are RBCs, which are lower than the others in the Sunda porcupine. Hence, the MCV and MCH of the Sunda porcupine are higher than the other animals.</p><p>The average WBC and platelet (PLT) levels in Sunda porcupine were 9.67 <italic toggle="yes">&#215;</italic> 10<sup>3</sup>/ul and 503.00 <italic toggle="yes">&#215;</italic> 10<sup>3</sup>/ul, respectively. These results are still in the range of values that are almost the same as the values for crested porcupines (WBC: 2.50&#8211;15.80 <italic toggle="yes">&#215;</italic> 10<sup>3</sup>/ul; PLT: 238&#8211;910 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup>/ul), ferrets (WBC: 8.1&#8211;22.5 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup>/ul; PLT: 86&#8211;1479 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup>/ul) (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Tilley <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Coppola <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2020</xref>), Guinea pigs (WBC: 6.3&#8211;6.4 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup>/ul; PLT: 260&#8211;278 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup>/ul) (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Coleman <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>), and African hedgehog (WBC:11.50&#8211;21.65 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup>/ul) (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Okorie-Kanu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). Neutrophils in Sunda porcupines (62.68%) are still in the range of ferrets (16.5%&#8211;81.30%) and African hedgehog (52%&#8211;76%), but the minimum levels in Sunda porcupines are like guinea pigs (43%&#8211;45%). The average basophil value of the Sunda porcupine (0.80%) is like the basophil level in ferrets (0.0%&#8211;1.8%), African hedgehog (0.0%&#8211;1.00%), and guinea pigs (0.2%). The average eosinophil value in Sunda porcupines (2.90%) is similar to that of ferrets (0.0%&#8211;6.7%), guinea pigs (1%&#8211;2.2%), and African hedgehog (0.0%&#8211;2.0%). The average Sunda porcupine lymphocytes (25.08%) are still in the range of ferret lymphocytes (15.3%&#8211;72.8%), crested porcupines (12.9%&#8211;44.6%), and African hedgehog (22%&#8211;47%), but when compared with the average guinea pig lymphocyte levels (49%&#8211;50%) they are low. Sunda porcupine monocyte levels (8.55%) when compared with ferret monocyte levels (0.0%&#8211;8.8%) are still within the range, whereas when compared with crested porcupine monocyte levels (2.7%&#8211;3.9%), African hedgehog (0.0%&#8211;4.0%), and in guinea pigs (3.5%&#8211;4.5%), Sunda porcupine monocyte levels are much higher.</p><p>The morphology of Sunda porcupine RBCs was not significantly different from the morphology of RBCs in other mammals. The morphology of WBCs in Sunda porcupine blood smear preparations shows that neutrophils have a ribbon-like nucleus and are segmented. Lymphocytes are irregularly shaped, with different shapes from one monocyte to another. A cytoplasm is widened, and a cytoplasm is narrowed to resemble the shape of the nucleus. The monocytes in the blood smear are seen to have gray lobes, nuclei, and cytoplasm with granulations. The Sunda porcupine eosinophil is seen to have lobes with granulations clustered around the nucleus. The morphology of Sunda porcupine WBCs, when compared with the morphology of WBCs in other mammals, does not show a significant difference. The Sunda porcupine is an endangered breed; thus, understanding the normal range of hematological and biochemical markers is critical for determining if the animal is healthy or suffering from a pathological condition. This knowledge is vital in plans for protecting endangered breeds, such as the Sunda porcupine, and the overall landscape of biodiversity. More research with a larger sunda porcupine population is required to establish a credible breed-based reference range.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The results of Sunda porcupine blood measurements were 4.04 &#215; 106/ul for RBC; Hgb 12.83 g/dl; Hematocrit 37.8%; MCV 107.1 fl; MCH 31.80 pg; MCHC 31.23 g/dl; WBC 9.67 &#215; 103/ul and platelet (PLT) value 503.00 &#215; 103/ul. The morphology of red and WBCs from the Sunda porcupine does not differ significantly from the morphology of other mammals&#8217; red and WBCs. Until now, there has been limited research on the hematology of Sunda porcupines, which has led to a limited understanding of their health status. We anticipate that the findings of this study will serve as a diagnostic instrument for evaluating the health condition of Sunda porcupine and serve as a benchmark.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors thank the Faculty of Veterinary Medicine Universitas Gadjah Mada for the research location and support.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that no commercial or financial relationships existed that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest when conducting the research.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>TB prepared and managed the implementation of the research. YHF, TB, and ADL collected samples and conducted laboratory examinations for hematology. YHF critically analyzed the hematology data and prepared the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>The author declares that no financial support is accepted for authorship and publication by the Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Gajah Mada University.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/supplementary material; further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adi</surname><given-names>Y.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prihatno</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>A., Padeta</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Budipitojo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Body measurements correlation and X-ray imaging of three Hystrix javanica fetuses in different fetal development stages</article-title><source>Anim. Reprod</source><year>2021</year><volume>18</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>e20210005</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34691263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/1984-3143-AR2021-0005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8480987</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agungpriyono</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prawira</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darusman</surname><given-names>A.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farida</surname><given-names>H.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Novelina</surname><given-names>W.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Savitri</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Macroscopic anatomy and hematological changes during the wound healing process in the skin of the Java porcupine (Hystrix javanica)</article-title><source>J. Vet.</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anita</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farida</surname><given-names>W.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agusta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nugroho</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutritional components from the tail meat of the Sunda porcupine ( Hystrix javanica F</article-title><source>Cuvier, 1823) that could be related with aphrodisiac potency. The 4th International Symposium for Sustainable Humanosphere (ISSH)&#8211;A Forum of Humanosphere Science School (HSS). Research Center for Biomaterials&#8211;LIPI, Jakarta, pp: 199&#8211;204.</source><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Budipitojo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Padeta</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yulianti</surname><given-names>B.U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masithoh</surname><given-names>D.B.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution profile and function of carbohydrate residues in testes of immature and mature sunda porcupine (Hystrix javanica)</article-title><source>J. World Poult. Res.</source><year>2020a</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>59</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Budipitojo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shofiyah</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masithoh</surname><given-names>D.B.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khasanah</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Padeta</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The placenta anatomy of Sunda Porcupine (Hystrix javanica)</article-title><source>Adv. Anim. Vet. Sci.</source><year>2020b</year><volume>8</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>228</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cantlay</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meredith</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review of zoonotic infection risks associated with the wild meat trade in Malaysia</article-title><source>EcoHealth</source><year>2017</year><volume>14</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28332127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10393-017-1229-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5486459</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spengler</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hematology and clinical chemistry reference intervals for inbred strain 13/N Guinea pigs (Cavia porcellus)</article-title><source>J. Am. Assoc. Lab. Anim. Sci.</source><year>2019</year><volume>58</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31010455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.30802/AALAS-JAALAS-18-000118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6526494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coppola</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#8217;Addio</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casini</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sagona</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aloisi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Felicoli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hematological and serum biochemistry values in free-ranging crested porcupine</article-title><source>Vet. Sci.</source><year>2020</year><volume>7</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/vetsci7040171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7720117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33182396</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duffin</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Porcupine stones</article-title><source>Pharm. Historian</source><year>2013</year><volume>43</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24620538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farida</surname><given-names>W.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sari</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sofyani</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amalia</surname><given-names>R.L.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth performance and prediction of carcass production of captive javan porcupine (Hystrix javanica)</article-title><source>E3S Web of Conferences</source><year>2022</year><volume>335</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toomes</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Valuable stones: the trade in porcupine bezoars</article-title><source>Glob. Ecol. Conserv. 24(3&#8211;4), e01204</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuehnel</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Color atlas of cytology, histology, and microscopic anatomy</article-title><source>New York, NY: Thieme Stuttgart</source><year>2003</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Okorie-Kanu</surname><given-names>C.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Onuja</surname><given-names>R.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Achegbulu</surname><given-names>E.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okorie-Kanu</surname><given-names>O.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Normal haematological and serum biochemistry values of African hedgehog (Atelerix albiventris)</article-title><source>Comp. Clin. Pathol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00580-013-1870-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Proverbio</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perego</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baggiani</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ravasio</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giambellini</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spada</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hematological and biochemical reference values in healthy captive tigers (Panthera tigris)</article-title><source>Animals</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>3440</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34944217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ani11123440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8698039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salasia</surname><given-names>S.I.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hariono</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patologi Klinik Veteriner: Kasus Patologi Klinis</article-title><source>Yogyakarta, Indonesia: Samudra Biru</source><year>2010</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suparmin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunanti</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noviana</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agungpriyono</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The normal radiographic anatomy of the forelimb in Sunda Porcupine</article-title><source>Buletin Veteriner Udayana</source><year>2018</year><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24843/bulvet.2019.v11.i02.p02</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Theml</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diem</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haferlach</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Color atlas of hematology</article-title><source>NY, New York: Thieme Stuttgart</source><year>2004</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tilley</surname><given-names>L.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>W.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smitch</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blackwell&#8217;s five-minute veterinary consult</article-title><source>Ames, IA: Blackwell</source><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahid</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prawira</surname><given-names>A.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nisa</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agungpriyono</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulum</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sonoanatomy of female reproductive organ of Sunda porcupine (Hystrix javanica)</article-title><source>Anatom. Histol. Embryol.</source><year>2020</year><volume>49</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>779</fpage><lpage>787</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/ahe.12582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32537746</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>