<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2846</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">openvetj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Veterinary Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2226-4485</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2218-6050</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tripoli</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11563625</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11563625.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11563625</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11563625</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39553770</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/OVJ.2024.v14.i9.23</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OVJ-14-2348</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Biocompatibility assessment of an integrated contraceptive and RFID-based intravaginal device in cats (<italic toggle="yes">Felis catus</italic>): A preliminary study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santoso</surname><given-names initials="MIB">Muhammad Irham Bagus</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ainun</surname><given-names initials="SS">Sella Sofia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Utami</surname><given-names initials="D">Dian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names initials="FA">Fathan Abdul</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puspitaningsih</surname><given-names initials="R">Resti</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashar</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yaomil</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunanti</surname><given-names initials="G">Gunanti</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarian</surname><given-names initials="MN">Murni Nazira</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulum</surname><given-names initials="MF">Mokhammad Fakhrul</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Program of Veterinary Medicine, School of Veterinary Medicine and Biomedical Sciences, IPB University, Bogor, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Division of Surgery and Radiology, School of Veterinary Medicine and Biomedical Sciences, IPB University, Bogor, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Institut Biologi Sistem (INBIOSIS), Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia, Bandar Baru Bangi, Malaysia</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Faculty of Mechanical Engineering, Universiti Teknologi Malaysia, Johor Bahru, Malaysia</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Division of Reproduction, Obstetrics and Gynaecology, School of Veterinary Medicine and Biomedical Sciences, IPB University, Bogor, Indonesia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Mokhammad Fakhrul Ulum. Division of Reproduction, Obstetrics and Gynaecology, School of Veterinary Medicine and Biomedical Sciences, IPB University, Bogor, Indonesia. <email>ulum@apps.ipb.ac.id</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>9</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">475085</issue-id><fpage>2348</fpage><lpage>2360</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-11-18 15:25:24.860"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2348.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>An intravaginal device (IVD) made from polyethylene plastic and copper wire, integrated with a radio frequency identification (RFID) chip, was developed as a biocompatible contraceptive and identity device for cats.</p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>This study evaluates the local and systemic biocompatibility of IVD in five non-pregnant female cats.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>The IVD was successfully inserted into the vaginal lumen after estrogen administration. Radiographic imaging confirmed the IVD&#8217;s position, which lasted up to two days post-insertion.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Systemic response, assessed through hematological examinations on days 0, 1, and 3 post-insertion, showed no significant changes in erythrogram and leukogram parameters. Local response, evaluated through vulvar inspection and vaginal cytology on days 0, 1, 3, and 7, revealed no neutrophil infiltration in 4 out of 5 cats, indicating compatibility with vaginal tissue. Furthermore, epithelial cell profile changes were observed, showing an increase in superficial cells, which is typical during the estrus phase.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>These findings suggest that the IVD is biocompatible and suitable for use as a contraceptive and identity device in cats. However, further long-term studies are necessary to evaluate the device&#8217;s prolonged efficacy and potential for contraception failure prevention by mating trials.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Intravaginal device</kwd><kwd>Biocompatibility</kwd><kwd>Contraception</kwd><kwd>RFID identification</kwd><kwd>Feline population control</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>The growing population of cats requires urgent attention due to its potential to cause public discomfort and increase the risk of zoonotic disease transmission (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Madyantari <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2016</xref>). Traditional population control methods, such as castration for males and ovariohysterectomy for females, involves removing reproductive organs via surgery. While effective in some contexts, these methods face significant field obstacles, including post-surgical complications, increased risk of neoplasia, musculoskeletal disorders, and hormonal imbalances (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Kustritz, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Hekman, 2020</xref>).</p><p>Current contraceptive options for cats, including surgical spaying and chemical contraceptives, have notable limitations such as the need for anesthesia, high costs, and potential side effects (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Nielsen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). Non-surgical methods, such as immunocontraceptives, hormonal contraceptives, chemical contraceptives, physical reproductive barriers, and gene delivery, offer promising alternatives but often remain costly and impractical for large-scale applications (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Cathey and Memon, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">Vansandt <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). The development of an innovative, less invasive, and cost-effective solution like the intravaginal device (IVD) integrated with RFID technology is necessary to address these challenges (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Boone <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>).</p><p>An intrauterine device (IUD) is commonly used in humans and some animals for contraception, operating through mechanisms such as sperm motility disruption and spermicidal activity of released metal ions (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">Winner <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). Despite successful applications in other species, adapting IUDs for cats has been difficult due to the anatomical structure of the feline cervix (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Aspinall, 2011</xref>). Radio frequency identification (RFID) technology has been extensively used for identification, tracking, storing, and retrieving data via radio waves (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Suresh and Chakaravarthi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). Typically, RFID is used for tracking animal whereabouts, conducting animal censuses, and maintaining medical records (Lord <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007). Implanting RFID in animals is commonly performed subcutaneously or in other body parts (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Gillenson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>), and it serves purposes such as tracking (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">Fong <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>), behavior assessment (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Alindekon <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>), and physiological monitoring (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Ahmmed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). Integrating RFID with a contraceptive device could provide dual functionality, facilitating both contraception and animal identification.</p><p>Due to the anatomical challenges of the feline cervix, which consists of tightly closed sphincter muscles with a narrow lumen (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Aspinall, 2011</xref>), this preliminary research explores the insertion of an IVD in the vaginal lumen. The aim is to control cat populations by placing the contraceptive device in the vaginal lumen as a controlled internal drug release (CIDR) system.</p><p>Recent advances in RFID technology have facilitated its integration into various veterinary applications, including identification and health monitoring (<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Pereira <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). Combining RFID technology with contraceptive devices offers significant benefits for population control and efficient animal tracking, which is critical for managing stray and feral cat populations (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Hamer <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). Furthermore, studies have demonstrated the effectiveness of non-surgical contraceptive methods in reducing feral cat populations with fewer welfare concerns compared to traditional methods (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Hekman, 2020</xref>).</p><p>Materials implanted in the body must meet stringent biocompatibility standards, evaluated based on local and systemic cytotoxicity, as well as the potential to cause allergic reactions or carcinogenicity (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Anusavice, 2003</xref>). Ensuring biocompatibility is crucial for any implanted device to avoid adverse immune responses or local tissue damage, especially for contraceptive devices that need to remain in place for extended periods (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">Williams, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Anderson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>).</p><p>This study aims to develop and test the biocompatibility of an integrated contraceptive and RFID-based IVD in cats, addressing the need for a novel, practical solution for feline population control. We focus on evaluating both the local and systemic biocompatibility of this innovative IVD by analyzing hematological parameters and conducting cytological evaluations to confirm its safety for long-term use in felines (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">Nasution <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>). The successful implementation of this device could offer a non-surgical solution for controlling cat populations while improving identification and monitoring practices.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Animals</title><p>This study involved five female cats aged between 1.0 and 1.5 years, with body weights ranging from 1.5 to 2.5 kg.</p></sec><sec><title>Pregnancy examination</title><p>To confirm that the five clinically healthy female cats were not pregnant prior to IVD insertion, ultrasound examinations (Sonodop S3X, China) using a 7.5 MHz linear array transducer were performed. The cats&#8217; abdominal areas were shaved, the gel was applied for better imaging, and the transducer was used to locate the uterus in a dorsal recumbency position (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Acclimatization and maintenance of the experimental animals</title><p>The cats were acclimatized for seven days in individual cages. On the first day of acclimatization, anthelmintic and anti-ectoparasitic ivermectin (Intermectin, Holland) was administered subcutaneously at a dose of 0.02 ml/kg body weight. On the second day, vitamin B complex (Supra Ferbindo Farma, Indonesia) was given orally. The cats were fed with a combination of wet (Whiskas, Indonesia) and dry (Bolt Copetindo, Indonesia) cat foods in the morning and evening, with water provided ad libitum throughout the acclimatization and study period.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>Results of ultrasound examination of reproductive organ status in five cats that were not pregnant before IVD contraception was installed. (a) 1st cat, (b) 2nd cat, (c) 3rd cat, (d) 4th cat, and (e) 5th cat. <italic toggle="yes">Note:</italic> UT = uterus, VU = urinary bladder.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2348-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Fabrication of IVD</title><p>The IVD was constructed using two main materials: copper wire with a diameter of 0.2 mm and a polyethylene pipe. The polyethylene pipe measured 1 cm in length with a diameter of 0.3 mm. Copper wire was wound around the surface of the polyethylene pipe for 0.5 cm. An RFID chip (Star Security Technologies, China) was inserted into a segment of the polyethylene pipe that did not contain copper coils. Nylon with a diameter of 0.1 mm and 2 cm in length was added to both ends of the pipe and formed into an oval shape using a hot hair dryer (Philips Hair Dryer, China). The assembled device was glued with cyanoacrylate (Dextone, PT Dextone Lemindo, Indonesia) and sterilized using a UV sterilizer (PSKY, China) for one hour before insertion (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Insertion of IVD</title><p>One week after acclimatization, the IVD was inserted into the vaginal lumen using aseptic techniques. Cats were pre-treated with an intramuscular injection of estrogen (Ovalumon, PT Wonderindo Pratama, Indonesia) at a dose of 0.5&#8211;1.5 mg/kg body weight (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Leyva <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2014</xref>) three hours before IVD insertion to relax the vaginal muscles. Premedication with atropine (Atropine Sulfate, PT Ethica Industri Farmasi, Indonesia) at a dose of 0.025 mg/kg body weight was administered 10 minutes before anesthesia. The cats were then anesthetized using a combination of ketamine (Ilium Ketamil, Holland) at a dose of 10 mg/kg body weight and xylazine (Xyla, Holland) at a dose of 2 mg/kg body weight, administered intramuscularly (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Hellebrekers, 1996</xref>). The IVD was inserted using an applicator tube, which was advanced to the cervix, and the IVD was then deployed into the vaginal lumen by pressing the piston (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). The insertion process was monitored using an RFID reader (Star Security Technologies, China).</p></sec><sec><title>Radiographic examination</title><p>Vaginal contrast radiography was conducted to measure the size of the vaginal lumen. A 1 ml contrast agent (Iohexol, 35 ml infusion, Indonesia) was administered intravaginally. The contrast material was inserted by lifting the ventral part of the sacrum to form an angle of approximately 60&#186;, ensuring that the caudal body of the cat was higher than the cranial part. 1 ml of positive contrast material was then slowly inserted into the vaginal lumen using a 1 ml syringe. Radiographs were taken with an exposure factor of 52 kVp and 1.2 mAs at lateral and ventrodorsal angles using a radiography machine (VR 1020, Japan). Post-contrast, the vaginal lumen was flushed with physiological saline (Otsu-NS<sup>&#174;</sup>, PT Otsuka Indonesia) to remove residual contrast material. Radiographs were repeated on days 3 and 7 post-insertion to confirm IVD placement.</p></sec><sec><title>Vulva photography</title><p>Photographic documentation of the vulva was performed using a smartphone camera (ASUS Zenfone Max Pro M1, Taiwan) to observe changes in mucous discharge, color, and swelling. Photographs were taken the day before and after IVD insertion in the vaginal lumen.</p></sec><sec><title>Blood sample examination</title><p>Blood samples were collected on days 0, 1, and 3 post-insertion of the IVD into the vaginal lumen. Cats were premedicated with atropine (0.025 mg/kg body weight) and anesthetized using ketamine (10 mg/kg body weight) and xylazine (2 mg/kg body weight) as previously described (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Hellebrekers, 1996</xref>). The lateral part of the foreleg was disinfected with 70% alcohol cotton. Blood samples were taken from the dorsal antebrachial cephalic vein (1 ml) using a syringe (One Med, Indonesia). The blood was placed in 3 ml ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid vacutainer tubes (Intherma Vacuum, Indonesia), homogenized, and stored in a cooling box for delivery to the Commercial Laboratory at Klinik Medialisa Bogor for hematological analysis using a hematology analyzer.</p><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>Fabrication of the IVD used in research cats. (a) Parts of the IVD, (b) side view, (c) bottom view, and (d) top view. <italic toggle="yes">Note:</italic> 1 = Nylon Backing, 2 = Copper wire winding, 3 = RFID Chip, and 4 = Nylon Marker.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2348-g002.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><title>Process of insertion of IVD in the vagina and monitoring ID in cats. (a) IVD insertion process: (b) insert IVD, (c) radiographic imaging of contraceptives that have been inserted, and (d) Read RFID identity on those that have been inserted.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2348-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Cytological observation of vaginal epithelial cells</title><p>Vaginal cytology was performed on days 0, 1, 3, and 7 post IVD insertion. The female cat&#8217;s vagina was swabbed using a cotton swab (Baby Huki, Indonesia) moistened with distilled water. The tip of the cotton swab was inserted into the vulva at an upward angle to enter the vaginal lumen, then straightened forward to a depth of 1 cm (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Pratiwi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>). Swabs were taken by rotating the tip of the cotton swab clockwise 2&#8211;3 times. The tip of the cotton swab was then attached to a glass slide (Sail Brand, China) and rotated slowly to transfer the vaginal epithelial cells onto the glass slide. The swab results on the slide were fixed using methanol for 5 minutes and stained with 10% Giemsa dye (Merck KGaA, Germany) for 30 minutes. The stained slides were then observed using a light microscope (Olympus Binocular Microscope, Olympus Corp, Japan) with 10x magnification.</p></sec><sec><title>Data analysis</title><p>Data were analyzed using the statistical package for the social sciences (SPSS) software application version 25. Differences in blood profiles between observation times were tested using the independent T-test, while differences in vaginal cytology profiles between observation times were tested using one-way ANOVA followed by the Post Hoc Duncan test with a 95% confidence interval.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>The research protocol received approval from the Commission for Supervision of Welfare and Use of Experimental Animals at the Veterinary Teaching Hospital (RSHP), School of Veterinary Medicine and Biomedical Sciences, Bogor Agricultural University (IPB University), under approval number 130/KEH/SKE/V/2019.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Insertion and retention of the IVD</title><p>The insertion of the IVD into the vaginal lumen was successful in all five cats. Radiographic imaging of the cat&#8217;s vaginal lumen was performed before and after IVD insertion. Radiographic imaging confirmed the correct placement of the IVD before and after insertion. For the first cat, radiographs were taken up to seven days post-insertion, while for cats 2, 3, 4, and 5, imaging was performed before (H0) and immediately after insertion (H1) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). The IVD in the first cat remained in place until between the third and seventh days post-insertion, while in the other cats, the IVDs were expelled by the second day. RFID readers successfully identified the RFID chips in all cats. <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref> shows the radiographic appearance of the cat&#8217;s reproductive tract before and after insertion of the IVD, indicating that the IVD (marked with a black star) is in the vaginal lumen.</p></sec><sec><title>Hematological analysis</title><p>The hematological profile of cats before and after IVD insertion is presented in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Most hematological parameters were within the normal range before and after IVD insertion, except for erythrocytes, hemoglobin, mean corpuscular volume (MCV), and mean corpuscular hemoglobin (MCH). The total number of erythrocytes and hemoglobin levels were below normal values before insertion and decreased further after insertion. MCV and MCH values were above normal before insertion and decreased post-insertion. The total number of neutrophils, lymphocytes, monocytes, and eosinophils increased post-insertion but remained within normal ranges. The neutrophil to lymphocyte (N/L) ratio was above normal before insertion and decreased post-insertion. Overall, there were no significant differences in hematological parameters before and after IVD insertion (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p></sec><sec><title>Vulva observation</title><p><xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref> shows the vulva of the cats before and after IVD insertion. Visual inspection of the vulva in all five cats indicated that prior to IVD insertion, the vulva was rose-colored with no mucus discharge. Post-insertion observations showed clear mucus discharge and redness, with no signs of purulent exudate or significant inflammation.</p></sec><sec><title>Vaginal cytology</title><p>Morphological examination of epithelial cells in cat vaginal smears were conducted on days 0, 1, 3, and 7 after IVD insertion (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>). Cats were injected with estrogen three hours before IVD insertion. The ovarian activity phase before estrogen injection was in the proestrus phase (1st, 3rd, 4th, and 5th cats), characterized by a dominant number of intermediate cells, and in the estrus phase (2nd cat), characterized by a dominant number of superficial cells (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Vaginal cytology profiles before and after IVD insertion are presented in <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Cytological examination revealed a shift from proestrus to estrus phases in all cats following estrogen injection. Significant decreases (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in parabasal and intermediate cell counts were observed post-insertion, with a corresponding increase in superficial cells and neutrophils, indicating an estrogen-induced estrus phase. Only one cat showed neutrophil infiltration indicative of inflammation, while the others did not exhibit inflammatory responses (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig4" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><title>The radiographic appearance of the cat's reproductive tract before and after insertion of the IVD, it can be seen that the IVD (black star) is in the vaginal lumen. Day 0 before IVD insertion image in ventrodorsal position of (a) 1st cat, (i) 2nd cat, (m) 3rd cat, (q) 4th cat, and (u) 5th cat. Day 0 before IVD insertion image in laterolateral position of (e) 1st cat, (k) 2nd cat, (o) 3rd cat, (s) 4th cat, and (w) 5th cat. Day 1 after IVD insertion image in ventrodorsal position of (b) 1st cat, (j) 2nd cat, (n) 3rd cat, (r) 4th cat, and (v) 5th cat. Day 1 after IVD insertion image in laterolateral position of (f) 1st cat, (l) 2nd cat, (p) 3rd cat, (t) 4th cat, and (x) 5th cat. Day 3 after IVD insertion image in ventrodorsal position (c) and laterolateral (g) of 1st cat. Day 7 after IVD insertion image in ventrodorsal position (d) and laterolateral (h) of 1st cat.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2348-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>This preliminary research was successfully conducted to assess the potential biocompatibility of an IVD as a combined contraceptive and intravaginal radiofrequency-based identity device for local vaginal and systemic tissue in non-pregnant cats (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). The IVD, developed for cats, is made from polyethylene plastic with a copper coil and is equipped with an RFID chip (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). The contraceptive device operates by releasing copper ions (Cu), which impair and disrupt the motility of sperm deposited in the vaginal lumen (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Manuaba, 2009</xref>). To facilitate the insertion process, cats receiving IVD are first injected with estrogen to relax the vaginal muscles by increasing blood supply to the area (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Dewi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2011</xref>). The RFID chip embedded in the contraceptive device was successfully read by an RFID reader in all five cats, providing data in the form of a serial number from the RFID chip (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Hematological profile of cats before and after IVD insertion.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal Value&#450;</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 0, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=5</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 1, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=5</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 3&#8224;, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Erythrocytes (x 10<sup>6</sup>/&#956;l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00&#8211;10.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.50 &#177; 0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.18 &#177; 0.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.564</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hemoglobin (g/dl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.30&#8211;15.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.64 &#177; 2.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.24 &#177; 2.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.387</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hematocrit (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.00&#8211;45.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.00 &#177; 8.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.40 &#177; 5.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.448</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCV (fl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.00&#8211;49.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.11 &#177; 1.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.74 &#177; 3.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.410</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCH (pg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.00&#8211;17.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.33 &#177; 0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.36 &#177; 1.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.229</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCHC (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00&#8211;36.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.06 &#177; 0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.60 &#177; 1.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.306</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leukocytes (x 10<sup>3</sup>/&#956;l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.60&#8211;12.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.42 &#177; 1.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.10 &#177; 3.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.390</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutrophils (x 10<sup>3</sup>/&#956;l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.32&#8211;10.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.82 &#177; 1.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.51 &#177; 2.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.656</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymphocytes (x 10<sup>3</sup>/&#956;l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05&#8211;6.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.11 &#177; 0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.06 &#177; 1.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.202</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monocytes (x 10<sup>3</sup>/&#956;l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50&#8211;0.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37 &#177; 0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52 &#177; 0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.336</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eosinophils (x 10<sup>3</sup>/&#956;l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10&#8211;0.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 &#177; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21 &#177; 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.247</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basophils (x 10<sup>3</sup>/&#956;l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00&#8211;1.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 &#177; 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.538</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/L ratio</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66&#8211;2.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.24 &#177; 2.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45 &#177; 1.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.356</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are presented as mean &#177; standard deviation (x &#177; SD). The value (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) shows a significant difference between the days before and after IVD insertion. Day 0 = Day before IVD insertion and before estrogen injection, day 1 = Day 1 after IVD insertion, Day 3 = Day 3 after IVD insertion. &#8224; = Not included in the test, because<italic toggle="yes"> n </italic>= 1; MCV = Mean Corpuscular Volume; MCH = Mean Corpuscular Hemoglobin; MCHC = Mean Corpuscular Hemoglobin Concentration; N/L = Ratio of the number of neutrophils compared to lymphocytes. Source: &#450; (Wassmuth <italic toggle="yes">et al.,</italic> 2011).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig5" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><title>The appearance of the cat's vulva before IVD insertion was rose-colored with no mucus discharge (a&#8211;e), and showed clear mucus discharge and redness, with no signs of purulent exudate or significant inflammation after IVD insertion (f&#8211;j).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2348-g005.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig6" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><title>The appearance of the epithelial cell of vagina before and after estrogen (E2) injection and an IV) insertion. Day 0, Before E2 injection of (a) 1st cat, (f) 2nd cat, (j) 3rd cat, (n) 4th cat, and (r) 5th cat. Day 0, after E2 injection of (b) 1st cat, (g) 2nd cat, (k) 3rd cat, (o) 4th cat, and (s) 5th cat. Day 1 after IVD insertion of (c) 1st cat, (h) 2nd cat, (l) 3rd cat, (p) 4th cat, and (t) 5th cat. Day 3 after IVD insertion of (d) 1st cat, (i) 2nd cat, (m) 3rd cat, and (q) 4th cat. Day 7 after IVD insertion of 1st cat (e). Note: &#450; = vaginal smear slides were not readable, &#8224; = vaginal smear was not taken due to the inserted IVD expelled.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2348-g006.jpg"/></fig><p>Radiographic examination showed that the IVD was still present in the vaginal lumen of all five cats (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). The IVDs in four cats were expelled on the second-day post-insertion, with only one device remaining in place until the fifth-day post-insertion (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>a&#8211;h). The expulsion of the IVD from the cat&#8217;s vaginal lumen occurred because the nylon plastic retainer could not hold the IVD in place for an extended period. <xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">Volpe <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2001)</xref> conducted a study in which they installed IUD contraceptives in nine female dogs, and the devices remained in place for two years (three estrous cycles). The IUD contraceptives lasted longer because they had two retaining arms situated in the uterine lumen, which is deeper than the vaginal lumen, and their flexibility helped prevent the contraceptives from moving out of position (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">Volpe <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2001</xref>).</p><p>The insertion of an IVD into the vaginal lumen has the potential to cause a rejection reaction by the body in the form of inflammation; however, this was not evident in the blood profiles of the cats in this study (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The immune response begins when the IVD is inserted into the vaginal lumen. Inflammation is a response to harmful stimuli, infection by pathogenic agents, cell damage, or irritation, which causes a complex biological response in the tissue (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Nathan, 2002</xref>). The local response to IVD insertion was examined by observing the morphological appearance of the vulva (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>) and through cytological examination of vaginal epithelial cells (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>). The appearance of the vulvas in the five cats showed no signs of inflammation, as indicated by the absence of purulent exudate. Inflammation of the vagina can be identified by the presence of purulent exudate on the vulva (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">Nicastro and Walshow, 2007</xref>). The vulvas of the five cats appeared swollen with clear mucus discharge (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Changes in the vulva&#8217;s condition, such as color, size, and mucus discharge, are related to the hormone estrogen, which increases during estrus. <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Frandson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2003)</xref> stated that estrogen stimulates increased vascularization in the external genitals, making them swollen and reddish, and increases mucus secretion in the vulva.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Epithelial cell profiles in individual cat vaginal smears before and after IVD insertion.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cel type (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cat #1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cat #2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cat #3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cat #4</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cat #5</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>Day 0 before estrogen (E2) injection</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parabasal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.53 &#177; 4.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.21 &#177; 6.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.43 &#177; 1.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.86 &#177; 8.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.38 &#177; 2.52</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermediate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.04 &#177; 16.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.05 &#177; 9.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.09 &#177; 17.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.21 &#177; 26.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.97 &#177; 14.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Superficial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.43 &#177; 12.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.74 &#177; 16.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.49 &#177; 10.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.93 &#177; 15.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.65 &#177; 14.90</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutrophil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus phase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proestrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proestrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proestrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proestrus</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>Day 0 after estrogen (E2) injection</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parabasal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 &#177; 0.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.99 &#177; 5.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.04 &#177; 3.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65 &#177; 0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermediate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.71 &#177; 5.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.06 &#177; 3.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.10 &#177; 15.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.84 &#177; 15.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 &#177; 0.66</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Superficial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.26 &#177; 14.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.16 &#177; 29.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.86 &#177; 18.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.50 &#177; 10.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.86 &#177; 21.40</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutrophil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus phase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>Day 1 after IVD insertion</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parabasal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.43 &#177; 5.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermediate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37 &#177; 0.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.57 &#177; 29.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.57 &#177; 3.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.01 &#177; 7.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Superficial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66 &#177; 0.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.97 &#177; 31.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.43 &#177; 27.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.99 &#177; 33.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00 &#177; 39.17</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutrophil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.96 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus phase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>Day 3 after IVD insertion</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parabasal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 &#177; 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26 &#177; 2.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#450;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermediate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95 &#177; 0.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.37 &#177; 2.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.67 &#177; 3.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.44 &#177; 5.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#450;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Superficial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 &#177; 0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.38 &#177; 26.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.33 &#177; 16.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.56 &#177; 31.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#450;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutrophil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.43 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#450;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus phase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>Day 7 after IVD insertion</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parabasal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8224;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8224;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8224;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8224;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermediate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.08 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8224;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8224;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8224;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8224;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Superficial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.92 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8224;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8224;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8224;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8224;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutrophil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8224;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8224;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8224;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8224;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus phase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estrus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are presented as mean &#177; standard deviation (x &#177; SD). &#450; = the vaginal smear was not readable, &#8224; = the vaginal smear was not taken because the IVD was expelled.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Epithelial cell profile in feline vaginal smears before and after IVD insertion.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell type (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 0, before E2 injection, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=5</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 0, after E2 injection, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=5</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 1, after IVD insertion<italic toggle="yes">, n</italic>=5</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 3, after IVD insertion, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=4</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 7, after IVD insertion&#8224;, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parabasal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.26 &#177; 3.04<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05 &#177; 1.76 <sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 &#177; 0.00 <sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 &#177; 0.61<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intermediate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.67 &#177; 13.19<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.55 &#177; 10.59 <sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.70 &#177; 8.02 <sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.86 &#177; 3.62<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.08 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Superficial</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.65 &#177; 13.30<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.93 &#177; 13.05<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.81 &#177; 40.63<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.44 &#177; 45.32<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.92 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutrophil <sup>&#450;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.96 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.43 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.a.</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are presented as mean &#177; standard deviation (x &#177; SD). Different superscript letters on the same line indicate significant differences (p &lt; 0.05). &#8224; = Not included in the test, because n = 1, &#450; = Not included in statistical tests because only one cat responded, n.a.= not available, and E2 = Estrogen.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Cytological examination of vaginal epithelial cells in cats was conducted to determine the presence of inflammation due to IVD insertion (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Tables 2</xref> and <xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Inflammation from IVD insertion was observed in only one cat (20% of the population). Inflammation is characterized by the presence of neutrophil cell infiltration in the vaginal smear examination (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Harold, 2002</xref>). The inflammatory process results in the migration of various inflammatory cells from the circulatory system to the tissues. The duration and intensity of these responses depends on the area of injury caused by the implant placement, chemical composition of the material, surface shape, porosity, roughness, and the shape and size of the implant (Li <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005).</p><p>Systemic biocompatibility of an implant can be determined through hematological examination (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Omerkovic <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2015</xref>). Biocompatibility refers to a material&#8217;s ability to function appropriately according to the recipient tissue&#8217;s response under specific conditions (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Bosco <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). The erythrocyte index values in cats were not influenced by IVD insertion (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The decrease in erythrocyte index values in cats could be attributed to the effects of anesthesia before blood sampling. General anesthesia causes dilation of splenic blood vessels and constriction of peripheral blood vessels, resulting in significant blood accumulation in the splenic blood vessels and a consequent decrease in erythrocyte index values (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">Schaefer, 2022</xref>). Estrogen injection did not contribute to the decrease in erythrocyte index values. Estrogen injection stimulates hematopoietic stem cell division and erythropoiesis (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">S&#225;nchez-Aguilera <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>).</p><p>The erythrocyte index value in cats can also indicate the occurrence of normochromic macrocytic anemia from the beginning of the study. Normochromic macrocytic anemia is characterized by erythrocytes that are larger than normal in size, with a normal hemoglobin concentration (normal MCHC) but increased MCV and MCH, which is often caused by a deficiency of vitamin B12 or folic acid (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">Muttaqin, 2009</xref>). This condition is thought to be due to the cats experiencing stress while adapting to a new environment, resulting in impaired vitamin absorption (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Hastjarjo <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>). Despite the administration of oral vitamin B-complex during the acclimatization period, the amount provided was insufficient to meet the cats&#8217; needs during the adaptation period.</p><p>The research cats used were feral cats that were then kept in cages. At the beginning of the study, the cats&#8217; behavior changed to become more aggressive; they often hid and consumed little food. <xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">Turner and Bateson (2014)</xref> stated that stressful conditions in cats could cause changes in normal behavior, such as increased aggression, prolonged hiding, reduced exploration, and anorexia. At the start of the study, the cats were fed with a mixture of wet and dry food three times a day, and drinking water was provided ad libitum. The cats were also given vitamin B complex to reduce stress levels. <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">McDowell (2000)</xref> stated that administering vitamin B complex can alleviate stress. Over time, stress was decreased, as indicated by reduced aggressive behavior and increased food consumption, suggesting that the cats were beginning to adapt to their new environment.</p><p>Leukocytes play a crucial role in the body&#8217;s immune system, defending against infectious agents and foreign objects (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Keohane <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2015</xref>). The number of leukocytes in the cats&#8217; blood was not significantly affected by the insertion of the IVD into the vagina, remaining within the normal range even though there was a slight increase post-insertion. Lymphocytes and neutrophils are key defense cells involved in the inflammatory response. Neutrophils are the first line of defense against bacterial infections and tissue trauma, commonly appearing at the onset of acute inflammation and playing a role in the phagocytosis of microorganisms, particularly bacteria (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Paramitha <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2013</xref>). Lymphocytes, along with neutrophils in the inflammatory process, also contribute to the body&#8217;s defense mechanisms (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Izzaty <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). The insertion of an IVD in the vagina affected the neutrophil response in cats, causing a slight increase post-insertion, but it remained within the normal range (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">Park and Hyun (2016)</xref> stated that the number of neutrophils increases due to the inflammatory process. This increase in neutrophils is a normal response to the presence of the IVD, which the body recognizes as a foreign object.</p><p>Monocytes are a type of leukocyte that plays a role in both acute and chronic inflammatory processes. Monocytes migrate into inflamed tissue along with neutrophils, although in smaller numbers (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Subowo, 2009</xref>). Upon tissue damage caused by the IVD insertion, monocytes are rapidly recruited to the site, where they can differentiate into macrophages or dendritic cells and phagocytose the damages tissue. Eosinophils are another type of leukocyte involved in regulating acute allergies, parasitic infections, and inflammatory processes. The production of eosinophils increases during infections and allergic reactions. Eosinophils, basophils, and mast cells are responsible for releasing inflammatory mediators (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Behm and Ovington, 2000</xref>). Basophils are involved in allergic and antigen responses by releasing histamine, which causes blood vessel dilation during allergic reactions (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Saladin, 2009</xref>). The insertion of the IVD did not significantly affect the responses of eosinophils and basophils; although there was a slight increase, the levels remained within the normal range (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The neutrophil-to-lymphocyte (N/L) ratio in cats indicated high-stress levels at the beginning of the study, which decreased after the insertion of the IVD. This change in stress levels is likely due to the cats adapting to their new cage and environment (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig7" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7.</label><caption><title>The mechanism of spermatozoa toxicity caused by Cu ions inside the vaginal lumen. It shows that if the concentration of Cu ions are above 100 &#956;M, the spermatozoa will start to form head-to-head agglutination, whereas, if the concentration of Cu ions are above 5 &#956;M, the spermatozoa motility will be significantly reduced.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2348-g007.jpg"/></fig><p>According to <xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Roy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2014)</xref>, spermatozoa forward motility is significantly enhanced by the presence of copper ions (Cu<italic toggle="yes">2+</italic>) in a dose-dependent manner. However, when spermatozoa come into contact with a high concentration of Cu<italic toggle="yes">2+</italic> exceeding 5 &#181;M inside the vaginal lumen, their motility is significantly reduced. This clear evidence suggests that sperm motility is regulated by Cu<italic toggle="yes">2+</italic>. Furthermore, sperm head-to-head agglutination occurs when the concentration of Cu<italic toggle="yes">2+</italic> exceeds 100 &#956;M, causing oxidative stress and leading to spermatozoa toxicity. The abundant amount of Cu<italic toggle="yes">2+</italic> prevents fertilization by inhibiting spermatozoa migration and viability. Therefore, by halting sperm motility and preventing them from reaching the ovum, the copper IUD functions as an emergency contraceptive method (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Roy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Ramanadhan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref> illustrates the mechanism of toxicity caused by Cu ions in the vaginal lumen.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The initial testing of the developed IVD indicated that it holds a good potential as a biocompatible contraceptive and identity device for cats. The IVD was generally well-tolerated, with no significant adverse local or systemic reactions observed during the short-term evaluation period. However, the retention of the device was limited, as four out of five cats expelled the IVD by the second-day post-insertion. Only one cat retained the IVD for up to seven days. Further research needs to be done regarding the design of the IVD so that the duration of the IVD in the vaginal lumen can last longer, as well as attempts at conception failure by mating cats that have had the IVD inserted with male cats.</p><sec><title>Limitations</title><p>This preliminary study indicated that the integrated contraceptive and intravaginal radiofrequency-based identity device (IVD) is generally well-tolerated in female cats, with no significant adverse reactions observed in the short term. However, the study had a small sample size of only five cats and a short duration of seven days post-insertion, limiting the generalizability and long-term assessment of biocompatibility and contraceptive efficacy.</p><p>Future research should include a larger sample size and more extended monitoring periods to provide more comprehensive data. Additionally, device design improvements, such as using materials with lower tissue reactivity and refining the insertion procedure for better stability, are recommended. Long-term studies and mating trials are necessary to evaluate the IVD&#8217;s effectiveness in preventing pregnancies and its impact on the overall health and behavior of the cats.</p><p>Overall, while the study provides promising preliminary evidence for the IVD&#8217;s potential as a contraceptive and identity device for felines, addressing these limitations and conducting further research is crucial to confirming its utility and safety for widespread use.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>The authors would like to thank the Directorate of Research and Innovation of IPB University for the Riset Kolaborasi Nasional Grant that supports this project.</p></ack><sec><title>Funding</title><p>This research was funded by Dana Abadi Perguruan Tinggi-Lembaga Pengelola Dana Pendidikan (DAPT-LPDP) through International Research Collaboration Funding Program (Riset Kolaborasi Internasional) with the Grant No. 571/IT3.D10/PT.01.03/P/B/2023.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#8217; contribution</title><p>MFU: Conceptualization, methodology; MIBS, SSA, DU, FAA, RP, YA: Data curation, writing-original draft preparation; MIBS, SSA, DU, FAA, RP, YA: Visualization, investigation; MFU, G: Supervision; MFU: Validation; MIBS, MFU, MNS, AHY: Writing-reviewing and editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>The authors have no conflicts of interest to declare.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Some of the data supporting we used in this paper are obtained from MIBS Undergraduate Thesis during his study in the School of Veterinary Medicine and Biomedical Sciences, Bogor Agricultural University (IPB University), MIBS is an author of this paper. Thesis data are deposited in the Bogor Agricultural University repository and are free-accessed online through http://repository.ipb.ac.id/handle/123456789/105279.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmmed</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bozkurt</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Subcutaneously injectable implant for multimodal physiological monitoring in animals</article-title><source>IEEE Sens J.</source><year>2024</year><volume>24</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>11205</fpage><lpage>11216</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alindekon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodenburg</surname><given-names>T.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langbein</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puppe</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilmsmeier</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Louton</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Setting the stage to Tag&#8217;n&#8217;Track: a guideline for implementing, validating and reporting an RFID system for monitoring resource visit behavior in poultry</article-title><source>Poult Sci.</source><year>2023</year><volume>102</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>102799</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37315427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.psj.2023.102799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10404737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>D.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Foreign body reaction to biomaterials</article-title><source>Semin. Immunol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>20</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18162407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.smim.2007.11.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2327202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anusavice</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phillip&#8217;s science of dental materials, 8th ed</article-title><source>USA: Saunders Company</source><year>2003</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Aspinall</collab><article-title>Reproductive system of the dog and cat Part 1&#8212;the female system</article-title><source>Vet. Nurs. J.</source><year>2011</year><volume>26</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>45</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Behm</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ovington</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of eosinophils in parasitic helminth infections: insights from genetically modified mice</article-title><source>Parasitol. Today</source><year>2000</year><volume>16</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>202</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10782080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0169-4758(99)01620-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boone</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benka</surname><given-names>V.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawler</surname><given-names>D.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slater</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zawistowski</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A long-term lens: cumulative impacts of free-roaming cat management strategy and intensity on preventable cat mortalities</article-title><source>Front. Vet. Sci.</source><year>2019</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>238</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31403048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fvets.2019.00238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6676151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Den Beucken</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leeuwenburgh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surface engineering for bone implants: a trend from passive to active surfaces</article-title><source>Coatings.</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>119</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cathey</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Memon</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonsurgical methods of contraception in dogs and cats: Where are we now? Vet</article-title><source>Med.</source><year>2010</year><volume>105</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>17</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suresh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chakaravarthi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RFID technology and its diverse applications: a brief exposition with a proposed machine learning approach</article-title><source>Measurement.</source><year>2022</year><volume>195</volume><fpage>111197</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dewi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahyuningsih</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Widayati</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Respons estrus pada kambing Peranakan Etawah dengan body condition score 2 dan 3 terhadap kombinasi implant controlled internal drug release jangka pendek dengan injeksi prostaglandin F<sub>2</sub> Alpha</article-title><source>J. Kedokt. Hewan.</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>14</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jury</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PyMouseTracks: flexible computer vision and RFID-based system for multiple mouse tracking and behavioral assessment</article-title><source>eNeuro.</source><year>2023</year><volume>10</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1523/ENEURO.0127-22.2023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10198609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37185293</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frandson</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilke</surname><given-names>W.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fails</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name></person-group><source>The ovary and estrous cycles in: anatomy and physiology of farm animal</source><year>2003</year><edition>7th</edition><publisher-loc>USA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Lippincott Williams and Wilkins</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillenson</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muthitacharoen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasarnphanich</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>i&#8217;ve got you under my skin: the past, present, and future use of RFID technology in people and animals</article-title><source>Inf. Technol. Manag.</source><year>2019</year><volume>30</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>29</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamer</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>R.Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Proft</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>C.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A triple threat: high population density, high foraging intensity and flexible habitat preferences explain high impact of feral cats on prey</article-title><source>Proc. R. Soc. B.</source><year>2021</year><volume>288</volume><fpage>20201194</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1098/rspb.2020.1194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7892407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33402069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harold</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiesenfeld</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillip</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marijane</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharon</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antonio</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between elevated neutrophil defense levels and endometritis</article-title><source>J. Infect. Dis.</source><year>2002</year><volume>186</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>792</fpage><lpage>797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12198613</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1086/342417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastjarjo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunanti</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noviana</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Profil hematologi pada kucing lokal selama proses kesembuhan skin flaps H-plasty dan linear closure</article-title><source>ARSHI Vet. Lett.</source><year>2018</year><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>36</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hekman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Non-surgical contraception: the state of the field</article-title><source>In High-quality, high-volume spay and neuter and other shelter surgeries</source><year>2020</year><publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>528</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hellebrekers</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Injection anasthesia in dog and cat</article-title><source>Vet. Q.</source><year>1996</year><volume>1</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/01652176.1996.9694689</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22074539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Izzaty</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dewi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pratiwi</surname><given-names>D.I.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extract of haruan (Channa striata) decreases lymphocyte count in inflammatory phase of wound healing process effectively</article-title><source>Dentofasial.</source><year>2014</year><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>181</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keohane</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walenga</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rodaks&#8217;s hematology: clinical principles and applications, 5th Edition</article-title><source>St. Louis, MO: Elsevier</source><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kustritz</surname><given-names>V.M.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of surgical sterilization on canine and feline health and on society</article-title><source>Reprod. Domest. Anim.</source><year>2012</year><volume>47</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>214</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22827373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1439-0531.2012.02078.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leyva</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Veliz</surname><given-names>F.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Domininguez</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of small dose of estradion cypionate after artificial insemination on reproductive performance in Holstein cows</article-title><source>J. Appl. Res.</source><year>2014</year><volume>44</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>3</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>L.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingwerson</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of animals with microchips entering animal shelters</article-title><source>J. Am. Vet. Med. Assoc.</source><year>2009</year><volume>235</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19601734</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2460/javma.235.2.160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madyantari</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hidayat</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahab</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perancangan buku ilustrasi kucing di Bandung [Bahasa]</article-title><source>E-Proceeding of Art and Design.</source><year>2016</year><volume>3</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>746</fpage><lpage>753</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manuaba</surname><given-names>I.B.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Memahami Kesehatan Reproduksi Wanita [Bahasa]</article-title><source>Jakarta, Indonesia: EGC.</source><year>2009</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McDowell</surname><given-names>L.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vitamins in animal and human nutrition, 2nd ed</article-title><source>USA: Iowa State University Press</source><year>2000</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muttaqin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Asuhan Keperawatan Klien dengan Gangguan Sistem Pernapasan [Bahasa]</article-title><source>Jakarta, Indonesia: Salemba Medika</source><year>2009</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasution</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulum</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kadir</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hermawan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanical and corrosion properties of partially degradable bone screws made of pure iron and stainless steel 316L by friction welding</article-title><source>Sci. China Mater.</source><year>2018</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>606</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nathan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Points of control in inflammation</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>420</volume><issue>6917</issue><fpage>846</fpage><lpage>852</lpage><comment><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature01320">https://doi.org/10.1038/nature01320</uri></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12490957</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nature01320</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicastro</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walshaw</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic vaginitis associated with vaginal foreign body in cat</article-title><source>J. Am. Hospital Assoc.</source><year>2007</year><volume>43</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5326/0430352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17975219</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>H.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meilby</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sand&#248;e</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating the population of unowned free-ranging domestic cats in Denmark using a combination of questionnaires and GPS tracking</article-title><source>Animals</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>920</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35405908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ani12070920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8996992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Omerkovic</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lazovic</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadzimehmedagic</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Static or dynamic intramedullary nailing of femur and tibia</article-title><source>Med. Arch.</source><year>2015</year><volume>69</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26005261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5455/medarh.2015.69.110-113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4430006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paramitha</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Estuningsih</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noviana</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulum</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hermawan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of Fe-based degradable materials in mice skeletal muscle</article-title><source>Eur. Cell Mater.</source><year>2013</year><volume>26</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>59</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyun</surname><given-names>Y.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neutrophil extravasation cascade: What can we learn from two-photon intravital imaging? Immune</article-title><source>Netw</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4110/in.2016.16.6.317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5195840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28035206</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ara&#250;jo, &#205;., Silva</surname><given-names>L.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Batista</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>J&#250;nior</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barboza</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraga</surname><given-names>I.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davanso</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>D.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RFID technology for animal tracking: a survey</article-title><source>IEEE J. Radio. Freq. Identif.</source><year>2023</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>609</fpage><lpage>620</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pratiwi</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tumbelaka</surname><given-names>L.I.T.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulum</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrasonographic and vaginal cytological diagnostics of the Queen</article-title><source>J. Ilmu. Ternak. dan. Vet.</source><year>2018</year><volume>23</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>142</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramanadhan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldstuck</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Che</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dodge</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edelman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Progestin intrauterine devices versus copper intrauterine devices for emergency contraception</article-title><source>Cochrane. Database. Syst. Rev.</source><year>2023</year><volume>2023</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/14651858.CD013744.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9969955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36847591</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Majumder</surname><given-names>G.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Copper: a biphasic regulator of caprine sperm forward progression</article-title><source>Syst. Biol. Reprod. Med.</source><year>2014</year><volume>60</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24156751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3109/19396368.2013.848243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saladin</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anatomy and physiology: the unity of form, and function</article-title><year>2009</year><edition>5th</edition><publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>McGraw Hill Company</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#225;nchez-Aguilera</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arranz</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;n-P&#233;rez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garc&#237;a</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stavropoulou</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kubovcakova</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isern</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;n-Salamanca</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langa</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skoda</surname><given-names>R.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwaller</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#233;ndez Ferrer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estrogen signaling selectively induces apoptosis of hematopoietic progenitors and myeloid neoplasms without harming steady-state hematopoiesis</article-title><source>Cell. Stem. Cell.</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>791</fpage><lpage>804</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25479752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.stem.2014.11.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hematology of cats</article-title><source>Schalm&#8217;s Vet. Hematol.</source><year>2022</year><volume>2022</volume><fpage>983</fpage><lpage>992</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Subowo</collab><article-title>General histology</article-title><source>Jakarta, Indonesia: CV Sagung Seto</source><year>2009</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>B.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beteson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The domestic cat: the biology of it&#8217;s behaviour, 3rd Edition</article-title><source>Cambridge (UK): Cambridge University Press</source><year>2014</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vansandt</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meinsohn</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Godin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagykery</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sicher</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kano</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kashiwagi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chauvin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saatcioglu</surname><given-names>H.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>A.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Durable contraception in the female domestic cat using viral-vectored delivery of a feline anti-M&#252;llerian hormone transgene</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3140</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37280258</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41467-023-38721-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10244415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Volpe</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Izzo</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iannaeti</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intrauterine device for contraception on dog</article-title><source>Vet. Rec.</source><year>2001</year><volume>149</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11497398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/vr.149.3.77</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wassmuth</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riond</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lehman</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the Mythic 18 hematology analyzer for use with canine, feline, and equine samples</article-title><source>J. Vet. Diagn. Invest.</source><year>2011</year><volume>23</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>436</fpage><lpage>453</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21908272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1040638711403416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>D.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the mechanisms of biocompatibility</article-title><source>Biomaterials.</source><year>2008</year><volume>29</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>2941</fpage><lpage>2953</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18440630</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2008.04.023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winner</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peipert</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buckel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allsworth</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Secura</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of long-acting reversible contraception</article-title><source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source><year>2012</year><volume>366</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>1998</fpage><lpage>2007</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22621627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1056/NEJMoa1110855</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>