<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2846</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">openvetj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Veterinary Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2226-4485</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2218-6050</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tripoli</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10072832</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10072832.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10072832</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10072832</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37026074</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/OVJ.2023.v13.i3.10</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OVJ-13-337</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Computed tomographic evaluation of heart size in clinically healthy cats</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wanglerm</surname><given-names initials="A">Aphisit</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samachikthummakun</surname><given-names initials="C">Chawanwith</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitnitchee</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sirinitikorn</surname><given-names initials="T">Thiranan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Junnong</surname><given-names initials="S">Sapawut</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutthigran</surname><given-names initials="S">Somchin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choisunirachon</surname><given-names initials="N">Nan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thanaboonnipat</surname><given-names initials="C">Chutimon</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Faculty of Veterinary Science, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, Thailand</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Veterinary Surgery, Faculty of Veterinary Science, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, Thailand</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Chutimon Thanaboonnipat. Department of Veterinary Surgery, Faculty of Veterinary Science, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, Thailand. <email>Chutimon.Th@chula.ac.th</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">432757</issue-id><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>05</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-05-29 08:25:09.593"><day>29</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-13-337.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Computed tomography (CT) is currently one of the most useful diagnostic imaging tools for evaluating cardiac disorders in humans and animals. However, studies concerning CT and the feline heart remain scarce. </p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>To create measuring techniques for the feline heart size on CT and to determine the relationships of feline heart size observed on CT with internal parameters including age, bodyweight (BW), and sex. </p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods:</title><p>Four parameters observed on CT including thoracic height/width ratio (THW), relative heart area (RHA), CT vertebral heart score (ctVHS), transverse vertebral heart score (tVHS) in 1.25 mm slice thickness, and both pre- and post-contrast enhanced images were examined. Additionally, radiographic vertebral heart score (rVHS) was also evaluated. </p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>THW was significantly influenced by age (<italic toggle="yes">p </italic>&lt; 0.05). RHA was affected by age and gonadal status of cats (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.001 and <italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.016, respectively). Age also significantly affected tVHS (<italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.038). Interestingly, ctVHS was not influenced by age, sex, gonadal status, or BW. tVHS and ctVHS had significantly moderately positive correlations with rVHS (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.476; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.048 and <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.6112; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.011, respectively). THW and RHA had non-significant correlations with rVHS (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.2642; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.302 and <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.1920; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.455, respectively). </p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>CT heart size evaluation can be performed in both pre- and post-contrast enhanced images of 1.25 mm slice thickness. tVHS and ctVHS are recommended parameters for evaluating feline heart size in clinical practice.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Cats</kwd><kwd>Computer tomography</kwd><kwd>Feline heart</kwd><kwd>Transverse vertebral heart score</kwd><kwd>Vertebral heart score</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>The heart is the most vital organ of the vertebrate species that acts as a pump to propel and deliver blood throughout the body (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">Stephenson <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). Dysfunctions of the heart can cause serious clinical problems. Heart disease is one of the major clinical problems in cats (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Freeman <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). The prevalence of feline heart disease has been noted as being 0.2% of the total number of visiting cats and 7.3% of cats were diagnosed with heart disease (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Riesen <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; Michal, 2020). Feline heart disease can be categorized into congenital and acquired heart disease (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Khor and Chin, 2020</xref>). The two most common types of congenital heart disease are ventricular septal defect and tricuspid valve dysplasia (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Tidholm <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Acquired cardiac diseases in cats can have several causes including primary cardiomyopathies (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Sisakian, 2014</xref>) or secondarily from other diseases (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">Spalla <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). The most common acquired heart disease in cats in clinical practice is hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Fuentes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). </p><p>The diagnostic methods of feline heart disease include history taking, physical examination, thoracic auscultation, thoracic radiography, electrocardiography (ECG), and echocardiogram (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Fuentes <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). Additionally, the advanced diagnostic imaging modality, computed tomography (CT), is currently one of the most useful diagnostic tools for evaluating cardiac disorders in both humans (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Savino <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>) and cats (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">d&#8217;Anjou, 2018</xref>). Thoracic radiography is a routine diagnostic test for heart size evaluation (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">Kittleson and Cote, 2021</xref>). This technique is non-invasive, has wide availability, and is less expensive compared to other imaging modalities (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Schober <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Although thoracic radiography is readily accessible in general practice, it provides limited information for some definitive diagnoses (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Henninger, 2003</xref>). There are some disadvantages of radiography such as low image resolution, and distortion and magnification effects on acquired images (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Nyathi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Furthermore, the detail obtained from the standard radiograph normally provides only two-dimensional images that cause a superimposition of each organ (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Ruderman and Flaherty, 2017</xref>). This effect could interfere with interpretation accuracy and occasionally, can make diagnosis difficult (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Henninger, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Bruno, 2017</xref>). Therefore, CT has been increasingly applied in veterinary clinical practice (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Keane <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). CT can provide more accurate information and has several benefits over radiography (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Bertolini and Angeloni, 2017</xref>). For example, CT images are not affected by the superimposition effect (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Mikla and Mikla, 2014</xref>) and can be expressed as three-dimensional images with higher resolution. This allows radiologists to identify details including the size, shape, and texture of internal organs (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Bertolini and Angeloni, 2017</xref>), and assist in locating lesions more precisely (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">d&#8217;Anjou, 2018</xref>). The combination of radiography and CT could increase the chances of finding intrathoracic lesions when compared to without (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Prather <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>). A recent study in dogs demonstrated that CT could assist veterinary practitioner in evaluating and diagnosing airway disorders. Furthermore, it provided information regarding heart volume and thoracic volume (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Uehara <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>).</p><p>Since there is less information concerning feline heart size as observed on CT, the purposes of this study were, first, to create measuring techniques for feline heart size on CT. Second, to establish a reference range value of normal feline heart size on CT. Finally, to determine the relationships of feline heart size observed on CT with internal parameters such as age, bodyweight (BW), and sex.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materialsandmethods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Animals</title><p>This study utilized the clinical, thoracic radiographs, and CT data of included client-owned cats that were presented to the Diagnostic Imaging Unit, the Small Animal Hospital, Faculty of Veterinary Science, Chulalongkorn University between February and June 2017. The data were retrieved from the hospital information system and picture archiving and communication systems (PACs). Clinical information including age, sex, breed, and BW were recorded. The exclusion criteria were incomplete clinical information, any abnormalities related to cardiocirculatory disease, abnormal feline proBNP test, incomplete information of thoracic radiographs and CT, thoracic/abdominal mass or tumors, respiratory abnormality, duration of thoracic radiographs and CT data difference of more than 1 month, cardiomegaly based on radiographic vertebral heart score (rVHS), and any thoracic vertebrae abnormalities based on radiographs and CT. All healthy cats were divided into two groups according to the age of growth plate closure (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Miranda <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>) which yielded a group of age less than or equal to 18 months (Gr. A) and a group aged more than 18 months (Gr. B).</p></sec><sec><title>Thoracic radiograph evaluation</title><p>The right lateral projection of thoracic radiographs of all included cats in this study was collected as digital information and communication (DICOM) files for measuring the rVHS through DICOM viewer software (Osirix<sup>&#174;</sup>, Geneva, Switzerland) as shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. The rVHS was examined by measuring the long axis (LA) and the short axis (SA) as described by <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Lister and Buchanan (2000)</xref>. The LA and SA were manually measured using a digital caliper and the values were recorded. The LA was the distance from the ventral border of the mainstem bronchus to the cardiac apex. The SA was the widest distance of the heart perpendicular to the LA line. The LA and SA lines were transposed onto the vertebral column and the number of vertebrae beginning from the cranial end plate of the fourth thoracic vertebrae (T4) were recorded as rVHS. All radiographic measurements were performed by the same investigator using the same image archiving PACs system with the DICOM viewer software.</p></sec><sec><title>Thoracic CT images evaluation</title><p>All CT images at both pre- and post-contrast enhancement of 1.25 mm slice thickness were evaluated using a DICOM viewer (Osirix<sup>&#174;</sup>, Geneva, Switzerland), and a non-CT unit workstation with 2,560 &#215; 1,440 pixels monitor. All CT images were completed using a 64 CT slice scanner (Optima 660, General Electric, Japan) in sternal positioning with 120 kVP, automated milliampere, matrix size of 512 &#215; 512. All images were performed using multiplanar reconstruction and the soft tissue window was set [350 Hounsfield units (HU) of window width and 40 HU of window level] during evaluation to ensure the best visualization and symmetry of the thoracic structures. The measuring methods of the four parameters in this study are described as follows.</p><p>On cross-sectional images at the carina level, thoracic height/width ratio (THW) was determined as described previously (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Uehara <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). A manual drawing using a digital caliper from the ventral border of the vertebrae to the sternum was performed to identify the thoracic height (TH). For the thoracic width (TW), a digital caliper was used from the right to left thoracic wall at the widest part and perpendicular to the TH as shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>. THW was then calculated. Relative heart area (RHA) was evaluated by manually drawing the outline of the heart to evaluate the heart area (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A</xref>). For the thoracic area (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3B</xref>), manual drawing was performed as described previously (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Uehara <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Finally, RHA was then calculated as the ratio of heart area to thoracic area at the carina level. Transverse vertebral heart score (tVHS) was determined by manual drawing using a digital caliper. Heart height (HH) was the height of the heart and heart width (HW) was the widest distance perpendicular to the HH. The ratio of the sum of HH and HW to the height of the vertebral body at the carina level was then calculated as tVHS (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). CT vertebral heart score (ctVHS) was evaluated on the sagittal plane images. The measurement method was performed in the same way as on radiography (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Lister and Buchanan, 2000</xref>) (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). All CT measurements were performed by the same experienced radiologist using the same image archiving PACs system through DICOM viewer software.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>rVHS measurement methods. rVHS was measured on right lateral thoracic radiograph. LA was the distance from ventral border of the mainstem bronchus to the cardiac apex. SA was the widest distance of the heart perpendicular with the LA line. LA and SA lines were transposed onto the vertebral column and the number of vertebrae beginning from the cranial end plate of the fourth thoracic vertebrae (T4) were recorded as rVHS. rVHS: radiographic vertebral heart score; LA: long axis; SA: short axis; T4: the fourth thoracic vertebrae.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-13-337-g001.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>THW measurement methods. THW was measured on cross-sectional CT image at the carina level. TH was distance from ventral border of the vertebrae to the sternum. TW was distance from the right to left thoracic wall at the widest part and perpendicular to TH. THW: thoracic height/width ratio; CT: computed tomography; TH: thoracic height; TW: thoracic width.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-13-337-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All data were analyzed using statistical software (Prism 9, GraphPad<sup>&#174;</sup>, CA, USA). The descriptive data of clinical information were expressed as mean &#177; standard deviation (SD) including minimum and maximum values. All data sets were analyzed using the Shapiro&#8211;Wilk test to determine the normalization of the data. All parameters were compared between age, sex, and gonadal status using the unpaired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test and Mann&#8211;Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic> test. The correlations and associations of each parameter with other factors such as age and BW were evaluated using Pearson&#8217;s correlation coefficient and Spearman&#8217;s correlation coefficient. A <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value less than 0.05 was considered a statistically significant difference.</p><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><title>RHA measurement methods. RHA was measured on cross-sectional CT image at the carina level. (A) Heart area was the area of the heart. (B) Thoracic area was the area of the thoracic cavity. RHA was calculated as the ratio of heart area to thoracic area at the carina level. RHA: relative heart area; CT: computed tomography.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-13-337-g003.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig4" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><title>tVHS measurement methods. tVHS was measured on cross-sectional CT image at the carina level. Heart height (HH) was the height of the heart. HW was the widest distance perpendicular to HH. The ratio of the sum of HH and HW to the height of the vertebral body (black line) at the carina level was then calculated as tVHS. tVHS: transverse vertebral heart score; CT: computed tomography; HH: he.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-13-337-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>This study was designed as a retrospective observational investigation. All information such as clinical demographic data, history, and all images were permitted for use by the committee of the Small Animal Hospital, Faculty of Veterinary Science, Chulalongkorn University (Approval number: 228/2563).</p><fig position="float" id="fig5" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><title>ctVHS measurement methods. ctVHS was measured on the sagittal plane image. LA was the distance from ventral border of the mainstem bronchus to the cardiac apex. SA was the widest distance of the heart perpendicular with the LA line. LA and SA lines were transposed onto the vertebral column and the number of vertebrae beginning from the cranial end plate of the fourth thoracic vertebrae (T4) were recorded as ctVHS. ctVHS: computed tomography vertebral heart score; LA: long axis; SA: short axis; T4: the fourth thoracic vertebrae.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-13-337-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Clinical demographic data</title><p>There were 24 cats that presented at the Diagnostic Imaging Unit, The Small Animal Hospital, Faculty of Veterinary Science, Chulalongkorn University and that met our inclusion criteria. There were domestic shorthair (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 19, 79.17%), American Shorthair (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 2, 8.34%), Scottish Fold (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 2, 8.34%), and Persian (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 1, 4.15%). There were eight male cats (4 castrated and 4 intact cats) and 16 female cats (9 spayed and 7 intact cats). All cats were reviewed and categorized into two groups, those aged younger or equal to 18 months (Gr. A) and those aged older than 18 months (Gr. B). Each group was composed of 12 cats. All clinical demographic information is summarized in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The BW of cats in Gr. A was significantly lower than that of cats in Gr. B ( <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0015). The neutered cats had significantly higher BW than the intact cats (<italic toggle="yes">p </italic>&lt; 0.001).</p></sec><sec><title>Computed tomographic (CT) heart size parameters</title><p>In this study, there was no significant difference in each parameter between pre- and post-contrast enhanced images (THW; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.5457, RHA; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.6128, ctVHS; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.8166, and tVHS; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.9148) (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Therefore, for the rest of the study, an average of pre- and post-contrast values of each parameter was used for further statistical analysis.</p><p>The comparisons of each parameter between age groups which were Gr. A and Gr. B are shown in <xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. The results indicated that cats in Gr. B had significantly higher TH, thoracic area, height of the vertebral body, and THW than cats in Gr. A (<italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.0307, <italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.0161, <italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.0061, and <italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.0414, respectively). Cats in Gr. A had significantly higher RHA and tVHS than those of Gr. B (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0014 and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0380, respectively). There was no significant difference in ctVHS between Gr. A and Gr. B. Regarding gender, male cats had significantly higher TH, TW, heart area, thoracic area, HH, and HW than female cats (<italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.0344, <italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.0276, <italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.0032, <italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.0447, <italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.0064, and <italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.0225, respectively) (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). No significant difference of THW, RHA, tVHS, and ctVHS between male and female cats was detected. </p><p>Considering gonadal status, we found that neutered cats (both male and female) had significantly higher TH, thoracic area, and height of vertebral body than intact cats (male; <italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.0362, <italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.0129, and <italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.0057, female; <italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.0260, <italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.0129, and <italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.0275, respectively) (<xref rid="tab5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). Neutered males also had significantly higher TW than intact males and neutered female cats had significantly lower RHA than intact females ( <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0166). No significant difference of THW, tVHS, and ctVHS between neutered and non-neutered cats was found in this study. The summarized reference range values of each calculated heart size parameter observed on CT in clinically healthy cats is summarized in <xref rid="tab6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>The correlations among heart size parameters</title><p>In this present study, cat age had significant positive correlations with TH, thoracic area, and height of the vertebral body (<italic toggle="yes">r </italic>= 0.4979; <italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.0355, <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.5941; <italic toggle="yes">p </italic>= 0.0093, and <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.4879; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0400, respectively) and had a significant negative correlation with RHA ( <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.7228; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0007). BW of cats had significant positive correlations with TH, TW, thoracic area, and height of the vertebral body (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.6628; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0006, <italic toggle="yes">r </italic>= 0.6514; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0008, <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.7772; <italic toggle="yes">p </italic>&lt; 0.0001, and <italic toggle="yes">r </italic>= 0.4516; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0305, respectively) and had a significant negative correlation with RHA ( <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.5801; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0036). </p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Clinical demographic information of all included cats in this study.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Clinical information</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#177; SD</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1"><bold>Age</bold> (<bold>months)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.17<bold> &#177; </bold>48.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#8211;132</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8)<break/>Intact (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4)<break/>Castrated (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.13<bold> &#177; </bold>47.27<break/>6.25 <bold>&#177;</bold> 1.50<break/>66.00<bold> &#177; </bold>53.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#8211;132<break/>4&#8211;7<break/>12&#8211;132</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 16)<break/>Intact (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7)<break/>Spayed (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.69<bold> &#177; </bold>49.24<break/>9.71 <bold>&#177;</bold> 6.87<break/>80.78<bold> &#177;</bold> 45.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#8211;132<break/>4&#8211;24<break/>7&#8211;132</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1"><bold>Body</bold>
<bold>weight</bold> (<bold>kg)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">All (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.28<bold> &#177; </bold>1.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50&#8211;5.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8)<break/>Intact (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4)<break/>Castrated (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.57<bold> &#177; </bold>0.97<break/>2.85 <bold>&#177;</bold> 0.69<break/>4.30<bold> &#177; </bold>0.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00&#8211;5.00<break/>2.00&#8211;3.50<break/>3.70&#8211;3.50</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 16)<break/>Intact (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7)<break/>Spayed (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.14<bold> &#177; </bold>1.16<break/>2.19 <bold>&#177;</bold> 0.64<break/>3.88<bold> &#177; </bold>0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50&#8211;4.70<break/>1.50&#8211;3.10<break/>2.00&#8211;4.70</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gr. A (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12)<break/>Gr. B (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.62<bold> &#177; </bold>0.92<break/>3.94<bold> &#177; </bold>0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50&#8211;4.50<break/>2.00&#8211;5.00</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Gr.A: <bold>&#8804;</bold>18 months; Gr. B: <bold>&gt;</bold>18 months.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Computed tomographic heart size parameters of all cats.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">1.25 mm of slice thickness</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-contrast</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-contrast</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">THW</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 &#177; 0.09<break/>(0.75&#8211;1.14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 &#177; 0.08<break/>(0.75&#8211;1.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5457</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RHA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38 &#177; 0.06<break/>(0.26&#8211;0.51)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44 &#177; 0.05<break/>(0.30&#8211;1.59)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6128</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ctVHS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.38 &#177; 0.45<break/>(6.50&#8211;8.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.37 &#177; 0.43<break/>(6.80&#8211;8.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8166</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tVHS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.79 &#177; 1.38<break/>(7.57&#8211;13.94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.95 &#177; 1.37<break/>(8.33&#8211;13.42)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9148</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are expressed as mean &#177; SD and range.</p><p>Statistical difference of each parameter was made using unpaired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test and Mann&#8211;Whitney test.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The correlations between calculated heart size parameters observed on CT and rVHS, tVHS, and ctVHS were significantly, moderately positive correlation with rVHS (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.4769; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0480 and <italic toggle="yes">r </italic>= 0.6112; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0109, respectively) (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>). While, THW and RHA had non-significant correlation with rVHS (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.2642; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.3026 and <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.1920; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.4559, respectively).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>This present study used a slice thickness of 1.25 mm for heart size evaluation based on the recommendations of a previous study as being suitable for intrathoracic structure evaluation in cats (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">Thammasiri <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>). Additionally, several advantages of the greater slice thickness images when compared to the smaller ones have been reported, including less data storage required and greater signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Alshipli and Kabir, 2017</xref>). Higher SNR reflects better CT image quality. SNR is determined by slice thickness, where a greater slice thickness results in an increasing signal compared to the amount of noise in each area (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Alshipli and Kabir, 2017</xref>). Accordingly, 1.25 mm of CT images can provide a comparable and high image quality and also require less data storage. Moreover, the CT-scanning time for a 1.25 mm slice thickness is faster compared to a smaller slice thickness which is suitable in clinical practice due to decreased time of radiation and anesthetization (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Schwarz and O&#8217;Brien, 2011</xref>). </p><p>TH, thoracic area, and THW were significantly higher in Gr. B than Gr. A. In contrast, RHA was significantly lower in Gr. B than Gr. A. These results correspond with a study in dogs (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Uehara <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>), in which anatomical features of the heart and thoracic cavity were influenced by body size. tVHS was significantly higher in Gr. A than in Gr. B. This may be due to the vertebral height on CT images used as a normalized parameter of tVHS. The older cats had a greater vertebral body height than younger cats due to their larger body size. Additionally, this may also be because cats in Gr. A were in the stage of incomplete bone growth as described in a previous report (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Miranda <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>CT heart size parameters between Gr. A and Gr. B of cats (mean &#177; SD and range).</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Groups</th><th colspan="11" rowspan="1">Parameters</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TH (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TW (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart area (cm<sup>2</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thoracic area (cm<sup>2</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height of vertebrae body (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart height (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart width (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">THW</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RHA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">tVHS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ctVHS</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gr. A<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.33 &#177; 0.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 3.90 &#177; 0.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.12 &#177; 1.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.31 &#177; 2.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 &#177; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.68 &#177; 0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47 &#177; 0.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 &#177; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42 &#177; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.34 &#177; 0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.41 &#177; 0.44</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.72&#8211;4.04)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.14&#8211;4.94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.91&#8211;6.98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(8.14&#8211;18.56)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.40&#8211;0.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.21&#8211;3.01)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.87&#8211;3.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.76&#8211;0.98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.34&#8211;0.51)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.22&#8211;13.53)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6.90&#8211;8.00)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gr. B<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.74 &#177; 0.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.20 &#177; 0.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.36 &#177; 1.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.14 &#177; 2.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51 &#177; 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.76 &#177; 0.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53 &#177; 0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 &#177; 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 &#177; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.25 &#177; 1.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.42 &#177; 0.46</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.95&#8211;4.55)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.65&#8211;4.68)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.48&#8211;7.62)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(11.23&#8211;19.80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.46&#8211;0.61)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.01&#8211;3.36)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.00&#8211;3.27)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.80&#8211;1.14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.26&#8211;0.41)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7.56&#8211;12.30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6.90&#8211;8.00)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0307<xref rid="table3_fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0823</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9177</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0161<xref rid="table3_fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0061<xref rid="table3_fn2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6109</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7381</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0414<xref rid="table3_fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0014<xref rid="table3_fn2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0380<xref rid="table3_fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4834</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table3_fn1"><label>*</label><p><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05. </p></fn><fn id="table3_fn2"><label>**</label><p><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></fn><p>Gr.A: &#8804;18 months; Gr. B: &gt;18 months.</p><p>Statistical difference between groups of each parameters was made using unpaired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test and Mann&#8211;Whitney test.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><title>CT heart size parameters of male and female cats (mean &#177; SD and range)</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sex</th><th colspan="11" rowspan="1">Parameters</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TH (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TW (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart area (cm<sup>2</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thoracic area (cm<sup>2</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height of vertebral body (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart height (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">HW (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">THW</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RHA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">tVHS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ctVHS</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Male<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.79 &#177; 0.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.25 &#177; 0.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.18 &#177; 0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.38 &#177; 3.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 &#177; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.77 &#177; 0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.95 &#177; 0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 &#177; 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41 &#177; 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.75 &#177; 1.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.45 &#177; 0.46</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.20&#8211;4.55)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.47&#8211;4.94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5.15&#8211;7.61)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.14&#8211;19.80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.44&#8211;0.60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.38&#8211;3.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.78&#8211;3.36)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.80&#8211;1.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.35&#8211;0.51)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9.38&#8211;13.94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7.00&#8211;8.00)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Female<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.36 &#177; 0.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.75 &#177; 0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.70 &#177; 1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.61 &#177; 2.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 &#177; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.38 &#177; 0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.62 &#177; 0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 &#177; 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36 &#177; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.51 &#177; 1.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.30 &#177; 0.48</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.72&#8211;3.98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.14&#8211;4.34)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.79&#8211;6.71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(8.14&#8211;16.69)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.40&#8211;0.53)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.87&#8211;2.78)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.07&#8211;3.32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.75&#8211;1.01)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.26&#8211;0.46)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7.57&#8211;12.37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6.80&#8211;8.00)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0344<xref rid="table4_fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0276<xref rid="table4_fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0032<xref rid="table4_fn2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0447<xref rid="table4_fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2237</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0064<xref rid="table4_fn2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0225<xref rid="table4_fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5484</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1201</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0694</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4822</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table4_fn1"><label>*</label><p><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05. </p></fn><fn id="table4_fn2"><label>**</label><p><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></fn><p>Gr.A: &#8804;18 months; Gr. B: &gt;18 months.</p><p>Statistical difference between groups of each parameters was made using unpaired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test and Mann&#8211;Whitney test.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><title>CT heart size parameters of neutered and non-neutered cats (mean &#177; SD and range).</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="2">
<bold>Neuter status</bold>
</th><th colspan="11" rowspan="1">
<bold>Parameters</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TH (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TW (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart area (cm<sup>2</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thoracic area (cm<sup>2</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height of vertebral body (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart height (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart width (cm)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">THW</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RHA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">tVHS</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ctVHS</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Male<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Intact<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.53 &#177; 0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.91 &#177; 0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.79 &#177; 0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.13 &#177; 1.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 &#177; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.65 &#177; 0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.84 &#177; 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 &#177; 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 &#177; 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.42 &#177; 1.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.45 &#177; 0.50</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.20&#8211;3.85)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.47&#8211;4.29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5.14&#8211;6.98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.14&#8211;14.26)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.44&#8211;0.55)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.38&#8211;3.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.78&#8211;2.97)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.79&#8211;0.98)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.36&#8211;0.51)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10.07&#8211;12.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7.00&#8211;8.00)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Castrated<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.13 &#177; 0.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.70 &#177; 0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.69 &#177; 0.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.38 &#177; 1.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58 &#177; 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.66 &#177; 0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10 &#177; 0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 &#177; 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36 &#177; 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.81 &#177; 1.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.45&#177; 0.50</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.81&#8211;4.55)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4.49&#8211;4.94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5.86&#8211;7.61)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(15.61&#8211;19.80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.55&#8211;0.60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.67&#8211;3.06)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.91&#8211;3.36)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.81&#8211;0.97)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.35&#8211;0.39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(8.20&#8211;11.24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7.00&#8211;8.00)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0362<xref rid="table5_fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0177<xref rid="table5_fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2315</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0129<xref rid="table5_fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0057<xref rid="table5_fn2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2629</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1088</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6981</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0997</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9822</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9672</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Female (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 16)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Intact<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.15 &#177; 0.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.76 &#177; 0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.54 &#177; 1.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.14 &#177; 2.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 &#177; 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.27 &#177; 0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60 &#177; 0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 &#177; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41 &#177; 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.73 &#177; 1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.39 &#177; 0.45</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.72&#8211;3.68)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.08&#8211;4.28)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.48&#8211;6.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(8.14&#8211;14.14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.40&#8211;0.51)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.87&#8211;2.65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.21&#8211;3.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.76&#8211;0.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.32&#8211;0.46)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9.50&#8211;12.28)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6.90&#8211;8.00)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Spayed<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.62 &#177; 0.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.07 &#177; 0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.81 &#177; 1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.29 &#177; 1.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 &#177; 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47 &#177; 0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63 &#177; 0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 &#177; 0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 &#177; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.35 &#177; 1.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.22 &#177; 0.50</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.94&#8211;4.17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.65&#8211;4.68)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3.00&#8211;6.71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(11.23&#8211;16.70)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.46&#8211;0.55)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1.97&#8211;2.78)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2.10&#8211;3.32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.75&#8211;1.14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.26&#8211;0.41)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7.56&#8211;12.37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6.90&#8211;8.00)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0260<xref rid="table5_fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6143</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0067<xref rid="table5_fn2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0275<xref rid="table5_fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1815</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8449</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2576</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0166<xref rid="table5_fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5430</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5100</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table5_fn1"><label>*</label><p><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05. </p></fn><fn id="table5_fn2"><label>**</label><p><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></fn><p>Statistical difference between groups of each parameters was made using unpaired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6.</label><caption><title>Summarized the reference range values of each calculated heart size parameter observed on CT in clinical healthy cats.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Gr. of cats</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gr. A</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gr. B</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">THW</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 &#177; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 &#177; 0.10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.83&#8211;0.96)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.83&#8211;0.92)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">RHA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42 &#177; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 &#177; 0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.38&#8211;0.45)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.31&#8211;0.37)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">tVHS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.34 &#177; 0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.25 &#177; 1.22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9.70&#8211;11.52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9.53&#8211;11.88)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">ctVHS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.41 &#177; 0.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.42 &#177; 0.46</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7.05&#8211;7.58)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7.13&#8211;7.72)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are expressed as mean &#177; SD and 95% confidence interval. Gr.A: &#8804;18 months; Gr. B: &gt;18 months.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The results revealed that gender affected the thoracic cavity and also the heart size. Male cats had significantly greater TH, TW, heart area, thoracic area, HH, and HW than female cats. These results correspond with studies in dogs (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Uehara <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>), humans (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Wooten <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>), and marine mammals (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Ralls and Mesnick, 2009</xref>), in which cats have a form of sexual dimorphism where the male&#8217;s body size is bigger than the female (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Meachen-Samuels and Binder, 2010</xref>). It has been reported that males also have a larger heart size than females in various species such as humans (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Wooten <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Frayer and Wolpoff, 1985</xref>), cats (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Meachen-Samuels and Binder, 2010</xref>), and dogs (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Uehara <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>).</p><p>For the association of neutering status and each parameter, the results showed that neutered female cats had significantly higher TH and thoracic area than intact female cats and had significantly lower RHA than intact females. Similarly, neutered male cats had significantly higher TH, TW, and thoracic area than intact male cats. The results indicated and supported that the anatomical structures related to the heart and thoracic cavity are influenced by body size and gonadal status. These results correspond with those for human (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Wooten <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>) and dog (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Uehara <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) studies. In dogs, it has been reported that the relative heart volume is lower in large dogs than small/medium dogs, consistent with the results of this study. Additionally, the heart volume was relative to the size of the thoracic cavity (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Uehara <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Both neutered males and females had significantly higher vertebral body height than intact males and females. This may be because most of neutered male and female cats in this study were aged more than 18 months. </p><p>This study observed RHA instead of relative heart volume as in a previous study of dogs (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Uehara <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). This is because the method for relative heart volume evaluation is more cumbersome and difficult than RHA assessment. Additionally, it takes a lot of time to complete relative heart volume evaluation which is not suitable for practitioners in clinical practice. Our results demonstrated that RHA can be used for heart size and thoracic cavity evaluation as relative heart volume and provides results consistent with a previous canine study (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Uehara <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>).</p><p>The correlations between heart size parameters observed on CT and age and BW of cats showed that age and BW had significant positive correlations with TH, thoracic area, and vertebral body height. On the contrary, age had a significant negative correlation with RHA. These findings were also in agreement with previous studies in humans (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Wooten <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>) and dogs (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Uehara <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>), where a higher BW and age were related to a larger body size, which influenced heart and thoracic cavity size. </p><p>Additionally, we evaluated the correlations between heart size parameters observed on CT and rVHS; the results showed that among four CT heart size parameters, tVHS and ctVHS had significant moderately positive correlations with rVHS. This could indicate that tVHS and ctVHS could be recommended parameters for evaluating feline heart size on CT images in clinical practice. Additionally, in the author&#8217;s opinion, both tVHS and ctVHS are easier to determine than other parameters in the current study. </p><p>According to the nature of the retrospective study, we could not control the ECG gate and respiratory phase of cats during the CT procedure in this study. Involuntary motion from respiration or cardiac motion during image acquisition can cause artifacts in the reconstructed images (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Barrett and Keat, 2004</xref>). However, in the present study, the mild motion artifact including blurring and stair-step artifact did not affect image quality and feasibility to measure all parameters. </p><p>The present study used a 64-slice multidetector CT (MDCT) to scan and generate the images. Two previous reports about thoracic CT in dogs (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Uehara <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) and cats (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) used a 16-slice MDCT in their study. Although using different MDCT scanner in each study, our study demonstrated that the results of this study correspond with a previous study in dogs (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Uehara <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Accordingly, different MDCT scanners may not affect the measured parameters, especially when following the previous study protocol.</p><p>This study is the first report describing the use of CT for evaluating heart size and also providing a reference range for each CT heart size parameter in clinically healthy cats. This information could be useful for clinical practitioners and be of interest to researchers in further studies. </p><fig position="float" id="fig6" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><title>Correlations between calculated heart size parameters observed on CT and rVHS. (A) tVHS and rVHS. (B) ctVHS and rVHS. CT: computed tomography; rVHS: radiographic vertebral heart score; tVHS: transverse vertebral heart score; ctVHS: CT vertebral heart score.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-13-337-g006.jpg"/></fig><p>The main limitation of this study was the small sample size. Additionally, we did not perform the echocardiography due to the nature of the retrospective study. However, all cats were determined as being normal before inclusion in this study. Furthermore, this study did not compare all parameters between clinically healthy cats and cats with heart disease and also could not perform and control the ECG gate and respiratory phase of cats during the CT procedure; a limitation of the retrospective study. Therefore, future studies should be considered in order to provide further information.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>This study demonstrated that CT heart size evaluation could be performed using 1.25 mm slice thickness and both pre- and post-contrast enhanced images. The anatomical structures related to the heart and thoracic cavity are associated with the age, sex, and gonadal status of cats. Among four CT heart size parameters in this study, tVHS and ctVHS are recommended for evaluating feline heart size on CT images in clinical practice. However, further studies comparing clinically healthy cats and heart disease cats should be performed to fulfill and validate the information.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors would like to thank the Small Animal Hospital, Faculty of Veterinary Science, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, Thailand for all support and information.</p></ack><sec><title>Funding</title><p>This study was granted from Faculty of Veterinary Science, Chulalongkorn University, Bangkok, Thailand. </p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interests related to this article.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p>CT and NC conceived the ideas of the study; CT and NC conceived the ideas for the analysis; AW, CS, ZK, TS, SJ, SS and CT performed the analyses; AW, CS, ZK, TS, SJ, NC and CT wrote the manuscript; CT and NC were major contributors in writing the manuscript and all other authors commented on the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alshipli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kabir</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of slice thickness on image noise and diagnostic content of single-source-dual energy computed tomography</article-title><source>J. Physics. Conference Series, Series 851</source><year>2017</year><volume>851</volume><fpage>012005</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1742-6596/851/1/012005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>J.F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keat</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Artifacts in CT: recognition and avoidance</article-title><source>Radiographics</source><year>2004</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1679</fpage><lpage>1691</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15537976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1148/rg.246045065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertolini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angeloni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Halefoglu</surname><given-names>A.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vascular and cardiac CT in small animals</article-title><source>In Computed tomography-advanced applications</source><year>2017</year><publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>InTechOpen</publisher-name><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>266</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>M.A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>256 Shades of gray: uncertainly and diagnostic error in radiology</article-title><source>Diagnosis (Berl)</source><year>2017</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29536935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1515/dx-2017-0006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>d&#8217;Anjou</surname><given-names>M.A</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thrall</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Principle of computed tomography and magnetic resonance imaging</article-title><source>Textbook of Veterinary Diagnostic Radiology</source><year>2018</year><edition>7th</edition><publisher-name>Elsevier saunders</publisher-name><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>95</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frayer</surname><given-names>D.W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolpoff</surname><given-names>M.H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sexual dimorphism</article-title><source>Annual Review of Anthropology</source><year>1985</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.an.14.100185.002241</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>L.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rush</surname><given-names>J.E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>J.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huggins</surname><given-names>G.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maron</surname><given-names>M.S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Feline hypertrophic cardiomyopathy: a spontaneous large animal model of human HCM</article-title><source>Cardiol. Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28868097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14740/cr578w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5574284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>L.V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chetboul</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cote</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>R.P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haggstrom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kittenson</surname><given-names>M.D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schober</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>A.J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ACVM consensus statement guidelines for the classification, diagnosis and management of cardiomyopathies in cats</article-title><source>J. Vet. Intern. Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>1062</fpage><lpage>1077</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32243654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jvim.15745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7255676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henninger</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of computed tomography in the diseased feline thorax</article-title><source>J. Small Anim. Pract</source><year>2003</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12622469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1748-5827.2003.tb00121.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keane</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sturrock</surname><given-names>C.J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rutland</surname><given-names>C.S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Halefoglu</surname><given-names>A.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computed tomography in veterinary medicine: currently published and tomorrow&#8217;s vision</article-title><source>In Computed tomography-advanced applications</source><year>2017</year><publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>InTechOpen</publisher-name><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>289</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khor</surname><given-names>K.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>M.X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Occurrences of heart disease in apparently healthy cats in Klang Valley. Malaysia</article-title><source>J. Adv. Vet. Anim. Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33005676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5455/javar.2020.g446</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7521808</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kittleson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cote</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The feline cardiomyopathies</article-title><source>J. Feline Med. Surg</source><year>2021</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1009</fpage><lpage>1027</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34693806</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1098612X211021819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8723176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lister</surname><given-names>A.L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>J.W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vertebral scale system to measure feline heart size in radiographs of cats</article-title><source>J. Am. Vet. Med. Assoc</source><year>2000</year><volume>216</volume><fpage>210</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10649755</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2460/javma.2000.216.210</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meachen-Samuels</surname><given-names>J.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Binder</surname><given-names>W.J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sexual dimorphism and ontogenetic growth in the American lion and sabertoothed cat from Rancho La Brea</article-title><source>J. Zool</source><year>2010</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>279</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Michal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Congenital heart defects in cat&#8212;prevalence and survival</article-title><year>2010</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">6 September 2022</date-in-citation><comment>Available via <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://stud.epsilon.slu.se/7580/17/michal_j_150202.pdf">https://stud.epsilon.slu.se/7580/17/michal_j_150202.pdf</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikla</surname><given-names>I.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikla</surname><given-names>V.V</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikla</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikla</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computed Tomography</article-title><source>Medical Imaging Technology</source><year>2014</year><edition>1st</edition><publisher-name>Elsevier Saunders</publisher-name><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miranda</surname><given-names>F.G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>I.P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Viegas</surname><given-names>F.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Megda</surname><given-names>T.T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nepomuceno</surname><given-names>A.C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>R.C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezende</surname><given-names>C.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Radiographic study of the development of the pelvis and hip and the femorotibial joints in domestic cats</article-title><source>J. Feline Med. Surg</source><year>2020</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>476</fpage><lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31184248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1098612X19854809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10814335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyathi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chirwa</surname><given-names>T.F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van der Merwe</surname><given-names>D.G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A survey of digital radiography practice in four South African teaching hospitals: an illuminative study</article-title><year>2010</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">16 December 2021</date-in-citation><comment>Available via <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.biij.org/2010/1/e5">http://www.biij.org/2010/1/e5</uri></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2349/biij.6.1.e5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3097796</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21611065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>C.R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>M.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>R.T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thoracic computed tomography in feline patients without use of chemical restraint</article-title><source>Vet. Radiol. Ultrasound</source><year>2011</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1740-8261.2011.01814.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21447036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prather</surname><given-names>A.B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>C.R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thrall</surname><given-names>D.E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of radiography in combination with computed tomography for the assessment of non-cardiac thoracic disease in the dog and cat</article-title><source>Vet. Radiol. Ultrasound</source><year>2005</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15869154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1740-8261.2005.00023.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ralls</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mesnick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perrin</surname><given-names>W.F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wuersig</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thewissen</surname><given-names>J.G.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sexual dimorphism</article-title><source>Encyclopedia of marine mammals</source><year>2009</year><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name><fpage>1005</fpage><lpage>1011</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riesen</surname><given-names>S.C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kovacevic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lombard</surname><given-names>C.W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amberger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of heart disease in symptomatic cats: an overview from 1998 to 2005</article-title><source>Euro. J. Companion Anim. Pract</source><year>2007</year><volume>149</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1024/0036-7281.149.2.65</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17343132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruderman</surname><given-names>E.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flaherty</surname><given-names>J.P</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelley</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Firestein</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Mycobacterial infections of bones and joints</article-title><source>In Textbook of rheumatology</source><year>2017</year><edition>10th</edition><publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier Saunders</publisher-name><fpage>1905</fpage><lpage>1917</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Savino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zwerner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herzog</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Politi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonomo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoepf</surname><given-names>U.J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CT of cardiac function</article-title><source>J. Thorac. Imag</source><year>2007</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/RTI.0b013e3180317433</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17325580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schober</surname><given-names>K.E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maerz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ludewig</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>J.A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnostic accuracy of electrocardiography and thoracic radiography in the assessment of left atrial size in cats: comparison with transthoracic 2-dimensional echocardiography</article-title><source>J. Vet. Intern. Med</source><year>2007</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>709</fpage><lpage>718</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17708390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1892/0891-6640(2007)21[709:daoeat]2.0.co;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Brien</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tobias</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jimmy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CT Acquisition Principles</article-title><source>Veterinary Computed Tomography</source><year>2011</year><publisher-loc>Hoboken NJ</publisher-loc><publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>27</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sisakian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cardiomyopathies: evolution of pathogenesis concepts and potential for new therapies</article-title><source>World J. Cardiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>478</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24976920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4330/wjc.v6.i6.478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4072838</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spalla</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Locatelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riscazzi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santagostino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cremaschi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brambilla</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survival in cats with primary and secondary cardiomyopathies</article-title><source>J. Feline Med. Surg</source><year>2016</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>509</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26058586</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1098612X15588797</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11185237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephenson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>J.W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaccarezza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The vertebrate heart: an evolutionary perspective</article-title><source>J. Anat</source><year>2017</year><volume>231</volume><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28905992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/joa.12687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5696137</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tidholm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ljungvall</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haggstrom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoglund</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Congenital heart defects in cats: a retrospective study of 162 cats (1996-2013)</article-title><source>J. Vet. Cardiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>S215</fpage><lpage>S219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26776580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jvc.2014.09.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thammasiri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thanaboonnipat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choisunirachon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darawiroj</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multi-factorial considerations for intra-thoracic lymph node evaluations of healthy cats on computed tomographic images</article-title><source>BMC Vet. Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33509167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12917-021-02771-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7844987</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uehara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CT-based anatomical features of large airway and heart volume in dogs of different body size</article-title><source>Vet. J</source><year>2009</year><volume>246</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.tvjl.2019.01.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30902185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wooten</surname><given-names>S.V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moestl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chilibeck</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alvero</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>J.R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mittag</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tank</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rittweger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age-and sex-differences in cardiac characteristics determined by echocardiography in masters athletes</article-title><source>Front. Physiol</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>630148</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33536945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fphys.2020.630148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7848176</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>