<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2846</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">openvetj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Veterinary Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2226-4485</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2218-6050</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tripoli</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11682776</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11682776.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11682776</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11682776</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39737028</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/OVJ.2024.v14.i11.8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OVJ-14-2794</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effectiveness of gaseous ozone on <italic toggle="yes">Arcobacter butzleri</italic> and bacterial loads on retailed meat sold at Iraqi Wasit markets</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanaan</surname><given-names initials="MHG">Manal Hadi Ghaffoori</given-names></name><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff>Department of Nursing, Technical Institute of Suwaria, Middle Technical University, Baghdad, Iraq</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Manal Hadi Ghaffoori Kanaan. Department of Nursing, Technical Institute of Suwaria, Middle Technical University, Baghdad, Iraq. <email>manalhadi73@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>11</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">477914</issue-id><fpage>2794</fpage><lpage>2805</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>04</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-12-31 15:25:20.740"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2794.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Ozone (O<sub>3</sub>) is a promising alternative antibacterial agent that has recently been used in meat processing. The understanding of the appropriate functional settings of O<sub>3</sub> for addressing food safety problems is still insufficient.</p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>The aim of this study was, therefore, to investigate the effects of exposure to O<sub>3</sub> on the bacteriological quality of retail meat inoculated with <italic toggle="yes">Arcobacter butzleri</italic> at refrigeration temperatures.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods:</title><p>Chicken and cattle meat were inoculated with 7 log CFU/g of <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> previously isolated from fresh and chilled retail meat. Using an O<sub>3</sub> generator (Ivation, Multipurpose Air Sterilizing, USA), the meat samples were treated with O<sub>3</sub> gas (0.5 ppm) for 20 and 40 minutes at temperatures ranging from 3&#176;C to 7&#176;C for 48 hours. Anaerobic and aerobic bacterial growth, as well as <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> were assessed.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>The growth rates of <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic>, total aerobic bacteria, and anaerobic bacteria in chilled meat samples were all slowed by significant reduction by 0.75, 1.13, and 0.7 log CFU/g, respectively, when exposed to O<sub>3</sub> gas (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.05). Compared to control samples kept at 3&#176;C&#8211;7&#176;C for a further 24 hours, the decrease was greater with an additional exposure time of 20 minutes. In contrast to the samples that did not appear to be exposed to O<sub>3</sub>, the total bacterial count of the samples exposed to O<sub>3</sub> showed a statistically significant reduction (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.01) compared to the samples that were not exposed to O<sub>3</sub>. This decrease is important for the health of the population.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>This study explored the use of O<sub>3</sub> experience as a potential antibacterial agent for meat and meat products stored in refrigerators. The results of this research may support further applications of O<sub>3</sub> exposure, such as the installation of an O<sub>3</sub> generator inside a refrigerator. However, further research is needed on O<sub>3</sub> levels and exposure durations.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Arcobacter butzleri</italic></kwd><kwd>Cattle meat</kwd><kwd>Chicken meat</kwd><kwd>Ozone</kwd><kwd>Storage conditions</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Meat is a valuable source of protein with high biological value, and the human body has become accustomed to eating meat over the course of evolution. Furthermore, the nutritional profile of meat is rich in vitamins, minerals, and other elements, and some of these nutrients are either more bioavailable or found exclusively in animal products (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Font-i-Furnols, 2023</xref>). The Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development and the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations forecast a 14% increase in meat consumption by 2030. The growing world population is the main reason for this increase in meat consumption (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">OECD/FAO, 2021</xref>).</p><p>The environments in which animals have been reared up and processed, along with the properties of the end products, in which it provides ideal conditions for the development and maintenance of spoilage and harmful bacteria, making meat and meat products vulnerable to microbiological contamination (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">Mohammed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). The microbiological safety of meat has been a public health concern for many years (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022a</xref>; <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan, 2024</xref>). Different species of bacteria that cause food poisoning have been detected in meat and meat products that cause food poisoning, including Shiga-toxin-producing <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> species, <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Listeria monocytogenes</italic> (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan and Al-Isawi, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">Xu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan and Mohammed, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>,<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr"> 2022b</xref>; <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan and Khashan, 2022</xref>; <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan, 2023</xref>). Moreover, chicken meat has been recognized as the primary source of foodborne outbreaks of <italic toggle="yes">Arcobacter butzleri</italic> (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">Shange <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). Infections caused by <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> provide a considerable threat to human health, resulting in severe food poisoning and sepsis (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. 2023</xref>). A global epidemic of <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> has been documented, although the incidence of human infection is limited (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Chieffi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Jim&#233;nez-Guerra <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). The bacterium <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> has been mentioned in several studies as one of the numerous <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic>-like bacteria in human feces (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Jim&#233;nez-Guerra <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). Moreover, any obstacles to infection with this type of bacteria are compounded by the fact that the multidrug resistant <italic toggle="yes">Arcobacter</italic> spreads much more widely than <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> (<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">Son <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">Riesenberg <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017</xref>). Various disinfectants and some common chemical agents such as chlorine, peracetic acid, hydrogen peroxide, butylated hydroxytoluene, and tetra-butylhydroquinone were mentioned by <xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">Xue <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2023)</xref>, for treatment and preservation to remove bacterial contamination and improve the shelf life of meat quality. Numerous of research studies have examined and assessed many food processing technologies, encompassing both thermal and non-thermal processes (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Jiang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">Stadler <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Chacha <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan and Tarek, 2022</xref>).</p><p>Aqueous chlorine (0.5&#8211;1 ppm) is employed in the meat sector to diminish microbial load, mitigate cross-contamination risk, and maintain carcass safety. The efficacy of chlorine is contingent upon the amount employed. Nevertheless, several research indicates that chlorine by-products, including trihalomethanes, haloacetic acids, and chloramines, may possess carcinogenic properties (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Gil <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan and Abdullah, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2024a</xref>). Investigations are underway about alternatives to traditional cleaning chemicals and disinfectants that pose no risk to human and environmental health, yet possess the capability to diminish and eradicate the transmission of foodborne diseases (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2024a</xref>).</p><p>O<sub>3</sub> is classified as a Generally Recognized as Safe food processing additive that has minimal or no risk. It works considerably better for washing or sanitizing food than chemical sanitizers. O<sub>3</sub> is a more eco-friendly technique than other antimicrobial agents currently in use as it kills microbes without leaving harmful residues on food or equipment (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">Pandiselvam <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Roobab <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). <xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Megahed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2018)</xref> discovered that temperature, pH, and O<sub>3</sub>-oxidizable materials have a significant impact on O<sub>3</sub> degradation rate and half-life. Therefore, O<sub>3</sub> is useful in the meat processing industry when stored in cold, moist, and refrigerated environments (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Bridges <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>). O<sub>3</sub> is very effective against bacteria due to its significant oxidation potential; even at doses as low as 0.01 ppm, the condition remains dangerous to microbes (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Megahed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>). In addition to bacteria, molds, viruses, and protozoa are also susceptible to the antibacterial properties of O<sub>3</sub> (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan, 2018</xref>). Therefore, it has proposed O<sub>3</sub> as a strong substitute for conventional disinfectants (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Megahed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>).</p><p>This study was conducted to investigate the efficacy of gaseous O<sub>3</sub> against bacterial growth on chicken and cattle meat inoculated with <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> and to evaluate its effectiveness in preserving meat at refrigeration temperature.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Study period and location</title><p>This study was conducted from October 2023 to January 2024, in Al-Suwaira, a city in Iraq&#8217;s Wasit governorate in the middle east.</p></sec><sec><title>Collection and processing of samples</title><p>Between October 2023 and January 2024, a total of 32 samples of chicken (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 16) and cattle (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 16) meat were randomly collected from various supermarkets and vendor shops. The samples were packed separately in a sterile plastic bag and sent to the laboratory with ice packs within 3 hours. From the time of collection until use, all samples were stored at a temperature of &#8722;20&#176;C in a freezer. After defrosting in the refrigerator at a temperature of 4&#176;C for 12 hours, the wrapped meat bags were allowed to cool to room temperature for 1 hour before being inoculated. To inoculate the samples with <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri,</italic> around 20 g of the material was placed on a sterile petri dish (65 &#215; 15 mm; FB0875711C, Fisherbrand <sup>TM</sup>, UK). Two separate plastic containers, one for the inoculated and one for the non-inoculated samples, were washed with 70% ethanol to eliminate the possibility of contamination and cross-contamination before and during treatment. This study utilized a 600 mg/hour O<sub>3</sub> generator (Ivation, Multipurpose Air Sterilising, USA) to produce O<sub>3</sub> gas (0.5 ppm) in an O<sub>3</sub> container, informed by previous research (<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Khudhir and Mahdi, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">Mohammed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2024b</xref>) that employed the O<sub>3</sub> generator 600 mg/hour to generate aqueous O<sub>3</sub> at a concentration of 0.5 ppm over varying durations (20, 30, and 45 minutes). The O<sub>3</sub> generator was used according to the manufacturer&#8217;s instructions. This generator has 15-time grades, so it may conduct a variety of disinfection and sterilizing duties by selecting different durations. An automatic timer plug was used to program it for 20 and 40-minute operation times, respectively. The efficacy of O<sub>3</sub> gas (0.5 ppm) on <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> and on the total bacterial population (log CFU/g) was carried out daily during this time.</p></sec><sec><title>Calculation of ozone (O<sub>3</sub>) concentration</title><p>Ozone- CHEMets Visual Kit (K-7404 O<sub>3</sub> analysis kit, USA) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>) was used to measure the O<sub>3</sub> concentration (ppm). A plastic container with 1.5 liter of tap water was covered. The container was injected with an aeration stone via the lid cavity. Four contact periods (10, 15, 30, and 45 minutes) were selected. After each exposure, the tap water was changed and the container was cleaned with fresh tap water. Five drops of A-7400 activator were added to the empty sample cup, which was filled to the 25 ml mark with ozonated water, the CHE-Met ampoule tip was inserted into the cup, the tip was broken off and ingested by the water. The ampoule was inverted several times and left for 1 minute to allow the color to change. The ampoule was placed between the color standards until a high-range comparator indicated the best color. The maximum concentration was 0.5 ppm after 15, 30, and 45 minutes.</p></sec><sec><title>Bacterial strain preparation</title><p>The <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> used in this study was obtained from a previous study (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan, 2021</xref>) in which the bacterium was isolated from retail chicken and cattle meat sold in the markets of Wasit governorate in the middle east of Iraq. The bacterial strains were prepared by thawing them at 4&#176;C and then resuscitating them on modified charcoal cefoperazone deoxycholate agar (mCCDA, Oxoid CM739, UK). They were then incubated at 30&#176;C for 2 days. The pure colonies were cultured in Lauryl Tryptose Broth (Oxoid, CM0451, UK) (overnight at 30&#176;C) and optical density was measured after 2 washing with buffered peptone water (BPW, Oxoid, CM0509, UK).</p></sec><sec><title>Microbiological assessment</title><p>For each type of sample containing both chicken and cattle meat, two different groups were formed. In the first group, an inoculum of <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> at a concentration of 10<sup>7</sup> CFU per milliliter was spread evenly on the surface of meat using sterile spatulas. The second group, on the other hand, received no inoculum for comparison. Also, each group was divided into two sections, the first one was placed in a plastic chamber (L &#215; W &#215; H = 30 &#215; 25 &#215; 25 cm) with normal air (21% oxygen, 78% nitrogen, and 1% other gasses) and represented the control group. The other section was placed in an airtight O<sub>3</sub> chamber made of sturdy Tritan plastic with a lockable lid (L &#215; W &#215; H = 30 &#215; 25 &#215; 25 cm), with an O<sub>3</sub> gas intake port to inject O<sub>3</sub> gas using an aeration stone (Diffuser) and disperse it uniformly throughout the air. An O<sub>3</sub> generator (600 mg/hour) was used to inject gas. The O<sub>3</sub> generator was fed with 1 liter per minute [flow rate (l pm)] of compressed air as feed gas. The gaseous O<sub>3</sub> (0.5 ppm) was diffused into the meat samples at two different exposure times (20 and 40 minutes) at a temperature of 3&#176;C&#8211;7&#176;C (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">supplementary Fig. 2</xref>). First, O<sub>3</sub> gas (0.5 ppm) was injected for 20 minutes at 3&#176;C&#8211;7&#176;C. The container was then kept at the same temperature for 24 hours before being compared with untreated samples that had also been stored at 3&#176;C&#8211;7&#176;C for 24 hours. In addition, the treated samples were exposed to O<sub>3</sub> gas (0.5 ppm) at 3&#176;C&#8211;7&#176;C for a further 20 minutes. The chamber containing the treated samples was kept at 3&#176;C&#8211;7&#176;C for a further 24 hours to compare the bacterial load of the treated and untreated samples (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). During this period, the effect of O<sub>3</sub> gas (0.5 ppm) on <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> and on the total bacterial population was constantly monitored. After every 24 hours, another meat sample was taken to assess the log CFU/g. The samples were weighed (1 g each), homogenized in a stomacher for 2 minutes, and then diluted with 9 ml of buffered peptone water. Plate Count Agar (Oxoid, CM0325B, UK) was used for the count of aerobes and anaerobes, and mCCDA-free agar was used for the total <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> count. Incubation was carried out continuously at 30&#176;C for 2 days. Dilutions were then performed according to the decimal system.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Arcobacter butzleri</italic> and total aerobic bacteria were counted by incubating the plates aerobically for 48 hours at 30&#176;C and 24 hours at 37&#176;C, respectively. To perform the enumeration of anaerobic bacteria, Oxoid&#8482; AnaeroGen<sup>&#8482;</sup> 2.5 l Sachet (Oxoid, AN0025A, UK) was used in an anaerobic jar (Oxoid, AG25, UK) under anaerobic conditions. The plates were incubated at 37&#176;C for a duration of 24 hours. The total count of aerobic and anaerobic bacteria, as well as <italic toggle="yes">Arcobacter butzleri</italic>, was determined using the standard plating procedure.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>The Statistical Analysis System (<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">SAS, 2018</xref>) program, version 9, 6th edition (N.C., USA), was employed to ascertain the influence of diverse factors on the study parameters. In this research, the Least Significant Difference (LSD) test, part of the Analysis of Variance, was employed for mean comparisons (<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">SAS, 2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>The Middle Technical University/Medical Ethics Committee/Ethics Committee Reference Number: MEC: 17 granted approval for this research on October 1, 2023. No humans or animals were employed in this investigation. Fresh meat samples were purchased from various supermarkets and vendor shops. All processes were carried out in compliance with the applicable norms and legislation.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>In this study, the efficacy of gaseous O<sub>3</sub> against the bacterial load in meat preserved at a refrigerated temperature was investigated. The results (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref> and <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) showed that the initial concentrations of <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> in the inoculated chicken and cattle meat samples were 3.72 and 4.05 log CFU/g, respectively. When the inoculated chicken and cattle meat samples were exposed to gaseous O<sub>3</sub> (0.5 ppm) for 20 minutes, the number of <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> decreased by 0.75 and 0.68 log CFU/g, respectively, after being kept at 3&#176;C&#8211;7&#176;C for 24 hours. Compared to samples not exposed to O<sub>3</sub>, high counts of <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> were detected. In addition, this study showed that the total count of aerobic and anaerobic bacteria decreased in chicken and beef meat samples treated with O<sub>3</sub> gas for 20 minutes during 24 hours of storage at 3&#176;C&#8211;7&#176;C compared to the untreated samples. The changes in chicken meat were also smaller: the number of aerobic and anaerobic bacteria decreased to only 1.13 log CFU/g and 0.7, respectively. The chicken meat was then kept at a refrigeration temperature of 3&#176;C&#8211;7&#176;C for a further day. The observations indicated a decrease in <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic>, aerobic and anaerobic bacteria (CFU/g) by 0.5, 0.32, and 0.29, respectively, compared to the samples used in the control group. Cattle meat showed a similar trend, with a reported lower aerobic bacterial count of 0.59 log CFU/g. Compared to the non-O<sub>3</sub>-exposed samples, a statistically significant decrease (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.01) in bacterial counts was observed in the O<sub>3</sub>-exposed samples. As shown in <xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Tables 3</xref> and <xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, the non-inoculated meat samples showed no growth of <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> (zero growth). Furthermore, after the non-inoculated samples were exposed to gaseous O<sub>3</sub> at 3&#176;C&#8211;7&#176;C for 48 hours, there was a decrease of 0.53 log CFU/g in aerobic bacteria and 0.98 log CFU/g in anaerobic bacteria. The total count number of aerobic and anaerobic bacteria decreased by 0.65 and 0.8 log CFU/g, respectively, in the non-inoculated cattle meat samples that were exposed to O<sub>3</sub> in the same way. These samples showed a similar trend (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). The number of aerobic and anaerobic bacteria decreased significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.01) in the samples that were exposed to O<sub>3</sub> compared with the samples that were not exposed to O<sub>3</sub> (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Tables 3</xref> and <xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>A flow diagram for the study design.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2794-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Researchers have examined the effects of gaseous and liquid O<sub>3</sub> on many microorganisms, such as viruses, protozoa, bacterial and fungal spores, and even coronaviruses, on food (<xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">Xue <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). Consumers in Iraq could be at risk of infection with <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic>, due to the recent detection of this bacterium in both fresh and chilled retail meat sold in the country (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Jasim <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan, 2021</xref>). Therefore, this bacterium was introduced into meat samples to evaluate the effects of O<sub>3</sub> gas at temperatures between 3&#176;C and 7&#176;C over a 48-hour storage period.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Effect of O<sub>3</sub> gas on the <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic>, total aerobic and anaerobic bacterial counts (log CFU/g) of inoculated chicken meat with <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> during storage at 3&#176;C&#8211;7&#176;C.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Bacteria</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Ozone treatment</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Exposure time to gaseous ozone</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">LSD value<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 minutes/ 1 day</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 minutes/ 2 day</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Arcobacter butzleri</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chicken + ozone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.72 &#177; 0.19 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97 &#177; 0.17 <sup>Bb</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47 &#177; 0.17 <sup>B c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.308 **<break/>(0.0019)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chicken</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.72 &#177; 0.19 <sup>A b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.57 &#177; 0.33 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.57 &#177; 0.25 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.392 **<break/>(0.0063)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD value<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.327 NS<break/>(1.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.455 **<break/>(0.0001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.370 **<break/>(0.0001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">---</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Aerobic bacteria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chicken+ ozone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10 &#177; 0.18 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97 &#177; 0.17 <sup>Bb</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65 &#177; 0.13 <sup>Bb</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.533 **<break/>(0.0001)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chicken</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10 &#177; 0.18 <sup>A b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.47 &#177; 0.12 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.55 &#177; 0.19 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.317 *<break/>(0.0374)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD value<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.315 NS<break/>(1.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.259 **<break/>(0.0001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.282 **<break/>(0.0001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">---</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Anaerobic bacteria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chicken+ ozone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.42 &#177; 0.17 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.72 &#177; 0.17 <sup>Bb</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43 &#177; 0.22 <sup>Bb</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.402 **<break/>(0.0001)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chicken</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.42 &#177; 0.17 <sup>A b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75 &#177; 0.13 <sup>A b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.85 &#177; 0.13 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.351 *<break/>(0.0446)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD value<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.295 NS<break/>(1.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.261 **<break/>(0.0001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.314 **<break/>(0.0001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">---</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Means with different capital letters in the same column and small letters in the same row are significantly different; * (<italic toggle="yes">p </italic>&#8804; 0.05); ** (<italic toggle="yes">p </italic>&#8804; 0.01). </p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Data in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Tables (1</xref> and <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) indicated that the exposure of meat samples infected with <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> to O<sub>3</sub> gas (0.5 ppm) for 20 minutes at 3&#176;C&#8211;7&#176;C resulted in a strong reduction (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.01) of bacterial counts. Moreover, a significant decrease in aerobic and anaerobic counts in chicken meat was observed, with aerobic counts at 1.13 log CFU/g and the anaerobic counts at 0.7 log CFU/g. This study confirmed the findings of the previously mentioned studies (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Cho <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Muhlisin <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Khudhir and Mahdi, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Megahed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">Megahed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Gim&#233;nez <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>). <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Balamatsia <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2007)</xref> and <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Capita <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2013)</xref>, whose research included microbial counts by type of meat at various stages of the distribution chain, found that total bacterial loads in poultry meat at the start of the storage period ranged from 4.9 to 5.66 log CFU/g. In the study by <xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">Rani <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2023)</xref>, the most negative result was reported, the mean &#177; SE was only 7.7 &#177; 0.17 log of total bacterial count CFU/cm<sup>2</sup> in beef during high capacity abatements. Therefore, the findings of this study were also of crucial importance for the improvement of public health and for sustainable improvement of quality and safety of food products.</p><p>Due to its high reactivity and lack of toxic residues, O<sub>3</sub> was actively studied for its bactericidal effect against foodborne pathogens. <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Cho <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2014)</xref> conducted some studies of this type and demonstrated that the growth of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O157:H7 and some other anaerobic and aerobic bacteria was significantly inhibited (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.05) when ground beef samples were exposed to an O<sub>3</sub> concentration of 10 &#215; 10<sup>-6</sup> kg O3/hour for 3 days at 4&#176;C.</p><p><xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Muhlisin <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2016)</xref> also explored the bactericidal properties of O<sub>3</sub> in a gaseous state with regard to the total bacterial count of the chicken meat. Anaerobic and aerobic bacterial growth as well as coliform bacilli growth was inhibited, when chicken meat was treated with O<sub>3</sub> (temperature 4&#176;C &#177; 1&#176;C) at a concentration of 10 mg O<sub>3</sub>/m<sup>3</sup>/hour over a period of 4 days.</p><p>In another study conducted by <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Khudhir and Mahdi (2017)</xref>, there was a very significant effect of antimicrobial influence on microbial counts (reduction as much as 6 logs) after aqueous O<sub>3</sub> exposure of 0.5 parts per million for 20 minutes on bovine and ovine soft cheeses that were locally produced.</p><p><xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Megahed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2018)</xref> studied the efficacy of gaseous and aqueous O<sub>3</sub> in eliminating pathogens derived from dairy cow dung that had infected various farm surfaces under varying operating circumstances. The researchers found that 4 minutes of gaseous O<sub>3</sub> at 9 ppm inactivated 3.3 log of the pathogens detected in the manure. Additionally, they discovered that on rather rough surfaces, aqueous O<sub>3</sub> at 9 ppm for 2 minutes may be an effective way to eliminate manure-based pathogens to a safe level. In contrast, on smooth surfaces, it was determined to be 4 ppm. Furthermore, <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan (2018)</xref> found that after half an hour of exposure to 0.5 ppm O<sub>3</sub> in water, the bacterial count of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> in infected chicken meat decreased by up to 2 logs.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Effect of O<sub>3</sub> gas on the <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic>, total aerobic and anaerobic bacterial counts (log CFU/g) of inoculated cattle meat with <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> during storage at 3&#176;C&#8211;7&#176;C.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Bacteria</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Ozone treatment</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Exposure time to gaseous ozone</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">LSD value<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 minutes/ 1 day</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 minutes/ 2 day</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Arcobacter butzleri</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beef + ozone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.05 &#177; 0.35 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.37 &#177; 0.17 <sup>Bb</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.02 &#177; 0.25 <sup>Bb</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.418 **<break/>(0.0001)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beef</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.05 &#177; 0.35 <sup>Ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.05 &#177; 0.23 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2 &#177; 0.18 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.549 **<break/>(0.0001)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD value<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.607 NS<break/>(1.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.358 **<break/>(0.0001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.379 **<break/>(0.0001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">---</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Aerobic bacteria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beef + ozone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.35 &#177;0.13 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.82 &#177; 0.17 <sup>Bb</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.23 &#177; 0.17 <sup>Bc</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.502 **<break/>(0.0001)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beef</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.35 &#177;0.13 <sup>Ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.02 &#177; 0.22 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.17 &#177; 0.20 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.542 **<break/>(0.0001)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD value<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.223 NS<break/>(1.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.342 **<break/>(0.0001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.327 **<break/>(0.0001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">---</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Anaerobic bacteria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beef + ozone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.72 &#177;0.27 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.17 &#177; 0.17 <sup>Bb</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.97 &#177; 0.17 <sup>Bb</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.569 **<break/>(0.0001)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beef</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.72 &#177;0.27 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.97 &#177; 0.22 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.05 &#177; 0.19 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.344 NS<break/>(0.078</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD value<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.476 NS<break/>(1.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.342 **<break/>(0.0012)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.314 **<break/>(0.0002)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">---</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Means with different capital letters in the same column and small letters in the same row are significantly different; ** (<italic toggle="yes">p </italic>&#8804; 0.01).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Effect of O<sub>3</sub> gas on the total aerobic and anaerobic bacterial counts (log CFU/g) of non-inoculated chicken meat with <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> during storage at 3&#176;C&#8211;7&#176;C.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Bacteria</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Ozone treatment</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Exposure time to gaseous ozone</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">LSD value<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 minutes/ 1 day</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 minutes/ 2 day</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Aerobic bacteria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chicken+ ozone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50 &#177; 0.18<sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.22 &#177; 0.09 <sup>Bab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97 &#177; 0.17 <sup>Bb</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.397 **<break/>(0.0001)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chicken</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50 &#177; 0.18<sup>Ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75 &#177; 0.22<sup>Aab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.87 &#177; 0.22 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.359*<break/>(0.0272)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD value<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.315 NS<break/>(1.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.295 **<break/>(0.0039)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.342 **<break/>(0.0007)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">---</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Anaerobic bacteria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chicken+ ozone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45 &#177; 0.13<sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77 &#177; 0.20 <sup>Bb</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47 &#177; 0.25 <sup>Bb</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.438 **<break/>(0.0001)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chicken</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45 &#177; 0.13<sup>Ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70 &#177; 0.08<sup>Aab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.85 &#177; 0.13 <sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.355 *<break/>(0.0381)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD value<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.223 NS<break/>(1.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.271 **<break/>(0.0002)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.344 **<break/>(0.0001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">---</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Means with different capital letters in the same column and small letters in the same row are significantly different; * (<italic toggle="yes">p </italic>&#8804; 0.05); ** (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.01).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><title>Effect of O<sub>3</sub> gas on the total aerobic and anaerobic bacteria counts (log CFU/g) of non-inoculated cattle meat with <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> during storage at 3&#176;C&#8211;7&#176;C.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Bacteria</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Ozone treatment</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Exposure time to gaseous ozone</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">LSD value<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 minutes/ 1 day</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 minutes/ 2 day</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Aerobic bacteria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beef + ozone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.52 &#177; 0.27<sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.05 &#177; 0.13<sup>Bb</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.87 &#177; 0.22 <sup>Bb</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.455 **<break/>(0.0078)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beef</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.52 &#177; 0.27<sup>Ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.75 &#177; 0.31<sup>Aab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.02 &#177; 0.22<sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.407 **<break/>(0.0037)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD value<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.476 NS<break/>(1.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.412 **<break/>(0.0060)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.383 **<break/>(0.0003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">---</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Anaerobic bacteria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beef + ozone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.72 &#177; 0.17<sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.12 &#177; 0.17<sup>Bb</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.92 &#177; 0.17<sup>Bb</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.512 **<break/>(0.0001)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beef</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.72 &#177; 0.17<sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.97 &#177; 0.15<sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.12 &#177; 0.17<sup>Aa</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.315 NS<break/>(0.086)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LSD value<break/>(<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.296 NS<break/>(1.00)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.278 **<break/>(0.0003)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.296 **<break/>(0.0001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">---</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Means with different capital letters in the same column and small letters in the same row are significantly different; ** (<italic toggle="yes">p </italic>&#8804; 0.01).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>Log CFU/g reduction of bacterial counts in inoculated and non-inoculated samples after exposure to gaseous O<sub>3</sub>.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2794-g002.jpg"/></fig><p><xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">Megahed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2020)</xref> examined the microbial eradication capacity of aqueous mixtures of O<sub>3</sub> and lactic acid-O<sub>3</sub> (O<sub>3</sub>-LA) under various operation settings on chicken meat infected with a high load of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic>. Further studies showed that aqueous O<sub>3</sub> (8 ppm) had a lethal effect of 1.6 log/cm<sup>2</sup> when administered topically, while it was 1.2 log/cm<sup>2</sup> and 1 when injected subcutaneously.</p><p>Based on the observation obtained by <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Gim&#233;nez <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2021)</xref>, it was found that increasing the O<sub>3</sub> concentration greatly reduced the quantity of mesophilic bacteria, lactic acid bacteria, <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae</italic>, molds, and yeasts. In contrast, <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Botta <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2018)</xref> found in their study that the initial bacterial count did not change when beef samples were treated with aqueous O<sub>3</sub>.</p><p>According to <xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">Xue <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2023)</xref>, the inactivation of O<sub>3</sub> is a multiphase process that affects various cellular structures and content elements. O<sub>3</sub> primarily affects cell membranes, as it can filter intracellular material during stress (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Botta <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>). <xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">Sheng <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2018)</xref> noted that O<sub>3</sub> may be able to interfere with enzymes and prevent the growth and activity of bacteria. This could be the reason for the changes reported by <xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Aponte <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2018)</xref>, which are due to the permeability of the cell membrane. Another research showed that O<sub>3</sub> can cleave the DNA double bond by oxidation using of a highly reactive form of O<sub>2</sub> (O) (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Botta <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>).</p><p>There are a variety of internal and external variables that influence O<sub>3</sub> when applied to microbes. According to <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Crowe <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2012)</xref>, <xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">Shu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2021)</xref>, <xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2022)</xref>, and other authors, these include various different intrinsic microbiological factors such as the type of microorganisms, characteristic of food, the physiological conditions of the microbial cells, and the microorganisms that are naturally present or artificially introduced. Additionally, the intrinsic parameters of food include the type of food, surface properties, weight, and water activity (aW) (<xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">Xue <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Brodowska <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2018)</xref>, <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2020)</xref>, <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Liu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2021)</xref>, <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Bigi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2021)</xref>, and <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Onopiuk <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2021)</xref> have reported that the variables for O<sub>3</sub> therapy include temperature, contact time, O<sub>3</sub> concentration, and the application techniques were the most common stress factors. As a result, these variations may arise from differences between studies.</p><p><xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref> and <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> demonstrate that following preservation at 3&#176;C&#8211;7&#176;C for an additional 24 hours, an extension of the duration of exposure to 20 minutes resulted in a greater reduction compared with the controls.</p><p>Other studies also showed that with increased exposure to O<sub>3</sub>, its efficiency against bacteria becomes higher. This was evident from the works of <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan (2018)</xref>; <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2020)</xref>; <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Onopiuk <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2021)</xref>; <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Aslam <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2021)</xref>; and <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Kanaan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2024b)</xref>. However, this increase in effects seems to reach an asymptote beyond which further increases are not possible to achieve, probably due to structures within food or even due to non-viable microbial cells assumed to protect against the oxidative action of O<sub>3</sub> (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Ayranci <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>).</p><p>The result also showed that the bacterial inhibition rate was significantly lower when an additional day of cooling was applied. Such an effect seems to be related to the limitations of O<sub>3</sub> exposure, as the O<sub>3</sub> exposure could only remove superficial bacterial contamination.</p><p><xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Tables 3</xref> and <xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, and <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> confirm that, with time, the counts of total aerobic and anaerobic bacteria were lower in the case of inoculated samples than in the case of non-inoculated samples. Furthermore, the study demonstrated that exposure to O<sub>3</sub> could in some way inhibit or retard the germs&#8217; growth in a cold environment. According to this perspective, O<sub>3</sub> treatment acts as an antimicrobial agent for meat products kept or stored at a cold temperature to eliminate surface bacterial infection. <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">C&#225;rdenas <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2011)</xref> previously studied the application of gaseous O<sub>3</sub> treatment on bacterial counts on meats. Total and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> bacterial counts decreased by 0.5 log to attain 0 log, while the count of <italic toggle="yes">L. monocytogenes</italic>, injected at 10<sup>2</sup> CFU/g tissue under cold storage conditions, fell below the limit of detection. Another study conducted by <xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Muhlisin <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2016)</xref> discovered that gaseous O<sub>3</sub> applied to the beef samples did not destroy the internal form of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">O157:H7</italic>, but only eliminated the external contamination by this bacterium. A further piece of data supporting the effectiveness of O<sub>3</sub> treatment during immersion chilling in improving the microbiological protection of beef comes from the finding of <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Kalchayanand <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2019)</xref> found that aqueous O<sub>3</sub> sprays cool significantly decreased the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">O157:H7</italic> on raw beef surfaces by 1.46 log. Studies that have used O<sub>3</sub> to reduce bacterial contamination in meat have generally shown that the surface area of ozonated meat is the primary target of O<sub>3</sub>&#8217;s antibacterial activity. The most frequent and common cause of contamination in meat is surface contamination from pathogenic microorganisms. This is an alarming situation for both health and food safety. In addition to that, O<sub>3</sub> has been suggested as a more appropriate antibacterial agent that can improve the shelf life of meat and meat products stored in the refrigerator.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>From this investigation, it was found that gaseous O<sub>3</sub> of 0.5 ppm was effective in inhibiting the growth of <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> in meat samples infected with <italic toggle="yes">A. butzleri</italic> for the first and second days of storage. In addition, gaseous O<sub>3</sub> caused a significant reduction of bacterial populations including both aerobic and anaerobic bacteria, and greater efficacy was demonstrated for the treatment as the time of the exposure period at the same dosage was increased. In terms of public health, these results are important. The cost-effective and effective antibacterial O<sub>3</sub>-preserving treatments for food products have a number of advantages over others. Application of O<sub>3</sub> is more efficient and energy saving in the food industry because O<sub>3</sub> can be dissolved in much colder water, and without chemical residues, waste disposal and final rinsing are cheaper. This method improves food safety, quality, and shelf life, decreasing decomposition and spoiling losses and saving money. Additional research using different exposure times and various O<sub>3</sub> concentrations is necessary to elucidate the impact of O<sub>3</sub> on spoilage microorganisms and meat borne pathogens to substantiate its use and scalability in industrial environments.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The author thanks the Technical Institute of Suwaria for letting her use its microbiology lab. The author would like to express her gratitude to Assist. Prof. Dr. Zuhair Al-Chalabi for his guidance and support. She would like to extend her gratitude to Prof. Dr. Nasr Noori Al-Anbari, College of Agriculture Engineering Sciences, University of Baghdad, for his statistical analysis support. She is also very grateful to Dr. Morteza Saki, Ahvaz Jundishapur University of Medical Sciences for his assistance in editing the English language.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>According to what the author has claimed, there are no conflicting interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>No funding or contributions supported this research.</p></sec><sec><title>Author&#8217;s Contributions</title><p>MHGK was in charge of everything involved in this work, from the research planning to the final revisions of the publication. The study&#8217;s design, sample collection, laboratory work, analysis, and writing are all included. The author evaluated and agreed to the final version of the manuscript before and during the submission of her paper.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data are provided in the manuscript.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Aponte, M., Anastasio, A., Marrone, R., Mercogliano, R., Peruzy, M.F. and Murru, N. 2018. Impact of gaseous ozone coupled to passive refrigeration system to maximize shelf-life and quality of four different fresh fish products. LWT. 93, 412&#8211;419.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Aslam, R., Alam, M.S., Singh, S. and Kumar, S. 2021. Aqueous ozone sanitization of whole peeled onion: process optimization and evaluation of keeping quality during refrigerated storage. LWT. 151, 112183.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Ayranci, U.G., Ozunlu, O., Ergezer, H. and Karaca, H. 2020. Effects of ozone treatment on microbiological quality and physicochemical properties of turkey breast meat. Ozone: Sci. Eng. 42(1), 95&#8211;103.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Balamatsia, C.C., Patsias, A., Kontominas, M.G. and Savvaidis, I.N. 2007. Possible role of volatile amines as quality-indicating metabolites in modified atmosphere-packaged chicken fillets: correlation with microbiological and sensory attributes. Food Chem. 104(4), 1622&#8211;1628.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Bigi, F., Haghighi, H., Quartieri, A., De Leo, R. and Pulvirenti, A. 2021. Impact of low-dose gaseous ozone treatment to reduce the growth of <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> broth cultures of foodborne pathogenic/spoilage bacteria in a food storage cold chamber. J. Food Saf. 41(3), e12892.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Botta, C., Ferrocino, I., Cavallero, M.C., Riva, S., Giordano, M. and Cocolin, L. 2018. Potentially active spoilage bacteria community during the storage of vacuum packaged beefsteaks treated with aqueous ozone and electrolyzed water. Int. J. Food Microbiol. 266, 337&#8211;345.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2017.10.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29033074</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Bridges, D.F., Rane, B. and Wu, V.C. 2018. The effectiveness of closed-circulation gaseous chlorine dioxide or ozone treatment against bacterial pathogens on produce. Food Control. 91, 261&#8211;267.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Brodowska, A.J., Nowak, A. and &#346;migielski, K. 2018. Ozone in the food industry: principles of ozone treatment, mechanisms of action, and applications: an overview. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr.58(13), 2176&#8211;2201.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/10408398.2017.1308313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28394634</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Capita, R., &#193;lvarez-Fern&#225;ndez, E., Fern&#225;ndez-Buelta, E., Manteca, J. and Alonso-Calleja, C. 2013. Decontamination treatments can increase the prevalence of resistance to antibiotics of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> naturally present on poultry. Food Microbiol. 34(1), 112&#8211;117.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.fm.2012.11.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23498186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>C&#225;rdenas, F.C., Andr&#233;s, S., Giannuzzi, L. and Zaritzky, N. 2011. Antimicrobial action and effects on beef quality attributes of a gaseous ozone treatment at refrigeration temperatures. Food Control. 22(8), 1442&#8211;1447.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Chacha, J.S., Zhang, L., Ofoedu, C.E., Suleiman, R.A., Dotto, J.M., Roobab, U., Agunbiade, A.O., Duguma, H.T., Mkojera, B.T., Hossaini, S.M. and Rasaq, W.A. 2021. Revisiting non-thermal food processing and preservation methods action mechanisms, pros and cons: a technological update (2016&#8211;2021). Foods. 10(6), 1430.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/foods10061430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8234293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34203089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Chen, C., Zhang, H., Zhang, X., Dong, C., Xue, W. and Xu, W. 2020. The effect of different doses of ozone treatments on the postharvest quality and biodiversity of cantaloupes. Postharvest Biol. Technol.163, 111124.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Chieffi, D., Fanelli, F. and Fusco, V. 2020. <italic toggle="yes">Arcobacter butzleri</italic>: up-to-date taxonomy, ecology, and pathogenicity of an emerging pathogen. Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf. 19, 2071&#8211;2109.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/1541-4337.12577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33337088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Cho, Y., Choi, J.H., Hahn, T.W. and Lee, S.K. 2014. Effect of gaseous ozone exposure on the bacteria counts and oxidative properties of ground hanwoo beef at refrigeration temperature. Korean J. Food Sci. An. 34(4), 525.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5851/kosfa.2014.34.4.525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4662157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26761291</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Crowe, K.M., Skonberg, D., Bushway, A. and Baxter, S. 2012. Application of ozone sprays as a strategy to improve the microbial safety and quality of salmon fillets. Food Control. 25(2), 464&#8211;468.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Font-i-Furnols, M. 2023. Meat consumption, sustainability and alternatives: an overview of motives and barriers. Foods. 12(11), 2144.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/foods12112144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10252260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37297389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Gil, M.I. Mar&#237;n, A., Andujar, S. and Allende, A. 2016. Should chlorate residues be of concern in fresh-cut salads? Food Control. 60, 416&#8211;421.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Gim&#233;nez, B., Graiver, N., Giannuzzi, L. and Zaritzky, N. 2021. Treatment of beef with gaseous ozone: physicochemical aspects and antimicrobial effects on heterotrophic microflora and <italic toggle="yes">Listeria monocytogenes</italic>. Food Control. 121, 107602.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Jasim, S.A., Al-Abodi, H.R. and Ali, W.S. 2021. Resistance rate and novel virulence factor determinants of <italic toggle="yes">Arcobacter</italic> spp., from cattle fresh meat products from Iraq. Microb. Pathog<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> 152(1), 104649.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.micpath.2020.104649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33249163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Jiang, H., Liu, Z. and Wang, S. 2018. Microwave processing: effects and impacts on food components. Crit. Rev. Food Sci. Nutr. 58(14), 2476&#8211;2489.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/10408398.2017.1319322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28613917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Jim&#233;nez-Guerra, G., Moreno-Torres, I.C., Moldovan, T.D., Navarro-Mar&#237;, J.M. and Guti&#233;rrez-Fern&#225;ndez, J. 2020. <italic toggle="yes">Arcobacter butzleri</italic> and intestinal colonization. REV ESP QUIM<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> 33(1), 73.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.37201/req/060.2019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6987627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31895525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Kalchayanand, N., Worlie, D. and Wheeler, T. 2019. A novel aqueous ozone treatment as a spray chill intervention against <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> O157: H7 on surfaces of fresh beef. J. Food Prot. 82 (11), 1874&#8211;1878.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-19-093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31622163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Kanaan, M.H. 2018. Antibacterial effect of ozonated water against methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> contaminating chicken meat in Wasit Province, Iraq. Vet. World. 11(10), 1445&#8211;1453.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14202/vetworld.2018.1445-1453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6247883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30532500</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Kanaan, M.H. 2021. Prevalence, resistance to antimicrobials, and antibiotypes of <italic toggle="yes">Arcobacter</italic> species recovered from retail meat in Wasit marketplaces in Iraq. Int. J. One Health. 7(1), 142&#8211;150.Kanaan, M.H.G. 2023. Prevalence and antimicrobial resistance of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enterica</italic> serovars Enteritidis and Typhimurium isolated from retail chicken meat in Wasit markets, Iraq. Vet. World. 16(3), 455&#8211;463.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14202/vetworld.2023.455-463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10082727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37041841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Kanaan, M.H. 2024. Effect of biofilm formation in a hostile oxidative stress environment on the survival of <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic> recovered from poultry in Iraqi markets. Vet. World. 17(1), 136&#8211;142.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14202/vetworld.2024.136-142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10884572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38406363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Kanaan, M. and Abdullah, S. 2021. Evaluation of aqueous ozone as a method to combat multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> tainting cattle meat sold in Wasit marketplaces. Mansoura Vet. Med. J. 22(3), 117&#8211;123.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Kanaan, M.H.G. and Al-Isawi, A.J.O. 2019. Prevalence of methicillin or multiple drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> in cattle meat marketed in Wasit province. Biochem. Cell. Arch. 19(1), 495&#8211;502.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Kanaan, M.H.G., Al-Isawi, A.J.O. and Mohammed, F.A. 2022b. Antimicrobial resistance and antibiogram of thermotolerant campylobacter recovered from poultry meat in Baghdad markets, Iraq. Arch. Razi. Inst. 77(1), 249&#8211;255.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.22092/ARI.2021.356362.1828</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9288606</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35891742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Kanaan, M.H.G., Al-Shadeedi, S.M., Al-Massody, A.J. and Ghasemian, A. 2020. Drug resistance and virulence traits of <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> from Turkey and chicken raw meat. Comp. Immunol. Microbiol. Infect. Dis. 70, 101451.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cimid.2020.101451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32171936</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Kanaan, M.H.G., Khalil, Z.K., Khashan, H.T. and Ghasemian, A. 2022a. Occurrence of virulence factors and carbapenemase genes in <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Enteritidis isolated from chicken meat and egg samples in Iraq. BMC Microbiol. 22(1), 1&#8211;8.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12866-022-02696-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9682753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36418940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Kanaan, M.H. G. and Khashan, H.T. 2022. Molecular typing, virulence traits and risk factors of pandrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> spread in intensive care unit centers of Baghdad city, Iraq. Rev. Med. Microbiol. 33(1), 51&#8211;55.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Kanaan, M.H.G. and Mohammed, F.A. 2020. Antimicrobial resistance of <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic><italic toggle="yes">jejuni</italic> from poultry meat in local markets of Iraq. Plant Arch. 20(Suppl. 1), 410&#8211;415.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Kanaan, M.H.G., Mohammed, F.A. and Abdullah, S.S. 2024a. The effectiveness of aqueous ozone on residual chlorination by products in treated chicken meat. IOP Publishing. Conf. Ser. Earth Environ. Sci. 1371(6), 062036.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Kanaan, M.H.G., Razak, F.S.A. and Abdullah, S.S. 2024b. Effect of ozone treatment on thermo tolerant <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> contaminated poultry products retailed at Baghdad markets, Iraq. Egypt. J. Nutr. 39(2), 1&#8211;10.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Kanaan, M.H.G. and Tarek, AM. 2022. Innovative modern bio-preservation module of meat by lytic bacteriophages against emergent contaminants. Open Vet. J. 12(6), 1018&#8211;1026.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5455/OVJ.2022.v12.i6.30</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9805770</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36650867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Khudhir, Z. and Mahdi, A.M. 2017. The efficacy of ozonated water on the microbial quality of locally produced soft cheese in Baghdad. Int. J. Sci. Res. 6(10), 338&#8211;387.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Liu, C., Chen, C., Jiang, A., Zhang, Y., Zhao, Q. and Hu, W. 2021. Effects of aqueous ozone treatment on microbial growth, quality, and pesticide residue of fresh-cut cabbage. Food Sci. Nutr<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> 9(1), 52&#8211;61.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/fsn3.1870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7802563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33473270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Liu, Z., Shaposhnikov, M., Zhuang, S., Tu, T., Wang, H. and Wang, L. 2023. Growth and survival of common spoilage and pathogenic bacteria in ground beef and plant-based meat analogues. Food Res. Int. 164, 112408.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.foodres.2022.112408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36737989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Liu, Q., Zhang, R., Xue, H., Bi, Y., Li, L., Zhang, Q., Kouasseu, C.J., Nan, M. and Prusky, D. 2022. Ozone controls potato dry rot development and diacetoxyscirpenol accumulation by targeting the cell membrane and affecting the growth of <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium sulphureus</italic>. Pysiol. Mol. Plant 118, 101785.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Megahed, A., Aldridge, B. and Lowe, J. 2018. The microbial killing capacity of aqueous and gaseous ozone on different surfaces contaminated with dairy cattle manure. PLoS One. 13(5), e0196555.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0196555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5951574</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29758045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Megahed, A., Aldridge, B. and Lowe, J. 2020. Antimicrobial efficacy of aqueous ozone and ozone&#8211;lactic acid blend on <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic>-contaminated chicken drumsticks using multiple sequential soaking and spraying approaches. Front. Microbiol. 11, 593911.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmicb.2020.593911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7768038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33381091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Mohammed, F.A., Kanaan, M.H.G. and Tarek, A.M. 2022. Assessment of the effect of aqueous ozone treatment on the sensory attributes of retail meat in the Iraqi Wasit governorate. Rev. Electron. Vet<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> 23(3), 28&#8211;38.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Muhlisin, M., Utama, D.T., Lee, J.H., Choi, J.H. and Lee, S.K. 2016. Effects of gaseous ozone exposure on bacterial counts and oxidative properties in chicken and duck breast meat. Korean J. Food Sci. Anim. Resour. 36(3), 405.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5851/kosfa.2016.36.3.405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4942556</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27433112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>OECD/FAO. 2021. OECD-FAO Agricultural Outlook 2021&#8211;2030, Paris, France: OECD Publishing.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Oliveira, M.G.X.D., Cunha, M.P.V., Moreno, L.Z., Saidenberg, A.B.S., Vieira, M.A.M., Gomes, T.A.T., Moreno, A.M. and Kn&#246;bl, T. 2023. Antimicrobial resistance and pathogenicity of <italic toggle="yes">Aliarcobacter</italic><italic toggle="yes">butzleri</italic> isolated from poultry meat. Antibiotics. 12(2), 282.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antibiotics12020282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9952011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36830193</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Oliveira, M.G.X.D., Gomes, V.T.D.M., Cunha, M.P.V., Moreno, L.Z., Moreno, A.M. and Kn&#246;bl, T. 2018. Genotypic characterization of <italic toggle="yes">Arcobacter</italic> spp. isolated from chicken meat in Brazil. Foodborne Pathog. Dis. 15(5), 293&#8211;299.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1089/fpd.2017.2368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29406776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Onopiuk, A., Szpicer, A., Wojtasik-Kalinowska, I., Wierzbicka, A. and P&#243;&#322;torak, A. 2021. Impact of ozonisation time and dose on health related and microbiological properties of rapanui tomatoes. Agriculture. 11(5), 428.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Pandiselvam, R., Kaavya, R., Jayanath, Y., Veenuttranon, K., Lueprasitsakul, P., Divya, V., Kothakota, A. and Ramesh, S.V. 2020. Ozone as a novel emerging technology for the dissipation of pesticide residues in foods&#8211;a review. Trends Food Sci. Technol. 97, 38&#8211;54.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Rani, Z.T., Mhlongo, L.C. and Hugo, A. 2023. Microbial profiles of meat at different stages of the distribution chain from the abattoir to retail outlets. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health. 20(3), 1986.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijerph20031986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9916197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36767353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Riesenberg, A., Fr&#246;mke, C., Stingl, K., Fe&#223;ler, A.T., G&#246;lz, G., Glocker, E.O., Kreienbrock, L., Klarmann, D., Werckenthin, C. and Schwarz, S. 2017. Antimicrobial susceptibility testing of <italic toggle="yes">Arcobacter butzleri</italic>: development and application of a new protocol for broth microdilution<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> J. Antimicrob. Chemother. 72(10), 2769&#8211;2774.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jac/dkx211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29091194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Roobab, U., Chacha, J.S., Abida, A., Rashid, S., Muhammad Madni, G., Lorenzo, J.M., Zeng, X.A. and Aadil, R.M. 2022. Emerging trends for nonthermal decontamination of raw and processed meat: ozonation, high-hydrostatic pressure and cold plasma. Foods. 11(15), 2173.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/foods11152173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9330470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35892759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Shange, N., Gouws, P. and Hoffman, L.C. 2019. <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Arcobacter</italic> species in food-producing animals: prevalence at primary production and during slaughter. World J. Microbiol. Biotechnol. 35, 1&#8211;16.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11274-019-2722-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31493271</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Sheng, L., Hanrahan, I., Sun, X., Taylor, M.H., Mendoza, M. and Zhu, M.J. 2018. Survival of <italic toggle="yes">Listeria innocua</italic> on Fuji apples under commercial cold storage with or without low dose continuous ozone gaseous. Food Microbiol. 76, 21&#8211;28.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.fm.2018.04.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30166144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Shu, X., Singh, M., Karampudi, N.B.R., Bridges, D.F., Kitazumi, A., Wu, VC. and De los Reyes, B. G. 2021. Responses of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Listeria monocytogenes</italic> to ozone treatment on non-host tomato: efficacy of intervention and evidence of induced acclimation. PLoS One. 16(10), e0256324.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0256324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8553054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34710139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Son, I., Englen, M.D., Berrang, M.E., Fedorka-Cray, P.J. and Harrison, M.A. 2007. Antimicrobial resistance of <italic toggle="yes">Arcobacter</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> from broiler carcasses. Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents. 29(4), 451&#8211;455.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2006.10.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17303391</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Stadler, D., Berthiller, F., Suman, M., Schuhmacher, R. and Krska, R. 2020. Novel analytical methods to study the fate of mycotoxins during thermal food processing. Anal. Bioanal. Chem. 412, 9&#8211;16.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00216-019-02101-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6989622</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31637463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Statistical Analysis System (SAS), 2018. User&#8217;s guide. Statistical. Version 9, 6th ed. Cary, NC: SAS. Inst. Inc..</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Xu, J., Zhang, P., Zhuang, L., Zhang, D., Qi, K., Dou, X., Wang, C. and Gong, J. 2019. Multiplex polymerase chain reaction to detect <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella serovars</italic> Indiana, Enteritidis, and Typhimurium in raw meat. J. Food Saf. 39(5), e12674.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Xue, W., Macleod, J. and Blaxland, J. 2023. The use of ozone technology to control microorganism growth, enhance food safety and extend shelf life: a promising food decontamination technology. Foods. 12(4), 814.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/foods12040814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9957223</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36832889</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec><title>Supplementary Materials</title><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>Ozone- CHEMets Visual Kit (K-7404 ozone analysis kit).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2794-g003.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig4" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>The diagram of the gaseous O<sub>3</sub> chamber.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2794-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec></back></article></pmc-articleset>