<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2846</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">openvetj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Veterinary Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2226-4485</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2218-6050</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tripoli</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11018443</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11018443.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11018443</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11018443</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38633169</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/OVJ.2024.v14.i1.11</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OVJ-14-116</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ameliorative effect of BIO-MOS<sup>&#174;</sup> as a dietary supplementation on growth performance, physiological response, oxidative status, and immunity-linked gene expression in Nile tilapia (<italic toggle="yes">Oreochromis niloticus</italic>) fingerlings challenged with <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moustafa</surname><given-names initials="EM">Eman M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farrag</surname><given-names initials="FA">Foad A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shukry</surname><given-names initials="M">Mustafa</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salah El-Din</surname><given-names initials="HM">Haguer M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Omar</surname><given-names initials="AA">Amira A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Fish Diseases and Management Department, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Kafrelsheikh University, Kafr El-Sheikh, Egypt</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Basic Veterinary Sciences, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Delta University for Science and Technology, Dakahlia, Egypt</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Animal Physiology Department, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Kafrelsheikh University, Kafr El-Sheikh, Egypt</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Eman Moustafa Moustafa. Fish Diseases and Management Department, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Kafrelsheikh University, Kafr El-Sheikh, Egypt. <email>emantarek2002@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">460065</issue-id><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>17</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-04-24 20:25:32.927"><day>24</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-116.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Mannanoligosaccharides (MOS) usage in fish production has drawn more attention because of their positive benefits on disease resistance and fish performance.</p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>The ongoing research was executed to assess the potential advantages of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> dietary supplementation regarding the growth outcomes, physiological response, oxidative biomarkers, and immunity-linked gene expression in Nile tilapia (<italic toggle="yes">Oreochromis niloticus</italic>) fingerlings exposed to bacterial infection with <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">hydrophila</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>Four experimental diets were developed using a 30% protein baseline diet, with Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> added at variable levels; 0.0, 0.5, 1, and 2 g/kg, respectively. 240 healthy Nile tilapia fingerlings were split into 4 groups at random and assigned to 12 glass aquariums (three replicates of 20 fish/treatment). Diets were admitted at a 3% rate of fish biomass/aquarium for 8 weeks. Following the feeding trial, fish from every treatment were intraperitoneally injected with pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic>, and then observed for 15 days to record the survival rate percent (SR%) post challenge.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Results revealed significant improvement in growth performance, physiological response, immunological parameters (phagocytic index, phagocytic activity, and lysozyme), and antioxidant parameters [catalase, malondialdehyde, glutathione peroxidase (GSH-Px), and superoxide dismutase (SOD)] among Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> treated groups. Moreover, Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> increased the expression of tumor necrosis factor alpha and Interleukin 1&#946;, genes linked to the liver immune system. Growth-related genes (<italic toggle="yes">GHr</italic>), antioxidant-related genes (SOD and GSH-Px). In fish subjected to pathogens, dietary MOS supplementation could significantly lower oxidative stress, showing promise as a preventative supplement for Nile tilapia in place of antibiotics. On the other hand, Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> considerably improved each of the three intestinal morphological measures (villus width, villus length, and crypt depth), showing the best overall intestinal structure-improving impact. The challenge with<italic toggle="yes"> A. hydrophila</italic> caused marked degenerative alterations in the intestine, hepatopancreas, spleen, and posterior kidney of Nile tilapia, in the control group. However, lesion severity was greatly decreased and showed marked amelioration with an increased concentration of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>. The <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic>-challenged groups revealed a 100% SR% mainly among the Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> supplemented groups.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>It is recommended to enrich the Nile tilapia fingerlings diets with 2 g.kg<sup>&#8722;1</sup> of MOS for better results on the growth rate, physiological response, immunological response, and intestinal absorptive capacity.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila</italic></kwd><kwd>Immunity linked gene expression</kwd><kwd>Mannanoligosaccharide</kwd><kwd>Nile tilapia</kwd><kwd>Oxidative status</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>In respect to Egypt, aquaculture serves as the fundamental origin of fish yield. The majority of fish produced in Egypt is produced through aquaculture (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Adeleke <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>). It accounts for 77% of the entire production of fish, with pond-based aquaculture in the Nile Delta lakes providing 85% of this supply (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">Mehrim and Refaey, 2023</xref>). According to <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Al-Wakeel <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2019</xref>), Egypt produces roughly 73.8% of fish raised in Africa and ranks tenth globally in terms of overall cultured fish production with about a million tons produced annually (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">FAO, 2022</xref>).</p><p>As a result of the expanded element of escalation and cultivated regions (<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">Nguyen, 2008</xref>), tilapia is the dominant fish population in these ponds and records around 65% of complete aquaculture production (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Dickson <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Oreochromis niloticus</italic>, often known as Nile tilapia, continues to be a very important extensively cultivated fish species globally (<xref rid="ref60" ref-type="bibr">Prabu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>) because of their ease of reproduction, resilience to a variety of conditions and illness, quick development, and substantial consumer demand (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Elumalai <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>).</p><p><xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">Merrifield <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2010</xref>) investigated that nutrition plays a critical part in fish growth, development, and maintenance of fish welfare. Prior recently, the primary protein source in tilapia diets was fish meal. Numerous experiments were compelled to enhance the flourishing exhibition and lower the costs related to the production of cultivated tilapia due to the rising cost and unstable supply of this element. This was accomplished by using probiotics or prebiotics as secure supplements that do not affect consumers or leave residues in farmed fish (<xref rid="ref81" ref-type="bibr">Welker and Lim, 2011</xref>).</p><p>Prebiotics are dietary carbohydrates that cannot be digested and bypass the upper gastrointestinal tract. Prebiotics favorably affect the host by increasing the growth and/or initiating the metabolic process of favorable bacteria residing in the alimentary tract (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Manning and Gibson, 2004</xref>). Another way they modify the composition of gut bacteria is by altering the substrate type that is available to the existing gut microbiome (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">FAO, 2007</xref>).</p><p>Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>, a feed element generated from yeast cell walls (<italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>), is mannanoligosaccharides (MOS) where the primary constituents of yeast cell walls are mannans, glucans as well as chitin (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Hady <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). It improves digestion and gut health in animals by lessening local colonization of pathogenic microorganisms in the alimentary tract. As a prebiotic, MOS promotes healthy bacteria development in the gut, prevents harmful bacteria from conforming to and colonizing in the gut tract, and lessens the negative effects of commensal microflora metabolites which may be attributed to its binding affinity to the intestinal microorganisms through the gastrointestinal tract where the microorganisms are eliminated with excreta and the undigested MOS (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">Gainza and Romero, 2020</xref>).</p><p>The aquaculture sector still deals with a number of disease-related issues these days, most of which are brought on by bacteria, parasites, and viruses (<xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">Rigos <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>). The maintenance of fish immune competence and disease resistance while contending with rising feed prices and treatment constraints is one of the industry&#8217;s most significant concerns (<xref rid="ref85" ref-type="bibr">Yassien <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2022</xref>). Because MOS improve fish health and disease resistance, their application in fish farming has drawn great attention in the prior 10 years (<xref rid="ref80" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2022</xref>).</p><p>The goal of the ongoing research was to assess the potential advantages of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> nutritional supplementation on the state of oxidative stress, physiological response, development performance, and immunity-linked gene expression in Nile tilapia <italic toggle="yes">(O. niloticus)</italic> fingerlings rescued by bacterial infection with <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila.</italic></p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>The ongoing investigation was executed at the fish diseases laboratory, Fac. Vet. Med., Kafrelsheikh Univ., Egypt, for 12 weeks during 2021.</p><sec><title>Preparation of the experimental diet</title><p>A baseline (control) diet comprising fish meal, yellow maize, soybean meal, wheat bran, minerals mix, vitamins, and fish oil was prepared using commercial items (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The diet was designed to be both isonitrogenous and isocaloric, with 300 g/kg of crude protein and 12.6 MJ/kg of digestible energy. Using a feed processor, the dry materials were ground into small particles. In the case of the second, third, and fourth diets, Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> was incorporated in the baseline diet at 0.5, 1, and 2 g/kg, respectively, utilizing rice bran as a filler (Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> (Alltech Inc., Nicholasville, KY)). After thoroughly combining all components with a mixture of oil, water, dicalcium phosphate, minerals, and vitamins, the dough was extruded through a 2 to 3 mm die using a pelleting apparatus. The pellets were placed in a refrigerator set to 4&#8451; after air drying. To verify the nutritional profile of the test diets, a conventional procedure was employed (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">AOAC, 2012</xref>).</p><p>The commercial prebiotic product, Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> (Alltech Inc., Nicholasville, KY), is retrieved from <italic toggle="yes">S. cerevisiae</italic> outer cell wall and contains MOS. <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> as an entire yeast cell (Probiotic), its extract (MOS-prebiotic), and its pre-probiotic mixture (Synbiotic) act as immune modulators and engines of growth in farmed <italic toggle="yes">O. niloticus</italic> (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Dawson and Pirvulescu, 1999</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Experimental design</title><p>Healthy 240 Nile tilapia (<italic toggle="yes">O. niloticus</italic>) fingerlings (beginning body weight, 19.00 &#177; 3,00 g), got from a local private fish farm in Kafr El-Sheikh governorate, Egypt and transferred to Fish Diseases Laboratory, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Kafrelsheikh University. All gathered fish were housed in a fiberglass tank. Fish were acclimated to their basic food before the trial [having a level of 30% dietary protein (CP)] for 2 weeks.</p><p>Following the period of acclimatization, the fingerlings were split into 4 groups of 60, with each group being divided into 3 sets of 20 fingerlings a pond. The fingerlings were held in glass aquariums of 60 &#215; 30 &#215; 40 cm, that can hold 20 fish each, 70 liters of water, and a functional aeration system. First, Groups 1 (the control group) were given a commercial basal meal, while Groups 2 through 4 were given diets enriched with 0.5, 1, and 2 g/kg) of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>.</p><p>Feeding rates for the experimental diets were 3% of the total stocking biomass in each aquarium for a total of 8 weeks. Over the trial course, fish were weighed every fortnight, and the alteration in live body mass was used to adjust the feed levels. Fish wastes and excreta were removed by siphoning, and each aquarium&#8217;s water was gradually refilled with fresh, dechlorinated water to make up about half of its total volume.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Composition and chemical analysis of experimental diets (on a dry matter basis).</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Components</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Diets</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fish meal (72% CP)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean meal (45% CP)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">360</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">360</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">360</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">360</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat bran</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yellow corn</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rice bran</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">199</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">198</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fish oil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean oil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dicalcium phosphate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vitamins mixture<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minerals mixture<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carboxymethyl cellulose</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chemical analysis</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dry matter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crude protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ether extract</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total ash</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.31</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crude fiber</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.62</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogen-free extract</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gross energy (kcal/g)<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>(<sup>a</sup>): Vitamin premix (per kg of premix): thiamine, 2.5 g, pyridoxine, 2.0 g, riboflavin, 2.5 g, biotin, 0.3 g, inositol, 100.0 g, folic acid, 0.75 g, pantothenic acid, 100.0 g, para-aminobenzoic acid, 2.5 g, nicotinic acid, 10.0 g choline, 200.0 g, cyanocobalamine, 0.005 g, a-tocopherol acetate, 20.1 g, menadione, 2.0 g, retinol palmitate, 100,000 IU, cholecalciferol, 500,000 IU. (<sup>b</sup>): Mineral premix (g/kg of premix): CaHPO<sub>4</sub>.2H<sub>2</sub>O, 727.2, MgCO<sub>4</sub>.7H<sub>2</sub>O, 127.5, KCl 50.0, NaCl, 60.0, FeC<sub>6</sub>H<sub>5</sub>O<sub>7</sub>.3H<sub>2</sub>O, 25.0, ZnCO<sub>3</sub>, 5.5, MnCl<sub>2</sub>.4H<sub>2</sub>O, 2.5, Cu(OAc)<sub>2</sub>.H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.785, CoCl<sub>3</sub>.6H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.477, CaIO<sub>3</sub>.6H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.295, CrCl<sub>3</sub>.6H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.128, AlCl<sub>3</sub>.6H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.54, Na2SeO<sub>3</sub>, 0.03. (<sup>c</sup>): Gross energy (GE) was calculated from NRC (2011) as 5.65, 9.45, and 4.11 kcal/g for protein, lipid, and carbohydrates, respectively. </p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Two times a week, water quality attributes were checked utilizing a water analysis instrument (Lamotte device, USA). Temperature varied between (24&#8451;&#8211;27&#8451;), dissolved oxygen 6.5 &#177; 0.5 mg l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, pH 7.1 &#177; 0.8, EC 219 &#177; 2 &#956; mho/cm, ammonia amended to the standard allowable limits (&#706;0.1 mg total ammonia) and during the experimental period, the day and night photoperiods were 12:12 hours. Water quality assessments were conducted in accordance with <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">APHA (1989</xref>) (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Determination of fish growth parameters</title><p>After 8 weeks, an electronic balance was used to weigh each fish (20 fish per replicate).</p><p>All growth parameters; average daily gain (ADG), specific growth rate (SGR), total weight gain, protein efficiency ratio, feed conversion ratio (FCR), and survival rate percent (SR%) were computed utilizing techniques stated by <xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">Magouz <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2019</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Hematological and biochemical parameters</title><p>All fish were starved 24 hours before the final sampling. For hematological examination, a dose of 100 mg/l of tricaine methane sulfonate was used to anesthetize fish to avoid stress during sampling (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Dawood <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). Nine fishes were randomly sampled and weighed from every group (3 fishes/every replicate). Blood was collected, utilizing syringes with a 5 ml gauge, from the caudal blood vessels. Blood samples were split in half. Half of the blood was used right away for differential leukocyte count and hematological analysis after being stored in tubes that had been EDTA-heparinized. According to <xref rid="ref79" ref-type="bibr">Urbinate and Carneiro (2006</xref>), blood samples taken from three to four fish were combined due to the tiny size of the fish. White blood cells (WBCs &#215; 10<sup>3</sup>/mm), red blood cells (RBCs &#215; 10<sup>6</sup>/mm), hemoglobin concentration (Hb g/dl), packed cell volume (PCV%), mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration (MCHC), and mean corpuscular volume (MCV) were determined as stated by <xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">Magouz <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2019</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Water quality parameters measured in the current study.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> 0.5%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> 1%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> 2%</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0.5 g/kg Feed)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1 g/kg Feed)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2 g/kg Feed)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salinity (ppt)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature (&#176;C)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.3 &#177; 0.32<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.9 &#177; 0.09<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.3 &#177; 0.03<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.9 &#177; 0.02<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8 &#177; 0.01<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.9 &#177; 0.62<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.02 &#177; 0.31<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.02 &#177; 0.48<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dissolved oxygen (mg/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 &#177; 0.81<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4 &#177; 0.33<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8 &#177; 0.32<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1 &#177; 0.23<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NH3 (mg/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 &#177; 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 &#177; 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 &#177; 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 &#177; 0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NH4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25 &#177; 0.32<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38 &#177; 0.48<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39 &#177; 0.81<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41 &#177; 0.73<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NO<sub>2</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042 &#177; 0.43<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037 &#177; 0.22<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040 &#177; 0.52<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046 &#177; 0.62<sup>a</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>(T1): control with non-prebiotic diet; (T2): 0.5 % Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> diet; (T3): 1% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> diet; (T4): 2% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> diet.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To obtain serum, the leftover blood was stored in non-heparinized tubes. Taken samples underwent centrifugation (SCILOGEX, Model: DM0412, USA) at 1,008 &#215; g/15 minutes at 4&#8451; after 2 hours. The serum was then separated and stored at &#8722;20&#8451; for additional analysis. A thin blood film was created, let to air dry, fixed for 3&#8211;5 minutes with methanol, and then stained for 8&#8211;10 minutes with Giemsa stain. It was then scrubbed utilizing distilled water and let to dry. Differential WBC counts were done in accordance with <xref rid="ref76" ref-type="bibr">Thrall <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2012</xref>). Albumins, total serum proteins, serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT), serum aspartate aminotransferase (AST), urea, uric acid, and creatinine analyses were estimated as previously stated (<xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">Moustafa <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Determination of immune parameters</title><p>a- Phagocytic index (PI) and phagocytic activity (PA):</p><p>The PI was estimated following <xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">Moustafa <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2019</xref>). However, PA was estimated with reference to Kawahara <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (1991).</p><p>b- Serum lysozyme activity:</p><p>Serum Lysozyme activity was investigated in light of the Gram-positive lysozyme delicate lyophilized bacterium, <italic toggle="yes">Micrococcus lysodeikticus,</italic> (Sigma, St. Louis, MO) using the method outlined by <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Demers and Bayne (1997</xref>).</p><p>c- Superoxide dismutase (SOD) was colorimetrically determined following <xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">Nishikimi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (1972</xref>).</p><p>d- Catalase (CAT) activity was carried out by spectrophotometric verification of hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>), as previously prescribed (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Aebi, 1984</xref>).</p><p>e- Glutathione peroxidase (GSH-Px) was ascertained utilizing the technique performed by <xref rid="ref61" ref-type="bibr">Prieto <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (1999</xref>).</p><p>f- Lipid peroxide (Malondialdehyde) (MDA): was colorimetrically detected following <xref rid="ref71" ref-type="bibr">Satoh (1978</xref>) and <xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">Ohkawa <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (1979</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Challenge with A. hydrophila</title><p>The purpose of the experimental infection was to ascertain how Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> feed supplementation affected the fingerlings of <italic toggle="yes">O. niloticus&#8217;</italic> ability to fend off <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">hydrophila</italic> bacterial infection. According to <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2011</xref>), an intraperitoneal injection containing 0.2 ml of fresh culture suspension of <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic> (3 &#215; 10<sup>7</sup> CFU) was used for the experimental infection. Daily mortalities have been documented for 15 days after infection.</p><p>The concentration of <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic> strain per 1 ml and the dosage for the experimental investigations were estimated using the drop plate method (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Cruickshank, 1975</xref>). For plate counts on TSA, a 24-hour colony culture of the <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic> strain was employed. After being lifted up and suspended in sterile saline through a 10-fold serial dilution, the colonies were incubated for 24 hours at 28&#8451;. The dilutions (102 to 107 CFU) were on<sup>l</sup>y used. Every group received an intraperitoneal injection of 0.5 ml per fish for every bacterial dilution. For 2 weeks following injection, every fish was housed for observation. <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Ibrahim <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2011</xref>) stated that the fatalities were documented twice a day. The recently deceased fish were relocated for a more thorough investigation. Per <xref rid="ref64" ref-type="bibr">Reed and Muench (1938</xref>), the LD<sub>50</sub> (the dosage that kills 50% of the inoculated fish) was determined.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Primers sequences of genes analyzed in real-time PCR.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Target genes</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward primer</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse primer</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accession No.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">&#946;. Actin</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAGCAAGCAGGAGTACGATGAG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGTGTGGTGTGTGGTTGTTTTG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="EU887951.1">EU887951.1</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">IL-1B</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAAGGATGACGACAAGCCAACC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGCGGACAGACATGAGAGTGC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="XM_003460625.2">XM_003460625.2</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">TNF-&#945;</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGAAGCAGCTCCACTCTGATGA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CACAGCGTGTCTCCTTCGTTCA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="JF957373.1">JF957373.1</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">SOD</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCCTACGTCAGTGCAGAGAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTCACGTCTCCCTTTGCAAG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="JF801727.1">JF801727.1</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">GPX</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGCCGAAGGTCTCGTTATTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCCCTGGACGGACATACTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_001279711.1">NM_001279711.1</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">GHR</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAGACTTCTACGCTCAGGTC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTGGATTCTGAGTTGCTGTC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AY973232.1">AY973232.1</ext-link></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Gene expression analysis</title><p>Following the guidelines provided by the manufacturer, the process of extracting total RNA was carried out utilizing the TRIzol reagent (Life Technologies, Gaithersburg, MD). Using the MultiScribe RT enzyme kit (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA), the cDNA was generated right away. Three separate real-time PCR analyses were performed on the resulting cDNA. Power SYBR Green PCR Master Mix (Applied Biosystems, Life Technologies, CA) was used to conduct real-time PCR studies using a 7,500 real-time PCR System (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA). Comparing the various genes&#8217; relative fold changes in mRNA expression to the control was done. &#946;-actin, a standard house-keeping gene, expression was utilized to standardize the fold change in mRNA expression of the assessed genes. <xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> provides the accession codes and primer sequences for genes.</p></sec><sec><title>Histopathological examinations</title><p>Following deep anesthesia with 40% ethyl alcohol, tissue samples were collected from the anterior section of the intestine, the hepatopancreas, the kidney, and the spleen from five randomly chosen fish from each treatment (0%, 0.05%, 0.10%, and 0.20% of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>) both before and after the fish were infected with <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic>. Ethyl alcohol was provided in ascending levels of concentrations (70% to 100% alcohol) for dehydration after being fixed for 24 to 48 hours in a 10% neutral buffer formaldehyde solution. After being cleaned in xylene, the dehydrated samples were embedded in paraffin wax. Following <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Bancroft and Gamble (2007</xref>), sections of 4&#8211;5 &#181;m thickness were stained with hematoxilin and eosin (HandE), and inspected under a light microscope for histopathological and morphometric examination.</p></sec><sec><title>Morphometry of intestinal villi</title><p>With the aid of image analysis software (NIH, Bethesda, MD), the intestinal villi&#8217;s width, length, and crypt depth, along with their surface area, were assessed. A total of ten villi and villus-associated crypts were randomly selected from each of the five intestinal cross-sections. A one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was performed on the gathered data using SPSS version 22, SPSS Inc., Chicago, Il. At <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> 0.05, the accepted level of significance was established. All data are displayed in the form of means &#177; standard error (SE).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The effects of dietary MOS, challenge, and their interactions were tested using two-way ANOVA. Once the interaction between the two factors was identified, one-way ANOVA was used to examine each of the four groups for every level of the two factors combined. Tukey-Kramer was used to compare each group&#8217;s data to that of the control group, as well as to examine variations within the same group and between sampling periods for every parameter. One-way ANOVA tests (SPSS version 22, SPSS Inc., Chicago, Il) were used to evaluate all statistical differences, and the Duncan <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> test was used where there were differences across experimental groups. At <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, the significance level was deemed acceptable. The presentation of all data is as means &#177; SE.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>The ongoing research complied with all relevant laws and guidelines of the Animal Ethics Committee of Kafrelsheikh University, Egypt (KFS-IACUC/137/2023) with regard to techniques, animal care, and experimental protocol.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>In the present research, Nile tilapia fingerlings physiological responses to Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> were investigated through assurance of fish growth, and hematological, biochemical, and immune parameters.</p><sec><title>Growth performance</title><p>In the ongoing research, the impact of the utilized prebiotic on <italic toggle="yes">O. niloticus</italic> growth responses to Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> was evaluated. It was found that all treated groups showed increased ADG, SGR, fish final weight, weight gain %, and feed intake with the T4 group showing the highest values in comparison to the control group (T1) (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt;</italic> 0.05), as shown in <xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. In addition, the impact of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> on food conversion rate (FCR) was summarized. It was found that, in comparison to the control group (T1), the T3 and T4 groups had the best food conversion rate values (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt; 0.05</italic>) (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). SR% was 100% in all groups.</p></sec><sec><title>Hematological parameters</title><p>RBCs showed no appreciable difference in hematological features across the groups. PCV was noticeably lowered in groups (T2 and T3) as opposed to the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt;</italic> 0.05), with the exception of the T4 group, where there were no obvious differences. The T4 group experienced a large rise in Hb, MCV, and MHC as opposed to the control group, while in MCHC all treatment groups exhibited a noticeable increase (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt;</italic> 0.05) (<xref rid="tab5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><title>The effect of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> on growth performance of <italic toggle="yes">O. niloticus.</italic></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth performance</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial fish weight(g)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.13 &#177; 0.22<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.97 &#177; 0.18<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.10 &#177; 0.06<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.93 &#177; 0.09<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Final fish weight (g)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.77 &#177; 0.25<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.85 &#177; 0.85<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.17 &#177; 0.19<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.90 &#177; 0.42<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight gain (g)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.63 &#177; 0.34<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.88 &#177; 0.74<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.07 &#177; 0.25<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.97 &#177; 0.48<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight gain %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.79 &#177; 2.24<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.56 &#177; 3.33<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104.82 &#177; 1.53<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110.24 &#177; 2.79<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SGR, %/fish/day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 &#177; 0.03<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.53 &#177; 0.04<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59 &#177; 0.08<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65 &#177; 0.03<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feed intake</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.14 &#177; 0.20<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.17 &#177; 0.46<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.34 &#177; 0.05<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.43 &#177; 0.11<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FCR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15 &#177; 0.07<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42 &#177; 0.04<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39 &#177; 0.01<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34 &#177; 0.02<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.33 &#177; 0.67<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.33 &#177; 1.76<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.00 &#177; 0.58<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.00 &#177; 1.00<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fish biomass (g)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">655.33 &#177; 4.91<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">797.00 &#177; 17.04<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">823.33 &#177; 3.84<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">838.07 &#177; 8.45<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial number</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00 &#177; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Final number</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00 &#177; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fish survival (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00 &#177; 0.00</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The data represent the mean &#177; SE. The values with an alternative superscript on the same row denote notable variations (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt; 0.05</italic>). (T1): (control group); (T2): (0.5% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>); (T3): (1% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>); (T4): (2% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>); (SGR): Specific growth rate; (ADG): Average daily gain; (FCR): Feed conversion rate. </p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><title>Effect of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> on hematological parameters of <italic toggle="yes">O. niloticus.</italic></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RBCs (&#215;10<sup>6</sup>/mm&#179;)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.28 &#177; 0.01<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.17 &#177; 0.01<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20 &#177; 0.02<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.22 &#177; 0.06<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hb (g/100 ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.37 &#177; 0.40<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.52 &#177; 0.31<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.11 &#177; 0.25<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.11 &#177; 0.04<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCV (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.33 &#177; 0.88<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.33 &#177; 0.33<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00 &#177; 0.58<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.67 &#177; 0.33<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.65 &#177; 0.05<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.21 &#177; 1.84<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.29 &#177; 2.37<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.37 &#177; 1.24<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.98 &#177; 0.48<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.72 &#177; 1.62<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.02 &#177; 1.24<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.90 &#177; 0.75<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCHC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.36 &#177; 0.46<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.03 &#177; 1.14<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.87 &#177; 2.15<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.18 &#177; 0.28<sup>a</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The data represent the mean &#177; SE. The values with an alternative superscript on the same row denote notable variations (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt; 0.05</italic>). (T1): (control group); (T2): (0.5% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>); (T3): (1% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>); (T4): (2% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>); (RBCs): Red Blood Cells; (HB): Haemoglobin; (PCV): Packed Cell Volume; (MCV): Mean corpuscular volume; (MCH): Mean corpuscular hemoglobin; (MCHC): Mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Concerning differential leukocytic count, the findings showed no noticeable change between the T2 and T3 groups and a considerable elevation (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the heterophil%. In comparison to the T2 and T3 groups, T4 exhibited a substantial (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) decline. Lymphocyte% was significantly decreased (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in T2 and T3 groups as opposed to the T1 and there were no noticeable differences between T2 and T3 groups, and no noticeable variation between T4 and T1 was obvious. The results for monocyte and eosinophil% did not reveal any appreciable variations among the treated groups. While there were no significant changes between T3 and T1, basophil% was noticeably greater (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the T2 group as opposed to T1 while it was noticeably lower (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the T4 group (<xref rid="tab6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title> Biochemical analysis</title><p>According to data presented in <xref rid="tab7" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>, globulin levels and total protein in the T4 group exhibited a noticeable increase as opposed to the other treatment groups and the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt;</italic> 0.05), whereas albumin levels in all groups showed no appreciable changes. In contrast to other treated groups, the T4 group showed a noticeable decrease in ALT level (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt;</italic> 0.05), while there were no changes in AST levels across all groups. When opposed to other treatment groups, the outcomes for urea and uric acid revealed a considerable drop (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt;</italic> 0.05), especially in the T4 group, and the levels of creatinine in all groups remained unchanged.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunological and antioxidant parameters</title><p>Regarding immunological measures, there was a slight increase in the T4 group as opposed to the control group, although PA was dramatically lessened in the T2 and T3 groups as opposed to the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt;</italic> 0.05). The PI failed to detect any difference between the groups. As shown in <xref rid="tab8" ref-type="table">Table 8</xref>, lysozyme activity noticeably decreased in the T2 and T3 groups in contrast to the T4 group as opposed to the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt;</italic> 0.05). The antioxidant activity revealed that CAT, GSH-Px, and SOD activities were raised in all treatment groups, with the T4 group having the greatest value when opposed to the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt;</italic> 0.05). MDA activity increased in the T2 and T3 groups, but it dramatically lessened in the T4 group (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt;</italic> 0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6.</label><caption><title>Effect of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> on the differential leukocytic count of <italic toggle="yes">O. niloticus.</italic></title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterophil (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.67 &#177; 2.03<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.67 &#177; 0.33<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.67 &#177; 0.33<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.00 &#177; 1.73<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymphocyte (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.67 &#177; 3.18<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.00 &#177; 0.00<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.67 &#177; 0.33<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.11 &#177; 2.03<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monocyte (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.60 &#177; 0.00<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.67 &#177; 0.33<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.67 &#177; 0.33<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.67 &#177; 0.33<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eosinophil (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 &#177; 0.88<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60 &#177; 0.00<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65 &#177; 0.58<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 &#177; 0.33<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basophil (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 &#177; 0.33<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00 &#177; 0.00<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 &#177; 0.33<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 &#177; 0.33<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterophil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71 &#177; 0.13<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59 &#177; 0.02<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73 &#177; 0.01<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43 &#177; 0.13<sup>abc</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymphocyte</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.26 &#177; 1.11<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.71 &#177;0.03<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.90 &#177; 0.06<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.75 &#177; 0.80<sup>ab</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monocyte</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 &#177; 0.06<sup>cd</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 &#177; 0.03<sup>de</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58 &#177; 0.03<sup>e</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 &#177; 0.08<sup>cd</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eosinophil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 &#177; 0.01<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 &#177; 0.00<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11 &#177; 0.06<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18 &#177; 0.03<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basophil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19 &#177; 0.02<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21 &#177; 0.00<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16 &#177; 0.03<sup>abc</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 &#177; 0.03<sup>cd</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The data represent the mean &#177; SE. The values with an alternative superscript on the same row denote notable variations (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt; 0.05</italic>). (T1): (control group); (T2): (0.5% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>); (T3): (1% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>); (T4): (2% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;)</sup>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab7" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 7.</label><caption><title>Effect of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> on biochemical analysis of<italic toggle="yes"> O. niloticus</italic>.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT (U/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.22 &#177; 0.15<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.32 &#177; 0.02<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.28 &#177; 0.01<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.11 &#177; 0.14<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST (U/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.37 &#177; 2.92<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.37 &#177; 0.30<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.12 &#177; 2.31<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.39 &#177; 0.54<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total protein (g/dl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.76 &#177; 0.03<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.77 &#177; 0.04<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.76 &#177; 0.03<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.95 &#177; 0.09<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Albumin (g/dl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 &#177; 0.03<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 &#177; 0.03<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 &#177; 0.01<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 &#177; 0.01<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Globulin (g/dl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.72 &#177; 0.05<sup>bc</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60 &#177; 0.01<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61 &#177; 0.01<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78 &#177; 0.08<sup>ab</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea (mg/dl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.06 &#177; 0.02<sup>abc</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.11 &#177; 0.01<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.12 &#177; 0.01<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.07 &#177; 0.04<sup>abc</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Creatinine (mg/dl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 &#177; 0.01<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 &#177; 0.02<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 &#177; 0.03<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 &#177; 0.03<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uric acid (mg/dl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87 &#177; 0.06<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83 &#177; 0.03<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82 &#177; 0.05<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79 &#177; 0.06<sup>c</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The data represent the mean &#177; SE. The values with an alternative superscript on the same row denote notable variations (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt; 0.05</italic>). (T1): (control group); (T2): (0.5% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>); (T3): (1% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>); (T4): (2% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>); (ALT): Alanine aminotransferase; (AST): Aspartate aminotransferase.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Antioxidant activity after experimental challenge with A. hydrophila</title><p>SOD activity was noticeably higher in the T4 group as opposed to the control group, while CAT and GSH-Px activities were up in all treatment groups, with the T4 group having the highest value (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt;</italic> 0.05). MDA did not differ noticeably between the T2 and T3 groups and the control group; however, the T4 group experienced a sharp decline (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt;</italic> 0.05). The <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic> challenged groups indicated a 100% SR% mainly among the Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> supplemented groups (<xref rid="tab9" ref-type="table">Table 9</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Relative gene expression</title><p> Liver showed upregulation of mRNA expression of growth hormone receptor (GHR), GSH-Px and SOD in T2 and T3 groups supplemented with 0.5 and 1 mg/kg Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> in relation to other treated groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), while there is no noticeable differences among T2 and T3 groups supplemented with 0.5 and 1 mg/kg Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>, (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figs. 1</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).</p><p>Liver showed upregulation of mRNA expression of tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-&#945;) in T2 and T3 groups supplemented with 0.5 and 1 mg/kg Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> in relation to other treated groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), while there is no noticeable variations between T2 and T3 groups supplemented with 0.5 and 1 mg/kg Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>, post challenge with <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic>, while there is no noticeable differences between the all treated groups fed with Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> and the control group, before the challenge with <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic> (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). Interleukin 1&#946; (IL-1&#946;) was noticeably upregulated in fish of T2 and T3 groups supplemented with 0.5 and 1 mg/kg Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>, post challenge with <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic> in relation to other treated groups, with the highest level of (IL-1&#946;) in T3 group supplemented with 1 mg/kg Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05), while there are no noticeable changes among the all treated groups supplemented with Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>and the control group, before the challenge with <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic> (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab8" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 8.</label><caption><title>Effect of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> on immunity and oxidative status of <italic toggle="yes">O. niloticus</italic>.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.73 &#177; 0.33<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.17 &#177; 0.04<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.16 &#177; 0.02<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.77 &#177; 0.32<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23 &#177; 0.13<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 &#177; 0.02<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 &#177; 0.00<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 &#177; 0.06<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">lysozyme (u/ml)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.59 &#177; 0.25<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.12 &#177; 0.01<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.27 &#177; 0.00<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.68 &#177; 0.21<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOD (IU/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.30 &#177; 0.03<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.88 &#177; 0.08<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.90 &#177; 0.05<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.37 &#177; 0.18<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAT (IU/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.22 &#177; 0.07<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.78 &#177; 0.11<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.80 &#177; 0.08<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.43 &#177; 0.16<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSH-Px (IU/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.29 &#177; 0.07<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.25 &#177; 0.15<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.02 &#177; 0.11<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.75 &#177; 0.06<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDA (IU/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.39 &#177; 0.10<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.45 &#177; 0.04<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.36 &#177; 0.05<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.31 &#177; 0.07<sup>c</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The data represent the mean &#177; SE. The values with an alternative superscript on the same row denote notable variations (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt; 0.05</italic>). (T1): (control group); (T2): (0.5% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>); (T3): (1% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>); (T4): (2% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>); (SOD):Superoxide dismutase; (CAT): Catalase; (GSH-Px): Glutathione peroxidase; (MDA): Malondialdehyde.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab9" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 9.</label><caption><title>Effect of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> on oxidative status of<italic toggle="yes"> O. niloticus</italic> after challenge with<italic toggle="yes"> A. hydrophila</italic>.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">T4</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOD (IU/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.75 &#177; 0.27<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.46 &#177; 0.13<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.69 &#177; 0.16<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.01 &#177; 0.19<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAT (IU/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.19 &#177; 0.06<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.60 &#177; 0.14<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.80 &#177; 0.14<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.18 &#177; 0.25<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSH-Px (IU/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.14 &#177; 0.05<sup>d</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.58 &#177; 0.02<sup>d</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.29 &#177; 0.14<sup>d</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.85 &#177; 0.22<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDA (IU/l)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.57 &#177; 0.05<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.64 &#177; 0.06<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.25 &#177; 0.04<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.39 &#177; 0.31<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SR%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The data represent the mean &#177; SE. The values with an alternative superscript on the same row denote notable variations (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt; 0.05</italic>). (T1): (control group); (T2): (0.5% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>); (T3): (1% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>); (T4): (2% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>); (SOD): Superoxide dismutase; (CAT): Catalase; (GSH-Px): Glutathione peroxidase; (MDA): Malondialdehyde.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>Gene expression of the liver (GHR) of Nile tilapia in different groups fed diets with different doses of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> for 8 weeks. * indicate significant differences between groups (p &lt; 0.05), ns = indicate no significant differences between groups.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-116-g001.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>Gene expression of the liver (SOD) of Nile tilapia in different groups fed diets with different doses of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> for 8 weeks. * indicate significant differences between groups (p &lt; 0.05), ns = indicate no significant differences between groups.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-116-g002.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><title>Gene expression of liver GSH-Px of Nile tilapia in different groups fed diets with different doses of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> for 8 weeks. * indicate significant differences between groups (p &lt; 0.05), ns = indicate no significant differences between groups.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-116-g003.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig4" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><title>Gene expression of liver (TNF-&#945;) of Nile tilapia pre and post challenge with A. hydrophila in different groups fed diets with different doses of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> for 8 weeks. * indicate significant differences between groups (p &lt; 0.05), ns = indicate no significant differences between groups.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-116-g004.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig5" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><title>Gene expression of liver (IL-1&#946;) of Nile tilapia pre and post challenge with A. hydrophila in different groups fed diets with different doses of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> for 8 weeks. * indicate significant differences between groups (p &lt; 0.05), ns = indicate no significant differences between groups.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-116-g005.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tab10" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 10.</label><caption><title>Morphometric analysis of the intestine of <italic toggle="yes">O. niloticus</italic> fed on diets containing different levels Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Groups</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> 0.00%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> 0.05%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> 0.10%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> 0.20%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>. value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Villi length (&#181;m)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">167.0 &#177; 9.09<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">216.0 &#177; 9.80<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">392.6 &#177; 24.69<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">273.0 &#177; 8.80<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crypt depth (&#181;m)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.20 &#177; 2.26<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.83 &#177; 1.99<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.51 &#177; 3.26<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.91 &#177; 1.98<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">villi width (&#181;m)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.62 &#177; 2.86<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.67 &#177; 3.77<sup>bc</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.44 &#177; 5.48<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.32 &#177; 4.10<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Villi length/crypt depth</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.91 &#177; 0.71<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.19 &#177; 0.52<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.14 &#177; 0.56<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.26 &#177; 0.41<sup>ab</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Villi surface area (&#181;m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,583 &#177; 639.7<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,861 &#177; 820.3<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29,499 &#177; 1770<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17,707 &#177; 819.5<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The presented data represent the mean &#177; SE. The values with different superscripts in the same row indicate significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt; 0.05</italic>).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Histopathological findings</title><p>Intestinal morphometric analysis of pre-challenged groups revealed a noticeable increase in villi length, width, crypt depth, villi length/crypt depth, and villi surface area in a dose-dependent pattern especially 0.10% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> group than the other treated groups as illustrated in <xref rid="tab10" ref-type="table">Table 10</xref>. Moreover, the 0.10% and 0.20% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> groups showed increased branching of intestinal villi as opposed to the other groups.</p><p>The histopathological examination of the intestine of fish challenged with <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic> shows marked degenerative changes and necrosis in the intestinal villi and sloughing of the apical epithelium into the intestinal lumen especially 0.0% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> group while the intestine of the other groups shows a marked decrease in the degenerative changes in the intestinal villi especially in 0.10% and 0.20% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> groups compared with 0.05% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> group (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>).</p><p>The hepatopancreas of pre-challenged groups shows the normal architecture of the liver with polyhedral-shaped hepatocytes separated by hepatic sinusoids and radiating from a central vein and intact pancreatic acini. On the other hand, the hepatopancreas of the 0.0% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> challenged group shows severe vacuolar degeneration and a large focal area of necrosis in hepatic and pancreatic tissue in addition to severe congestion in hepatic and pancreatic blood vessels. The severity of the lesion shows marked amelioration in both hepatic and pancreatic tissue with increased concentration of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>).</p><p>The histopathological examinations of the posterior kidney of pre-challenged groups show the normal architecture of the kidney with intact glomeruli and renal tubules with interstitial hematopoietic tissue. The kidney of the 0.0% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> challenged group shows severe degenerative changes and necrosis of renal glomeruli and tubular epithelium, interstitial edema, and congestion of renal blood vessels. The aforementioned lesions gradually decreased with an increased concentration of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig6" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><title>Photomicrograph of HandE stained panel of anterior part of intestine of O. niloticus fed on ration contained 0%, 0.05%, 0.10%, and 0.20% of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> pre and post-challenge with A. hydrophila showing intestinal villi lined with simple columnar cells of lamina epithelialis (E), lamina propria (P), muscular layer (M), tunica serosa (S), branched alveoli (arrow head), areas of necrosis and sloughing of intestinal villi (N), in addition to lymphocytic aggregation in the lamina propria (L).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-116-g006.jpg"/></fig><p>The histopathological examinations of the spleen of pre-challenged groups show the normal architecture of the spleen with mixed red and white pulp, ellipsoids, and melanomacrophage centers. The spleen of the 0.0% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> challenged group shows severe degenerative changes and necrosis, depletion of white pulp, increase in melanomacrophage centers interstitial edema, and congestion of splenic blood vessels. The previously mentioned degenerative changes were greatly decreased with increased concentration of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig7" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7.</label><caption><title>Photomicrograph of HandE stained panel of hepatopancreas of O. niloticus pre-challenge (A) and post-challenge with A. hydrophila fed on ration contained 0% (B), 0.05% (C), 0.10% (D) and 0.20% (E) of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> showing central vein (CV), hepatocytes (H), blood sinusoids (S), pancreatic acini (P), focal areas of necrosis (N), vacuolar degeneration (V), and congestion of blood vessels (C).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-116-g007.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>A functional dietary supplement is a key managemental tool for improving the resistance of farmed fish against infectious diseases, as well as improving the overall growth parameters (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Dawood <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). Antibiotic application in aquaculture has raised public concerns due to the increased danger of antibiotic-resistant bacteria emerging in these ecosystems, which is detrimental to aquaculture as well as consumers, terrestrial animals, and the environment (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Ghiasi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>). Inclusion of prebiotics in response to the worldwide need for safe food as natural substitute growth accelerators to be preferential to antibiotic therapy, which improved fish resistance and reduced mortalities associated with pathogens infection (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Ahmad <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>).</p><sec><title>Growth performance</title><p>In the present research, all evaluated growth parameters were raised in prebiotic-treated groups having the greatest values in the T4 group (fed on Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> 2g/kg); these findings may be due to the fish&#8217;s improved feed utilization. The obtained growth parameters findings are in accordance with those previously investigated (<xref rid="ref70" ref-type="bibr">Samuel <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). However, they conflict with those published by <xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">Peterson <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2010</xref>) who revealed that the feed conversion ratio and growth outcomes of a number of fish species were not improved by the addition of mannan-oligosaccharide.</p><fig position="float" id="fig8" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 8.</label><caption><title>Photomicrograph of HandE stained panel of kidney of O. <italic toggle="yes">niloticus</italic> pre-challenge (A) and postchallenge with A. <italic toggle="yes">hydrophila</italic> fed on ration contained 0% (B), 0.05% (C), 0.10% (D) and 0.20% (E) of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> showing renal tubules (T), interstitial areas of hematopoietic tissue (I), congestion of blood vessels (C), degeneration and separation of renal tubular epithelium from its basement membrane (arrow heads), necrosis of some renal tubules (N) and edema in the interstitial tissue (E) beside the accumulation of hyaline droplets in the lumen of some renal tubules (H).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-116-g008.jpg"/></fig><p>Improvement in feed conversion rate may be attributed to the effect of the currently used prebiotic which decreased the quantity of feed needed to produce one unit of fish and as a result, lowered production cost. The findings concur with those of certain authors (<xref rid="ref86" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Moreover, Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> modulated gut microbiota, improving villus integrity and resistance to harmful bacteria, leading to improved intestine growth and an increase in the region where nutrients are absorbed; the outcomes are in accordance with previous records (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">G&#243;mez and Balc&#225;zar 2008</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Hematological parameters</title><p>When fish consume functional feed additives, blood biochemical measures are typically employed to detect potential changes in the fishes&#8217; overall health status (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Dawood <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>). Concerning the hematological parameters, no appreciable difference in RBCs across the groups was recorded in this current research. The result is in agreement with <xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr">Sado <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2008</xref>). While, the T4 group experienced a large rise in Hb, MCV, and MHC. Moreover<bold>,</bold> a considerable elevation in the heterophil% in Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> treated groups; that may be due to the enhanced defense response brought about by Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> feed supplementation. The obtained result is similar to <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Khanjani <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2022</xref>) and in contrast to <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Ali <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2017</xref>). The kind and dosage of probiotics, fish&#8217;s physiological state, species, size, age, ecological environments, and feeding schedule may all have an impact on the variance in the results of hematological parameters (<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">Osuigwe <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig9" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 9.</label><caption><title>Photomicrograph of HandE stained panel of spleen of <italic toggle="yes">O. niloticus</italic> pre-challenge (A) and postchallenge with A. <italic toggle="yes">hydrophila</italic> fed on ration contained 0% (B), 0.05% (C), 0.10% (D), and 0.20% (E) of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> showing mixed red (R) and white (W) pulp, melanomacrophage centers (MMC), congestion of splenic blood vessels (C), area of necrosis(N), and edema (E).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-116-g009.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Biochemical analysis</title><p>The noticeable heightened globulin and total protein levels in the T4 prebiotic-treated group might be due to the increased inherited body defense and better innate response of fish in response to prebiotic supplementation (<xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">Sahoo and Mukherjee, 2001</xref>). These parameters have been employed as a comprehensive clinical measure of fish health, immunological competence, stress, and nutritional status. The outcomes resemble those reported previously <xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">Sahoo and Mukherjee (2001</xref>); however, opposite to those reported by <xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr">Sado <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2008</xref>). Alterations in hematological and serum biochemical variables might be species-related and rely on the amount at which MOS are incorporated into the diet, the components in the diet, and/or the rearing period (<xref rid="ref75" ref-type="bibr">Ta&#8217;ati <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>).</p><p>The noticeable decrease in ALT levels in the T4 prebiotic-treated group is a similar result to that recorded by <xref rid="ref83" ref-type="bibr">Yal&#231;inkaya <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2008</xref>). This may be attributed to that both ALT and AST levels should be increasing in the plasma when liver cells sustain an injury or have their membranes broken, allowing these enzymes to seep out (<xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr">Rehulka, 1996</xref>). However, there was a decrease in uric acid, urea, and AST levels in fish-fed Bio-Mos; the outcomes are in agreement with <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">El Mesallamy <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2016</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Immunological and antioxidant parameters</title><p>The current study investigated that <italic toggle="yes">O. niloticus</italic> fingerlings&#8217; immune responses were fundamentally altered and boosted in all groups, with the highest levels in the T4 group.</p><p>Fish body defense depends heavily on non specific immunity (<xref rid="ref63" ref-type="bibr">Reda <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>). Lysozyme, which can break down the link between N-acetyl intracytoic acid and N-acetyl glucosamine and harm the pathogen microorganisms&#8217; cell wall structure, is an essential protective element of the humoral immune response (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Han <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>).</p><p>This research clarified that one of the most fundamentally safe processes in fish is lysozyme. It comes from macrophages and neutrophils that are released into the mucus and blood to possess bacteriolytic properties, aiding organisms in fighting against bacterial, viral, and parasite illnesses (<xref rid="ref84" ref-type="bibr">Yano, 1997</xref>). The current findings showed that Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> supplementation substantially altered the dimensions of lysozyme action. Fish that were encouraged to eat diets with 0.2% Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> diet expressed the highest serum lysozyme activity. The immune-stimulating properties of dietary Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> may be the cause of the increased lysozymal action. The outcomes are similar to those reported in hybrid grouper and European eel (<italic toggle="yes">Anguilla anguilla</italic>), channel catfish (<italic toggle="yes">Ictalurus punctatus</italic>), Nile tilapia (<italic toggle="yes">O. niloticus</italic>), and red drum (<xref rid="ref66" ref-type="bibr">Ren <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>).</p><p>Reactive oxygen species (ROS) are produced in excess, which causes oxidative stress (<xref rid="ref72" ref-type="bibr">Sinha <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Oxidative stress can be ensured by a variety of poor rearing conditions, including low oxygen levels, overcrowding, and high ammonia nitrogen levels, which can lead to a number of damages, including cell death by apoptosis or necrosis (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Klein and Ackerman, 2003</xref>). MDA is one of the primary byproducts of lipid peroxidation induced by ROS (<xref rid="ref82" ref-type="bibr">Xu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). CAT together with GSH-Px and SOD developed the main defensive mechanism for enzymes opposing the harmful effects of ROS (<xref rid="ref89" ref-type="bibr">Zhou <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). The evaluation of these variables can reveal information about the antioxidant capacity of fish.</p><p>The dramatic increase in antioxidant activity (CAT, GSH-Px, and SOD activities) in all Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> treated groups with the highest increase in T4 group clarify the oxidative capability of ROS, which are delivered by phagocytic cells that have been activated and are in charge of eliminating or deteriorating ingested items, including microorganisms (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Atencio <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>).</p><p>The prebiotic-supplemented T4 groups in the current study showed higher CAT activity levels with decreased MDA. The finding suggested that CAT and MDA were not necessarily inversely associated. These outcomes are in line with numerous research (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Danesh <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2022</xref>). Since CAT is simply one of many antioxidant enzymes that could stop the synthesis of MDA, the explanation is rather simple. In addition to enzymes, other antioxidants that may affect fish&#8217;s final MDA level include non-enzymatic substances like vitamins C and E as well as specific prebiotics and probiotics (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">Mishra <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). The mechanisms of these prebiotics&#8217; actions typically included a minimum of one of the subsequent elements: the prebiotic aided in the development of antioxidant bacteria (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">Cao <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>); the prebiotic itself was a potent antioxidant <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Liu and Huang, 2018</xref>); and the prebiotic was able to attach itself to intestinal receptors and use receptor-related pathways to provide antioxidant benefits (<xref rid="ref77" ref-type="bibr">Torrecillas <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). MOS could react with ROS (like hydroxyl radical) (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Liu and Huang, 2018</xref>). However, MOS can also cause fish to express more of the antioxidant enzyme gene by activating the mannose receptor (<xref rid="ref90" ref-type="bibr">Zhu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2023</xref>). The enhanced lysozyme, bactericidal, and antioxidant activities shown in this study could be linked to the dietary Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> stimulatory effects on resistance. It implies that the activation of antioxidant defense mechanisms such as CAT, GSH-Px, and SOD takes place in the context of both Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">K&#246;hrle <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Antioxidant activity after experimental challenge with A. hydrophila</title><p>Prebiotics in the diet have been proven in numerous studies to significantly increase fish resistance to harmful microorganisms (<xref rid="ref87" ref-type="bibr">Zhao <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">Poolsawat <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>).</p><p>Fish may experience oxidative stress due to <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila,</italic> one of the most virulent harmful bacteria connected to aquatic environments (<xref rid="ref78" ref-type="bibr">Turutoglu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Based on a recent study, <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic> infections are characterized by the activation of strong ROS generation in the host, which causes oxidative damage (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). MDA and PC are known as signs of ROS-induced cell damage, and the antioxidant system can lessen this damage (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Birben <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). The current findings demonstrated that adding a suitable amount of MOS to a diet suppresses excessive ROS generation and lowers MDA and PC levels. ROS mostly consist of superoxide anions and hydroxyl radicals, which can harm cells through oxidative stress when present in excess (<xref rid="ref62" ref-type="bibr">Reczek and Chandel, 2014</xref>). In the ongoing research, Nile tilapia fingerlings fed Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> revealed the highest SOD, CAT, and GSH-Px activities were recorded in the prebiotic supplemented T4 group while, recorded sharp decline in MDA activity after infection with <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic>. The outcome is comparable to studies by <xref rid="ref66" ref-type="bibr">Ren <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2020</xref>), which found that MOS could increase grouper resistance to<italic toggle="yes"> Vibrio harvey</italic>, <xref rid="ref90" ref-type="bibr">Zhu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2023</xref>), which found that MOS could increase grouper resistance to <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic>, and <xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">Lu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2023</xref>) increase grass carp resistance to <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila</italic>.</p><p>MOS has been shown to increase the scavenging of free radicals (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">Lu <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>), indicating that it is a superb natural antioxidant with a wide range of free radical-scavenging characteristics. The principal antioxidant enzymes in fish may also be responsible for their excessive capacity to scavenge free radicals (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Atli <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Relative gene expression</title><p>Immune system health is correlated with TNF-&#945;, IL-1&#946;, and SOD gene expression levels (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Elbahnaswy and Elshopakey, 2020</xref>), physiological status (<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Morano, 2007</xref>), and oxidative status (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">E&#711;cimovi&#180;c <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>) of fish. When comparing the Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup> treated fish groups to the control fish group, the proinflammatory IL-1&#946; and cytokines TNF-&#945; had higher levels of gene expression. Concurrently, those for GHR, SOD, and GSH-Px were upregulated. In addition, no noticeable variation was observed between T2 and T3 groups supplemented with 0.5 and 1 mg/kg Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>, post challenge with <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic>, regarding TNF-<italic toggle="yes">a</italic> and IL-1&#946; gene expression in the liver. The outcomes resemble those reported by <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">Jomeh <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2021</xref>). These findings unequivocally validated Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>&#8217;s potential impact on boosting immunity and reducing inflammation in Nile tilapia infected with <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila.</italic></p></sec><sec><title>Histopathological findings</title><p>Morphological consistency is fundamental for keeping up with the ordinary elements of the intestine (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">Gao <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Fish with a healthy gut have certain intestinal morphological parameters (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Han <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). An important morphometry indicator to explore when comparing different feeding strategies for aquatic animals is the healthiness of their intestines. This includes their ability to absorb food and digest it, which can be seen by the number of goblet cells, the thickness of the muscular layer, and the height of the intestinal villi (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Khojasteh, 2012</xref>).</p><p>Prebiotics in the diet can help farmed fish consume their feed more effectively and maintain the health of their intestinal mucosal epithelium (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Dimitroglou <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). This was also confirmed through the upregulation of the <italic toggle="yes">GHR</italic>. In the current investigation, MOS considerably improved each of the three intestinal measures (villus width, villus length, and crypt depth), showing the greatest overall effect on enhancing gut structure. The results are consistent with previous research, in which MOS increased the crypt depth of subadult trout (<xref rid="ref74" ref-type="bibr">Staykov <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), and MOS increased the intestinal villi length of redfish (<xref rid="ref88" ref-type="bibr">Zhou <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). The challenge with<italic toggle="yes"> A. hydrophila</italic> induced marked degenerative changes in the intestine, hepatopancreas, spleen, and posterior kidney of Nile tilapia, as shown in the histopathological study mainly in the control group, not treated with Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>. The overexpression of genes linked to inflammation (TNF-&#945;) and IL-1&#946; confirms the presence of inflammation. However, the severity of the lesion was greatly decreased and showed marked amelioration with increased concentration of Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>. An increase in the accessible absorption surface area and/or mucus generated by many goblet cells, which has a bactericidal effect by masking pathogen receptors and maintaining intestinal epithelium integrity, may be the cause of increased intestinal absorptive and defensive activities (<xref rid="ref73" ref-type="bibr">Smirnov <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The current study advances our understanding of the functional nutritional strategies of the use of MOS as a prebiotic in the diets of freshwater fish. It could be concluded that prebiotics in addition to <italic toggle="yes">O. niloticus</italic> fingerlings diets boost illness resistance and raise fish&#8217;s antioxidant capability, which is significant in modern intensive aquaculture. The Dietary MOS supplementation plays a crucial part in moderating the increased oxidative stress caused by <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila;</italic> they could effectively reduce fish oxidative stress under pathogen-challenge circumstances, showing promise as a preventative supplement for Nile tilapia in place of antibiotics. It could be recommended to enrich the Nile tilapia fingerlings diets with 2 g.kg<sup>&#8722;1</sup> of MOS due to the better results on growth rate, physiological response, immunological response, and intestinal absorptive capacity.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>None.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors acknowledged no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>This work was entirely supported by the authors&#8217; contributions; there was no outside financial source.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p>All authors took part in the goal and design of the work. Eman Moustafa and Amira Omar designed the study idea and planning. Data collection, analysis, and material preparation were carried out by Eman Moustafa, Amira Omar, and Haguer Salah El-Din. Statistical analyses were performed by Haguer Salah El-Din. Gene expression analysis was performed by Mustafa Shukry. The histological investigation was conducted by Foad Farrag. The manuscript&#8217;s first draft was written by Haguer Salah El-Din, Amira Omar, and Eman Moustafa. Every author offered feedback on earlier drafts of the work. The final manuscript was then edited and revised by Eman Moustafa. The manuscript was read and approved in its final form by all authors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The current manuscript contains all the information needed to support the study&#8217;s conclusions of this study. In response to reasonable demand, the corresponding author will provide any further information needed.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adelekea</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson-Anderssona</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moodleya</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylorb</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aquaculture in Africa: a comparative review of Egypt, Nigeria, and Uganda Vis-A-Vis South Africa</article-title><source>Rev. Fish. Sci. Aquac</source><year>2021</year><volume>29</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>197</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aebi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Catalase <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>, methods in enzymology</article-title><year>1984</year><publisher-loc>Amsterdam, The Netherlands</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0076-6879(84)05016-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6727660</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Mousallamy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd El-Naby</surname><given-names>A.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>S.Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of prebiotic as natural additives on growth performance and blood biochemistry for Nile tilapia (<italic toggle="yes">Oreochromis niloticus</italic>)</article-title><source>Mid. East. J. Appl. Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>526</fpage><lpage>533</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>S.R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ambasankar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Praveena</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nandakumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Syamadayal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of dietary mannan oligosaccharaide on growth, body composition, hematology and biochemical parameters of Asian seabass (<italic toggle="yes">Lates calcarifer</italic>)</article-title><source>Aquac. Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>899</fpage><lpage>908</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Wakeel</surname><given-names>A.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zahran</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hafez</surname><given-names>E.E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaki</surname><given-names>V.H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impacts of mannan oligosaccharides (MOS) on growth performance and gastrointestinal health of Nile tilapia (<italic toggle="yes">Oreochromis niloticus</italic>)</article-title><source>Man. Vet. Med. J</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>AOAC</collab><article-title>Official methods of analysis</article-title><year>2012</year><edition>18th</edition><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Association of Official Analysis of Chemists</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>APHA</collab><article-title>Standard methods for the examination of water and wastewater, part 3, determination of metals</article-title><year>1989</year><edition>17th</edition><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>American Public Health Association</publisher-name><fpage>164</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Atencio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jos</surname><given-names>&#193;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>A.I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moyano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Came&#225;n</surname><given-names>A.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of dietary selenium on the oxidative stress and pathological changes in tilapia (<italic toggle="yes">Oreochromis niloticus</italic>) exposed to a microcystin producing cyanobacterial water bloom</article-title><source>Toxicon</source><year>2009</year><volume>53</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19073206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.toxicon.2008.11.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Atli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Canli</surname><given-names>E.G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eroglu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Canli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of antioxidant system parameters in four freshwater fish species</article-title><source>Ecotoxicol. Environ. Saf</source><year>2016</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26707186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2015.12.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bancroft</surname><given-names>J.D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gamble</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Theory and practice of histological techniques</article-title><year>2007</year><edition>6th</edition><publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Churchill Livingstone</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Birben</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahiner</surname><given-names>U.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sackesen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erzurum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalayci</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative stress and antioxidant defense</article-title><source>World. Aller. Org. J</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/WOX.0b013e3182439613</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3488923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23268465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kajbaf</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of dietary supplementation with &#946;-glucan and <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> on growth, fillet quality, immune capacity, and antioxidant status of Pengze crucian carp <italic toggle="yes">(Carassius auratus var. Pengze)</italic></article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>2019</year><volume>508</volume><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>112</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruickshank</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medical microbiology: a guide to diagnosis and control of infection</article-title><year>1975</year><publisher-loc>Edinburgh and London, UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>E and S Livingston Ltd.</publisher-name><fpage>888</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Danesh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ziamajidi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mesbah-Namin</surname><given-names>S.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nafisi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbasalipourkabir</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association between oxidative stress parameters and hematological indices in breast cancer patients</article-title><source>Int. J. Breast. Cancer</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>59410</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2022/1459410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9550463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36225290</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawood</surname><given-names>M.A.O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>AbdEl-kader</surname><given-names>M.F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moustafa</surname><given-names>E.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gewaily</surname><given-names>M.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdo</surname><given-names>S.E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth performance and hemato-immunological responses of Nile tilapia <italic toggle="yes">(Oreochromis niloticus) </italic>exposed to deltamethrin and fed immunobiotics</article-title><source>Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>11608</fpage><lpage>11617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11356-020-07775-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31965509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawood</surname><given-names>M.A.O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koshio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Sabagh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Billah</surname><given-names>M.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaineldin</surname><given-names>A.I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zayed</surname><given-names>M.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>A.A.E.D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in the growth, humoral and mucosal immune responses following &#946;-glucan and vitamin C administration in red sea bream, <italic toggle="yes">Pagrus major</italic></article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>2017</year><volume>470</volume><fpage>214</fpage><lpage>222</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawood</surname><given-names>M.A.O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magouz</surname><given-names>F.I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salem</surname><given-names>M.F.I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Daim</surname><given-names>H.A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulation of digestive enzyme activity, blood health, oxidative responses and growth-related gene expression in GIFT by heat-killed<italic toggle="yes"> Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> (L-137)</article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>2019</year><volume>505</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>136</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>K.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pirvulescu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mananoligossacar&#237;deos derivados de leveduras como moduladores da resposta imunol&#243;gica e alternativas aos promotores de crescimento antimicrobianos</article-title><year>1999</year><edition>9th</edition><publisher-loc>Curitiba, Brasil</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Ronda Latino Americanada Alltech</publisher-name><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>41</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Demers</surname><given-names>N.E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayne</surname><given-names>C.J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The immediate effect of stress on hormones and plasma lysozyme in rainbow trout</article-title><source>Develop. Comp. Immunol</source><year>1997</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0145-305x(97)00009-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9303274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasr-Allah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenawy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kruijssen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increasing fish farm profitability through aquaculture best management practice training in Egypt</article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>2016</year><volume>465</volume><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>178</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dimitroglou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merrifield</surname><given-names>D.L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moate</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>S.J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spring</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sweetman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dietary mannan oligosaccharide supplementation modulates intestinal microbial ecology and improves gut morphology of rainbow trout, <italic toggle="yes">Oncorhynchus mykiss </italic>(Walbaum)</article-title><source>J. Anim. Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>3226</fpage><lpage>3234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19617514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2527/jas.2008-1428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>E&#711;cimovi&#180;c</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Velki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vukovi&#180;c</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#711;Camagajevac</surname><given-names>I.&#352;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bo&#353;njakovi&#180;c</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grgi&#180;c</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Engelmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bod&#243;</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Filipovi&#180;c-Mariji&#180;c</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute toxicity of selenate and selenite and their impacts on oxidative status, efflux pump activity, cellular and genetic parameters in earthworm <italic toggle="yes">Eisenia andrei</italic></article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><year>2018</year><volume>212</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30145422</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2018.08.095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elbahnaswy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elshopakey</surname><given-names>G.E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential gene expression and immune response of Nile tilapia <italic toggle="yes">(Oreochromis niloticus)</italic> challenged intraperitoneally with<italic toggle="yes"> Photobacterium damselae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila</italic> demonstrating immunosuppression</article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>2020</year><volume>526</volume><fpage>735364</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El Mesallamy</surname><given-names>A.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Souleman</surname><given-names>A.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Morsy</surname><given-names>A.T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd El-Naby</surname><given-names>A.S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of Roselle calyx <italic toggle="yes">(Hibiscus sabdariffa L.)</italic>-supplemented diets on growth and disease <italic toggle="yes">(Aeromonas hydrophila) </italic>resistance in Nile tilapia <italic toggle="yes">(Oreochromis niloticus L.).</italic> Egypt</article-title><source>Pharm. J</source><year>2016</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>78</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elumalai</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prakash</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Musthafa</surname><given-names>M.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faggio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of alkoxy glycerol on growth performance, immune response and disease resistance in Nile Tilapia (<italic toggle="yes">Oreochromis niloticus</italic>)</article-title><source>Res. Vet. Sci</source><year>2019</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>298</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30769237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.rvsc.2019.01.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>FAO</collab><article-title>FAO technical meeting on prebiotics</article-title><year>2007</year><publisher-loc>Rome, Italy</publisher-loc><publisher-name>FAO</publisher-name><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>16</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>FAO</collab><article-title>The state of world fisheries and aquaculture 2022. Towards blue transformation</article-title><year>2022</year><publisher-loc>Rome, Italy</publisher-loc><publisher-name>FAO</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4060/cc0461en</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gainza</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efect of mannan oligosaccharides on the microbiota and productivity parameters of <italic toggle="yes">Litopenaeus vannamei</italic> shrimp under intensive cultivation in Ecuador</article-title><source>Sci. Rep</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>2719</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32066764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-020-59587-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7026423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in gut microbial populations, intestinal morphology, expression of tight junction proteins, and cytokine production between two pig breeds after challenge with <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> K88: a comparative study</article-title><source>J. Anim. Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>5614</fpage><lpage>5625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24126267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2527/jas.2013-6528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghiasi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasrollahzadeh</surname><given-names>S.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fazli</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Safari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farabi</surname><given-names>S.M.V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Binaii</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yaghobzadeh</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zare</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Behrouzi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Habibi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of some risk factors on the rainbow trout production with emphasis on water microbial indices and heavy metals of farms along the Haraz River</article-title><source>Iran. Sci. Fish. J</source><year>2021</year><volume>30</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>42</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#243;mez</surname><given-names>G.D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balc&#225;zar</surname><given-names>J.L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review on the interactions between gut microbiota and innate immunity of fish</article-title><source>FEMS. Immun. Med. Microb</source><year>2008</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1574-695X.2007.00343.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18081845</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hady</surname><given-names>M.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Banna</surname><given-names>R.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taleb</surname><given-names>H.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimaa</surname><given-names>R.A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of manna oligosaccharide (Bio-Mos<sup>&#174;</sup>) and esterified glucomannan (MTB-100<sup>&#174;</sup>) dietary supplementation on performance and health status of Barki Lambs Under Egyptian conditions</article-title><source>Int. J. Chem. Eng. Appl</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>268</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Si</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of dietary <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus licheniformis</italic> on growth performance, immunological parameters, intestinal morphology and resistance of juvenile Nile tilapia <italic toggle="yes">(Oreochromis niloticus)</italic> to challenge infections</article-title><source>Fish. Shellfish. Immunol</source><year>2015</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26108035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.fsi.2015.06.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>M.D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahed</surname><given-names>I.B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abo El-Yazeed</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Korani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of the susceptibility of poly culture reared African catfish and Nile Tilapia to <italic toggle="yes">Edwardsiella tarda</italic></article-title><source>J. Amer. Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>779</fpage><lpage>786</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jomeh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chitsaz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akrami</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of anthocyanin extract from Roselle, <italic toggle="yes">Hibiscus sabdariffa</italic>, calyx on haematological, biochemical and immunological parameters of rainbow trout, <italic toggle="yes">Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic></article-title><source>Aquac. Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>3736</fpage><lpage>3744</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> phagocytic activity of white spotted shark cells after injection with <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas salmonicida</italic> extracelluar products</article-title><source>Gyo. Ken. Japan</source><year>1991</year><volume>26</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>214</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khanjani</surname><given-names>M.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghaedi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharifinia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of diets containing &#946;-glucan on survival, growth performance, haematological, immunity and biochemical parameters of rainbow trout <italic toggle="yes">(Oncorhynchus mykiss) </italic>fingerlings</article-title><source>Aquac. Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>1842</fpage><lpage>1850</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khojasteh</surname><given-names>S.M.B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The morphology of the post-gastric alimentary canal in teleost fishes: a brief review</article-title><source>Int. J. Aquat. Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>88</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>J.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ackerman</surname><given-names>S.L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative stress, cell cycle, and neurodegeneration</article-title><source>J. Clin. Investig</source><year>2003</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>785</fpage><lpage>793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12639981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1172/JCI18182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC153779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>K&#246;hrle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brigelius-Floh&#233;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>B&#246;ckA G&#228;rtner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Floh&#233;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selenium in biology: facts and medical perspectives</article-title><source>Biol. Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>381</volume><issue>9&#8211;10</issue><fpage>849</fpage><lpage>864</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11076017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1515/BC.2000.107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>X.D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C.P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of three virulence genes alt, ahp and aerA in Aeromonas hydrophila and their relationship with actual virulence to zebrafish. J. Appl</article-title><source>Microb</source><year>2011</year><volume>110</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>823</fpage><lpage>830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2011.04944.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21219556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Terhune</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peatman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evasion of mucosal defenses during <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila </italic>infection of channel catfish (<italic toggle="yes">Ictalurus punctatus</italic>) skin</article-title><source>Dev. Comp. Immunol</source><year>2013</year><volume>39</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23219904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.dci.2012.11.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The derivatization and antioxidant activities of yeast mannan</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol</source><year>2018</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>755</fpage><lpage>761</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28928062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2017.09.055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z.Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>W.D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mannan oligosaccharides application: multipath restriction from <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila </italic>infection in the skin barrier of grass carp (<italic toggle="yes">Ctenopharyngodon idella</italic>)</article-title><source>Front. Immunol</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>742107</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34733280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2021.742107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8559429</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuang</surname><given-names>S.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>C.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mannan oligosaccharides alleviate oxidative injury in the head kidney and spleen in grass carp (<italic toggle="yes">Ctenopharyngodon idella</italic>) via the Nrf2 signaling pathway after <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila </italic>infection</article-title><source>J. Ani. Sci. Biotech</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>58</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s40104-023-00844-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10105433</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37060042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Magouz</surname><given-names>F.I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salem</surname><given-names>M.F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moustafa</surname><given-names>E.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elkhamy</surname><given-names>S.A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of biomos and agrimos dietary supplementation on growth performance, feed utilization and immunological parameters of Nile tilapia (<italic toggle="yes">Oreochromis Niloticus</italic>) fingerlings</article-title><source>Slov. Vet. Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>56</volume><issue>Suppl 22</issue><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>98</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prebiotics</article-title><source>Best. Pract. Res. Clin. Gastroenterol</source><year>2004</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15123070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bpg.2003.10.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehrim</surname><given-names>A.I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Refaey</surname><given-names>M.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An overview of the implication of climate change on fish farming in Egypt</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><year>2023</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1679</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Merrifield</surname><given-names>D.L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dimitroglou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>S.J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>R.T.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The current status and future focus of probiotic and prebiotic applications for salmonids</article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>2010</year><volume>302</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mokashe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chavan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prajapati</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probiotics as potential antioxidants: a systematic review</article-title><source>J. Agric. Food. Chem</source><year>2015</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>3615</fpage><lpage>3626</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25808285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/jf506326t</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morano</surname><given-names>K.A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New tricks for an old dog: the evolving world of Hsp70</article-title><source>Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci</source><year>2007</year><volume>1113</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1196/annals.1391.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17513460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moustafa</surname><given-names>E.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawood</surname><given-names>M.A.O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Assar</surname><given-names>D.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>A.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elbialy</surname><given-names>Z.I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farrag</surname><given-names>F.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shukry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zayed</surname><given-names>M.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulatory effects of fenugreek seeds powder on the histopathology, oxidative status, and immune related gene expression in Nile tilapia <italic toggle="yes">(Oreochromis niloticus)</italic> infected with <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila</italic></article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>2019</year><volume>515</volume><fpage>734589</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>T.N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The utilization of soybean products in tilapia feed-a review</article-title><source>In Proceeding of (ISTA), 8th International Symposium on Tilapia in Aquaculture</source><year>2008</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>67</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishikimi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roa</surname><given-names>N.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yogi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The occurrence of supeoxide anion in the reaction of reduced phenazine methosulfate and molecular oxygen</article-title><source>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Comm</source><year>1972</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>849</fpage><lpage>854</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4400444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0006-291x(72)80218-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>NRC</collab><article-title>Nutrient requirements of fish and shrimp</article-title><year>2011</year><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Animal Nutrition Series, National Research Council of the National Academies. The National Academies Press</publisher-name><fpage>376</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohkawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohishi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yagi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assay for lipid peroxides in animal tissues by thiobarbituric acid reaction</article-title><source>Anal. Biochem</source><year>1979</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0003-2697(79)90738-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Osuigwe</surname><given-names>D.I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Obiekezie</surname><given-names>A.I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Onuoha</surname><given-names>G.C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Some hematological changes in hybrid catfish (<italic toggle="yes">Heterobranchus longifilis</italic> x <italic toggle="yes">Clarias gariepinus</italic>) fed different dietary levels of raw and boiled jack bean (<italic toggle="yes">Canavalia ensiformis</italic>) seed meal</article-title><source>Afr. J. Biotech</source><year>2005</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1017</fpage><lpage>1021</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>J.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>R.P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>S.G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reisinger</surname><given-names>H.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>S.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Grady</surname><given-names>K.E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>B.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agar</surname><given-names>M.H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why don&#8217;t out-of-treatment individuals enter methadone treatment programes? Int</article-title><source>J. Drug. Policy</source><year>2010</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drugpo.2008.07.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2790538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18805686</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poolsawat</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>M.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boonpeng</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dietary xylooligosaccharide improved growth, nutrient utilization, gut microbiota and disease resistance of tilapia (<italic toggle="yes">Oreochromis niloticus </italic>X <italic toggle="yes">O. aureus</italic>)</article-title><source>Anim. Feed. Sci. Technol</source><year>2021</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>114872</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prabu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajagopalsamy</surname><given-names>C.B.T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahilan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeevagan</surname><given-names>I.J.M.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Renuhadevi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tilapia&#8212;an excellent candidate species for world aquaculture: a review</article-title><source>Ann. Res. Rev. Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>31</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pineda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spectrophotometric quantitation of antioxidant capacity through the formation of a phosphomolybdenum complex: specific application to the determination of vitamin E</article-title><source>Anal. Biochem</source><year>1999</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10222007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/abio.1999.4019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reczek</surname><given-names>C.R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandel</surname><given-names>N.S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ROS-dependent signal transduction</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Cell. Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25305438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ceb.2014.09.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4380867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reda</surname><given-names>R.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Hady</surname><given-names>M.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selim</surname><given-names>K.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Sayed</surname><given-names>H.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative study of three predominant gut <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus</italic> strains and a commercial <italic toggle="yes">B. amyloliquefaciens</italic> as probiotics on the performance of <italic toggle="yes">Clarias gariepinus</italic></article-title><source>Fish. Shellfish. Immunol</source><year>2018</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>416</fpage><lpage>425</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29920384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.fsi.2018.06.031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muench</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple method of estimating fifty percent end points</article-title><source>Am. J. Trop. Med. Hyg</source><year>1938</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>493</fpage><lpage>497</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehulka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blood parameters in common carp with spontaneous spring viremia (SVC)</article-title><source>Aquac. Int</source><year>1996</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>182</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of dietary mannan oligosaccharide supplementation on growth performance, antioxidant capacity, non-specifc immunity and immune-related gene expression of juvenile hybrid grouper (<italic toggle="yes">Epinephelus lanceolatus</italic> &#9792; X <italic toggle="yes">Epinephelus fuscoguttatus </italic>&#9794;)</article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>2020</year><volume>523</volume><fpage>735195</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rigos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katharios</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kogiannou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cascarano</surname><given-names>C.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infectious diseases and treatment solutions of farmed greater amberjack <italic toggle="yes">Seriola dumerili </italic>with particular emphasis in Mediterranean region</article-title><source>Rev. Aquac</source><year>2021</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>323</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sado</surname><given-names>R.Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bicudo</surname><given-names>&#193;.J.D.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cyrino</surname><given-names>J.E.P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Feeding dietary mannan oligosaccharides to juvenile Nile tilapia,<italic toggle="yes"> Oreochromis niloticus</italic>, has no effect on hematological parameters and showed decreased feed consumption</article-title><source>J. World. Aquac. Soc</source><year>2008</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>821</fpage><lpage>826</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahoo</surname><given-names>P.K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>S.C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of dietary 1,3 &#946;-glucan on immune responses and disease resistance of healthy and aflatoxin B1-induced immune compromised rohu <italic toggle="yes">(Labeo rohita Hamilton)</italic></article-title><source>Fish. Shellfish. Immunol</source><year>2001</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>695</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11759039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/fsim.2001.0345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adel</surname><given-names>A.C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malachi</surname><given-names>A.W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donald</surname><given-names>A.D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> strain and the prebiotic previda on growth, immune parameters and susceptibility to <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila</italic> infection in Nile Tilapia</article-title><source>Aquac. Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>2017</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Satoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serum lipid peroxide in cerebrovascular disorders de-termined by a new colorimetric method</article-title><source>Clin. Chim. Acta</source><year>1978</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">719890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0009-8981(78)90081-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>A.K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zinta</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>AbdElgawad</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asard</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blust</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Boeck</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High environmental ammonia elicits differential oxidative stress and antioxidant responses in five different organs of a model estuarine teleost (<italic toggle="yes">Dicentrarchus labrax</italic>)</article-title><source>Comp. Biochem. Physiol. Part C. Toxicol. Pharmacol</source><year>2015</year><volume>174&#8211;175</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cbpc.2015.06.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26073360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smirnov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amit-Romach</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sklan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uni</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mucin dynamics and microbial populations in chicken small intestine are changed by dietary probiotic and antibiotic growth promoter supplementation</article-title><source>J. Nut</source><year>2005</year><volume>135</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/jn/135.2.187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15671211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Staykov</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spring</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Denev</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sweetman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of a mannan oligosaccharide on the growth performance and immune status of rainbow trout <italic toggle="yes">(Oncorhynchus mykiss).</italic> Aquac</article-title><source>Int</source><year>2007</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>161</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ta&#8217;ati</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soltani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahmani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zamini</surname><given-names>A.A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Growth performance, carcass composition and immune physiological indices in juvenile great sturgeon <italic toggle="yes">(Huso huso)</italic> fed on commercial prebiotic, immunoster</article-title><source>Iran. J. Fish. Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>324</fpage><lpage>335</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref76"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thrall</surname><given-names>M.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiser</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>R.W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>T.W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Veterinary hematology and clinical chemistry</article-title><year>2012</year><edition>2nd</edition><publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref77"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torrecillas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Makol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caballero</surname><given-names>M.J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montero</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhanasiri</surname><given-names>A.K.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sweetman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Izquierdo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects on mortality and stress response in European sea bass, <italic toggle="yes">Dicentrarchus labrax (L.),</italic> fed mannan oligosaccharides (MOS) after <italic toggle="yes">Vibrio anguillarum</italic> exposure</article-title><source>J. Fish. Dis</source><year>2012</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>591</fpage><lpage>602</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22690841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1365-2761.2012.01384.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref78"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turutoglu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ercelik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corlu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila</italic>-associated skin lesions and septicaemia in a Nile crocodile (<italic toggle="yes">Crocodylus niloticus</italic>)</article-title><source>J. S. Afr. Vet. Assoc</source><year>2012</year><volume>76</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4102/jsava.v76i1.393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15900900</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref79"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Urbinate</surname><given-names>E.C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>P.C.F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sodium chloride added to transport water and physiological responses of Matrinx&#227; <italic toggle="yes">Brycon amazonicus </italic>(Teleost: Caracidae)</article-title><source>Acta. Amaz</source><year>2006</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>572</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref80"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An accidental discovery of mannan-oligosaccharide&#8217;s protection effect against air exposure and its potential mechanism in hybrid grouper (<italic toggle="yes">Epinephelus lanceolatus</italic> X <italic toggle="yes">Epinephelus fuscoguttatus</italic> &#9794;)</article-title><source>Fish. Physiol. Biochem</source><year>2022</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>1285</fpage><lpage>1297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36048294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s10695-022-01118-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref81"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Welker</surname><given-names>T.L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of probiotics in diets of tilapia</article-title><source>J. Aquac. Res. Develop</source><year>2011</year><volume>S1</volume><fpage>014</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref82"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological responses of <italic toggle="yes">Phragmites australis </italic>to wastewater with different chemical oxygen demands</article-title><source>Ecol. Eng</source><year>2010</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1341</fpage><lpage>1347</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref83"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yal&#231;inkaya</surname><given-names>l</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#252;ng&#246;r</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bafialan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erdem</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mannan oligosaccharides (MOS) from <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> in broilers: effects on performance and blood biochemistry</article-title><source>Turk. J. Vet. Anim. Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>32</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>48</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref84"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The nonspecific immune system:humoral defense</article-title><source>Fish. Physiol</source><year>1997</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>157</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref85"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yassien</surname><given-names>S.H.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd El-Rahim</surname><given-names>S.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osman</surname><given-names>M.F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamouda</surname><given-names>R.E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soliman</surname><given-names>M.A.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nageib</surname><given-names>R.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors affecting aquaculture farms&#8217; profitability and constraints facing fish farmers in Egypt</article-title><source>Egypt. J. Aquat. Biol. Fish</source><year>2022</year><volume>26</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>527</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref86"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of dietary mannan oligosaccharide on growth performance, gut morphology and stress tolerance of juvenile Pacific white shrimp <italic toggle="yes">(Litopenaeus vannamei).</italic> Fish</article-title><source>Shellfish. Immunol</source><year>2012</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1027</fpage><lpage>1032</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.fsi.2012.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22584202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref87"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ai</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liufu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of dietary &#946;-glucan on the growth, immune responses and resistance of sea cucumber, <italic toggle="yes">Apostichopus japonicus</italic> against <italic toggle="yes">Vibrio splendidus</italic> infection</article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>2011</year><volume>315</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>274</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref88"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buentello</surname><given-names>J.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gatlin</surname><given-names>D.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of dietary prebiotics on growth performance, immune response and intestinal morphology of red drum (<italic toggle="yes">Sciaenops ocellatus</italic>)</article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>2010</year><volume>309</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>257</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref89"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>J.G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dietary prebiotic inulin benefits on growth performance, antioxidant capacity, immune response and intestinal microbiota in Pacific white shrimp <italic toggle="yes">(Litopenaeus vannamei)</italic> at low salinity</article-title><source>Aquaculture</source><year>2020</year><volume>518</volume><fpage>734847</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref90"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of five prebiotics on growth, antioxidant capacity, non-specific immunity, stress resistance, and disease resistance of juvenile hybrid grouper (<italic toggle="yes">Epinephelus fuscoguttatus </italic>&#9792; X <italic toggle="yes">Epinephelus lanceolatus</italic> &#9794;)</article-title><source>Animals</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>754</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36830542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ani13040754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9952795</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>