<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2846</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">openvetj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Veterinary Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2226-4485</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2218-6050</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tripoli</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11563609</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11563609.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11563609</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11563609</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39553766</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/OVJ.2024.v14.i9.18</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OVJ-14-2294</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">In vivo</italic> toxicity study in Sprague&#8211;Dawley rats receiving different doses of <italic toggle="yes">Moringa oleifera</italic> extract</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kambuno</surname><given-names initials="NT">Norma Tiku</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Louisa</surname><given-names initials="M">Melva</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wuyung</surname><given-names initials="PE">Puspita Eka</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silaen</surname><given-names initials="OSM">Otto Sahat Martua</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Supali</surname><given-names initials="T">Taniawati</given-names></name><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Doctoral Program in Biomedical Sciences, Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Indonesia, Jakarta, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Medical Laboratory Technology, Poltekkes Kemenkes Kupang, Kupang, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Pharmacology and Therapeutics, Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Indonesia, Jakarta, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Animal Research Facility, Indonesia Medical Education and Research Institute, Jakarta, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Department of Pathological Anatomy, Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Indonesia, Jakarta, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>Animal Health Diagnostic Unit, PT Media Satwa Laboratories, Bogor, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label>Department of Parasitology, Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Indonesia, Jakarta, Indonesia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Taniawati Supali. Department of Parasitology, Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Indonesia, Jakarta, Indonesia. <email>taniawati@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>9</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">475085</issue-id><fpage>2294</fpage><lpage>2309</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-11-18 15:25:24.860"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2294.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Protein deficiency poses a significant challenge during the growth and development of children. <italic toggle="yes">Moringa oleifera</italic> Lam (MO) leaves, renowned for their high protein content, present a potential solution to address amino acid imbalances in protein-deficient conditions.</p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>This study aimed to evaluate the toxicity of MO leaf extract in Sprague-Dawley Rats.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>Protein extraction from <italic toggle="yes">Moringa oleifera</italic> (MO) leaves was performed using ultrasonic-assisted extraction (UAE) with ethanol. The ethanol leaf extract of MO (EEMO) was then characterized for protein content, amino acids, minerals, phytic acid, and phytochemicals. Antioxidant activity was assessed using the DPPH (2,2-diphenyl-1-picryl-hydrazyl-hydrate) test, while cytotoxicity was evaluated using the MTT (3-(4,5-dimethylthiazolyl-2)-2,5 diphenyltetrazolium bromide) assay on HepG2 and Madin-Darby canine kidney (MDCK) cells. EEMO was tested for acute toxicity in 60 healthy male and female Sprague&#8211;Dawley rats. The rats were divided into five groups of five rats each, receiving single oral doses of 5, 50, 300, 2,000, and 5,000 mg/kg body weight (BW) of EEMO. Observations were conducted daily till day 14 before the necropsy of rats. Liver and kidney tissues were harvested and preserved in 10% formalin for histopathological analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>The extraction process revealed a protein content of 45.5%, with phenylalanine being the predominant essential amino acid at 22.25 mg/g, and glutamic acid as the dominant non-essential amino acid at 60.03 mg/g. Potassium (1174.23 mg/100 g) and selenium (149 mg/100 g) were identified as the primary macro and micro minerals, respectively. The IC<sub>50</sub> and CC<sub>50</sub> values for antioxidant and cytotoxic activities in HepG2 and MDCK were found to be 41.04,182.66, and 121.04 ppm, respectively. Toxicity testing on experimental animals resulted in an LD<sub>50</sub> value of 5,000 mg/kg BW for EEMO, indicating its relative safety upon oral administration.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>MO extract produced by the UAE extraction method, containing high-quality food-grade protein, showed no cytotoxic effects on HepG2 and MDCK cells and exhibited no acute toxicity in rats.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Antioxidant</kwd><kwd>Cytotoxicity</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Moringa oleifera</italic></kwd><kwd>Protein</kwd><kwd>Toxicity</kwd><kwd>Ultrasound assisted extraction</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Protein plays a vital role in cellular maintenance and tissue building, a function that cannot be replaced by other nutrients. A deficiency in protein can significantly impact tissue development and cellular metabolism. In children, protein deficiency often manifests as underweight and stunting, with repercussions on the immune system, hepatic steatosis, muscle mass reduction, and cognitive disorders or delays in intellectual development (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Bourke <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>).</p><p>Various interventions have been explored to address protein deficiency, including the provision of food supplements (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Bourke <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). Protein sources can be derived from both plant and animal origins. While animal proteins are advantageous due to their high protein content and good digestibility, they are often expensive and inaccessible for those living below the poverty line (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Gidamis <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2003</xref>).</p><p>The <italic toggle="yes">Moringa oleifera</italic> Lam (MO) plant from Moringaceae family, known for its high protein content, thrives in various seasons and is drought-resistant, making it an excellent source of plant protein. Particularly, MO leaves are rich in fiber, vitamins, minerals, proteins, and other significant phytochemicals. Extensive research has shown that MO leaves contain protein levels ranging between 23% and 27% (<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Teixeira <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>).</p><p>MO extracts, derived from leaves, seeds, and bark, are highly concentrated in antioxidants, anti-inflammatory agents, and other beneficial compounds with medicinal properties. These extracts are often included in supplements, skincare, and health and wellness products (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Matic <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">Tshabalala <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Granella <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). Methods such as cold pressing, solvent extraction, and supercritical fluid extraction (SFE) are utilized to obtain these extracts. Several studies have highlighted that the highest protein content was found in leaf flour, dried leaves, and fresh leaves (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Gidamis <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Pe&#241;alver <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>).</p><p>Plant proteins, such as those from <italic toggle="yes">Spirulina platensis</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Camellia sinensis</italic> leaves, and <italic toggle="yes">Moringa oleifera</italic> (MO) leaves, are generally cell-bound, necessitating effective extraction methods to release them (Garcia-Salas <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2010; <xref rid="ref61" ref-type="bibr">Yucetepe <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Menezes <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>; Cheng <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021). Traditional techniques, such as maceration, are often used for extracting bioactive or phytochemical compounds. However, these methods have several disadvantages, including the need for large quantities of solvents or reagents, daily solvent replacement, environmental concerns, prolonged extraction times (3&#8211;5 days), lower protein content, and reduced yields in the final extract (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Alhakmani <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">Vongsak <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref62" ref-type="bibr">Zeitoun <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>).</p><p>Recently, novel extraction technologies like ultrasound-assisted extraction (UAE) have attracted attention for their reduced processing times, lower energy consumption, and higher extraction efficiency (Garcia-Salas <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2010; <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Cao <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). Fatima <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. reported a protein extraction yield of 39.12% from MO seeds using UAE, with an optimal extraction time of 20 minutes (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Fatima <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). Similarly, Kingwascharapong <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. achieved optimal protein extraction from <italic toggle="yes">Bombay locusts</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Patanga succinta L</italic>.) under UAE conditions with 60% amplitude and a 20-minutes extraction time (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Kingwascharapong <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>).</p><p>This study aims to characterize the compounds extracted from MO using the UAE method and to examine their acute toxicity in an animal model. These assessments are essential to determine the appropriate dosage of the extracts for potential use in humans, as required by the National Food and Drug Agency (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">BPOM, 2022</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Sample collection and species identification</title><p>MO leaves were collected from November 2021 to March 2022 from Kupang Regency in East Nusa Tenggara (NTT), Indonesia. To confirm the species of the MO leaves, samples were submitted to the Depokensis Herbarium (DEP) at the University of Indonesia&#8217;s Biota collection room with certificate number 851/UN2.F3.II/PDP.02.00/2021 on December 1, 2021; and to the Bogoriense Herbarium with certificate number B-168/II.6.2/DI.05.07/6/2022 on June 7, 2022. Species identification was carried out using reference materials and comparisons with herbarium collections in the Department of Biology, Faculty of Mathematics and Natural Sciences, Universitas Indonesia by Mr. Alexander Tianara, Botanical and Zoological Specimen Curator of Biota Collection Room, and Mr. Alex Sumadijaya, Plant Systematist at Herbarium Bogoriense, Research Center for Biosystematics and Evolution, from Bogoriense Herbarium, Directorate of Scientific Collection Management, National Research and Innovation Agency (BRIN). The voucher specimen of MO is maintained in the Directorate of Scientific Collection Management, BRIN-Indonesia.</p></sec><sec><title>Sample preparation</title><p>A total of 2.8 kg of fresh MO leaves underwent several preparation steps. Initially, the leaves were thoroughly washed and air dried. They were then dried for 24 hours in a 42&#176;C oven, a temperature safe for preserving the protein content. The weight of the dried leaves was recorded. Subsequently, the dried leaves were finely ground into a powder using a knife mill to achieve a particle size of 100 mesh. The resultant MO powder was carefully stored in a sealed container to maintain its quality. All methods were conducted in accordance with the International Union for Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources (IUCN) Policy Statement on Research Involving Species at Risk of Extinction.</p></sec><sec><title>Ultrasonic assisted extraction</title><p>Ultrasonic-assisted extraction (UAE) of MO from dried leaves followed a modified procedure outlined by Dadi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2019a). Fifty grams of MO leaf powder was mixed with 70% ethanol in a 1:10 (w/v) ratio. The extraction was performed using an ultrasonic bath (Ultrasonic H-D Ultra Selecta<sup>&#174;</sup>) operating at 40 kHz, at 40&#176;C, with an ultrasonic input power of 400 W. The mixture was then filtered through Whatman filter paper no. 1. The filtrate was concentrated using a rotary evaporator system (Buchi<sup>&#174;</sup> R-215 Rotary Evaporator with B-491 Heating Bath, V700 Vacuum Pump, V850 Vacuum Controller and F-100 Chiller) under the following conditions: vapor temperature of 50&#176;C, system pressure of 175 mbar, bath temperature of 50&#176;C, and condenser temperature of 20&#176;C. The concentrated solution was freeze-dried for 24 hours using a Hypercool<sup>&#174;</sup> Cooling Trap HC3110 at &#8722;110&#176;C and 1.3 &#215; 10<sup>&#8722;1</sup> Pa to obtain dry extracts, which were weighed and stored at 4&#176;C in a light-protected container.</p><p>Different durations of ethanol incubation were applied in this study. To ensure the reliability of the method, the extraction process using ethanol for 60 minutes, which produced a high protein content, was repeated four times.</p></sec><sec><title>Characterization of ethanol extract of MO leaves (EEMO)</title><p>EEMO was analyzed for protein, proximate chemical, mineral, and amino acid content, as well as mycotoxin contamination, moisture content, ethanol content, total plate count, yeast mold, bacterial contamination (including <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli, Enterobacteriaceae, Salmonella sp., Shigella sp.,</italic> and<italic toggle="yes"> Clostridium</italic>), and heavy metal contamination. These tests are necessary to meet the standard qualifications set by the National Food and Drug Agency of Indonesia Regulation Standard Number 32 of 2019 (BPOM RI, 2019). All tests were conducted by SNI ISO/IEC 17025:2017-certified laboratories, PT. Saraswanti Indo Genetech, Jakarta, Indonesia, accredited by the National Accreditation Committee (KAN) with number LP-184-IDN.</p></sec><sec><title>Phytic acid content determination</title><p>The phytic acid content was determined using the method described by Davies <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (1979). First, 1 g of the sample was suspended in 50 ml of 0.5 M HNO<sub>3</sub>. This suspension was stirred with a magnetic stirrer for 2 hours at room temperature and then filtered to obtain the filtrate. The phytic acid content was analyzed by mixing 0.5 ml of the filtrate, 0.9 ml of 0.5 M HNO<sub>3</sub>, and 1 ml of 0.3 mM FeCl<sub>3</sub> in a test tube. The test tube was closed and then soaked in boiling water for 20 minutes. After cooling down, 5 ml of amyl alcohol and 1 ml of 0.1 mM ammonium thiocyanate were added, followed by centrifugation (Eppendorf<sup>&#174;</sup> EP-5804) at 1.500 rpm for 10 minutes. Once two layers were formed, the absorbance of the amyl alcohol layer was measured using a spectrophotometer (Agilent<sup>&#174;</sup> Technology Type Cary 60) at a wavelength of 465 nm, with an amyl alcohol blank measured 15 minutes after adding ammonium thiocyanate.</p><p>
<bold>Phytochemical analysis</bold>
</p><p>The phytochemical components of EEMO were identified using liquid chromatography mass spectrometry/mass spectrometry (LCMS-MS) in positive ion mode. The extract was dissolved in an appropriate solvent and injected in a volume of 1 &#181;l of water for analysis. The electrospray ionization (ESI) mode was set to full scan m/z of 100&#8211;1,200. The mobile phase consisted of H<sub>2</sub>O+0.1% formic acid and acetonitrile + 0.1% formic acid. Analysis was performed on an LCMS-MS Waters&#8482; Acquity UPLC-1 Class and XEVO G2-XS QT of, ACQUITY UPLCTM BEH C18 column (1.7 &#181;hm 2.1 &#215; 50 mm), and XEVO G2-XS TOF mass spectroscopy.</p><p><bold>Antioxidant activity assay</bold>
</p><p>The possible antioxidant activities of EEMO were investigated using the DPPH (2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl-hydrate) assay as described by Desmarchelier <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (1997) and Rahman <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., (2015). Extracts at various concentrations (12.5&#8211;150 g/ml) were mixed with 2.4 ml of 0.1 mM DPPH. The solution mixture was vortexed and stored in the dark at room temperature for 30 minutes. The absorbance was measured by spectrophotometry at 517 nm, with butylated hydroxytoluene (BHT) as a reference. The IC<sub>50</sub> value was determined by plotting the concentration of EEMO (<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>-axis) and DPPH inhibition absorbance (<italic toggle="yes">y</italic>-axis) into a linear regression. The resulting straight-line equation was used to calculate the IC<sub>50</sub> value at <italic toggle="yes">y</italic> = 50%.</p></sec><sec><title>Cytotoxicity test</title><p>The cytotoxicity potential of EEMO was studied in HepG2 and Madin&#8211;Darby canine kidney (MDCK) cells using the MTT (3-(4,5-dimethylthiazolyl-2)-2,5 diphenyltetrazolium bromide) test by adopting the procedure from previous study (Abd-Rabou <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017; <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Barhoi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>a). HepG2 and MDCK cells were cultured in a complete medium containing Roswell Park Memorial Institute (RPMI), 10% Fetal Bovine Serum, 1% penicillin&#8211;streptomycin, and 1% amphotericin B in a 5% CO<sub>2</sub> incubator. Briefly, 10.000 cells of HepG2 or MDCK were grown in 96-well plates and treated with various concentrations of MO extracts (ranging from 3.0 to 500 &#956;g/mL) for 24 hours. Afterward, the cells were incubated with MTT reagents. The absorbance of the viable cells was then measured using an ELISA reader at a wavelength of 590 nm. The absorbance values were used to create a relationship curve between concentration and percentage of inhibition. From this curve, the concentration of MO extracts that inhibit 50% of cell viability (CC<sub>50</sub>) was determined.</p></sec><sec><title>In vivo acute toxicity analysis in animals</title><p>An in-vivo acute toxicity analysis was conducted using experimental animals. Acute toxicity testing was conducted in accordance with the guidelines set forth by the Food and Drug Administration (Badan Pengawas Obat dan Makanan) Number 10 of 2022 regarding preclinical in vivo toxicity testing (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">BPOM, 2022</xref>).</p><p>Healthy Sprague&#8211;Dawley rats aged 8&#8211;12 weeks, consisting of 30 males and 30 females (150&#8211;200 grams), were utilized, ensuring a weight variation of no more than 20% within each group. Female rats selected for the study had never given birth and were not pregnant. The rats were obtained from the Animal Breeding Facility of the National Food and Drug Agency (BPOM). Prior to the experiment, the rats were acclimatized for one week in a controlled environment with a temperature of 22&#176;&#177;3&#176; C, relative humidity of 30%&#8211;70%, and a 12-hours light/dark cycle. They were provided with standard laboratory feed and allowed access to water ad libitum. The test animals were fasted for 14&#8211;18 hours before treatment.</p><p>The rats were divided into five groups of six, each receiving different doses of EEMO: 5, 50, 300, 2,000, and 5,000 mg/kg BW, administered orally as a single dose. The test animals were observed individually for at least 30 minutes post-administration, with periodic checks every 4 hours during the first 24 hours, followed by daily observations for 14 days. Monitoring parameters included body weight (BW), skin condition, fur quality, eye appearance, mucous membranes, respiration, autonomic nervous system, and central nervous system. On the final day of observation, all rats underwent necropsy under anesthesia using ketamine (35 mg/kg BW) and xylazine (5 mg/kg BW). Liver and kidney tissues were harvested and preserved in 10% formalin for histopathological analysis. The LD<sub>50</sub> value was calculated according to BPOM Regulation No. 10 of 2022 (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">BPOM, 2022</xref>), based on the number of animal deaths and observed toxic symptoms.</p></sec><sec><title>Histological analysis</title><p>Tissue sectioning, paraffin block preparation, and tissue staining were performed at the Anatomic Pathology Laboratory, Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Indonesia. Liver and kidney tissue samples were collected and immediately preserved in 10% formalin for 24 hours. The dehydration process involved a series of graded alcohols, followed by clearing in xylene and paraffin block creation. The liver and kidney tissue sections were stained using hematoxylin and eosin (HE). All regions within the liver and kidney were observed at 10 High Power Fields (&#215;40) under a binocular light microscope (LEICA<sup>&#174;</sup> DM 1000 L30) and recorded using a SIGMA<sup>&#174;</sup> HD microscope camera/HDMI/USB with the IndoMicroview 3.7 digital camera application.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>IC<sub>50</sub> and CC<sub>50</sub> values were analyzed using Excel, employing linear regression of log concentration). The IC<sub>50</sub> value was derived from the linear equation relating log concentration (<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>-axis) to the percentage of inhibition (<italic toggle="yes">y</italic>-axis) from three repeated measurements of the sample. Similarly, the CC<sub>50</sub> value was obtained from the linear equation relating the log concentration of the test solution (<italic toggle="yes">x</italic>-axis) to the percentage of live cells (<italic toggle="yes">y</italic>-axis). Both IC<sub>50</sub> and CC<sub>50</sub> values were determined by substituting <italic toggle="yes">y</italic> = 50% into the linear regression equations. Differences in organ weights between the normal and treatment groups were analyzed using ANOVA, followed by Tukey&#8217;s multiple comparison test for post-hoc analysis. All statistical analyses were performed using GraphPad Prism 10.2.2 for Windows.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>In this study, the ethical approval was received from the Ethics Committee, Faculty of Medicine, Universitas Indonesia (KET-640/UN2.F1/ETIK/PPM.00.02/2022, June 27, 2022).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Optimal results of MO leaves extract in ethanol extraction using UAE method</title><p>The MO leaves used in this study were collected from the Kupang Regency in NTT. The duration of the extractions using the UAE method resulted in variations in protein content. Notably, the extraction of MO leaves from the Kupang Regency region using ethanol for 60 minutes yielded the highest protein content at 45.5%. Different durations of ethanol incubation were applied in this study, and the results showed that longer incubation times increased the protein yield. The net yield of MO extracts from dried leaves was 0.71%, with protein content ranging from 39.8% to 45.5% (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). A proximate analysis was performed to compare the levels of protein, fat, carbohydrates, water, ash, and crude fiber in unextracted MO leaves powder and MO leaves extracts obtained from the optimal protein extraction using ethanol (EEMO) for 60 minutes with the UAE method. The results, shown in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, indicate a difference in protein content between unextracted MO powder (28.76%) and EEMO (45.5%) extracted using the UAE method.</p></sec><sec><title>Examination of EEMO using standard test for herbal medicine</title><p>The extracted protein obtained from EEMO was examined using standard tests for herbal medicine. The results indicated that our extracts fully met the criteria for herbal medicine, including standards for aflatoxin levels, heavy metals, microbiological safety, moisture content (&lt;10%), and ethanol content (&lt;1%) (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Determination of essential and non-essential amino acids from EEMO</title><p>The EEMO was analyzed to determine the contents of essential and non-essential amino acids (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Eight types of essential amino acids were found, with phenylalanine (22.25 mg/g), valine (13.09 mg/g), threonine (6.41 mg/g), and leucine (5.84 mg/g) presented in the highest concentrations. Additionally, eight types of non-essential acids were detected, with glutamic acid (60.03 mg/g) found in the highest concentration followed by aspartic (40.33 mg/g), arginine (14.69 mg/g) and alanine (13.50 mg/g).</p></sec><sec><title>Determination of minerals and phytic acid flavonoids content from EEMO</title><p>The EEMO was analyzed to determine its mineral content. Among the macro-elements, potassium was found to be the highest concentration (1,174.23 mg/100 g), followed by chloride and magnesium (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). For the microelements, selenium was the most abundant element, with copper, zinc, and iron also presented in notable amounts (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p><p>The results of the phytochemical analysis revealed that the major compounds were flavonoids, such as kaempferol-3,7-diglucoside, kaempferol-3-O-rutinoside, and kaempferol-7-O-&#945;-L-rhamnoside, as well as phenyl propionic acid, as shown in the chromatogram (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>) and detailed in <xref rid="tab5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>. To confirm the presence of phytic acid in EEMO, which does not inhibit nutrient absorption, we measured its level using spectrophotometry and a phytic acid standard series. The analysis indicated that the phytic acid content in EEMO was 13 mg/g.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Antioxidant potential with low cytotoxicity of EEMO</italic>
</p><p>The antioxidant activity of EEMO was demonstrated with the IC<sub>50</sub> 41.04 ppm, while ascorbic acid, used as the positive control of antioxidant agent, had an IC<sub>50</sub> of 15.8 ppm (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). The concentrations of EEMO needed to produce antioxidant activity were substantially lower than those required to induce cytotoxicity in HepG2 and MDCK cell lines. The cytotoxicity of EEMO was assessed using the MTT [3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide] assay. The cytotoxicity activity (CC<sub>50</sub>) of HepG2 and MDCK were 182.66 and 121.04 ppm, respectively (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>a and b).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>The process of MO extraction from fresh leaves to freeze-dried extracts.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2294-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Safety of EEMO on test animals</title><p>The EEMO used in this study underwent acute oral toxicity testing at doses of 5, 50, 300, 2,000, and 5,000 mg/kg BW. The results indicated an LD<sub>50 </sub>value exceeding 5,000 mg/kg BW, with no signs of toxicity observed at the highest dose (<xref rid="tab6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). Throughout the 14-days observation period, no abnormalities were found in the skin, fur, eyes, mucous membranes, respiratory system, autonomic nervous system, and central nervous system, in any of the rats treated with different doses of EEMO. No animals displayed severe pain or distress at the end of the study. The effect of EEMO on BW is shown in Figure 5. There were no significant differences in the average BW of male and female groups receiving different doses of EEMO compared to the control group (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Organs such as the brain, lungs, heart, liver, kidneys, spleen, and gut from all groups were harvested after euthanasia. The organ weights of both male and female subjects in all EEMO treatment groups also did not significantly differ from those of the control group (<xref rid="tab7" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Proximate analysis of MO leaves powder <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> EEMO<sup>a</sup> from Kupang Regency.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample content</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MO leaves powder</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEMO</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water, %<break/>Ash, %<break/>Carbohydrate, %<break/>Protein, %<break/>Crude Fat, %<break/>Crude Fiber, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.35<break/>13.82<break/>34.15<break/>28.76<break/>7.49<break/>10.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.63<break/>10.20<break/>36.86<break/>45.50<break/>1.10<break/>1.81</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p><sup>a</sup>EEMO: Ethanol leaf extract of MO<italic toggle="yes">.</italic></p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Examination results of EEMO<sup>a</sup> following herbal medicine standard.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unit</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Content in EEMO</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quality standards<sup>b</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aflatoxin G2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#181;g/kg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804; 20 &#181;g/kg</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aflatoxin B2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#181;g/kg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804; 20 &#181;g/kg</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aflatoxin G1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#181;g/kg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804; 20 &#181;g/kg</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aflatoxin B1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#181;g/kg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804; 20 &#181;g/kg</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total aflatoxin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#181;g/kg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804; 20 &#181;g/kg</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water content</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;10%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;10%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethanol content</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#181;g/kg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;1%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;1%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total plate content</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">colony/g</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;10<sup>5</sup>colony/g</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804; 10<sup>5</sup>colony/g</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yeast and mould</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">colony/g</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;10<sup>3</sup>colony/g</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804; 10<sup>3</sup>colony/g</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">colony/g</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;10 colony/g</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804; 10 colony/g</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">colony/g</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;10<sup>3</sup>colony/g</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804; 10<sup>3</sup>colony/g</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Salmonella </italic>sp.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/g</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">negative/g</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">negative/g</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Shigella </italic>sp.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/g</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">negative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">negative/g</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Clostridium </italic>sp.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/g</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">negative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">negative/g</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arsenic (As)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/kg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804; 5 mg/kg</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mercury (Hg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/kg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804; 0.5 mg/kg</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cadmium (Cd)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/kg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804; 0.3 mg/kg</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lead (Pb)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/kg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804; 10 mg/kg</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>EEMO: ethanol leaf extract of MO, <sup>b</sup>: standard value was issued by the Indonesian National Agency for Food and Drug Control (PerKa BPOM no 32/2019). <sup>c</sup>: ND, not detected.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Analysis results of amino acid composition in EEMO<sup>a</sup>.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of amino acid</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concentrations (mg/g)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Essential amino acid</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histidine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.23</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isoleucine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.99</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leucine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.84</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lysine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenylalanine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Threonine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.41</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tryptophan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.09</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>Non-essential amino acid</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glutamic acid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">aspartic acid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.33</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arginine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.69</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alanine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.50</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proline</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tyrosine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.07</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>EEMO: Ethanol leaf extract of MO<italic toggle="yes">.</italic></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><title>Analysis result of mineral content in EEMO<sup>a</sup>.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mineral</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concentrations (mg/100 g)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Macro elements<break/>Chloride (Cl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">734.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potassium (K)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1174.23</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Magnesium (Mg)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">251.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcium (Ca)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">723.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microelements<break/>Zinc (Zn)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iron (Fe)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Copper (Cu)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Selenium (Se)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>EEMO: Ethanol leaf extract of MO.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>LC-MS/MS chromatogram showing the presence of bioactive compounds in EEMO.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2294-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>
<bold>HE staining of liver and kidney tissue</bold>
</p><p>The liver and kidneys are crucial organs in drug metabolism; therefore, histopathological evaluations were focused on these tissues as shown in Figure 6. The liver histology results at all doses revealed no damage to the liver architecture (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>A). Similarly, the kidney histology results showed no damage to the architecture, though there was slight congestion of the hepatocytes in the treated groups (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>A and B).</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Our study successfully extracted protein from MO leaves using the ultrasonic extraction (UAE) method with ethanol as the solvent, yielding up to 45.5% protein content. The ethanol-extracted MO (EEMO) exhibited high levels of flavonoids, complete amino acids, and complete minerals, and met the extract characterization standards set by the National Food and Drug Agency (BPOM). Our findings also showed that the toxicity dose of EEMO was six to seven times higher than the antioxidant dose on HepG2 cells and eight times higher on MDCK cells. The results of the acute oral toxicity test showed no death signs at the highest tested dose of 5.000 g/kg BW.</p><p>The UAE method has been developed as a cost-effective, low-temperature, solvent-efficient, environmentally friendly technique, with short extraction times and high yields for extracting bioactive compounds from different plant materials (<xref rid="ref64" ref-type="bibr">Zheng <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2016</xref>). It is particularly effective in producing extracts rich in nutritional components and phytochemicals using various solvents (Garcia-Salas <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2010; <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Dadi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>b). The primary mechanism of UAE in releasing protein from cells is based on cavitation phenomena and mechanical mixing effects. Ultrasonic energy from the ultrasonic bath causes the cell walls of MO to break due to the explosion of cavitation bubbles on the surface of the MO powder. This facilitates mass transfer and allows for greater ethanol penetration into the cells of MO, increasing the contact surface area between the MO cells and ethanol, thus resulting in rapid solute diffusion from the solid phase to the solvent phase (<xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">Toma <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Dranca and Oroian, 2016</xref>; Patil and Akamanchi, 2017).</p><p>Several studies have also reported the use of ethanol as a solvent for protein extraction, including ethanolic extract from <italic toggle="yes">Anneslea fragrans</italic> Wall (<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">Mentha piperita</italic> leaf extract, and <italic toggle="yes">Stevia rebaudiana</italic> (Bert.) leaf extract (<xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr">Zorzenon <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). The choice of solvent can significantly impact the quality of extraction and may even damage proteins. Both water and ethanol are recommended solvents for food processing by the National Food and Drug Agency (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">BPOM, 2023</xref>), food authorities in the USA, Australia, New Zealand, and the European Food Safety Authority (Carrillo-&#193;lvarez, 2023). Ethanol has the advantage of a low boiling point, is easily separated from the product, and can dissolve proteins (<xref rid="ref63" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref60" ref-type="bibr">Yu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Lafarga <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). The use of ethanol in industry has also developed because it is inexpensive and relatively non-toxic compared to acetone and methanol. It can also be used for various extraction methods, and its extraction products are safe for medicines and food (Jim&#233;nez-Moreno <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019; <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><title>Phytochemical compounds found in EEMO<sup>a</sup>. </title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compounds</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chemical formula</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chemical structure</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Observed m/z</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Retention time (minutes)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kaempferol-3,7-diglucoside</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>27</sub>H<sub>30</sub>O<sub>16</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2294-g007.jpg"/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">611.1633</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kaempferol-3-O-rutinoside</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>27</sub>H<sub>30</sub>O<sub>15</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2294-g008.jpg"/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">595.1684</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kaempferol-7-O-&#945;-L-rhamnoside</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>21</sub>H<sub>20</sub>O<sub>10</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2294-g009.jpg"/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">433.1143</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenyl propionic acid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>9</sub>H<sub>11</sub>NO<sub>2</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2294-g010.jpg"/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">166.0862</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tryptophan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>11</sub>H<sub>12</sub>N<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2294-g011.jpg"/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">205.0970</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.12</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>EEMO: ethanol leaf extract of MO.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>MO leaves are known for their high protein. Several studies have reported protein content in MO leaves ranging from 23%&#8211;27% (D&#8217;Auria <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023), depending on the part of the plant. Additionally, previous studies have reported the protein yield from MO leaves extracts from many areas ranging from 6.7%&#8211;33.82% (fresh leaves) (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">Sena <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1998</xref>; Reyes S&#225;nchez <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2006), 24.2%&#8211;29.8% (dried leaves) (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Hadju <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>), 27.1% (leaves flour), and 2.5% (seeds) (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Citra, 2019</xref>). Our extraction method, using the UAE extraction with ethanol solvent for 60 minutes, resulted in an optimal yield of protein obtained by ethanol extraction was 45.5% (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><title>Antioxidant activity of EEMO (A) compared to ascorbic acid (B) as a positive control. The antioxidant activity was measured using the DPPH radical scavenging assay, and the results are expressed as the percentage of DPPH inhibition.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2294-g003.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig4" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><title>Cytotoxicity concentrations of EEMO in (A) HepG2 and (B) MDCK cell lines.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2294-g004.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tab6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6.</label><caption><title>Acute toxicity (oral) in female and male mice 14 days after EEMO<sup>a</sup> consumption.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Group</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Doses mg/kg BW</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">D/T<sup>b</sup></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Signs of toxicity observed</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2 ml H<sub>2</sub>0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No toxic changes observed</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No toxic changes observed</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No toxic changes observed</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">300</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No toxic changes observed</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No toxic changes observed</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No toxic changes observed</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>EEMO: Ethanol leaf extract of MO; <sup>b</sup>D/T: Number of mice deaths/total number of mice (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig5" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><title>The effect of EEMO on BW.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2294-g005.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tab7" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 7.</label><caption><title>Comparison of organ weights in male and female mice due to administration of various concentrations of EEMO<sup>a</sup>.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Mice Sex</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Organ</th><th colspan="6" rowspan="1">Dose of EEMO (mg/kg BW)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">300</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,000</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,000</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="7" colspan="1">
<bold>Male</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79 &#177; 0.021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.74 &#177; 0.065</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71 &#177; 0.066</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79 &#177; 0.054</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76 &#177; 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81 &#177; 0.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27 &#177; 0.171</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 &#177; 0.190</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.252 &#177; 0.078</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49 &#177; 0.160</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.260 &#177; 0.129</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34 &#177; 0.093</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 &#177; 0.036</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 &#177; 0.055</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 &#177; 0.023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 &#177; 0.094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 &#177; 0.088</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 &#177; 0.052</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.65 &#177; 0.590</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.70 &#177; 0.575</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.06 &#177; 0.580</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.87 &#177; 0.884</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.52 &#177; 0.530</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.73 &#177; 1.018</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kidney</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95 &#177; 0.100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56 &#177; 0.194</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.72 &#177; 0.113</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.07 &#177; 0.196</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81 &#177; 0.108</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05 &#177; 10.771</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spleen</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 &#177; 0.111</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 &#177; 0.064</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 &#177; 0.046</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 &#177; 0.037</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 &#177; 0.066</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56 &#177; 0.024</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gut</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.17 &#177; 1.624</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.50 &#177; 0.616</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9 &#177; 1.459</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.04 &#177; 3.165</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.64 &#177; 3.275</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.33 &#177; 2.431</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="9" colspan="1">
<bold>Female</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Organ</td><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>Dose of EEMO (mg/kg BW)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>50</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>300</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2,000</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5,000</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61 &#177; 0.145</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71 &#177; 0.074</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 &#177; 0.105</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66 &#177; 0.107</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76 &#177; 0.047</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76 &#177; 0.051</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 &#177; 0.167</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29 &#177; 0.144</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 &#177; 0.245</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 &#177; 0.317</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54 &#177; 0.131</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57 &#177; 0.221</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 &#177; 0.054</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 &#177; 0.103</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68 &#177; 0.108</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 &#177; 0.031</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 &#177; 0.124</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 &#177; 0.090</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.92 &#177; 0.365</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.60 &#177; 1.070</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.50 &#177; 1.141</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.68 &#177; 0.690</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.60 &#177; 0.614</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.40 &#177; 1.117</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kidney</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71 &#177; 0.152</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56 &#177; 0.118</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55 &#177; 0.176</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56 &#177; 0.108</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56 &#177; 0.174</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54 &#177; 0.187</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spleen</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36 &#177; 0.112</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 &#177; 0.131</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 &#177; 0.190</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44 &#177; 0.042</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 &#177; 0.071</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46 &#177; 0.112</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gut</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.75 &#177; 2.036</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.92 &#177; 4.076</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.66 &#177; 2.767</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.93 &#177; 3.037</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.81 &#177; 2.370</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.09 &#177; 3.657</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>EEMO: Ethanol leaf extract of MO. Data are presented as the mean &#177; SD, median (range) (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5), Results were analyzed using O<italic toggle="yes">ne-way</italic> Anova, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value &lt; 0.05, <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> test or tukeys <italic toggle="yes">multiple comparisons test.</italic></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig6" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><title>Micrographs of the liver and kidney sections obtained from the normal group and the group treated with high doses of EEMO (5,000 mg/kg BB) are presented. Magnification: 400x. In (A), yellow arrows indicate the normal hepatocytes, red arrows indicate the Kupffer cells, and star shapes indicate the sinusoids. Both the normal group and the 5,000 mg/kg BB group show a normal structure of liver tissues. No degeneration or necrosis of the hepatocytes, cellular infiltration, or abnormalities were detected in these groups. Bar = 20 &#181;m. In (B), blue arrows indicate the normal features of the renal glomerulus, and black arrows indicate the normal features of the renal tubules. Both the normal group and the 5,000 mg/kg BW group show a normal structure of kidney tissue. No degeneration or necrosis, cellular infiltration, or abnormalities were detected in these groups. Bar = 20 &#181;m.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2294-g006.jpg"/></fig><p>According to National Food and Drug Agency standards (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">BPOM, 2022</xref>), several standard extraction methods are applicable for orally used products. Given the potential contamination of fresh MO leaves with heavy metals (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">Limmatvapirat <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Grosshagauer <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>) posing challenges in food processing, we conducted chemical and microbiological safety assessments on EEMO. Our findings indicated that EEMO produced using the UAE method met safety standards for physical, chemical, as well as metal and microbiological contamination (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><p>The high protein content in MO leaf extract had the potential to be a source of nutrition. Fresh MO leaves contain vitamins A, C, and B6, calcium, potassium, iron, and other nutritional content (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Katmawanti <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). Several studies have reported that the nutritional content of Ca, Mg, Na, P, and K was 1.63%&#8211;2.2%, 0.36%&#8211;0.53%, 0.18%&#8211;0.43%, 012%&#8211;0.22%, and 0.67%&#8211;0.76%, respectively. Polyphenol and flavonoid levels varied between 0.24%&#8211;0.34% and 192&#8211;209 ppm (<xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">Wardana <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>), respectively. The total amino acid content in MO leaves has been reported to range from 74.5 to 172.7 mg/g. The leaves contained the most amino acids, nearly double the amount found in the flowers. The amino acids in higher proportions were glutamic acid, arginine, and aspartic acid, while methionine and tryrosine were found in the lowest concentrations (<xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">Wu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2013</xref>). Natsir <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. reported 15 amino acids, with the highest concentrations of essential and non-essential amino acids being leucine and glutamic acid, respectively (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">Natsir <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). Another study by Alhakmani <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> also reported 20 amino acids from MO leaves, with the highest proportions being aspartic acid, glutamic acid, leucine, arginine, and valine (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Alhakmani <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2013</xref>). </p><p>Variations in amino acid composition can be influenced by protein quality and plant origin, whether cultivated or wild (<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Makkar and Becker, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">Sena <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1998</xref>). Our research identified complete amino acids in our extract, including essential amino acids such as phenylalanine, valine, threonine, and leucine, and non-essential amino acids such as glutamic acid, aspartic acid, arginine, and alanine (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Recent clinical nutrition studies emphasize not only total protein intake but also the balance and ratio of essential amino acids to total amino acids (Richard D. <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Semba <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2016</xref>a, b). The plant-derived amino acid content of EEMO is expected to complement the daily nutritional requirements of children and toddlers when combined with other animal-based foods.</p><p>Various studies reported the mineral content of MO leaves, with selenium and chromium being the highest minerals, while sodium and magnesium were found in lower levels (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Moyo <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">Natsir <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). Other researchers also reported variations in mineral content, but almost all types of minerals were found in MO leaves (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Mutar <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). Our investigation revealed that EEMO contained high levels of potassium, chloride, calcium, selenium, copper, and zinc (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Fortification of MO leaves in various food items, alongside the mineral content of EEMO in our study, is expected to complement the daily nutritional needs of children and toddlers (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Govender and Siwela, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">Saeed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Alphonce <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>).</p><p>MO leaves contain modest amounts of anti-nutrients such as saponins, phytates, and tannins, which may interfere with digestion and metabolic processes (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Hadju <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). These compounds are produced by plants during regular metabolism and interact with the chemical composition or interfere with digestion and metabolic processes in the body through various pathways, leading to results that contradict healthy nutrition (Rahman <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2015). Saponins, tannins, flavonoids, alkaloids, protease inhibitors, oxalates, phytates, hemagglutinins (or lectins), cyanogenic glycosides, cardiac glycosides, coumarins, and gossypol are all well-known anti-nutritional compounds. The phytic acid concentration in MO leaves was observed to be lower than that of other household vegetables, with a reported content of 22.3 mg/g in dried leaves (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Citra, 2019</xref>). Our investigation indicated that the amount of phytic acid in the ethanol extract was low (13 mg/g), which is unlikely to have significant anti-nutritional effects. In fact, the presence of phytic acid in low concentration may be advantageous, as it is known to display a broad range of pharmaceutical properties, including antioxidant, neuroprotective, anti-inflammatory, and lipid-lowering effects.</p><p>Aside from its nutritional value, our extract demonstrated antioxidant activity as measured by the DPPH test. DPPH test is a traditional and widely used in-vitro method for antioxidant activity assay due to its simplicity, speed, ease of use, sensitivity, and minimal sample requirements (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Dadi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>a; <xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). This method also benefits from the use of stable DPPH compounds, as well as comparator compounds such as vitamins C, A, and E. The IC<sub>50</sub> value in this approach measures the concentration of antioxidant compounds needed to inhibit 50% oxidation. The stronger the antioxidant activity, the lower the IC<sub>50</sub> value.</p><p>Several studies reported the antioxidant activity of MO leaves, attributing it to active compounds such as polyphenols, flavonoids, phenolics, and carotenoids. Several extraction methods have been used to extract antioxidant compounds, including the UAE method (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Desmarchelier <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">Hamed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr">Zorzenon <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>), subcritical water extraction (SWE), SFE, microwave-assisted extraction (MAE). The antioxidant compounds were also found in EEMO extracted by the UAE method in this study. The phytochemical analysis of EEMO revealed the presence of, several compounds expected to contribute to antioxidant activity, including kaempferol-3,7-diglucoside, kaempferol-3-O-rutinoside, and kaempferol-7-O-&#945;-L-rhamnoside. These three compounds are flavonoid derivatives known for their strong antioxidant properties (<xref rid="tab5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).</p><p>The antioxidant activity of EEMO, as measured by the IC<sub>50</sub> value, was 41.04 mg/l, with vitamin C as the standard, which had IC<sub>50</sub> of 1.58 mg/l (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>a and b). Previous studies have reported various IC<sub>50</sub> values for antioxidant activity in MO leaf extracts. The IC<sub>50</sub> value of dichloromethane extracts in MO leaves were 1.60 &#177; 0.03 mg/ml in the DPPH test and 1.02 &#177; 0.06 mg/ml in the ABTS test (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">Suphachai, 2014</xref>). Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> reported the IC<sub>50</sub> value of the MO extract was 0.7440 mg/l, compared to OPC as a standard which had IC<sub>50</sub> value of 0.0195 mg/l (<xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017</xref>).</p><p>To investigate the potential toxicity of EEMO, we used the MTT test to assess its cytotoxicity. The MTT Assay is a technique for determining a compound&#8217;s cytotoxicity against cells. The reduction of MTT to formazan crystals is the concept of the MTT test, which is based on the capacity of the cellular enzyme oxidoreductase to convert nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NADPH) into insoluble formazan with a purple color. Formazan will be created by live cells that have an active metabolism (Abd-Rabou <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017; <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Barhoi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>a).</p><p>We have tested our sample on two cells. HepG2 and MDCK cells, determined the CC<sub>50</sub> values to be 181.66 and 121.04 mg/l, respectively (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>a and b). HepG2 cells are a hepatocarcinoma cell line that has been successfully cultivated. These cells have a high degree of morphological and functional differentiation. They are more stable and uniform than primary liver cells, making them suitable as a model for studying human protein dynamics in vitro. Moreover, HepG2 cells can produce CYP3A4 enzymes which metabolize more than 50% of drugs (Iskandar mudasyah <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2012; Sae-be <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023). MDCK cells are known to be widely used for drug elimination, permeability, and drug solubility tests, making them useful for assessing the potential toxicity of MO extracts (<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">Varma <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">Hosey and Benet, 2015</xref>). Our study showed that the toxicity dose of EEMO was 6&#8211;7 times higher than the antioxidant dose in HepG2 cells and 8 times in MDCK cells (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figs. 3</xref> and 4).</p><p>The acute oral toxicity test of EEMO indicated that the highest dose of 5,000 mg/kg BW did not show any signs of toxicity or mortality in the test animals (<xref rid="tab6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). This result suggests that EEMO is safe for oral consumption (non-lethal) in acute exposure. Previous studies have reported toxicity tests on MO in various extract forms, including methanol MO extract, which was found to be toxic at doses of 1,600 and 3,200 mg/kg BW (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Adedapo <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2015</xref>). However, the methanol leaf extract of MO did not show toxic signs of death at doses &gt;4,500 mg/kg BW, and the protein isolated from MO (MO-LPI) was reported to be non-toxic at a dose of 2,500 mg/kg BW (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">Omodanisi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017</xref>).</p><p>The histopathological examination of liver and kidney tissues (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>) did not reveal any differences between the normal group and the group administered the highest dose (5,000 mg/kg BW) of EEMO in both, male and female rats. Furthermore, no remarkable lesions were found in the examined organs. These findings indicate that EEMO does not induce histological lesions in the liver and kidney.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The ethanol leaf extract of MO (EEMO) obtained through the UAE method at 40&#176; for 60 minutes meets safety standards and exhibits high nutritional value, including a rich protein and amino acid composition, balanced minerals, and low phytic acid content. It is also a potent natural source of antioxidants with non-cytotoxic properties. No acute toxic effects were found in the animals, and histological examinations revealed no lesions. Additionally, there was no effect of EEMO on BW and organ weight, indicating the safety of the extract as a source of nutrition and medicinal ingredients.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors thank the Directorate of Research and Community Engagement Universitas Indonesia for providing publication grants in 2022. The authors acknowledge the facilities, and scientific and technical support from Advanced Characterization Laboratories Serpong, National Research and Innovation Institute through E-Layanan Sains, National Research and Innovation Agency.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>NTK conceptualized the study, and performed sample collection, laboratory work, data management, analysis, and manuscript writing. ML participated in conceptualized the study, manuscript writing, and data analysis. PEK participated in the result interpretation. OSMS participated in manuscript writing and editing. TS participated in study supervision, and manuscript editing. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by Universitas Indonesia PUTI grants (PUTI NKB-1122/UN2.RST/HKP.05.00/2022).</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data supporting the findings of this study are available within the manuscript.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd-Rabou</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdalla</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zoheir</surname><given-names>K.M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moringa oleifera root induces cancer apoptosis more effectively than leave nanocomposites and its free counterpart</article-title><source>Asian Pac. J. Cancer Prev.</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>2141</fpage><lpage>2149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28843248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.22034/APJCP.2017.18.8.2141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5697473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adedapo</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falayi</surname><given-names>O.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oyagbemi</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the analgesic, anti-inflammatory, anti-oxidant, phytochemical and toxicological properties of the methanolic leaf extract of commercially processed Moringa oleifera in some laboratory animals</article-title><source>J. Basic Clin. Physiol. Pharmacol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>499</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26020553</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1515/jbcpp-2014-0105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alhakmani</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of total phenolic content, in-vitro antioxidant and anti-inflammatory activity of flowers of Moringa oleifera</article-title><source>Asian Pac. J. Trop. Biomed.</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>623</fpage><lpage>627</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23905019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S2221-1691(13)60126-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3703555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alphonce</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaale</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Millinga</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rweyemamu</surname><given-names>L.M.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enrichment of fermented cassava meal &#8216;mchuchume&#8217; with micronutrient ingredients from soya bean flour and Moringa oleifera leaves powder</article-title><source>J. Sci. Food Agric.</source><year>2021</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>3575</fpage><lpage>3581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33277688</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jsfa.10984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barhoi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Upadhaya</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbhuiya</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giri</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aqueous extract of Moringa oleifera exhibit potential anticancer activity and can be used as a possible cancer therapeutic agent: a study involving in vitro and in vivo approach</article-title><source>J. Am. Coll. Nutr.</source><year>2021a</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32191153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/07315724.2020.1735572</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barhoi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Upadhaya</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbhuiya</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giri</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aqueous extract of Moringa oleifera Exhibit potential anticancer activity and can be used as a possible cancer therapeutic agent: a study involving in vitro and in vivo approach</article-title><source>J. Am. Coll. Nutr.</source><year>2021b</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32191153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/07315724.2020.1735572</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourke</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>K.D.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prendergast</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current understanding of innate immune cell dysfunction in childhood undernutrition</article-title><source>Front. Immunol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31417545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2019.01728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6681674</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>BPOM</collab><source>Peraturan badan pengawas obat dan makanan nomor 10 Tahun 2022 Tentang Pedoman Uji Toksisitas Praklinik Secara in vivo</source><year>2022</year><publisher-name>Badan Pengawas Obat dan Makanan Republik Indonesia</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>220</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>BPOM</collab><source>Peraturan Badan Pengawas Obat dan Makanan Nomor 24 Tahun 2023 tentang Persyaratan Keamanan dan Mutu Suplemen Kesehatan</source><year>2023</year><publisher-name>Badan Pengawas Obat dan Makanan Republik Indonesia</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>36</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>BPOM RI</collab><source>Persyaratan Keamanan Dan Mutu Obat Tradisional Nomor 32 Tahun 2019</source><year>2019</year><publisher-name>Badan Pengawas Obat dan Makanan Republik Indonesia</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moringa oleifera leaf protein: extraction, characteristics and applications</article-title><source>J. Food Comp. Anal.</source><year>2023</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>105234</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrillo-&#193;lvarez</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perspective: food and nutrition insecurity in europe: challenges and opportunities for dietitians</article-title><source>Adv. Nutr.</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>995</fpage><lpage>1004</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37543145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.advnut.2023.07.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10509433</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parameter optimization and potential bioactivity evaluation of a betulin extract from white birch bark</article-title><source>Plants</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/plants9030392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7154890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32210064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Citra</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutritional Content of Moringa Plants, Fakultas Farmasi Universitas Surabaya</article-title><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dadi</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emire</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagos</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eun</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of ultrasound-assisted extraction of Moringa stenopetala leaves on bioactive compounds and their antioxidant activity</article-title><source>Food Technol. Biotechnol</source><year>2019a</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31316279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.17113/ftb.57.01.19.5877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6600301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dadi</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emire</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagos</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eun</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of ultrasound-assisted extraction of Moringa stenopetala leaves on bioactive compounds and their antioxidant activity</article-title><source>Food Technol. Biotechnol.</source><year>2019b</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31316279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.17113/ftb.57.01.19.5877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6600301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#8217;Auria</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nitride</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolai</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mamone</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montesano</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>E.N.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferranti</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of allergen encoding sequences in a novel food ingredient from Moringa oleifera leaves</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><year>2023</year><volume>401</volume><fpage>134185</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36113218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.foodchem.2022.134185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>N.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An evaluation of the phytate, zinc, copper, iron and manganese contents of, and Zn availability from, soya-based textured-vegetable-protein meat-substitutes or meat-extenders</article-title><source>Br. J. Nutr.</source><year>1979</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">572701</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1079/bjn19790073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Desmarchelier</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Novoa Bermudez</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coussio</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciccia</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boveris</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant and prooxidant activities in aqueous extracts of Argentine plants</article-title><source>Pharm. Biol.</source><year>1997</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>120</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dranca</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oroian</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrasonics sonochemistry optimization of ultrasound-assisted extraction of total monomeric anthocyanin (TMA) and total phenolic content (TPC) from eggplant (Solanum melongena L.)</article-title><source>peel. Ultrason. Sonochem.</source><year>2016</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>637</fpage><lpage>646</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26701808</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ultsonch.2015.11.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fatima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalid</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>AL-Farga</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alansari</surname><given-names>W.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shamlan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eskandrani</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrasound-assisted extraction of protein from Moringa oleifera seeds and its impact on techno-functional properties</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2023</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>2554</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36985527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/molecules28062554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10059246</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Salas</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morales-Soto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Segura-Carretero</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#225;ndez-Guti&#233;rrez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenolic-compound-extraction systems for fruit and vegetable samples</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2010</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>8813</fpage><lpage>8826</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21131901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/molecules15128813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6259353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gidamis</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panga</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarwatt</surname><given-names>S.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chove</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shayo</surname><given-names>N.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutrient and antinutrient contents in raw and cooked young leaves and immature pods of Moringa oleifera</article-title><source>Lam. Ecol. Food Nutr.</source><year>2003</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>411</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Govender</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siwela</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of Moringa oleifera leaf powder on the physical quality, nutritional composition and consumer acceptability of white and brown breads</article-title><source>Foods</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/foods9121910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7765909</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33371222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Granella</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bechlin</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christ</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coelho</surname><given-names>S.R.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paz</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An approach to recent applications of Moringa oleifera in the agricultural and biofuel industries</article-title><source>South Afr. J. Botany</source><year>2021</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>116</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grosshagauer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pirkwieser</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Somoza</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The future of moringa foods: a food chemistry perspective</article-title><source>Front. Nutr.</source><year>2021</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fnut.2021.751076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8594418</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34796194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadju</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dassir</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Putranto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadapotto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition of Moringa oleifera and Honey from three different Areas in South Sulawesi, Indonesia</article-title><source>Gac. Sanit.</source><year>2021</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>S396</fpage><lpage>S399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34929860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.gaceta.2021.10.060</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamed</surname><given-names>Y.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akhtar</surname><given-names>H.M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>and Zeng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extraction, purification by macrospores resin and in vitro antioxidant activity of flavonoids from Moringa oliefera leaves</article-title><source>South Afr. J. Botany</source><year>2019</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>270</fpage><lpage>279</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosey</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benet</surname><given-names>L.Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predicting the extent of metabolism using in vitro permeability rate measurements and in silico permeability rate predictions</article-title><source>Mol. Pharm.</source><year>2015</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1456</fpage><lpage>1466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25816851</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/mp500783g</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4666302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iskandarmudasyah</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Louisa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arleni, Jusman</surname><given-names>S.W.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suyatna</surname><given-names>F.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of primaquine and ritonavir interaction on CYP3A4 mRNA expression in HepG2 cell culture</article-title><source>Med. J. Indonesia</source><year>2012</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jim&#233;nez-Moreno</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Volpe</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moler</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esparza</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anc&#237;n-Azpilicueta</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of extraction conditions on the phenolic composition and antioxidant capacity of grape stem extracts</article-title><source>Antioxidants</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antiox8120597</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6943662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31795232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katmawanti</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Supriyadi, and Mariroh</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is instant porridge with a high calcium content based on Moringa oleifera as an alternative baby food to prevent stunting in Indonesia? J</article-title><source>Public Health Res.</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4081/jphr.2021.2233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8129761</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33855417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kingwascharapong</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaijan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karnjanapratum</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrasound&#8212;assisted extraction of protein from Bombay locusts and its impact on functional and antioxidative properties</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2021</year><volume>2021</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-021-96694-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8397741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34453091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lafarga</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#225;ndez-Sevilla</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez-L&#243;pez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aci&#233;n-Fern&#225;ndez</surname><given-names>F.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spirulina for the food and functional food industries</article-title><source>Food Res. Int.</source><year>2020</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>109356</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33233059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.foodres.2020.109356</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Limmatvapirat</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charoenteeraboon</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phaechamud</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometric determination of heavy metals in Moringa oleifera Lam</article-title><source>Leaves. Res. J. Pham. Biol. Chem. Sci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>952</fpage><lpage>958</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Makkar</surname><given-names>H.P.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutrional value and antinutritional components of whole and ethanol extracted Moringa oleifera leaves</article-title><source>Anim. Feed. Sci. Technol.</source><year>1996</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>228</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matic</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guidi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenzo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattei</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galgani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of medicinal dietary plants review traditionally supplements: on moringa used oleiferaas</article-title><source>J. Public Health Afr.</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4081/jphia.2018.841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6379786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30854178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>J.C.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>G.B.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>F.D.C.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>M.D.L.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>A.M.D.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Volatile compounds and quality analysis in commercial medicinal plants of Camellia sinensis</article-title><source>Ci&#234;ncia Rural</source><year>2019</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>e20180548</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moyo</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masika</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hugo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muchenje</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutritional characterization of Moringa (Moringa oleifera Lam.)</article-title><source>leaves. Afr. J. Biotechnol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>12925</fpage><lpage>12933</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mutar</surname><given-names>Y.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Rawi</surname><given-names>K.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moringa oleifera: nutritive importance and its medicinal application, as a Review</article-title><source>Egypt. J. Chem.</source><year>2021</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>6827</fpage><lpage>6834</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Natsir</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahab</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Budi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dali</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arif</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amino acid and mineral composition of Moringa oleivera leaves extract and its bioactivity as antioxidant</article-title><source>J. Phys. Conf. Ser. 1317:012030</source><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Omodanisi</surname><given-names>E.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aboua</surname><given-names>Y.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chegou</surname><given-names>N.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oguntibeju</surname><given-names>O.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hepatoprotective, antihyperlipidemic, and anti-inflammatory activity of Moringa oleifera in diabetic-induced damage in male wistar rats</article-title><source>Pharma. Res.</source><year>2017</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4103/0974-8490.204651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5424560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28539743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pe&#241;alver</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;nez-zamora</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenzo</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ros</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nieto</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khurshid Alam</surname><given-names>A.H.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutritional and antioxidant properties of Moringa oleifera leaves in functional foods</article-title><source>Foods</source><year>2022</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><comment>In vitro antioxidant and free radical scavenging activity of different parts of Tabebuia pallida growing in Bangladesh. BMC Res. Notes. 2015. 8, 1&#8211;9</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/foods11081107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9030530</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35454694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reyes S&#225;nchez</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sp&#246;rndly</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ledin</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of feeding different levels of foliage of Moringa oleifera to creole dairy cows on intake, digestibility, milk production and composition</article-title><source>Livest. Sci.</source><year>2006</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11250-006-4314-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17137136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sae-be</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiwatpanit</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varatthan</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Namporn</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laungkulldej</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiabma</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaiboonma</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sa-ngiamsuntorn</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sathirakul</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hongeng</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruenraroengsak</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative study between the 3D-Liver spheroid models developed from HepG2 and immortalized hepatocyte-like cells with primary hepatic stellate coculture for drug metabolism analysis and anticancer drug screening</article-title><source>Adv. Ther. (Weinh)</source><year>2023</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saeed</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramzan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physicochemical analysis of mango flavored yogurt supplemented with Moringa oleifera leaf powder</article-title><source>J Food Sci Technol</source><year>2021</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>4805</fpage><lpage>4814</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34629545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s13197-021-05146-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8479005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Semba, Richard D., Shardell</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakr Ashour</surname><given-names>F.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moaddel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trehan</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maleta</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ordiz</surname><given-names>M.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khadeer</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrucci</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manary</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Child stunting is associated with low circulating essential amino acids</article-title><source>Ebio. Med.</source><year>2016a</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ebiom.2016.02.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4856740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27211567</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Semba, Richard D, Trehan</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez-Friere</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moaddel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ordiz</surname><given-names>M.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrucci</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manary</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perspective: the potential role of essential amino acids and the mechanistic target of rapamycin complex 1</article-title><source>Adv. Nutr.</source><year>2016b</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>853</fpage><lpage>865</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27633102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3945/an.116.013276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5015042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sena</surname><given-names>L.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanderjagt</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsin</surname><given-names>A.T.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muhamadu</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahamadou</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Millson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pastuszyn</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glew</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of nutritional components of eight famine foods of the Republic of Niger</article-title><source>Plant Foods Human Nutr.</source><year>1998</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1023/a:1008010009170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9839831</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suphachai</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant and anticancer activities of Moringa oleifera leaves</article-title><source>J. Med. Plants Res.</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>318</fpage><lpage>325</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>E.M.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>M.R.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neves</surname><given-names>V.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arantes-Pereira</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical characteristics and fractionation of proteins from Moringa oleifera Lam</article-title><source>leaves. Food Chem.</source><year>2014</year><volume>147</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24206684</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.foodchem.2013.09.135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toma</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vinatoru</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paniwnyk</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of ultrasound on vegetal tissues during solvent extraction</article-title><source>Ultrason Sonochem</source><year>2001</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11326609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s1350-4177(00)00033-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tshabalala</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ncube</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madala</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyakudya</surname><given-names>T.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moyo</surname><given-names>H.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sibanda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ndhlala</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scribbling the cat: a case of the &#8220;miracle&#8221; plant, Moringa oleifera</article-title><source>Plants</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/plants8110510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6918402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31731759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Varma</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steyn</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nkansah</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rotter</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitney-Pickett</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cram</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fenner</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Kattan</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PH-dependent solubility and permeability criteria for provisional biopharmaceutics classification (BCS and BDDCS) in early drug discovery</article-title><source>Mol. Pharm.</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1199</fpage><lpage>1212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22489626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/mp2004912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vongsak</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sithisarn</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mangmool</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thongpraditchote</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wongkrajang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gritsanapan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maximizing total phenolics, total flavonoids contents and antioxidant activity of Moringa oleifera leaf extract by the appropriate extraction method</article-title><source>Ind. Crops Prod.</source><year>2013</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>566</fpage><lpage>571</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gui</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subcritical ethanol extraction of flavonoids from Moringa oleifera leaf and evaluation of antioxidant activity</article-title><source>Food Chem.</source><year>2017</year><volume>218</volume><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27719892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.foodchem.2016.09.058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang, Yifen, Luo</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protective effect of Anneslea fragrans ethanolic extract against CCl4-induced liver injury by inhibiting inflammatory response, oxidative stress and apoptosis</article-title><source>Food Chem. Toxicol.</source><year>2023</year><volume>175</volume><fpage>113752</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37004906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.fct.2023.113752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wardana</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jufri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mun&#8217;im</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physicochemical properties and nutrition of Moringa oleifera Lam</article-title><source>Leaf extract: a preliminary study on preparation phytosomes as herbal supplement for children. Int. J. Appl. Pharm.</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>287</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Z.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y.X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>G.L.G.Q.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Research advances in Moringa as a new plant protein feed</article-title><source>Chin. J. Anim. Nutr.</source><year>2013</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>511</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gui</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shentu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparation of Chlorella vulgaris polysaccharides and their antioxidant activity in vitro and in vivo</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2019</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31260772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2019.06.222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yucetepe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saroglu</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bildik</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozcelik</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daskaya</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimisation of ultrasound-assisted extraction of protein from Spirulina platensis using RSM</article-title><source>Czech J. Food Sci.</source><year>2018</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>108</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeitoun</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michael-Jubeli</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Khoury</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baillet-Guffroy</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tfayli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salameh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lteif</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Skin lightening effect of natural extracts coming from Senegal botanical biodiversity</article-title><source>Int. J. Dermatol.</source><year>2020</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31681985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/ijd.14699</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extraction of intracellular protein from Chlorella pyrenoidosa using a combination of ethanol soaking, enzyme digest, ultrasonication and homogenization techniques</article-title><source>Bioresour. Technol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>247</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28950135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biortech.2017.09.087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimization for ultrasound-assisted extraction of polysaccharides with chemical composition and antioxidant activity from the Artemisia sphaerocephala Krasch seeds</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>856</fpage><lpage>866</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27316764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2016.06.042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zorzenon</surname><given-names>M.R.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aristides</surname><given-names>L.G.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cabe&#231;a</surname><given-names>C.L.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>W.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grande</surname><given-names>G.C.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beltran</surname><given-names>L.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mareze-Costa</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dacome</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>P.G.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cipriani</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Claudio da Costa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of polysaccharides from a new variety of Stevia rebaudiana</article-title><source>Bioact Carbohydr Dietary Fibre</source><year>2023</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>100371</fpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>