<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2846</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">openvetj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Veterinary Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2226-4485</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2218-6050</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tripoli</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11563629</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11563629.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11563629</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11563629</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39553756</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/OVJ.2024.v14.i9.36</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OVJ-14-2475</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effects of fermented <italic toggle="yes">Crescentia cujete</italic> L. on the profile of hematology, clinical chemistry, and circulatory CD4+/CD8+ in Sprague Dawley rats</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wijayanti</surname><given-names initials="AD">Agustina Dwi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prakoso</surname><given-names initials="YA">Yos Adi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Isla</surname><given-names initials="KJV">Krestel Joy Viernes</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department Pharmacology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Gadjah Mada, Yogyakarta, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department Pharmacology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Wijaya Kusuma Surabaya, Surabaya, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>College of Veterinary Medicine, Tarlac Agricultural University, Tarlac, Philippines</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Agustina Dwi Wijayanti. Department Pharmacology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Gadjah Mada, Yogyakarta, Indonesia. <email>wagustinadwi@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>9</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">475085</issue-id><fpage>2475</fpage><lpage>2483</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-11-18 15:25:24.860"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2475.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>The calabash (<italic toggle="yes">Crescentia cujete</italic> L.) is a tropical fruit that offers numerous health benefits. Its fermented calabash (FC) has been found to affect the neurological system positively. However, its impact on hematology, clinical chemistry, and CD4+ and CD8+ levels has yet to be documented.</p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>Therefore, this study aims to examine the effects of FC on hematology, clinical chemistry, and the levels of CD4+ and CD8+ in the circulatory system using rat models.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>This study used twenty male Sprague Dawley rats. The rats were divided into group 1 (0 mg/kg BW FC), group 2 (50 mg/kg BW FC), group 3 (500 mg/kg BW FC), and group 4 (2,000 mg/kg BW FC). The treatment was administered using a gastric probe once daily for 14 days. On day 15, the blood samples were collected and tested against hematology, clinical chemistry, quality of the erythrocytes, and CD4+/CD8+. The data were then analysed using SPSS with <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value at 0.05.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>The conducted study demonstrated that the utilization of FC at varying doses did not have a significant impact on the hematological profile changes (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8805; 0.05), except for total lymphocytes and a decrease in the neutrophils/lymphocytes (N/L) ratio (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.05). Furthermore, FC did not influence the changes in clinical chemistry, circulatory protein, and electrolyte levels in rat models compared to the control (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8805; 0.05). The utilization of FC decreased the percentage of hemolysis and elevated the adenosine triphosphate (ATP) concentration (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.05). Additionally, the use of FC led to a significant increase in CD4+ and the ratio of CD4+/CD8+ (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.05), while no significant effect was observed regarding CD8+ (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8805; 0.05).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>The study highlighted FC&#8217;s beneficial effects on the haemorheology and immune system, specifically on the decrease in the percentage of hemolysis, elevated ATP concentration, number of lymphocytes, ratio N/L, CD4+, and the CD4+/CD8+ ratio, without causing significant changes to the hematological and clinical chemistry profiles in rat models.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>CD4+</kwd><kwd>CD8+</kwd><kwd>Clinical chemistry</kwd><kwd>Fermented <italic toggle="yes">Crescentia cujete</italic> (L)</kwd><kwd>Haematology</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>The calabash (<italic toggle="yes">Crescentia cujete</italic> L.) is a tropical fruit found in various countries, including Indonesia. It is known for its rich content of antioxidants and various beneficial biochemical compounds (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Das <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). Previous research has indicated that the calabash fruit contains compounds such as indomethacin, eriodyctiol, ferulic acid, ascorbic acid, apigenin, pinocembrin, and cinnamic acid, which have shown potential therapeutic properties against various diseases (Gonzales <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023). Additionally, fermented calabash (FC) has been found to contain choline (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Wilujeng <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>); and has demonstrated potential in treating neurological defects and reducing brain infarct area in rat models of ischemic stroke (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Hidayah <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). However, the mechanisms and effects of FC on the blood still need to be fully understood. </p><p>Blood, a vital component in humans and animals, consists of plasma and cells. Changes in the blood profile, such as erythrocytes, leukocytes, and erythrocyte indices, can serve as indicators of changes in organ function (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Watson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>), pathological mechanisms (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">Samuel, 2023</xref>), and the success of therapy (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Bodaghi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). Additionally, plasma is a carrier for proteins, hormones, and waste products after metabolism, making it a valuable tool for clinical chemistry analysis (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Haselbeck <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). Furthermore, increased levels of plasma markers, such as blood urea nitrogen (BUN) and creatinine, can indicate a decline in kidney function due to exposure to toxic agents (Griffin <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019) and other plasma markers in the other organs. </p><p>Blood, in addition to its other functions, also mirrors the immunological response through the transportation of biomarkers, including CD4+ and CD8+ (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Waschbisch <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). Both of these biomarkers are essential for maintaining immune status, with CD4+ playing a critical role in wound healing (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Prakoso and Kurniasih, 2018</xref>), infection, and internal organ repair after infection (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Kervevan and Chakrabarti, 2021</xref>), and CD8+ being involved in protection against infection (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Prakoso <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>) and tumorigenesis (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">Xie <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). Therefore, analyzing the levels of CD4+/CD8+ after herbal treatment is crucial to demonstrate the potency of herbal remedies on immunity.</p><p>This study focuses on elucidating the effects of FC on hematology profiles, clinical chemistry, and circulatory CD4+/CD8+ using rat models. </p></sec><sec><title>Material and Methods</title><sec><title>Time and place of study</title><p>This study was performed from August 2023 until April 2024. The animal experimentation and laboratory tests were conducted in the Laboratory of Pharmacology, University of Wijaya Kusuma Surabaya. The calabash (<italic toggle="yes">Crescentia cujete</italic> L.) was gathered from the Botanical Garden of the University of Wijaya Kusuma Surabaya, and the fermentation was conducted in the Laboratory of Pharmacology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Gadjah Mada. </p></sec><sec><title>Herbal preparation</title><p>The calabash was collected and washed using tap water. It was then peeled and weighed. The pulp was fermented following the procedure demonstrated in a previous study (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Wilujeng <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). After the fermentation, the FC product was stored inside the fridge at 4&#176;C until being used. </p><sec><title>Animal model and research design</title><p>This study utilized Sprague Dawley rats from the Laboratory of Pharmacology, UWKS, as the animal model. The selection criteria included male rats weighing 259.00 &#177; 9.82 g, 6 months old, with a total of 20 rats collected. The rats were individually housed and provided with oven-husk bedding. The room temperature was maintained at 25&#176;C using an air conditioner, with a humidity level of 70%, and light/dark intervals of 12/12 hours. The rats had ad libitum access to water and feed (Ratbio<sup>&#174;</sup>, Indonesia). Prior to treatment, the rats were acclimated for 7 days and then divided into four groups: Group 1 (0 mg/kg BW FC), Group 2 (50 mg/kg BW FC), Group 3 (500 mg/kg BW FC), and Group 4 (2,000 mg/kg BW FC). The treatment was administered using a gastric probe once daily for 14 days. </p></sec><sec><title>Sample collection</title><p>The blood from all rats in this study was then collected on day 15 via plexus retro-orbital using microcapillary (Onemed, Indonesia). During the blood collection, all rats were under general anesthesia using 50 mg/kg BW ketamine (Ket-A-100 Agrovet Market, Peru) and xylazine (Xyla Interchemie, Holland). The anesthesia was carefully injected intraperitoneally using a 25G syringe (Onemed, Indonesia), ensuring the comfort and safety of the animals. The blood was then divided into two parts. The first was inserted into a 0.5 ml ethylenediamine tetraacetic acid tube (Onemed, Indonesia), and it was homogenized using a blood roller mixer (KJMR II, Indonesia). The other part of the blood was inserted into a plain tube. Blood without anticoagulant was then centrifuged, and serum was collected. The sample was stored inside a fridge at 4&#176;C of temperature. </p></sec><sec><title>Hematology test</title><p>The blood was tested against routine hematological parameters, i.e., total erythrocytes, hemoglobin, packed cell volume (PCV), mean corpuscular volume (MCV), mean corpuscular hemoglobin (MCH), mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration (MCHC), total platelets, total leucocytes, differential leucocytes count, and neutrophils/lymphocytes ratio (N/L). The hematology analysis was performed using an automated veterinary hematology analyzer (Vetscan<sup>&#174;</sup> HM5, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>Clinical chemistry test</title><p>The serum was tested against several clinical chemistry parameters, including alanine transferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alkaline phosphatase (ALKP), cholinesterase, gamma-glutamyl transferase (GGT), sorbitol dehydrogenase (SDH), BUN, albumin, globulin, triglyceride, cholesterol, high-density lipoprotein, low-density lipoprotein (LDL), inorganic phosphorus (IPHS), natrium (Na), kalium (K), calcium (Ca), chloride (Cl). The reagents for AST, ALT, ALKP, cholinesterase, GGT, and Ca were gathered from Diasys, Indonesia; BUN, creatinine, albumin, triglyceride, cholesterol, HDL, LDL, and IPHS from Elitech, Indonesia; however, Na, K, and Cl from Glory Diagnostics, Indonesia. All the procedures were followed the demonstrated procedure by the manufacturer. </p><p>The clinical chemistry was tested using a photometer (Microlab 300, Vital Scientific, the Netherlands). </p></sec><sec><title>Erythrocytes quality test</title><p>The quality of erythrocytes was tested against the percentage of hemolysis and adenosine triphosphate (ATP) concentration. The percentage of hemolysis was performed using Drabkin&#8217;s method (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">Sowemimo-Coker, 2002</xref>). While, the ATP concentration was tested using a spectrophotometry test following the demonstrated procedure in a previous study (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Almizraq <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2013</xref>). </p></sec><sec><title>Microscopic observation of erythrocytes</title><p>During the blood collection, the blood was directly smeared on the object glass. The blood smear was dried and fixed using methanol. Further, the blood smear was stained using Giemsa and examined under a light microscope (Olympus CX33, Japan). The diameter of erythrocytes was measured using Image J software (NIH, USA). The quality of erythrocytes in the blood smear was analyzed by an expert in veterinary clinical pathology under a blindfold condition. </p></sec><sec><title>Cell tube block (CTB)</title><p>The blood was also tested using CTB. The parameters of this test were CD4+, CD8+, and CD4+/CD8+ ratio. The antibodies used for this test were antibody anti-CD4+ (Novocastra RTU-CD4-1F6, USA) and antibody anti-CD8+ (Novocastra RTU-CD8-295, USA). The CTB was conducted following the previous study by <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Marcos <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., (2017</xref>). However, the staining procedure of the CTB was conducted following <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">Prakoso <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., (2020</xref>). The result of CTB analysis was reported as a percentage (%) both of CD4+ and CD8+ expression.</p></sec><sec><title>Analysis data</title><p>The data were analyzed using SPSS version 23 (IBM Corp, USA). The data were tested regarding its homogeneity and normality. The normal and homogeny data were total erythrocytes, hemoglobin, PCV, MCV, MCH, MCHC, platelet, leucocytes, eosinophils, lymphocytes, monocytes, clinical chemistry, CD4+, ratio N/L, and ratio of CD4+/CD8+. Those data were then analyzed using ANOVA and it was confirmed using the Duncan test. However, the abnormal and non-homogeny data were basophils, LDL and CD8+. They were analysed using the Kruskal Wallis and Man Whitney-U test. The statistic was performed using <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value of 0.05. </p></sec><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>The ethical clearance committee from the Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Wijaya Kusuma Surabaya, declared that this study is ethically appropriate. The approval number was 141-KKE-2023. </p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The study findings revealed that the administration of FC at various doses did not produce a significant impact on the hematological profile of rat models compared to the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8805; 0.05) (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Additionally, FC did not affect platelet count, leucocytes, N/L, basophils, and monocytes (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8805; 0.05). However, FC did lead to a significant increase in circulatory lymphocytes and a decrease in the ratio of N/L compared to the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.05) (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The observed increase in lymphocytes and decrease in N/L were dose-dependent in the rat models.</p><p>Furthermore, the study indicated that clinical chemistry parameters did not change following a 14-day administration of FC. This was evidenced by similar results in various clinical chemistry parameters in the treated group using various doses of FC compared to the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8805; 0.05) (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Moreover, FC did not influence circulatory protein and electrolyte levels in rat models (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8805; 0.05) (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Tables 4</xref> and 5). </p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Profile of hematology in rats after utilization of FC.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Unit</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Group (dose in mg/kg BW)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,000</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Erythrocytes </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#215;10<sup>6 </sup>cells/ mm<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.78 &#177; 0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.78 &#177; 0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.78 &#177; 0.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.77 &#177; 0.21</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Haemoglobin </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">g/dl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.37 &#177; 0.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.59 &#177; 0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.16 &#177; 0.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.30 &#177; 0.24</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.18 &#177; 0.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.74 &#177; 1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.09 &#177; 0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.78 &#177; 1.55</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCV</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">fl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.01 &#177; 3.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.36 &#177; 4.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.14 &#177; 3.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.20 &#177; 3.81</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pg</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.87 &#177; 1.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.25 &#177; 1.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.24 &#177; 1.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.55 &#177; 1.12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCHC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.09 &#177; 1.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.94 &#177; 1.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.90 &#177; 0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.81 &#177; 1.63</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Profile of platelets, leucocytes, and differential leucocytes in rats after utilization of FC.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Unit</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Group (dose in mg/kg BW)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,000</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platelets </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#215;10<sup>5 </sup>cells/ mm<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.12 &#177; 0.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.11 &#177; 0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.11 &#177; 0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.16 &#177; 0.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leucocytes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#215;10<sup>3 </sup>cells/ mm<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.10 &#177; 0.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.09 &#177; 0.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.30 &#177; 0.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.59 &#177; 0.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutrophils </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#215;10<sup>3 </sup>cells/ mm<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 &#177; 0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.533 &#177; 0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61 &#177; 0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66 &#177; 0.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eosinophils </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#215;10<sup>3 </sup>cells/ mm<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13 &#177; 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19 &#177; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 &#177; 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07 &#177; 0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basophils </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#215;10<sup>3 </sup>cells/ mm<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09 &#177; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 &#177; 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 &#177; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lymphocytes </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#215;10<sup>3 </sup>cells/ mm<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.67 &#177; 0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.62 &#177; 0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.95 &#177; 0.43*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.33 &#177; 0.25**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monocytes </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#215;10<sup>3 </sup>cells/ mm<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52 &#177; 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 &#177; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 &#177; 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51 &#177; 0.10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 &#177; 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42 &#177; 0.03*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 &#177; 0.01**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38 &#177; 0.01***</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>N/L = neutrophils/lymphocytes ratio, */**/*** indicated significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.05).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Clinical chemistry parameters of liver and kidney function in rats after utilization of FC.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Unit</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Group (dose in mg/kg BW)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,000</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U/l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.03 &#177; 0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.40 &#177; 1.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.38 &#177; 1.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.13 &#177; 1.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U/l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.74 &#177; 3.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.50 &#177; 1.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.50 &#177; 4.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.07 &#177; 2.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALKP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U/l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.74 &#177; 2.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.39 &#177; 1.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.08 &#177; 2.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.26 &#177; 3.15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cholinesterase </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#215;10<sup>3</sup> U/l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.88 &#177; 1.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.71 &#177; 0.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.44 &#177; 0.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.69 &#177; 0.59</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U/l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.24 &#177; 0.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.32 &#177; 0.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.08 &#177; 0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.14 &#177; 0.26</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SDH</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U/l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.79 &#177; 0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.56 &#177; 1.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.84 &#177; 1.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.42 &#177; 1.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BUN</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/dl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.89 &#177; 0.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.41 &#177; 1.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.48 &#177; 0.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.89 &#177; 1.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Creatinine </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/dl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 &#177; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 &#177; 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28 &#177; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28 &#177; 0.05</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><title>Circulatory protein in rats after utilization of FC.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Unit</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Group (dose in mg/kg BW)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,000</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Albumin </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">g/dl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.56 &#177; 0.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.63 &#177; 0.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.49 &#177; 0.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40 &#177; 0.32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Globulin </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">g/dl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81 &#177; 0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.84 &#177; 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88 &#177;0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83 &#177; 0.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Triglyceride </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/dl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.98 &#177; 1.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.70 &#177; 3.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.80 &#177; 1.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.90 &#177; 1.31</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cholesterol </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/dl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.39 &#177; 2.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.16 &#177; 3.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.33 &#177; 4.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.18 &#177; 3.30</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmol/l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 &#177; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 &#177; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 &#177; 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 &#177; 0.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmol/l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 &#177; 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21 &#177; 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 &#177; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 &#177; 0.05</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><title>Circulatory electrolytes in rats after utilization of FC.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Unit</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Group (dose in mg/kg BW)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,000</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IPHS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/dl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.63 &#177; 0.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.64 &#177; 0.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.04 &#177; 1.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.98 &#177; 0.28</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Na</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmol/l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106.58 &#177; 6.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.08 &#177; 5.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.00 &#177; 8.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.86 &#177; 7.60</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmol/l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00 &#177; 0.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.67 &#177; 0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.01 &#177; 0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.98 &#177; 0.66</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg/dl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.81 &#177; 0.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.69 &#177; 1.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.18 &#177; 0.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.41 &#177; 0.67</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cl</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mmol/l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.36 &#177; 6.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.87 &#177; 7.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.06 &#177; 5.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.28 &#177; 1.10</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The analysis of the erythrocytes revealed a significant decrease in the percentage of hemolysis after treatment with FC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.05). The lowest percentage of hemolysis occurred in the group treated with 2,000 mg/kg BW, followed by the group treated with 500 mg/kg BW. However, the group treated with 50 mg/kg BW FC did not show a significant difference compared to the control (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8805; 0.05) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>A). Conversely, the ATP concentration in the treated groups increased with the dosage used in the study (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.05), reaching the highest level in the group treated with 2,000 mg/kg BW (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.05) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>B). However, the statistical analysis indicated that the different doses of FC did not have a significant effect on the diameter of erythrocytes (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8805; 0.05) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>C). The qualitative assessment of erythrocytes in the blood smear indicated the presence of anisocytosis in the control group and the groups treated with 50 and 500 mg/kg BW FC. However, anisocytosis was not observed in the group treated with 2,000 mg/kg BW FC. Acanthocytes, marked by spiculated erythrocytes, were observed in all groups, with minimal presentation of this change occurring in the group treated with 2,000 mg/kg BW (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). </p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>Percentage of hemolysis, ATP concentration, and diameter of erythrocytes in rats after utilization of FC.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2475-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>Finally, the assessment of circulatory lymphocytes using CTB revealed that FC potentially increased the expression of circulatory CD4+ and the ratio of CD4+/CD8+ (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.05), with no significant impact on CD8+ (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8805; 0.05) (<xref rid="tab6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The FC is a product resulting from the fermentation of calabash fruit. This study demonstrates that FC has notable effects on the number of circulatory lymphocytes and a reduction in the N/L ratio rather than impacting the hematological profile. These positive effects are attributed to the choline content in FC. A prior study indicated that FC contains choline at 110.33 mg/kg of fermented product (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Wilujeng <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). Another study supported this hypothesis, which found that choline supplementation promotes the proliferation of leucocytes and lymphocytes rather than affecting the hematological profile in broiler chickens (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Khose <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>). Additionally, <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Ramalho de Lima <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2024</xref>) suggested that choline supplementation enhances broiler performance without altering the birds&#8217; clinical parameters. </p><p>Choline deficiency promotes the apoptosis of leucocytes and negatively impacts the immune system (da Costa <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2006). Choline is essential for enhancing immunity due to its ability to induce the proliferation of lymphocytes (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Garcia <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>). Choline&#8217;s capacity to promote leucocyte proliferation stems from its metabolism into several essential products (e.g., phosphatidylcholine and betaine), which are essential as transporters and receptors at the cellular level (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Mori <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2003</xref>). Choline also activates the mRNA of lymphocytes, which is crucial in regulating the immune system&#8217;s function (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Fujita <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). Moreover, choline&#8217;s anti-inflammatory effect prevents excessive activity of neutrophils in secreting cyclooxygenase-2, which is essential in preventing oxidative stress (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>Qualitative assessment of erythrocytes in rats after utilization of FC. Anisocytosis in blood smear of the control group (A); 50 mg/kg BW FC (B); and 500 mg/kg BW FC (C); the size of erythrocytes appears</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2475-g002.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tab6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6.</label><caption><title>Percentage of expression of CD4+, CD8+, and CD4+/CD8+ in rats after utilization of FC.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Unit</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Group (dose in mg/kg BW)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,000</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD4+ </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.51 &#177; 0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.48 &#177; 0.81*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.79 &#177; 1.80**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.38 &#177; 1.09***</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD8+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45 &#177; 0.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.31 &#177; 0.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00 &#177; 0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.03 &#177; 0.10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD4+/CD8+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94 &#177; 0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.41 &#177; 0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42 &#177; 1.01*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.66 &#177; 0.70**</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>CD4+/CD8+ = ratio of CD4+/CD8+, */**/*** indicated significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.05).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The FC does not impact rat models&#8217; clinical chemistry parameters, circulatory protein, and electrolytes. This is attributed to choline in FC, which plays a vital role in maintaining the metabolism of nephrons and hepatocytes. Previous studies have demonstrated that choline improves renal function in acute kidney injury in mouse models (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Hasson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>) and has beneficial effects in ameliorating oxidative stress in kidney injury (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Baris <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). Additionally, choline intake in hepatocytes influences epigenetics on histones and DNA and modulates gene expression to uphold liver function (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Mehedint and Zeisel, 2013</xref>). These findings suggest that rich in choline, FC enhances liver and kidney function. The optimal functioning of the liver and kidneys may contribute to the regulation of circulatory serum protein (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Ko <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>) and electrolyte levels (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Chen <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>), aligning with the outcomes of this study.</p><p>Interestingly, the findings indicate that FC potentially benefits erythrocyte haemorheology by decreasing erythrocyte hemolysis and maintaining ATP concentration. The mechanism is attributed to the choline-rich composition of FC, which promotes erythrocyte membrane integrity, thereby preventing disruption due to changes in plasma osmolarity. The integrity of the erythrocyte membrane is potentially related to erythrocyte deformability and aggregation (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Santos <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2003</xref>). Membrane integrity also contributes to maintaining erythrocyte fluidity (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Li and Lykotrafitis, 2014</xref>). A higher number of intact erythrocytes may be correlated with ATP concentration. This study&#8217;s findings are similar to a previous study that demonstrated significant ATP release from erythrocytes due to blood hemolysis (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Sikora <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). Intact erythrocytes also provide high storage capacity, including ATP storage (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Zhong <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). ATP is an important energy source for cells and acts as an extracellular signaling molecule (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">McMahon <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). Within erythrocytes, ATP is released due to hypoxia or hemolysis (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Ferguson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). Furthermore, the study indicates that FC increases erythrocyte capability to maintain ATP concentration, thereby reducing oxidative stress within the circulatory system via its choline-derived herbal component. These findings are supported by qualitative assessments of erythrocytes post-FC use, as evidenced by the uniformity of erythrocyte size aligning with the increase in doses. </p><p>The utilization of FC has been demonstrated to elevate the percentage of CD4+ cells and the CD4+/CD8+ ratio in rat models. The choline constituent in FC upregulates lymphocytes expressing CD4+ rather than CD8+ in the circulatory system. Previous research has indicated that acetylcholine, a choline metabolite released from T-cells, may help mitigate inflammation and regulate vasculature (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Cox, 2023</xref>). Hence, the use of FC is presumed to augment choline levels in cells to counterbalance choline release during disease pathogenesis.</p><p>The increase in CD4+ cells influences the CD4+/CD8+ ratio and plays a significant role in immune regulation. CD4+ lymphocytes act as regulators, promoting differentiating and stimulating macrophages, B lymphocytes, CD8+ cells, and other cells within the immune system (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Shete <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). These cells are also crucial during the resolution of chronic pulmonary disease (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">Qin <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>), carcinogenesis (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Han <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Xie <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>), prevention of viral replication (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Kervevan and Chakrabarti, 2021</xref>), and facilitation of T-cell adhesion to cells expressing MHC. Furthermore, CD4+ cells in the circulatory system also contribute to initiating kinase signals to T-cell receptors (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Glatzov&#225; and Cebecauer, 2019</xref>).</p><p>The activation of CD4+ cells and the increased CD4+/CD8+ ratio signify a robust immune system. This activation accelerates the immune system&#8217;s response to exposure to pathogenic agents (<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Vidya Vijayan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017</xref>). Additionally, activating circulatory CD4+ cells is imperative in carcinogenesis and can reflect the body&#8217;s response during immunotherapy (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Poncette <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). It is essential to acknowledge the various benefits of FC on the circulatory system, and further research is critical to validate its effects, including its efficacy during disease pathogenesis and its impacts on the host body.</p><p>In light of the study&#8217;s outcomes, the following recommendations have been proposed: the utilization of FC for treating ailments associated with erythrocyte hemolysis in rats or other animal species, the administration of FC to enhance the immune system of animals, and further exploration of the effects of FC on a variety of animal species.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The study&#8217;s findings indicate that the administration of FC did not have a statistically significant impact on the hematological profile and clinical chemistry parameters in rat models compared to the control group. However, noteworthy observations include a significant decrease in erythrocyte hemolysis, promoting the maintenance of ATP concentration. </p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>The authors acknowledge Universitas Gadjah Mada, Indonesia for providing financial support for this study through Program Post Doctoral 2024, funding number 4292/UN1.P1/PT.01.03/2024. The authors also acknowledge all the research assistants from Dep. Pharmacology, FVM UWKS, for their assistance.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest. </p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>This study received funding from Program Post Doctoral 2024 from Universitas Gadjah Mada, Indonesia with funding number: 4292/UN1.P1/PT.01.03/2024.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>ADW supervised this study. ADW and YAP contributed to the design and performed the study. KJVI performed statistical analysis. ADW, YAP, and KJVI contributed to the drafting, revising, and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All the data supporting the findings are available within the manuscript. </p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Almizraq, R., Tchir, J.D., Holovati, J.L. and Acker, J.P. 2013. Storage of red blood cells affects membrane composition, microvesiculation, and <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> quality. Transfus. 53(10), 2258&#8211;2267.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/trf.12080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23320518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Baris, E., Simsek, O., Arici, M.A. and Tosun, M. 2023. Choline and citicoline ameliorate oxidative stress in acute kidney injury in rats. Bratisl Lek Listy. 124(1), 47&#8211;52.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4149/BLL_2023_007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36519607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Bodaghi, A., Fattahi, N. and Ramazani, A. 2023. Biomarkers: promising and valuable tools towards diagnosis, prognosis and treatment of Covid-19 and other diseases. Heliyon. 9(2), e13323.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e13323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9884646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36744065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Chen, X., Xu, J., Li, Y., Xu, X., Shen, B., Zou, Z., Ding, X., Teng, J. and Jiang, W. 2021. Risk scoring systems including electrolyte disorders for predicting the incidence of acute kidney injury in hospitalized patients. Clin. Epid. 13, 383&#8211;396.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/CLEP.S311364</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8168833</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34093042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Cox, M.A. 2023. Acetylcholine-producing CD4 T cells regulate vasculature in humans. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 120(16), e2303525120.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.2303525120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10120021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37036991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>da Costa, K.A., Niculescu, M.D., Craciunescu, C.N., Fischer, L.M. and Zeisel, S.H. 2006. Choline deficiency increases lymphocyte apoptosis and DNA damage in humans. Am. J. Clin. Nutr. 84(1), 88&#8211;94.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/ajcn/84.1.88</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2430662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16825685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Das, N., Islam, M.E., Jahan, N., Islam, M.S., Khan, A., Islam, M.R. and Parvin, M.S. 2014. Antioxidant activities of ethanol extracts and fractions of <italic toggle="yes">Crescentia cujete</italic> leaves and stem bark and the involvement of phenolic compounds. BMC Complement Altern. Med. 14, 45.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1472-6882-14-45</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3937116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24495381</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Ferguson, B.S., Neidert, L.E., Rogatzki, M.J., Lohse, K.R., Gladden, L.B. and Kluess, H.A. 2021. Red blood cell ATP release correlates with red blood cell hemolysis. Am. J. Physiol. Cell Physiol. 321(5), C761&#8211;C769.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajpcell.00510.2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34495762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Fujita, Y., Nagakura, T., Uchino, H., Inazu, M. and Yamanaka, T. 2021. Functional expression of choline transporters in human neural stem cells and its link to cell proliferation, cell viability, and neurite outgrowth. Cells. 10(2), 453.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/cells10020453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7924032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33672580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Garcia, M., Mamedova, L.K., Barton, B. and Bradford, B.J. 2018. Choline regulates the function of bovine immune cells and alters the mRNA abundance of enzymes and receptors involved in its metabolism <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>. Front. Immunol. 9, 2448.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2018.02448</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6211314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30410489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Glatzov&#225;, D. and Cebecauer, M. 2019. Dual role of CD4 in peripheral T lymphocytes. Front. Immunol. 10, 618.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2019.00618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6454155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31001252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Gonzales, A.L., Huang, S.K., Sevilla, U.T.A., Hsieh, C.Y. and Tsai, P.W. 2023. <italic toggle="yes">In silico</italic> analysis of anti-inflammatory and antioxidant properties of bioactive compounds from <italic toggle="yes">Crescentia cujete</italic> L. Molecules. 28(8), 3547.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/molecules28083547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10145697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37110781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Han, J., Zhao, L., Wu, J., Diao, Y., Guo, Q., Yang, J. and Luo, Y. 2022. Role of CD4<sup>+</sup>T, CD8<sup>+</sup>T cells, and CD4<sup>+</sup>T/CD8<sup>+</sup>T cell ratio in gastric cancer and its clinical significance. Appl. Bionic Biomechanic. 2022, 1094607.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2022/1094607</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9078800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35535325</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC10447133"/></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Haselbeck, A.H., Im, J., Prifti, K., Marks, F., Holm, M. and Zellweger, R.M. 2022. Serology as a tool to assess infectious disease landscapes and guide public health policy. Pathogens. 11(7), 732.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/pathogens11070732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9323579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35889978</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Hasson, D.C., Watanabe-Chailland, M., Romick-Rosendale, L., Koterba, A., Miner, D.S., Lahni, P., Ma, Q., Goldstein, S.L., Devarajan, P. and Standage, S.W. 2022. Choline supplementation attenuates experimental sepsis-associated acute kidney injury. Am. J. Physiol. Renal. Physiol. 323(3), F255&#8211;F271.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajprenal.00033.2022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9394731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35834274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Hidayah, J.H., Prakoso, Y.A. and Widyarini, S. 2023. Histopathological changes after treatment using calabash fruit (<italic toggle="yes">Crescentia cujete</italic> L.) in rat model with artificially induced ischemic stroke. Adv. Anim. Vet. Sci. 11(12), 2003&#8211;2009.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Kervevan, J. and Chakrabarti, L.A. 2021. Role of CD4+ T cells in the control of viral infections: recent advances and open questions. Int. J. Mol. Sci. 22(2), 523.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms22020523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7825705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33430234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Khose, K.K., Manwar, S.J., Sedmake, E.D., Ingole, R.S. and Rathod, P.R. 2018. Supplementation herbal choline in diets on haematological indices and development of vital organ in broilers. JEZS. 6(6), 1054&#8211;1058.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Ko, G. J., Rhee, C. M., Kalantar-Zadeh, K. and Joshi, S. 2020. The effects of high-protein diets on kidney health and longevity. JASN. 31(8), 1667&#8211;1679.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1681/ASN.2020010028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7460905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32669325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Li, H. and Lykotrafitis, G. 2014. Erythrocyte membrane model with explicit description of the lipid bilayer and the spectrin network. Biophys J. 107(3), 642&#8211;653.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.bpj.2014.06.031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4129483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25099803</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Marcos, R., Santos, M., Marrinhas, C. and Caniatti, M. 2017. Cell tube block: a new technique to produce cell blocks from fluid cytology samples. Vet. Clin. Pathol. 46(1), 195&#8211;201.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/vcp.12446</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28195650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>McMahon, T.J., Darrow, C.C., Hoehn, B.A. and Zhu, H. 2021. Generation and export of red blood cell ATP in health and disease. Front. Physiol. 12, 754638.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fphys.2021.754638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8602689</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34803737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Mehedint, M.G. and Zeisel, S.H. 2013. Choline&#8217;s role in maintaining liver function: new evidence for epigenetic mechanisms. Curr. Opin. Clin. Nutr. Metab. Care. 16(3), 339&#8211;345.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MCO.0b013e3283600d46</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3729018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23493015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Mori, N., Natarajan, K., Chacko, V.P., Artemov, D. and Bhujwalla, Z.M. 2003. Choline phospholipid metabolites of human vascular endothelial cells altered by cyclooxygenase inhibition, growth factor depletion, and paracrine factors secreted by cancer cells. Mol. Imag. 2(2), 124&#8211;130.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1162/15353500200303127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12964309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Poncette, L., Bluhm, J. and Blankenstein, T. 2022. The role of CD4 T cells in rejection of solid tumors. Curr. Opin. Immunol. 74, 18&#8211;24.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.coi.2021.09.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8933281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34619457</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Prakoso, Y.A. and Kurniasih. 2018. The effects of <italic toggle="yes">aloe vera</italic> cream on the expression of CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> lymphocytes in skin wound healing. J. Trop. Med. 2018, 6218303.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2018/6218303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5832127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29666657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Prakoso, Y.A., Hidayah, N., Rini, C.S. and Kurniasih, K. 2021. Dynamic change of blood profile in rat models with acute skin injury artificially infected with methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>. Vet. World 14(8), 2085&#8211;2090.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14202/vetworld.2021.2085-2090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8448642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34566324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Prakoso, Y.A., Rini, C.S., Rahayu, A., Sigit, M. and Widhowati, D. 2020. Celery (<italic toggle="yes">Apium graveolens</italic>) as a potential antibacterial agent and its effect on cytokeratin-17 and other healing promoters in skin wounds infected with methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>. Vet. World. 13(5), 865&#8211;871.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14202/vetworld.2020.865-871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7311862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32636580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Qin, K., Xu, B., Pang, M., Wang, H. and Yu, B. 2022. The functions of CD4 T-helper lymphocytes in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. Acta Biochim. Biophys. Sin. 54(2), 173&#8211;178.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3724/abbs.2021009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9827934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35130627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Ramalho de Lima, M., Kaneko, I.N., de Lima, A.V., de Melo, L.N., de Lima, M.C., de Brito, A.N.E.F., Costa, F.G.P., Boas, A.D.C.V., Toledo, A.L., Ferrer, S.L. and Marimuthu, S. 2024. Choline supplementation: impact on broiler chicken performance, steatosis, and economic viability from from 1 to 42 days. PLoS One. 19(3), e0295488.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0295488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10950236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38502648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Samuel, L. 2023. Direct-from-blood detection of pathogens: a review of technology and challenges. J. Clin. Microbiol. 61(7), e0023121.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/jcm.00231-21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10358183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37222587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Santos, T., Mesquita, R., Martins E Silva, J. and Saldanha, C. 2003. Effects of choline on hemorheological properties and NO metabolism of human erythrocytes. Clin. Hemorheol. Microcirc. 29(1), 41&#8211;51.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14561903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Shete, A., Thakar, M., Abraham, P.R. and Paranjape, R. 2010. A review on peripheral blood CD4+ T lymphocyte counts in healthy adult Indians. Indian J. Med. Res. 132(6), 667&#8211;675.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3102453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21245613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Sikora, J., Orlov, S.N., Furuya, K. and Grygorczyk, R. 2014. Hemolysis is a primary ATP-release mechanism in human erythrocytes. Blood. 124(13), 2150&#8211;2157.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1182/blood-2014-05-572024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4186543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25097178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Sowemimo-Coker, S.O. 2002. Red blood cell hemolysis during processing. Transfus. Med. Rev. 16(1), 46&#8211;60.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1053/tmrv.2002.29404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11788929</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Vidya Vijayan, K.K., Karthigeyan, K.P., Tripathi, S.P. and Hanna, L.E. 2017. Pathophysiology of CD4+ T-Cell depletion in HIV-1 and HIV-2 infections. Front. Immunol. 8, 580.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fimmu.2017.00580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5440548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28588579</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Waschbisch, A., Sammet, L., Schr&#246;der, S., Lee, D.H., Barrantes-Freer, A., Stadelmann, C. and Linker, R.A. 2014. Analysis of CD4+ CD8+ double-positive T cells in blood, cerebrospinal fluid and multiple sclerosis lesions. Clin. Experiment. Immunol. 177(2), 404&#8211;411.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/cei.12345</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4226591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24730443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Watson, J., Whiting, P.F., Salisbury, C., Hamilton, W.T. and Banks, J. 2022. Blood tests in primary care: a qualitative study of communication and decision-making between doctors and patients. Health Axpect. 25(5), 2453&#8211;2461.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/hex.13564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9615068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35854666</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Wilujeng, S., Prakoso, Y.A. and Wirjaatmadja, R. 2023. Effects of extraction, fermentation, and storage processes on the level of choline derived from calabash fruit (<italic toggle="yes">Crescentia cujete</italic> L.). J. Res. Pharm. 27(2), 620&#8211;626.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Xie, L., Fang, J., Yu, J., Zhang, W., He, Z., Ye, L. and Wang, H. 2023. The role of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells in tumor and chronic viral immune responses. Med. Comm. 4(5), e390.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/mco2.390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10565399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37829505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Xie, Q., Ding, J. and Chen, Y. 2021. Role of CD8<sup>+</sup> T lymphocyte cells: Interplay with stromal cells in tumor microenvironment. Acta Pharmaceutic. Sin. B. 11(6), 1365&#8211;1378.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.apsb.2021.03.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8245853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34221857</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Zhang, N., Li, Y. and Feng, Z. 2023. Inhibition effect of choline and parecoxib sodium on chronic constriction nerve injury-induced neuropathic pain in rats. BMC Anesthesiol. 23(1), 22.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s12871-022-01913-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9837992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36639747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>Zhong, R., Wu, X., Liu, Z., He, Z., Zhang, X., Liu, J., Cao, Y. and Wang, H. 2023. A study on the correlation between hemoglobin concentration and the storage quality of suspended red blood cells prepared from the whole blood of Tibetan male residents. Front. Med. 9, 1062778.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmed.2022.1062778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9895097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36743680</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>