<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2846</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">openvetj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Veterinary Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2226-4485</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2218-6050</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tripoli</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12124787</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12124787.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12124787</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12124787</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40453866</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/OVJ.2025.v15.i4.15</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OVJ-15-1637</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Prevalence and risk factors of toxocariasis in beef calves in Pandak, Indonesia: A cross-sectional study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suwito</surname><given-names initials="W">Widodo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andriani</surname></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kusumaningtyas</surname><given-names initials="E">Eni</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Primatika</surname><given-names initials="RA">Roza Azizah</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heryanto</surname><given-names initials="RB">Raden Bambang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Research Center Processing Food Technology, National Research and Innovation Agency (BRIN), Yogyakarta, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Veterinary Research Center, National Research and Innovation Agency (BRIN), Bogor, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Veterinary Public Health, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Gadjah Mada, Yogyakarta, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Research Center for Geospatial, Research Organization for Earth Science and Maritime, National Research and Innovation Agency (BRIN), Bogor, Indonesia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Widodo Suwito. Research Center Processing Food Technology, National Research and Innovation Agency (BRIN), Yogyakarta, Indonesia. <email>widodo.suwito@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>4</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">489607</issue-id><fpage>1637</fpage><lpage>1644</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>31</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-06-02 09:26:57.310"><day>02</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-15-1637.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Toxocariasis, caused by <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara vitulorum</italic>, is economically detrimental to beef calves. Despite its potential impact on cattle productivity, toxocariasis remains underrecognized by local farmers in Bantul, Yogyakarta, Indonesia.</p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>This study aimed to determine the prevalence and risk factors associated with toxocariasis in beef calves in the Pandak subdistrict of Bantul Regency, Yogyakarta, Indonesia.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods:</title><p>The study employed a cross-sectional design, and 175 beef calf feces samples were collected for analysis. Risk factors such as age, sex, breed, body condition score, feces consistency, type of cage, weaning age, number of beef cattle per cage, and cage flooring material were collected using a structured questionnaire. Eggs per gram of feces (EPG) were quantified using the McMaster technique, and the total EPG count was categorized as light, moderate, or heavy. Data were analyzed using univariate, bivariate, and multivariate methods with the Statistical Package for the Social Sciences, version 16.0 for Windows.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>The prevalence of toxocariasis in beef calves in the Pandak subdistrict, Bantul Regency, Yogyakarta, Indonesia was 11.4%. Ages 1&#8211;3 months and 4&#8211;6 months are identified as risk factors for toxocariasis in beef calves.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Toxocariasis is an endemic parasitic disease in beef calves aged under 6 months in Pandak subdistrict of Bantul Regency, Yogyakarta, Indonesia. Consequently, anthelmintic treatment should be routinely administered to beef calves aged below 6 months.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Beef calves</kwd><kwd>Bantul regency</kwd><kwd>Toxocariasis</kwd><kwd>Prevalence</kwd><kwd>Risk factors</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Toxocariasis is a parasitic disease caused by <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara vitulorum</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">T. vitulorum</italic>) in cattle. It is one of the most significant endoparasites affecting cattle, primarily residing in the small intestine (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Rast <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman, 2020</xref>). This leads to substantial economic losses, particularly in the tropical and subtropical regions. The disease causes considerable economic impact, primarily due to weight loss, poor meat quality, and increased mortality rates (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">CDC, 2023</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara vitulorum</italic> is particularly detrimental to cattle and buffalo, with a high mortality rate of up to 37.3% (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Rast <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). In cases of uncontrolled infections, mortality rates can reach as high as 80% (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Biswas <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). Calves affected by toxocariasis may experience up to 16 kg weight loss by 12 weeks of age in severe cases compared with uninfected calves (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Radostits <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman, 2020</xref>). The estimated economic losses due to <italic toggle="yes">T. vitulorum</italic> infection in the grazing dairy cattle population in Mexico were US$ 189,212,709 (Rodr&#237;guez-Vivas <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017). In buffalo calves aged 1&#8211;3 months, toxocariasis is the leading cause of morbidity and mortality (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">Rodr&#237;guez-Vivas <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017</xref>). If left uncontrolled, the infection prevalence can approach 100%, with mortality rates reaching up to 50% (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">Srivastava and Sharma, 1981</xref>; <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Radostits <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Rast <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2013</xref>).</p><p>Calf toxocariasis is highly prevalent, particularly in calves under 6 months of age (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Wyrosdick <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2025</xref>). Beef cattle become infected with <italic toggle="yes">T. vitulorum</italic> by ingesting grass contaminated with infected worm eggs or larvae. These eggs remain in the small intestine until they hatch into first-stage larvae (L<sub>1</sub>), which then progress to second-stage larvae (L<sub>2</sub>), and eventually to third-stage larvae (L<sub>3</sub>) (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Starke-Buzetti, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman, 2020</xref>). L<sub>3</sub> larvae penetrate the intestinal wall and migrate to the liver and lungs via the bloodstream. L<sub>3</sub> larvae are subsequently coughed up by the infected animal, ingested, and mature into adult worms in the intestine. Adult worms begin laying eggs 3&#8211;5 weeks after infection (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Starke-Buzetti, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman, 2020</xref>). The severity of disease is correlated with the number of worm eggs present in the animal&#8217;s feces.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Toxocara vitulorum</italic> can be transmitted to newborn calves through both the placenta and breast milk (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Starke-Buzetti, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman, 2020</xref>). Postnatal infection in calves, typically through the ingestion of L<sub>3</sub> larvae present in colostrum or milk, is common on farms and contributes to increased morbidity and mortality. Because L<sub>3</sub> larvae are secreted in colostrum and milk for up to 12 days after birth, beef calves are often infected while suckling. L<sub>3</sub> larvae have been detected in both colostrum and milk samples (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Starke-Buzetti, 2006</xref>). Microscopic examination revealed the presence of L<sub>3</sub> larvae in 4% of samples, whereas 10% of the samples tested positive using molecular techniques (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">Urhan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). L<sub>3</sub> larvae were found in colostrum and milk samples collected between 2 and 28 days postpartum. As calves suckle, they ingest L<sub>3</sub> larvae, which mature into adult worms in the intestine (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Starke-Buzetti, 2006</xref>). The adult worms began producing eggs daily, starting on the 12th day postinfection. The presence of <italic toggle="yes">T. vitulorum</italic> eggs in feces is associated with the prepatent period, which is defined as the time between infection and the onset of egg production (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman, 2020</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara vitulorum</italic> has a prepatent period of 22.3 &#177; 1.6 days, with peak egg production occurring at 5 weeks (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Starke-Buzetti, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman, 2020</xref>). After this peak, egg output gradually declines to zero after 3 months.</p><p>The topography of Pandak subdistrict consists of 10% hilly plains and 90% undulating lowlands. The area encompasses 1,344,785 hectares of paddy fields, 1,231,587 hectares of dry land, 0.8186 hectares of wetlands, 21,840 hectares allocated for public facilities, and 219,104 hectares of barren or sandy land (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">BPS, 2023</xref>). Pandak subdistrict is a lowland region characterized by numerous rivers that provide irrigation for rice fields. It also has the highest population of beef cattle in the area compared with other subdistricts in the area. Located in Bantul Regency, Yogyakarta, Indonesia, Pandak subdistrict experiences an average rainfall of 90.76 mm and a temperature of approximately 30&#176;C (BMKG, 2020). Due to its favorable topography and efficient irrigation system, agriculture is the primary source of income for local residents. In 2023,the beef cattle population in Pandak subdistrict is projected to reach 2,809 heads (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">BPS, 2023</xref>).</p><p>Most residents rely on farming and livestock breeding for their livelihoods, benefiting from the region&#8217;s abundant water resources and extensive land availability. The primary breeds of beef cattle raised in the study area include the Ongole crossbreed, Limousin-Ongole crossbreed (LIMPO), and Simmental-Ongole crossbreed (SIMPO) (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Suwito, 2020</xref>). In the Bantul sub-district, beef cattle are raised using three distinct methods: traditional, intensiv and semiintensive. Cattle are typically housed in communal or private enclosures, depending on the management system. The primary source of feed consists of agricultural waste, while King grass, harvested from adjacent agricultural land, is also commonly used. Additionally, beef farmers generally wean calves at three months of age to strengthen them and introduce them to green fodder, such as field grass (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Suwito, 2020</xref>).</p><p>Toxocariasis in beef cattle has been reported in Indonesia, particularly in areas with extensive irrigation (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Davila <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Purwandani <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). Considering that Pandak sub-district in Bantul Regency is well-irrigated, and local beef farmers frequently encounter confusion when calves, either still suckling or newly born, exhibit signs of worm infestation in their feces, it is essential to conduct research on the prevalence and risk factors of toxocariasis in beef calves in this region.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>The authors complied with all applicable international, national, and institutional guidelines for the care and use of animals. The ethical protocols followed during sample collection and animal handling are outlined as follows: The beef calf farmer provided a restraint device, and latex gloves were worn during the collection of feces samples, which were obtained either directly from the rectum or from freshly excreted feces. After collection, feces samples were placed in labeled ziplock plastic bags, which included essential information such as the calf&#8217;s identification number, gender, age, date of collection, breed, farm address, and farmer&#8217;s name.</p></sec><sec><title>Pattern and description area research</title><p>This research employed a cross-sectional study conducted from May to June 2022 in the Pandak subdistrict of Bantul Regency, Yogyakarta, Indonesia. Calf feces samples were collected from the study area, and their locations were recorded using a <italic toggle="yes">Garmin Handheld </italic>global positioning system (GPS)<italic toggle="yes"> eTrex 10.</italic></p></sec><sec><title>Sampling size</title><p>A total of 175 beef calf feces samples were collected, with the sample size estimated using the formula <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4PQ/L<sup>2</sup>, where P represents the apparent prevalence, Q is 1-P, and L denotes the desired precision (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Martin <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1987</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Risk factor </title><p>Risk factor data were collected through interviews and feces sampling using a structured questionnaire (Thrusfield, 2007). The questionnaire included inquiries regarding various variables, such as age of beef calf, gender of calf owner, breed of calf, body condition score (BCS), feces consistency, cage cleanliness, weaning age, type of cage, total beef cattle populationper cage, and type of cage flooring.</p></sec><sec><title>Feces examination</title><p>Fecal samples were sent to the Parasitology Laboratory at Veterinary Center for Investigation, Directorate General of Animal Husbandry and Health, Ministry of Agriculture, Wates, Indonesia, where they were stored in a refrigerator prior to testing. The beef calf feces were classified as normal, hard, watery, or soft. A 2 g sample from each specimen was examined using the flotation method with a saturated NaCl solution. The eggs per gram (EPG) of feces were determined using the McMaster technique, which has a sensitivity of 50 EPG. Based on conventional EPG counts, the severity of toxocariasis in beef calves was classified into three categories: light, moderate, and heavy (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Johnson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>Data were analyzed using univariate, bivariate, and multivariate methods. Prevalence was calculated by dividing the number of <italic toggle="yes">T. vitulorum-positive</italic> feces samples by the total number of examined samples and then multiplying the result by 100% (Thrusfield, 2007). To determine the relationship between risk factors and <italic toggle="yes">T. vitulorum</italic> prevalence, bivariate analysis was performed using the chi-squared test, with a significance level set at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Dahoo <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). The variables that exhibited statistical significance (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the bivariate analysis were selected as candidate variables for logistic regression. Statistical analysis was conducted using the Statistical Package for the Social Sciences, version 16.0 for Windows.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>According to GPS data, Pandak Subdistrict in Bantul District is located at an elevation of 27 m above sea level. The geographic coordinates range from 07&#176; 44&#8217; 04&#8221;S to 08&#176; 00&#8217; 27&#8221; Slatitude and from 110&#176; 12&#8217; 34&#8221; E to 110&#176; 31&#8217; 08&#8221;E longitude. The administrative boundaries of Pandak Sub-district are as follows: to the west, it borders Srandakan District; to the north, it borders Pajangan and Bantul Districts; to the east, it borders Bambanglipuro and Bantul Districts; and to the south, it borders Sanden District (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><p>Toxocariasis in beef calves was diagnosed based on the presence of eggs, with conventional EPG counts performed on positive samples. The results indicated that 10% of the calves had heavy infections, 75% had moderate infections, and 15% had light infections (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Bivariate chi-square test analysis revealed that the age of beef calves had a significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) effect on the prevalence of toxocariasis (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). In contrast, factors such as calf owner gender, breed of beef calf, BCS, cage cleanliness, calf weaning age, feces consistency, type of cage, number of beef cows per cage, and type of cage flooring did not show a significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05) effect on the occurrence of toxocariasis. Of the 10 variables hypothesized as potential risk factors, only calf age was identified as a significant (<italic toggle="yes">p </italic>&lt; 0.05) risk factor and was included in the final logistic regression model (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Many beef cattle farmers in Bantul Regency engage in agriculture, which enables them to use agricultural waste as feed for their cattle. Additionally, the region&#8217;s adequate water supply ensures consistent availability of green animal feed. As part of a free cattle health inspection program offered by veterinarians at local animal health centers, farmers conduct health checkups on their cattle every 3 months. However, this schedule is insufficient for effectively managing toxocariasis in beef calves. Toxocariasis can be transmitted to beef calves both transplacentally and through breastfeeding, indicating that calves may become infected either at birth or during suckling (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Starke-Buzetti, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman, 2020</xref>). Toxocariasis has been reported in breastfeeding crossbred Jersey beef calves, and its symptoms include intermittent diarrhea, poor growth, weakness, moderate dehydration, and anorexia (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2016</xref>).</p><p>The prevalence and risk factors of toxocariasis in beef calves are crucial for developing effective control strategies for parasitic diseases, particularly in Pandak Sub-district of Bantul Regency, Yogyakarta, Indonesia, where control measures for toxocariasis have been insufficient or inefficient. Toxocariasis is widespread globally, with significant implications for livestock, especially in tropical and subtropical regions (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Rast <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2013</xref>). Additionally, <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Ninditya <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2024)</xref> noted that Indonesia, as a tropical country with a humid climate and year-round rainfall, continues to face challenges in controlling and eradicating toxocariasis.</p><p>The protective shell of <italic toggle="yes">T. vitulorum</italic> eggs enables their persistence for many years, as it provides resistance to harsh environmental conditions (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Mahapatra <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). Continuous grazing by cattle on land can increase the risk of the area becoming a potential source of <italic toggle="yes">T. vitulorum</italic> infection. Controlling toxocariasis in beef cattle is challenging because of the high reproductive capacity of adult female <italic toggle="yes">T. vitulorum</italic>, which produces large numbers of eggs daily (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Starke-Buzetti, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Dey <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">Healy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). Various factors, including geography, season, age, sex, BCS, feces consistency, nutritional status, and cattle practices, may influence the prevalence of toxocariasis. Numerous studies have identified factors such as age, sex, BCS, season, and feces consistency as potential contributors to <italic toggle="yes">T. vitulorum</italic> infection in different geographical regions worldwide (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Woodbury <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Biswas <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>Study area collection beef calf feces.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-15-1637-g001.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Toxocariasis in beef calves based on <italic toggle="yes">T. vitulorum</italic> eggs and total of EPG feces count.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Toxocariasis</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Category infection</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total EPG</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postive (20/175)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Light </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50&#8211;500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/20 (15)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;500&#8211;1,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/20 (75)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heavy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1,000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/20 (10)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative (155/175)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prevalence of toxocariasis 11.4%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>EPG: Eggs per Gram feces. </p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The presence of <italic toggle="yes">T. vitulorum</italic> eggs in the feces of beef calves of different age groups, particularly those under 6 months of age, indicates that toxocariasis is highly prevalent in calves under 6 months. This suggests that age is a potential risk factor for infection. <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Dewair and Bess (2020)</xref> reported that toxocariasis predominantly affects beef calves older than 6 months, a finding consistent with <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Suwito (2020)</xref>, who observed that the prevalence of toxocariasis decreases with age. This reduction is likely due to the maturation of the immune system in older animals, which reduces their susceptibility to infection (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Starke-Buzetti, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Hern&#227;ndez <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). A similar study conducted in East Java, Indonesia, also noted a decrease in the prevalence of<italic toggle="yes"> T. vitulorum </italic>with age (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Nugroho <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Ridwan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2019)</xref> also reported that toxocariasis was more prevalent in beef calves than in adult beef cattle in the Kasiman District, Indonesia. The highest prevalence was reported in the 30-day age group (49.23%), followed by 39.38% in 31-60-day group, 29.82% in 61-90-day group, 18.85% in 91-120-day group, 12.93% in 121-150-day group, 9.23% in 151-180-day group, and 2.33% in calves older than 180 days. Toxocariasis has been reported in beef calves in the Siak Sriindrapura area, Riau, Indonesia, with a prevalence of 20% (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">Susana <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). In contrast, in Ada&#8217;a District, Central Ethiopia, the prevalence rate was 2.79% in urban and peri-urban areas (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Alkadir <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2024</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Risk factors associated with toxocariasis in beef calves. </title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prevalence % (CI) </th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average of EPG</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beef calf age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#8211;3 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.89 (3.52&#8211;5.29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002<sup>*</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.65</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1685.22 &#177; 273.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#8211;6 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.57 (3.95&#8211;4.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001<sup>*</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">900.27 &#177; 29.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#8211;9 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.65 (2.15&#8211;5.21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">361.52 &#177; 40.12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8211;12 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.44 (1.95&#8211;2.46)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110.22 &#177; 10.92</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender of farmer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.11 (3.95&#8211;5.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">131.56 &#177; 33.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.82 (2.21&#8211;4.15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">631.72 &#177; 150.62</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breed of calf</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SIMPO</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.28 (4.95&#8211;8.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1261.22 &#177; 161.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LIMPO</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.52 (3.57&#8211;5.19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">410.22 &#177;119.52</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PO</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.15 (4.95&#8211;8.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">161.12 &#177; 17.92</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BCS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BCS &gt; 3-5 </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.11 (2.95&#8211;5.67)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">469.65 &#177; 129.41</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BCS 2&#8211;3 </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00 (3.25&#8211;5.91)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">817.56 &#177; 123.18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BCS &lt;2 </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00 (2.95&#8211;6.19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1798.92 &#177; 571.71</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feces consistency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9 (6.75&#8211;5.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">539.5 &#177; 240.18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hard</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.84 (3.21&#8211;7.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">611.54 &#177; 127.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Watery</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.3 (1.95&#8211;5.21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.075</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">502.29 &#177; 215.56</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soft</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.00(8.215&#8211;9.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1266.06 &#177; 192.72</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cage cleanliness</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Good</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.20 (5.12&#8211;9.09)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">232.5 &#177; 306.12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.51(2.95&#8211;7.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">521.91 &#177; 275.16</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weaning age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.52 (3.57&#8211;7.39)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1312.22 &#177; 261.22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;3 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.04 (5.95&#8211;8.49)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">329.79 &#177; 451.65</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beef calf cage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Communal</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.56 (2.21&#8211;9.09)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.078</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">217.12 &#177; 15.28</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Individual</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.72 (5.15&#8211;8.91)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.092</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">710.26 &#177; 223.10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population in cage cage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.11 (2.21&#8211;9.31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">525.29 &#177; 193.29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.72 (3.59&#8211;7.28)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">552.25 &#177; 157.56</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Floor of cage</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Land</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.00 (2.47&#8211;6.32)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1229.22 &#177; 391.54</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cement</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.72 (2.36&#8211;7.51)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">569.27 &#177; 323.47</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>*</sup>Variable significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#706; 0.05); EPG: Eggs per Gram of feces; CI: Confidence Interval, OR: Odds Ratio</p><p>SEM; Standard Error of Mean.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Logistic regression model used to identify risk factors toxocariasis in beef calves. </title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">b</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SE(b)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CI 95%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (1&#8211;3) months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.958</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.297</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002<sup>*</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.78&#8211;27.54</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (4&#8211;6) months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.861</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.284</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004<sup>*</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.71</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.28&#8211;28.26</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constanta</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;0,182</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.279</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.437</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.778</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>*</sup>Variable significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05); OR:Odds Ratio, CI: Confidence Interval; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value: Probability value</p><p>b: Regression coefficient; SE(b): Standard Error of regression coefficient.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The sex of beef calves does not influence their susceptibility to toxocariasis. Similarly, <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Kozan <italic toggle="yes">et al </italic>(2021)</xref> and <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Waindok <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic> (2021)</xref> found no correlation between the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. vitulorum</italic> and the breed or sex of beef calves. This study also demonstrated that beef calf breeds, including SIMPO, LIMPO, and PO, do not exhibit a higher prevalence of toxocariasis. Although the prevalence of toxocariasis varies among different beef calf breeds, the breed does not appear to be a significant contributing factor. This is consistent with the findings of <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Kozan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2021)</xref>, who concluded that neither breed nor sex influences the occurrence of toxocariasis in cattle. <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Hiranmoy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2021)</xref> reported differences in toxocariasis prevalence between buffalo calves and indigenous river buffalo calves.</p><p>Toxocariasis in beef calves typically presents with clinical symptoms such as weight loss and anorexia, resulting in a BCS score of less than 2. However, toxocariasis can also occur in beef calves with a BCS greater than 2, as observed in calves from the Pandak subdistrict in Bantul. In contrast, <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Hiranmoy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2021)</xref> found that toxocariasis was associated with BCS and was more prevalent in calves with poor or medium BCS compared with those with adequate BCS. The low BCS observed in affected animals may be attributed to poor farming practices, malnutrition, and various comorbidities, such as toxocariasis, which could compromise the immune response to the infective stage of the parasite (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Hern&#227;ndez <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>).</p><p>Toxocariasis affects beef calves with varying stool consistencies. Our findings contrast those from China, where a significant association between toxocariasis and soft feces in calves was reported (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2016</xref>). However, in Cambodia, buffalo calves aged 1&#8211;3 months with soft feces were not identified as risk factors for toxocariasis (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Johnson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). There is an ongoing debate regarding whether soft feces influence the prevalence of toxocariasis in beef calves. In a study by <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Ifqiyyah <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2021)</xref>, a link was suggested between soft feces and increased susceptibility to toxocariasis in calves in Jombang District, Indonesia, whereas others found no such association in buffalo or calf populations in North America (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Johnson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>).</p><p>The cleanliness of cages can potentially be a source of various infectious agents, including toxocariasis. However, this was not observed in beef calves in the Pandak subdistrict of Bantul Regency, Yogyakarta, Indonesia. In contrast, studies by <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Ridwan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2019)</xref> and <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Purwandani <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2021)</xref> have demonstrated that toxocariasis is significantly more prevalent in unclean cages, as the eggs, worms, or larvae thrive and develop in such environments, leading to contamination of the environment such as feed or drink. Therefore, clean cage floors can help reduce worm infestations in cattle.</p><p>In the Pandak subdistrict of Bantul Regency, beef calves are typically weaned by farmers aged 3 months or older. This approach aims to ensure calves&#8217; strength and reduce the risk of toxocariasis. However, our research indicates that beef calves weaned at 3 months of age are not immune to toxocariasis because the infection can occur through the placenta or during breastfeeding. This finding is consistent with those of <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Kozan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2021)</xref> and <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">Urhan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2023)</xref>, who reported that toxocariasis is more prevalent in calves aged 1&#8211;6 months. Calves can become infected through colostrum, and the worms may be expelled spontaneously by the time the calf reaches 5 months of age (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Starke-Buzetti, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Bowman, 2020</xref>).</p><p>Beef cattle in the Pandak subdistrict of Bantul Regency, whether housed in private or communal pens, can become infected with <italic toggle="yes">T. vitulorum</italic>. Geographical conditions and cattle forage contaminated with L<sub>3</sub> larvae are believed to be the primary factors contributing to the onset of toxocariasis in beef cattle. In contrast, <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Purwandani <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2021)</xref> reported that the placement of cattle cages influences the occurrence of toxocariasis, with cattle in lowland areas being more affected than those in highland regions. This difference is likely due to the humidity and temperature conditions in lowland areas, which favor the development of worm egg larvae (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Hiranmoy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). Additionally, <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2016)</xref> suggested that the geographical origin of beef calves is a risk factor for <italic toggle="yes">T. vitulorum</italic> infection. Our research indicates that housing multiple beef cattle in a single cage has a minimal impact on the prevalence of toxocariasis. However, the rapid development of <italic toggle="yes">T. vitulorum</italic> eggs may occur when the cage floor is not cemented, and this issue is further exacerbated when multiple cattle are housed together in the same cage.</p><p>The regression analysis indicates that age is a risk factor for toxocariasis in beef calves. Calves aged 1&#8211;3 months and 4&#8211;6 months are significantly more likely to be affected by toxocariasis, with Odds ratios of 18.28 (95% CI = 11.78&#8211;27.54) and 9.71 (95% CI = 9.28&#8211;28.26), respectively. Specifically, calves aged 1&#8211;3 months have an 18.28-fold higher risk of toxocariasis compared to older calves, whereas calves aged 4&#8211;6 months have a 9.71-fold higher risk. These findings suggest that the risk of toxocariasis decreases with calves age. This is consistent with previous studies (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Tamire and Bedore, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Nugroho <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Ifqiyyah <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Kozan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Biswas <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>; <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">Urhan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>; <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Alkadir <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2024</xref>), which demonstrated that younger calves are at higher risk for toxocariasis. One contributing factor is the immature immune system of younger calves. <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Hern&#227;ndez <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2020)</xref> observed that as calves age, their immune system gradually strengthens. Additionally, factors such as semiintensive feeding systems and inadequate calf management also play a role in the development of toxocariasis.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Toxocariasis in beef calves in Pandak Sub-district, Bantul Regency, Yogyakarta, Indonesia is endemic, with a higher prevalence observed in calves under 6 months of age. Therefore, beef calves younger than 6 months should be promptly treated with anthelmintics.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors wish to express their sincere gratitude to the beef cattle farmers in Pandak Subdistrict of Bantul Regency, Yogyakarta, Indonesia. They also extend their thanks to Mrs Wahyu Ananingsih and Ms Sulasih for their technical suppor and Ms Dewi from the English Language Training Center at Universitas Gadjah Mada (UGM), Yogyakarta, Indonesia, for her assistance with manuscript copyediting.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>The authors declare that no funding was received for this research.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>All authors contributed equally to the planning, laboratory work, manuscript preparation, and statistical analysis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All relevant data are presented in the text.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wani</surname><given-names>Z.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allaie</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bushra</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Toxocara vitulorum </italic>in a suckling calf: a case study</article-title><source>J. Parasit. Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1330</fpage><lpage>1331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27876941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12639-015-0682-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5118308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alkadir</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayana</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wakjira</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fatalo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Helminth parasites transmission between species of ruminants in urban and peri-urban areas of Ada&#8217;a district of Central Ethiopia</article-title><source>J. Vet. Med. Anim Health</source><year>2024</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Badan Meteorologi Klimatologi dan Geofisika</collab><article-title>Profil Daerah Kabupaten Bantul. Profil daerah kabupaten Bantul</article-title><source>Badan Perencanaan Pembangunan Kabupaten Bantul</source><year>2020</year><publisher-loc>Yogyakarta, Indonesia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Bapeda Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Badan Pusat Statistik</collab><article-title>Badan Pusat Statistik Kabupaten Bantul. Kabupaten Bantul dalam Angka</article-title><source>Bantul Regency</source><year>2023</year><publisher-loc>Yogyakarta, Indonesia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>BPS Kabupaten Bantul Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>P.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Begum</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Talukder</surname><given-names>Md. H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of clinically used anthelmintics against toxocariasis of buffalo calves in Bangladesh</article-title><source>J. Parasit. Dis</source><year>2022</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>988</fpage><lpage>997</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36457785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12639-022-01522-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9606160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>D.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>History of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara sp.</italic> Adv</article-title><source>Parasit</source><year>2020</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/bs.apar.2020.01.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32381197</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Centers for Disease Control</collab><article-title>Toxocariasis</article-title><year>2023</year><publisher-name>National Center for Emerging and Zoonotic Infectious Diseases (NCEZID)</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dahoo</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stryhn</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Veterinary epidemiologic research</article-title><year>2014</year><publisher-loc>Charlottetown, CA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>VER, Inc.</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davila</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Irsik</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greiner</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Toxocara vitulorum</italic> in beef calves in north central Florida</article-title><source>Vet. Parasitol</source><year>2010</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20138706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vetpar.2009.11.026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dewair</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bessat</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular and microscopic detection of natural and experimental infections of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara vitulorum</italic> in bovine milk</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2020</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0233453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7239449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32433671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Begum</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alim, Md.A., Malakar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Islam, Md.T. and Alam</surname><given-names>M.Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gastrointestinal nematodes in goats in Bangladesh: a large-scale epidemiological study on the prevalence and risk factors</article-title><source>Parasit. Epid. Control</source><year>2020</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.parepi.2020.e00146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7171516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32322695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Healy</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prada</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Betson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First report demonstrating the presence of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. eggs on vegetables grown in community gardens in Europe</article-title><source>Food Waterborne. Parasit</source><year>2022</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.fawpar.2022.e00158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9061247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35518124</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hern&#225;ndez</surname><given-names>D.A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garc&#233;s</surname><given-names>L.F.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baquero-Parra</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Silva-Pinheiro</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alcantara-Neves</surname><given-names>N.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxocariasis and toxocara vaccine: a review</article-title><source>Orinoquia</source><year>2020</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>95</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hiranmoy</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>P.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parvin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choudhury</surname><given-names>D.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Begum</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Talukder</surname><given-names>Md. H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and risk factors of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara vitulorum </italic>in buffalo calves in cthe coastal northeastern, and northwestern regions of Bangladesh</article-title><source>Vet. Parasit. Regional Stud. Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vprsr.2021.100656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34879928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ifqiyyah</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Setiawan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wijaya</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of gastrointestinal parasites on beef cattle in Jombang district</article-title><source>J. Parasit. Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>50</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>W.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adkins</surname><given-names>C.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wehus-Tow</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krus</surname><given-names>C.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buttke</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chelladurai</surname><given-names>J.R.J.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparison of mini-FLOTAC and McMaster techniques, overdispersion and prevalence of parasites in naturally infected North American bison (<italic toggle="yes">Bison bison</italic>) in the USA</article-title><source>Curr. Res. Parasit. Vect. Borne. Dis</source><year>2022</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.crpvbd.2022.100103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9684701</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36437837</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozan</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Birdane</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erez</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goksu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara vitulorum </italic>in calves in Afyonkarahisar, Turkey</article-title><source>Koc. Vet. J</source><year>2021</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>230</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gui</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahzad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sizhu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li.</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chamba</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence, associated risk factors, and phylogenetic analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara vitulorum</italic> infection in Yaks the Qinghai Tibetan Plateau, China</article-title><source>Korea. J. Parasitol</source><year>2016</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>652</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3347/kjp.2016.54.5.645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5127537</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27853122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahapatra</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname> Ali, Md. H., Samal</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moulick</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnostic and treatment technologies for detection and removal of helminth in wastewater and sludge</article-title><source>Energy. Nexus</source><year>2022</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meek</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willeberg</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Veterinary epidemiology: principles and methods</article-title><year>1987</year><publisher-loc>Ames IA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Iowa State University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ninditya</surname><given-names>V.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekawasti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prastowo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Widiyono</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nurcahyo</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incidence and risk factors of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara vitulorum</italic> infection in beef cattle of Yogyakarta, Indonesia</article-title><source>World Vet. J</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>592</fpage><lpage>599</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nugroho</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aditya</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swastomo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aulanni&#8217;am</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Productivity, absence of a bull and endoparasitic nematodiosis in beef cattle farms in an upland area of East Java, Indonesia</article-title><source>Vet. World</source><year>2020</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1982</fpage><lpage>1987</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33132614</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.14202/vetworld.2020.1982-1987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7566263</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Purwandani</surname><given-names>C.E.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuncorojakti</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suwanti</surname><given-names>L.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of helminths in digestive tract of cows in Indonesia</article-title><source>World&#8217;s. Vet. J</source><year>2021</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>658</fpage><lpage>662</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Radostits</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gay</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blood</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinchcliff</surname><given-names>K.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Veterinary medicine: a textbook of the diseases of cattle, sheep, pigs, goats and horses</article-title><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>WB Saunders CO</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rast</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nampanya</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toribio</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khounsy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Windsor</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and clinical impact of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara vitulorum</italic> in cattle and buffalo calves in Northern Lao PDR</article-title><source>Trop. Anim. Health. Prod</source><year>2013</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>546</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22945429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11250-012-0256-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rast</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toribio</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhand</surname><given-names>N.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khounsy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Windsor</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why are simple control options for <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara vitulorum</italic> not being implemented by cattle and buffalo smallholder farmers in South East Asia?</article-title><source>Prev. Vet. Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24290495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.prevetmed.2013.10.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ridwan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Satrija</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winarso</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and risk factor of strongyloidosis in beef cattle in Kasiman Subdistrict, Bojonegoro</article-title><source>J. Ked. Hewan</source><year>2019</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>108</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodr&#237;guez-Vivas</surname><given-names>R.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grisi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angel P&#233;rez de Le&#243;nc</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva Villelad</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Felipe de Jes&#250;s</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torres-Acostaa, S&#225;ncheze</surname><given-names>H.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salasf</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruzg</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saldiernah</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrasco</surname><given-names>D.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential economic impact assessment for cattle parasites in Mexico</article-title><source>Review. Rev. Mex. Cienc. Pecu</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>74</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>D.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on the occurrence, clinical features and pathomorphological aspects of ascariasis in buffalo calves</article-title><source>Vet. Res. J</source><year>1981</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>162</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Starke-Buzetti</surname><given-names>W.A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>C.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>H.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Toxocara vitulorum</italic> in livestock</article-title><source>Toxocara: the Enigmatic Parasite</source><year>2006</year><publisher-loc>Wallingford, UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CAB International</publisher-name><fpage>260</fpage><lpage>277</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Susana</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suwanti</surname><given-names>L.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suprihati</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and prevalence of gastrointestinal parasites in beef calf in Siak Sriindrapura, Riau, Indonesia</article-title><source>Ind. J. Trop. Infec. Dis</source><year>2019</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>160</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suwito</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kejadian toxocariasis pedet lepas sapih pada UPSUS SIWAB di DIY</article-title><source>Badan Penelitian dan Pengembangan Pertanian</source><year>2020</year><publisher-loc>Jakarta, Indonesia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>IAARD Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamire</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedore</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study on prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara vitulorum</italic> in bovine of Senkale Faris Peasant Association of Ambo districts, west Shewa zone, Ethiopia</article-title><source>Am. J. Epid. Pub. Health</source><year>2019</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thursfiled</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Veterinary Epidmiology; describing disease Ocurrence</article-title><source>Third</source><year>2007</year><publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Urhan</surname><given-names>O.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erol</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Altay</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular detection and phylogenetic analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara vitulorum </italic>in feces and milk samples from naturally infected water buffaloes</article-title><source>Res. Vet. Sci</source><year>2023</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.rvsc.2023.104952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37473601</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Waindok</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kann</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aristizabal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dib</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strube</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> seroprevalence and risk factor analysis in four communities of the Wiwa, an indigenous tribe in Colombia</article-title><source>Micro</source><year>2021</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/microorganisms9081768</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8401469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34442846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wyrosdick</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riese</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerhold</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First report of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara vitulorum</italic> infection in a dairy calf in Tennessee</article-title><source>Vet. Parasitol: Reg. Stud. Rep</source><year>2025</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>101184</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vprsr.2024.101184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39855870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodbury</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernando</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clemence</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Toxocara vitulorum</italic> in a bison (bison bison) herd from Western Canada</article-title><source>Canadian Vet. J</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>791</fpage><lpage>794</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3377466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23277649</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>