<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2846</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">openvetj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Veterinary Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2226-4485</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2218-6050</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tripoli</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10399650</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10399650.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10399650</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10399650</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37545702</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/OVJ.2023.v13.i6.5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OVJ-13-705</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Experimental infection of post-weaned pigs with F18-encoding enterotoxigenic and enterotoxigenic/shigatoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> strain isolated from the diarrheic feces in Korea</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baek</surname><given-names initials="KH">Kang-Hyun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tangchang</surname><given-names initials="W">Warisraporn</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names initials="EJ">Eun-Jin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names initials="WK">Wan-Kyu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names initials="KH">Kyung-Hyun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names initials="HK">Hyun-Kyung</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Byun</surname><given-names initials="JW">Jae-Won</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Son</surname><given-names initials="HY">Hwa-Young</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Animal and Plant Quarantine Agency, Gimcheon, Republic of Korea</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>College of Veterinary Medicine, Chungbuk National University, Cheongju, Republic of Korea</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>College of Veterinary Medicine, Chungnam National University, Daejeon, Republic of Korea</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Hwa-Young Son. College of Veterinary Medicine, Chungnam National University, Daejeon, Republic of Korea. <email>hyson@cnu.ac.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>6</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">442423</issue-id><fpage>705</fpage><lpage>714</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>4</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>06</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>04</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-08-07 11:25:10.610"><day>07</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-13-705.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>In the porcine industry<italic toggle="yes">, Escherichia coli (E. coli) </italic>infections have been causing post-weaning diarrhea (PWD) and edema disease (ED) for many years. It is classified into pathotypes and serotypes in animals according to virulence factors. Serotyping is performed for O, K, H, and F antigens, essential for discriminating pathogenicity and epidemiology. Furthermore, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains that produce F18 fimbriae are major sources of ED and PWD associated with Shiga-toxin producing <italic toggle="yes">E. coli </italic>(STEC) expressing F18ab and enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (ETEC) expressing F18ac, respectively. </p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>To investigate the pathogenicity potential and infection characteristics of experimental infection and confirm the pathological features of the Korean STEC/ETEC strains F18ab and F18ac in piglets.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods:</title><p>Three-week-old pigs were randomized into three experimental groups: infected G1 (F18ab), infected G2 (F18ac), and G3 (control). General health status was monitored daily, and pathological changes were evaluated. </p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Diarrhea occurred in all infected piglets. Pathological changes were only observed in the small intestine and regional lymph nodes. In G1, mucosal necrosis, inflammatory cell infiltration with hemorrhagic lesions, and apoptotic cell death in the tunica media of arterioles in the small intestine were observed. In contrast, the mucosa and epithelium appeared almost intact, with no abnormal vessel lesions in G2. </p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Both strains, isolated from pigs in Korea, could be infected and did not spread from the alimentary tract to other organs. The pathological features were quite different among the F18 subtypes. The F18ab strain was more virulent than F18ac, and the virulence characteristics of the F18ac strain were more similar to ETEC than STEC.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Edema disease</kwd><kwd>Enteropathogenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></kwd><kwd>F18 variants</kwd><kwd>Korean strains</kwd><kwd>Post-weaning diarrhea</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli (E. coli)</italic> is a Gram-negative bacterium that belongs to Enterobacteriaceae (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Fairbrother and Nadeau, 2019</xref>). It is known as one of the common bacterial flora. However, some <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> acquires virulence factors, including pili and enterotoxins encoded in plasmids, and are mediated by bacteriophages and subsequently cause disease (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Pittman, 2010</xref>).</p><p><italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> is generally subdivided by pathotype and serotype, associated with certain virulence traits. Pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> in animals is classified as enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli </italic>(ETEC), Shiga toxin-producing <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (STEC), enterohemorrhagic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli </italic>(EHEC); enteropathogenic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (EPEC), and extraintestinal pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (ExPEC) by virulence mechanism, as indicated by the presence of virulence factors (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">Gyles and Fairbrother, 2010</xref>). ETEC colonizes the small intestine via specific adhesion factors (fimbriae) (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Nagy and Fekete, 1999</xref>) and produces heat-stable enterotoxins (STa or STb) and heat-labile enterotoxins (LT). STEC produces the Shiga toxin variant (stx2e), which causes vascular lesions in the intestine, subcutis, and brain, leading to edema and neurological symptoms (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Imberechts <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1992</xref>). EPEC, originally isolated from humans, resembles ETEC, which causes diarrhea. Intimin, the outer membrane protein of EPEC, is involved in the intimate attachment of the bacteria to enterocytes (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). For serotypes, they are designated by O (somatic), K (capsular), H (flagellar), and F (fimbria) antigens. At least 188 O, 103 K, 56 H, and over 20 F antigens have been officially recognized to date (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Fairbrother and Nadeau, 2019</xref>).</p><p><italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> infections are commonly associated with diarrhea, edema disease (ED), and septicemia in pigs (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Pittman, 2010</xref>). Among these, post-weaning diarrhea (PWD) and ED are major causes of economic loss in the porcine industry worldwide (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Pittman, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Nagy and Fekete, 1999</xref>). According to the Korea Animal Health Integrated System (www.kahis.go.kr), 880 cases of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>-associated pig infections were diagnosed from 2012 to 2014. Notably, these included <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolation (423), detection of pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (285), colibacillosis (110), ED (52), suspected colibacillosis (4), polyserositis (2), and suspected ED (2). The data showed that ED and PWD are constant causes of major concern in Korea. </p><p>PWD and ED could occur independently or simultaneously in pig farms, as it is difficult for the practitioner or farmer to distinguish between them because their symptoms overlap (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Imberechts <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1992</xref>; <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Fairbrother and Nadeau, 2019</xref>). Furthermore, F18-expressing <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> is associated with the pathogenesis of ED and PWD in post-weaned pigs (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Gannon <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1989</xref>; <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Do <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>).</p><p>In Korea, recent studies have reported that F18-positive <italic toggle="yes">E.</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">coli</italic> is the predominant strain causing diarrhea (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Kim <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). F18 is subtyped into three antigenic variants: F18ab (formerly F107), F18ac (2134P and 8813), and F18 (new variant) (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Byun <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2013</xref>). Generally, STEC-expressing F18ab fimbriae is associated with ED, whereas ETEC-expressing F18ac fimbriae is associated with PWD (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). The cause of the disease might be identified based on the pathological findings. However, the virulence traits and pathogenesis of ETEC/STEC that produce F18ac fimbriae are obscure, and only a few reports of <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> experimental data exist. Therefore, the present study aimed to determine the pathogenicity and pathological characteristics of the domestically isolated F18ab (STEC) and F18ac (STEC/ETEC) strains isolated in experimentally infected post-weaning piglets. </p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Escherichia coli strains</title><p>Two strains (O139:stx2e:F18ab:AIDA, O35:LT:STa:stx2e:F18ac:AIDA) isolated from pigs in Korea were used in this study. The strains were grown on blood agar (Asan, Korea) for 24 hours at 37&#176;C. The bacteria were washed thrice with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) and centrifuged at 8,000 &#215; g. Colony forming units/ml (CFU/ml) were counted by the standard 10-fold dilution method. For animal experiments, both strains were adjusted to 10<sup>10</sup> CFU/ml. </p></sec><sec><title>Animals and inoculation</title><p>Fifteen 3-week-old crossbred (Landrace &#215; Yorkshire &#215; large white) pigs, with a body weight range of 3&#8211;4 kg, were purchased from a commercial pig farm and randomized into three experimental groups: group 1 (G1, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5), group 2 (G2, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5), and group 3 (G3, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5). They were acclimated for 7days in animal isolation facilities (CAVAC, Korea) and fed commercial feed without antimicrobials. Before the experiment, the absence of pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and other pathogenic agents, such as rotavirus, transmissible gastroenteritis virus, porcine epidemic diarrhea virus, porcine circovirus type 2, porcine reproductive, and respiratory syndrome virus, was confirmed in the pigs. Water was provided <italic toggle="yes">ad libitum</italic>. Sodium deoxycholate (Sigma, USA) was added at 2 g/kg of feed (except in G3) to increase the permeability of intestinal mucosa (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">Waddell and Gyles, 1995</xref>). After acclimation, 3 ml of bacterial suspension of O139:F18ab and O35:F18ac strains were fed to the G1 and G2 pigs, respectively. The same volume of PBS was fed to G3.</p></sec><sec><title>Clinical signs, sample collection, and feces scoring</title><p>Clinical signs, such as neurologic disorders, lateral recumbency, or death, were monitored daily. Body weight and rectal temperature were measured at 0, 2, 4, 6, and 7 days post-inoculation (dpi). The fecal condition was scored (0, constipation; 1, normal; 2, mucoid; 3, watery; 4, watery and hemorrhage) and subjected to <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> identification by real-time PCR. </p></sec><sec><title>Discrimination of F18 subtypes in feces</title><p>To discriminate F18 subtypes in the feces, DNA templates were extracted using the QIAampDNA Stool Kit (Qiagen, USA) and subjected to real-time PCR, as previously described (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Byun <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2013</xref>). Briefly, it was performed using a Rotor-Gene 3000 (Corbette Research, Australia) with a reaction volume of 20 &#956;l containing 2 &#956;l of template, 2 &#215; TAKARA Mastermix (TAKARA, Japan), 1 &#956;M of each primer, and 0.5 &#956;M of each probe (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The thermocycling profile was 95&#176;C for 3 minutes, followed by 40 cycles at 95&#176;C for 20 seconds and 64&#176;C for 25 seconds.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Oligonucleotide primers and probes used in real-time PCR.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oligonucleotide sequence</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Position</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accession number</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> F18F-AGGTTTTGCTAATCAAGGGGG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">228&#8210;248</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="L26107">L26107</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> F18R-GTGCTATTCGACGCCTTAACC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">332&#8210;312</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> pF18ab-FAM-AACACAGGGGCAG-BHQplus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">516&#8210;528</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="M61713">M61713</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> pF18ac-Quasar670-ACAGCCGGCGCAG-BHQplus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">297&#8210;309</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="L26107">L26107</ext-link></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Necropsy and histopathology</title><p>The piglets were euthanized with an overdose of barbiturate. Tissues, including the brain, spinal cords, tonsil, lung, heart, liver, kidney, stomach, duodenum, jejunum, ileum, and mesenteric lymph nodes, were collected and fixed in 10% neutral buffered formalin. They were processed, trimmed, embedded in paraffin, and sectioned at a thickness of 2.5 &#956;m. Hematoxylin and eosin stain (H&amp;E) was performed by an automatic staining system (Ventana Symphony, USA). Pathological findings of the mucosa (villous atrophy, enterocyte degeneration, erosion, and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> attachment) were evaluated in the duodenum, jejunum, and ileum, and then scored (0, normal; 1, slightly abnormal; 2, moderately abnormal; 3, severely abnormal).</p></sec><sec><title>Ultrastructure electron microscopy</title><p>Ilea were fixed in 2.5% glutaraldehyde and 1% paraformaldehyde for 24 hours and post-fixed in 1% osmium tetroxide for 2 hours. The tissues were rinsed, dehydrated, and incubated in propylene oxide. Afterward, the tissues were embedded in an Epon mixture in Eponate 12 Embedding kit (Pelco, USA) and sectioned. Thin sections were stained with uranyl acetate and lead citrate and examined by a transmission electron microscope (Hitachi, Japan).</p></sec><sec><title>TUNEL assay</title><p>DNA fragmentations in myocytes of the ileal arterioles were evaluated by the terminal dUTP nick-end labeling (TUNEL) assay using ApopTag peroxidase <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> apoptosis detection kit (Millipore, USA), according to the manufacturer&#8217;s instructions. In brief, deparaffinized sections were treated with proteinase K (Takara, Japan) at room temperature (RT), approximately 20&#176;C&#8210;25&#176;C, for 15 minutes, washed in deionized water, and treated with 3% hydrogen peroxide in PBS for 5 minutes. Subsequently, the sections were treated directly with equilibration buffer, and a solution of terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase and digoxigenin-dUTP was added in a humidified chamber at 37&#176;C for 1 hour. After incubation, the sections were dipped in STOP buffer for 15 seconds and incubated for 10 minutes at RT. After treatment with anti-digoxigenin peroxidase, digoxigenin-dUTP end-labeled DNA was visualized by peroxidase detection with 0.05% diaminobenzidine and 0.02% hydrogen peroxidase. Sections were counterstained with Gill&#8217;s hematoxylin, dehydrated, cleaned in xylene substitute, and mounted for microscopic examination. </p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Statistical analysis was performed using SPSS version 21 (IBM, Armonk, NY). The survival rate was calculated using the Log-rank test. Body conditions (body weight changes, rectal temperature changes, and feces score) are expressed as mean &#177; SEM and analyzed using an independent <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test for group-group comparison. Pathologic scores are expressed as mean and range and analyzed using an independent <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test for group-group comparison. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> values less than 0.05 were regarded as statistically significant.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>All animal experiments were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Chungbuk National University (Approval no. CBNUA-759-14-01).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Survival rate</title><p>Survival rates were different in each group (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). Three of the 10 animals in infected groups died on the first day after inoculation (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). As a result, the survival rates of G1 and G2 on 7 dpi were 0% and 60%, respectively, while G3 was 100%.</p></sec><sec><title>Body conditions</title><p>No statistically significant differences in body weight or rectal temperature were observed between groups. However, the feces scores in G1 were significantly higher than those in G3 on days 4 and 6 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>), and the fecal condition in both groups was mucoid. Furthermore, watery and hemorrhagic feces were observed in two animals from G2 on days 4 and 6. The feces score of G1 (3.0 &#177; 0.00) was highest at 6 dpi; at 7 dpi, the feces score of G1 was absent, while that of G2 decreased due to the death or euthanasia of fatal pigs. </p></sec><sec><title>Detection of F18-encoding strain in feces</title><p>More than half of the feces were positive for each F18 positive strain at 2 dpi in G1 (4/5) and G2 (3/5). All samples from the infected groups tested positive by the end of the experiment. In G3, there were no positive results during the experiment (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Necropsy findings</title><p>All other organs were macroscopically normal. However, a thin small intestinal wall with redness was observed in G1 (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A</xref>) with hyperemia and enlargement of the mesenteric lymph node. In G2, parts of the intestinal wall were thin, with no hyperemic lesions (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3B</xref>). No significant abnormalities were found in G3 (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3C</xref>). </p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>Survival rate of the pigs after inoculation. Survival rate of the pigs are 0% in the G1, 60% in the G2, and 100% in the G3 at 7 dpi. Each group consists of five pigs. Groups: G1, F18ab infected; G2, F18ac infected; G3, control. ** <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-13-705-g001.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Detection of F18ab or F18ac strains in feces.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Group</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">No. of pigs</th><th colspan="6" rowspan="1">Days post inoculation (dpi)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">G1 (F18ab)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ (died)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ (died)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ (died)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ (died)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ (died)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">G2 (F18ac)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ (died)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ (died)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">G3 (control)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>NT: not tested.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>Feces score of pigs after inoculation. Data are presented as means &#177; SEM of pigs per group. Fecal condition is scored as 4 grades (0, constipation; 1, normal; 2, mucoid; 3, watery; 4, watery and hemorrhage). Feces scores are increased markedly in the G1 and G2 than in the G3 on 4 and 6 dpi. On 7 dpi, feces score is absent or decreased in the G1 and G2 due to death or euthanasia of fatal pigs. Groups: G1, F18ab infected; G2, F18ac infected; G3, control. * <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 versus the G3.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-13-705-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Histopathological findings</title><p>Pathological changes were prominent in the small intestine (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Additionally, abnormal findings of the mucosa in all parts of the small intestine (villous atrophy, enterocyte degeneration, erosion, and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> attachment) of G1 were of a moderate to severe grade and had the highest score compared with G2 and G3. The scores of villous atrophy in the duodenum and ileum were higher but not statistically significant as opposed to those of the jejunum. Severe enterocyte degeneration and erosion were observed in three parts of the intestine of G1, and these were significantly higher than in G2. <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> attachment to the villi was most prominent in the ileum of both G1 and G2 (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). Mucosal necrosis and detached villi with hemorrhagic lesions were observed in the duodenum and jejunum of the G1 group. These lesions were more severe, with necrotic tissue and colonies of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> in the ileum (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). The small intestinal mucosa and epithelium of G2 were relatively intact (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). Inflammatory cells were also observed in the ileum. Among the inflammatory cells, markedly increased eosinophils were observed in the lamina propria of G1 and G2 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>). In G1, mild perivascular edema and karyorrhectic cell death of myocytes in the tunica media were observed (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>). Thickened endothelial cells were also observed in affected blood vessels. These lesions were not observed in G2 or G3.</p></sec><sec><title>Ultrastructure findings</title><p>Transmission electron microscopy of the ileum revealed numerous <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> located on the microvilli (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>). Fimbriae were visualized between the bacteria and microvilli of G1 and G2. Vacuolation and loss of microvilli were more easily detectable in G1 than in G2. </p></sec><sec><title>TUNEL assay</title><p>TUNEL assay was performed to assess apoptotic cell death in the tunica media of blood vessels. In G1, one or two TUNEL-positive apoptotic bodies were observed in the tunica media of blood vessels (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>). In contrast, TUNEL-positive apoptotic bodies were not observed in G2 and G3.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains that cause diseases in pigs are generally characterized by their fimbriae type (F4, F5, F6, F41, and F18) and the presence of toxins (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Pittman, 2010</xref>). Previous studies have shown that both F4 receptors and age-dependent F18 receptors are present in enterocytes, usually during the post-weaning period (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Luppi, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Garc&#237;a <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>), while F5, F6, and F41-positive strains affect pigs at a younger age (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Luppi, 2017</xref>). F18-positive strains are known to cause diseases in the post-weaning period according to the subtype, either F18ab or F18ac (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Cheng <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005</xref>). Antigenic differences in F18 are related to the fedA fimbrial protein, which encodes the major fimbrial subunit of F18. In the fedA gene, F18ac has an additional proline at position 121, whereas it is either substituted or missing in F18ab (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Debroy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2009</xref>). We used pigs as subjects to understand the pathologic features of F18ab and F18ac <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolated in Korea by inoculation of bacterial suspensions via the oral route. </p><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><title>Gross findings. (A) Pleural and abdominal cavity of G1. Redness of the small intestines and thin intestinal wall are observed, 6 dpi. (B) Pleural and abdominal cavity of G2. Thin intestinal wall is observed in parts (arrow) of the small intestines, with no hyperemic lesion, 7 dpi. (C) Pleural and abdominal cavity of the G3. No significant findings, 7 dpi. Groups: G1, F18ab infected; G2, F18ac infected; G3, control.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-13-705-g003.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Histopathological findings in the small intestine of pigs infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic><xref rid="table3_fn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organs</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pathological findings<xref rid="table3_fn2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">G1 (F18ab infected)</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">G2 (F18ac infected)</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">G3 (Control)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significance<xref rid="table3_fn3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Duodenum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Villous atrophy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2~3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0~3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enterocyte degeneration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2~3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0~1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0~1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#8225;</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Erosion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1~3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0~1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#8224;</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> attachment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2~3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1~2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#8224;</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Jejunum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Villous atrophy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2~3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0~1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0~1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#8225;</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enterocyte degeneration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1~3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0~2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#8224;</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Erosion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1~3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0~1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#8224;</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> attachment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1~3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0~2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Ileum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Villous atrophy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1~3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0~2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0~1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enterocyte degeneration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2~3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0~2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0~1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#8224;</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Erosion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2~3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0~1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#167;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> attachment</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2~3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0~3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table3_fn1"><label>a</label><p>Data is presented as mean and (range).&#160;</p></fn><fn id="table3_fn2"><label>b</label><p>Pathologic score: 0, normal; 1, slightly abnormal; 2, moderately abnormal; 3, severely abnormal.</p></fn><fn id="table3_fn3"><label>c</label><p>Significance values of the G1 and G2 comparison are given as: &#8224;, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05; &#8225;, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01; &#167;, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001; NS, no significant difference.&#160;</p></fn><p>* Tissues with severe postmortem changes were not scored.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Almost all feces (8 of 10) of the infected group were confirmed positive through real-time PCR for each subtype within 2 dpi<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> Mucoid diarrhea occurred at 4 dpi and subsequently became watery and hemorrhagic. Body weight loss due to diarrhea was observed in both infected groups. These results indicated that the inoculated <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> was proliferative in intestinal organs and caused diarrhea, similar to the results in a previous F18 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> experimental infection study (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Mclamb <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2013</xref>). However, clinical signs, such as edema of the eyelids and subcutaneous area, were not observed in the present study. Clinical signs are not easily detectable through ED-STEC oral; approximately 30% of challenged pigs showed these signs at 3&#8210;10 dpi (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Bertschinger and Pohlenz, 1983</xref>). Due to these rationales, some studies have attempted to administer the stx2e intravenously, and clinical signs developed 1&#8211;2 days after injection (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Gannon <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1989</xref>; <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Macleod <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1991</xref>). As there were no clinical signs in the case of F18ab <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> infection, adjustment of inoculum will be needed to reduce mortality and extend the experimentation period long enough to develop clinical, edematous, and other signs. </p><p>It was reported that among 11 pigs that were orally inoculated with 2 &#215; 10<sup>11</sup> of F18ab STEC, 5 pigs died within 8 dpi (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Konstantinova <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). In the present study, all pigs from the F18ab infected group died within 7 days of the experiment, despite the concentration of the inoculum being decreased to 10<sup>10</sup>. The survival rate of the F18ac infected group was 60%, suggesting that the F18ab strain was more virulent than the F18ac strain. </p><fig position="float" id="fig4" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><title>Attachment of the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> in the ileum. (A) Ileum of G1. Small round-shaped <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> are attached to the villi (arrow) and some of them penetrate into tissue, 6 dpi. H&amp;E, Bar = 10 &#956;m. (B) Ileum of G2. <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> is also attached to the villi (arrow). H&amp;E, Bar = 10 &#956;m. Groups: G1, F18ab infected; G2, F18ac infected.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-13-705-g004.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig5" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><title>Eosinophils in the small intestine of the infected pigs. (A) Large numbers of eosinophils are infiltrated in the lamina propria of G1, 6 dpi. H&amp;E, Bar = 50 &#956;m. (B) Eosinophils are also infiltrated in the lamina propria of G2, 7 dpi. H&amp;E, Bar = 50 &#956;m. Groups: G1, F18ab infected; G2, F18ac infected.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-13-705-g005.jpg"/></fig><p>Pathological findings for both infected groups showed different features since the stx2e toxin of F18ab <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> can cause vascular damage, resulting in edema and hemorrhage (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Clugston <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1974</xref>). Stx2e toxin circulates throughout the body by binding to Gb3 and Gb4 receptors on erythrocytes, and the key target organs affected by stx2e toxin are the brain and intestinal tract (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Matise <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2000</xref>). Acutely affected pigs showed minimal microscopic lesions, which consisted of mild perivascular edema or karyorrhectic debris within myocytes of blood vessels (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Methiyapun <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1984</xref>). The G1 group, infected with the F18ab <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, showed necrotic enteritis with hemorrhagic lesions, which had been observed in previous studies (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Bertschinger and Pohlenz, 1983</xref>). The lesions were more severe in the ileum than in the proximal part of the small intestine because of the intense attachment of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> to the villi in the ileum. Moreover, karyorrhectic nuclei were also observed in the tunica media of blood vessels and positively identified by TUNEL labeling. TUNEL assay has been used in previous studies for the detection of apoptotic DNA fragmentation caused by stx2e toxin damage (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Wada <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Matise <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2000</xref>). Thus, the TUNEL assay results supported that the stx2e toxin released by STEC caused vascular damage in G1. </p><fig position="float" id="fig6" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><title>Histopathological findings in the ileum. (A) Mucosal necrosis and lymphoid depletion (asterisk) are observed in G1, 2 dpi. H&amp;E, Bar = 100 &#956;m. (B) Note the compound of necrotic enterocytes and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (arrow) in G1, 6 dpi. H&amp;E, Bar = 50 &#956;m. (C) No significant findings in mucosa of G2, 7 dpi. H&amp;E, Bar = 100 &#956;m. (D) Few neutrophils are observed in the epithelium and lamina propria of G2, 7 dpi. H&amp;E, Bar = 50 &#956;m. (E) No significant findings in mucosa of G3, 7 dpi. H&amp;E, Bar = 100 &#956;m. (F) Intact epithelium and lamina propria of G3, 7 dpi. H&amp;E, Bar = 50 &#956;m. Groups: G1, F18ab infected; G2, F18ac infected; G3, control.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-13-705-g006.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig7" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7.</label><caption><title>Apoptosis in tunica media of G1. An ilea arteriole of G1. Karyorrhectic single cell death (arrow) and thickened endothelial cell of the blood vessel are observed. H&amp;E, Bar = 10 &#956;m. Group: G1, F18ab infected.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-13-705-g007.jpg"/></fig><p>In contrast, G2 pigs infected with F18ac <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> showed mild lesions in the small intestine. Moreover, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> colonized on the villi, mucosa, and epithelium were almost intact with infiltration of a few polymorphonuclear neutrophils in the lamina propria, and the inflammatory cells were most easily detectable in the ileum. Pyknotic or karyorrhectic nuclei were not observed in the blood vessels of G2 pigs. These findings were in accordance with lesions of PWD caused by enterotoxins. Enterotoxins (LT, STa, and STb) released by <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> do not lead to pathological lesions or morphological alterations in the mucosa, but they do give rise to functional changes (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Nagy and Fekete, 1999</xref>). LT toxin activates the adenylate-cyclase system within the cell, resulting in increased fluid and electrolyte secretion and decreased absorption (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Konstantinova <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). STa toxin stimulates the guanylate-cyclase system, leading to intracellular accumulation of cGMP and reduced absorption of water and electrolytes on villi (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Francis <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1998</xref>). The mechanism and characteristics of STb toxin are less known, but STb seems to stimulate a non-chloride anion secretion by intestinal epithelial cells (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">Whipp <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1981</xref>). The toxins stimulate the small intestine by increasing water and electrolyte secretion and/or decreasing fluid absorption, resulting in diarrhea (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Garc&#237;a <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). In cases of severe PWD, some investigators have reported that marked infiltration of neutrophils in the superficial lamina propria and necrosis of villi could occur (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Faubert and Drolet, 1992</xref>). However, the strain inoculated in the G2 group was F18ac <italic toggle="yes">E. coli,</italic> which included both enterotoxins (LT and STa) and Shiga toxin (stx2e). Expression of stx2e was not pathologically detected in this study. Therefore, the results of this group suggest that the virulence trait of the strain was similar to that of ETEC rather than STEC.</p><p>Structural study of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> on microvilli using electron microscopy has been conducted in previous studies (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Methiyapun <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1984</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> was surrounded by an electron-lucent zone, which appeared to prevent the bacteria from making direct contact with each other and the microvilli. In the present study, an electron-lucent zone was also observed, and the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> were slightly apart from each other. In another study, 1&#8211;2 &#956;m long fine flexible fimbriae that cover the bacterial surface were identified in the peribacterial zone (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Hahn <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2000</xref>). Therefore, the electron-lucent zone in this study could be evidence of bacterial structures, such as fimbriae and flagella.</p><fig position="float" id="fig8" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 8.</label><caption><title>Ultrastructure of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> attachment. (A) Ilea microvilli of G1. Numerous rod-shaped <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> are on the microvilli of G1 (arrow). Bar = 500 nm. (B) Ilea microvilli of G2. Numerous rod-shaped <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> are also on the microvilli of G2 (arrow). Fine space between <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and microvilli suggests the presence of fimbriae. Bar = 1,000 nm. Groups: G1, F18ab infected; G2, F18ac infected.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-13-705-g008.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig9" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 9.</label><caption><title>Apoptosis of the blood vessel in the ileum of G1. TUNEL-positive (brown) apoptotic body (arrow) is presented in the tunica media, 6 dpi. Gill&#8217;s hematoxylin counterstain. Bar = 10 &#956;m. Group: G1, F18ab infected.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-13-705-g009.jpg"/></fig><p>In both infected groups, large numbers of eosinophils infiltrated the lamina propria. This lesion has been reported in STEC-infected pigs by previous studies (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Kurtz <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1969</xref>), and another study suggested that eosinophil bactericidal activity against <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> is comparable to that of neutrophils (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Persson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2001</xref>). Nevertheless, the specificity of eosinophil infiltration in STEC infection is currently unclear. </p><p>In conclusion, the results of this study suggest that both Korean F18ab and F18ac <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> cause diarrhea in post-weaned pigs. However, pathological lesions were distinctively observed in each subtype. The F18ab strain was more virulent than the F18ac strain, and the virulence characteristics of the F18ac strain were more similar to ETEC than STEC.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This study was supported by the Korea Institute of Planning and Evaluation for Technology in Food, Agriculture, Forestry, and Fisheries (IPET) through the Agri-Bio Industry Technology Development Program, funded by the Ministry of Agriculture, Food, and Rural Affairs (MARFRA) (114058-03-3-CG000) and Chungnam National University.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>All authors have no potential conflicts of interest.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p>Conceptualization: Baek KH, Lee WK, Byun JW, Son HY; Formal analysis: Choi EJ, Lee KH, Lee HK; Funding acquisition: Lee WK, Son HY, Byun JW; Methodology: Lee WK; Supervision: Son HY, Byun JW; Writing - original draft: Baek KH; Writing - review &amp; editing: Tangchang W.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertschinger</surname><given-names>H.U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pohlenz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial colonization and morphology of the intestine in porcine <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> enterotoxemia (edema disease)</article-title><source>Vet. Pathol</source><year>1983</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6336868</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/030098588302000111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Byun</surname><given-names>J.W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>B.Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H.Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fairbrother</surname><given-names>J.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>W.K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Real-time PCR for differentiation of f18 variants among enterotoxigenic and shiga toxin-producing <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> from piglets with diarrhoea and oedema disease</article-title><source>Vet. J</source><year>2013</year><volume>198</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>538</fpage><lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23992871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.tvjl.2013.07.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of fimbial colonization factors f18ab and f18ac in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> isolates from weaned piglets with edema and/or diarrhea in China</article-title><source>Vet. Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>110</volume><issue>1&#8211;2</issue><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16026940</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vetmic.2005.06.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clugston</surname><given-names>R.E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>N.O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D.L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental edema disease of swine (<italic toggle="yes">E coli</italic> enterotoxemia). 3. Pathology and pathogenesis</article-title><source>Can. J. Comp. Med</source><year>1974</year><volume>38</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4272956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1319964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Debroy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheuchenzuber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kariyawasam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jayarao</surname><given-names>B.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of genotypes of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> strains carrying f18ab and f18ac fimbriae from pigs</article-title><source>J. Vet. Diagn. Invest</source><year>2009</year><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19407090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/104063870902100310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Do</surname><given-names>K.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Byun</surname><given-names>J.W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>W.K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of O-serogroups, virulence genes, and F18 antigenic variants in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> isolated from weaned piglets with diarrhea in Korea during 2008-2016</article-title><source>J. Vet. Sci</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30481984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4142/jvs.2019.20.1.43</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6351757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fairbrother</surname><given-names>J.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadeau</surname><given-names>&#201;</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>J.J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Locke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karriker</surname><given-names>L.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>K.J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colibacillosis</article-title><source>In Diseases of swine</source><year>2019</year><edition>11th</edition><publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>John Wiley Sons</publisher-name><fpage>807</fpage><lpage>832</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faubert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drolet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hemorrhagic gastroenteritis caused by <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> in piglets: clinical, pathological and microbiological findings</article-title><source>Can. Vet. J</source><year>1992</year><volume>33</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17423984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1481210</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>D.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grange</surname><given-names>P.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeman</surname><given-names>D.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>D.R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>A.K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of mucin-type glycoprotein k88 receptors strongly correlates with piglet susceptibility to k88(+) enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>, but adhesion of this bacterium to brush borders does not</article-title><source>Infect. Immun</source><year>1998</year><volume>66</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>4050</fpage><lpage>4055</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9712746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/iai.66.9.4050-4055.1998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC108484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gannon</surname><given-names>V.P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gyles</surname><given-names>C.L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilcock</surname><given-names>B.P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> shiga-like toxins (verotoxins) in pigs</article-title><source>Can. J. Vet. Res</source><year>1989</year><volume>53</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>306</fpage><lpage>312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2670167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1255716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garc&#237;a</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gambino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haugegaard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>J.E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrero-Fresno</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>F4- and F18-positive enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> isolates from diarrhea of postweaning pigs: genomic characterization</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>86</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>e01913</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/AEM.01913-20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7657637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32948526</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gyles</surname><given-names>C.L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fairbrother</surname><given-names>J.M</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gyles</surname><given-names>C.L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prescott</surname><given-names>J.F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Songer</surname><given-names>J.G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Escherichia coli</article-title><source>In Pathogenesis of bacterial infections in animals</source><year>2010</year><edition>4th</edition><publisher-loc>Ames, IA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>308</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wild</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schraner</surname><given-names>E.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertschinger</surname><given-names>H.U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#228;ner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#252;ller</surname><given-names>S.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aebi</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural analysis of f18 fimbriae expressed by porcine toxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>J. Struct. Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>132</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11243892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1006/jsbi.2000.4323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Imberechts</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Greve</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lintermans</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pathogenesis of edema disease in pigs. A review</article-title><source>Vet. Microbiol</source><year>1992</year><volume>31</volume><issue>2&#8211;3</issue><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1626371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0378-1135(92)90080-d</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> from piglets in South Korea with diarrhea and characteristics of the virulence genes</article-title><source>Can. J. Vet. Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>74</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20357961</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2801314</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Konstantinova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamrik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kulich</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kummer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maskova</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of intramuscular administration of colistin on the development and course of experimentally induced oedema disease in weaned piglets</article-title><source>Vet. Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>128</volume><issue>1-2</issue><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17977672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vetmic.2007.09.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurtz</surname><given-names>H.J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergeland</surname><given-names>M.E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>D.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathologic changes in edema disease of swine</article-title><source>Am. J. Vet. Res</source><year>1969</year><volume>30</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>791</fpage><lpage>806</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5813671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S.K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>J.W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathophysiology of enteropathogenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> during a host infection</article-title><source>J. Vet. Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>23</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e28</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35187883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4142/jvs.21160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8977535</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luppi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Swine enteric colibacillosis: diagnosis, therapy and antimicrobial resistance</article-title><source>Porcine Health Manag</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>16</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28794894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s40813-017-0063-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5547460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Macleod</surname><given-names>D.L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gyles</surname><given-names>C.L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilcock</surname><given-names>B.P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reproduction of edema disease of swine with purified shiga-like toxin-ii variant</article-title><source>Vet. Pathol</source><year>1991</year><volume>28</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1826800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/030098589102800109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matise</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sirinarumitr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosworth</surname><given-names>B.T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>H.W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vascular ultrastructure and DNA fragmentation in swine infected with shiga toxin-producing <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Vet. Pathol</source><year>2000</year><volume>37</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>318</fpage><lpage>327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10896393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1354/vp.37-4-318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mclamb</surname><given-names>B.L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>A.J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Overman</surname><given-names>E.L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moeser</surname><given-names>A.J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early weaning stress in pigs impairs innate mucosal immune responses to enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">E.</italic> coli challenge and exacerbates intestinal injury and clinical disease</article-title><source>PLos One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e59838</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23637741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0059838</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3634819</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Methiyapun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pohlenz</surname><given-names>J.F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertschinger</surname><given-names>H.U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrastructure of the intestinal mucosa in pigs experimentally inoculated with an edema disease-producing strain of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> (0139: K12: H1)</article-title><source>Vet. Pathol</source><year>1984</year><volume>21</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>516</fpage><lpage>520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6385454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/030098588402100511</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fekete</surname><given-names>P.Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> (etec) in farm animals</article-title><source>Vet. Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>30</volume><issue>2-3</issue><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10367358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bodelsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laurell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Egesten</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bactericidal activity of human eosinophilic granulocytes against <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Infect. Immun</source><year>2001</year><volume>69</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>3591</fpage><lpage>3596</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11349018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/IAI.69.6.3591-3596.2001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC98343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pittman</surname><given-names>J.S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enteritis in grower-finisher pigs caused by f18-positive <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>J. Swine Health Prod</source><year>2010</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>86</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwanaga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apoptosis of enterocytes induced by inoculation of a strain of attaching and effacing <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> and verotoxin</article-title><source>J. Vet. Med. Sci</source><year>1997</year><volume>59</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>815</fpage><lpage>818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9342708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1292/jvms.59.815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Waddell</surname><given-names>T.E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gyles</surname><given-names>C.L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sodium deoxycholate facilitates systemic absorption of verotoxin 2e from pig intestine</article-title><source>Infect. Immun</source><year>1995</year><volume>63</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>4953</fpage><lpage>4956</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7591165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/iai.63.12.4953-4956.1995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC173714</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whipp</surname><given-names>S.C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>H.W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Argenzio</surname><given-names>R.A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of enterotoxic activities of heat-stable enterotoxins from class 1 and class 2 <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> of swine origin</article-title><source>Infect. Immun</source><year>1981</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7011991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/iai.31.1.245-251.1981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC351776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruesch</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of virulence genes in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> strains recently isolated from young pigs with diarrhea in the us</article-title><source>Vet. Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>123</volume><issue>1&#8211;3</issue><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17368762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vetmic.2007.02.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>