<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2846</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">openvetj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Veterinary Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2226-4485</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2218-6050</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tripoli</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11563616</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11563616.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11563616</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11563616</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39553782</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/OVJ.2024.v14.i9.22</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OVJ-14-2334</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Crude aqueous <italic toggle="yes">Proteus mirabilis</italic> extract with quorum sensing inhibitory activity can increase the susceptibility of multidrug resistant <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> to antimicrobials</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdul-Hussain</surname><given-names initials="SR">Samer Raad</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lafta</surname><given-names initials="IJ">Inam Jasim</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Microbiology, College of Veterinary Medicine, University of Diyala, Diyala, Iraq</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Microbiology, College of Veterinary Medicine, University of Baghdad, Baghdad, Iraq</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Inam Jasim Lafta. Department of Microbiology, College of Veterinary Medicine, University of Baghdad, Baghdad, Iraq. <email>inam.j@covm.uobaghdad.edu.iq</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>9</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">475085</issue-id><fpage>2334</fpage><lpage>2347</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>06</day><month>8</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>09</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-11-18 15:25:24.860"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2334.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Suppression of quorum sensing (QS) that regulates many virulence factors, including antimicrobial resistance, in bacteria may subject the pathogenic microbes to the harmful consequences of the antibiotics, increasing their susceptibility to such drugs.</p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>The current study aimed to make an aqueous crude extract from the soil <italic toggle="yes">Proteus mirabilis</italic> isolate with the use of the gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) technique for its analysis, and then, study the impact of the extract on clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa.</italic></p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>Preparation of crude extracts from <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> (both organic and aqueous), which were then analyzed by GC-MS to detect the bioactive ingredients. Furthermore, the extract&#8217;s capability to interfere with both the expression of the QS of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> and its antibacterial resistance was examined.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>The highest GC-MS peak (37.11%.) appeared for 1,3-benzodioxole, 4-methoxy-6-(2-propenyl), along with the presence of other components of antibacterial activities. When the aqueous extract was added to the culture of two multi-drug resistant (MDR) <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa,</italic> a significant reduction in the expression of the QS regulatory gene <italic toggle="yes">LasI</italic> occurred<italic toggle="yes">,</italic> indicating its interference with QS<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> Moreover, upon adding the extract to the culture of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> (MDR) and then subjecting it to Amikacin and Colistin, already not effective on the bacteria, the isolates became more susceptible to these antibiotics showing zones of inhibition of 25 and 17 mm, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>The crude aqueous extract of the soil <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> isolate might be a potential producer of QS inhibitors with antibacterial activities that render the MDR <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> more susceptible to antibiotics to whom they already exerted resistance.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Antibacterial activity</kwd><kwd>GC-MS analysis</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Proteus mirabilis</italic> extract</kwd><kwd>Quorum sensing inhibition</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>The majority of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> strains are motile, and they are rod-shaped, encapsulated, and non-spore-forming bacteria (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Razook <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). This is a multi-drug resistant (MDR) opportunistic pathogen that can cause acute or long-term infection in immunocompromised patients suffering from sepsis, burns, trauma, cancer, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, and ventilator-associated pneumonia (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">del Mar Cendra and Torrents, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Jurado-Mart&#237;n <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Khudair and Mahmood, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">Rossi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). Because <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> mutates quickly and adapts to become resistant to medicines, treating <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> infections is quite challenging (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Blomquist and Nix, 2021</xref>).</p><p>Additionally, due to its propensity to flourish on moist surfaces, <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> is among the top-ranked microorganisms responsible for hospital-acquired infections, which are frequently seen in medical devices (ventilation) (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Jangra <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). The pathogen <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> belongs to the MDR-ESKAPE group. <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter</italic> are together referred to by the abbreviation ESKAPE. According to the World Health Organization, the bacterium <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> is categorized as a &#8220;critical&#8221; pathogen since it is resistant to the antibiotic carbapenem. This means that there is a crucial demand for new medicines to cure infections caused by this bacterium in clinical settings (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Daikos <italic toggle="yes">et al.,</italic> 2021</xref>). Epidemiological studies have demonstrated an annual mortality rate of around 700,000 individuals due to bacterial infections that show antibiotic resistance (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Botelho <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). Resistance to established antibiotics remains a persistent issue in hospital-acquired infections attributed to <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Haque <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Al-Khazraji, 2023</xref>). This versatility in resistance mechanisms poses significant challenges in treating infections caused by <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, necessitating judicious antibiotic use and the improvement of novel therapeutic policies to combat its resistance (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Breidenstein <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2011</xref>).</p><p>Quorum sensing (QS) is a regulatory system that has a significant function in bacterial physiological processes. It regulates various characteristics, including the production of biofilms, resistance to antibiotics, and the virulence factors expression (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Sethupathy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Mohammed and Zgair, 2022</xref>). The QS system and its corresponding inhibitors offer pioneering approaches for the treatment of bacterial illnesses (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Dong and Zhang, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Kociolek, 2009</xref>). A wide range of QS inhibitors have been discovered in plants, fungi, actinomycetes, and macroalgae. These substances (QS inhibitors) involve halogenated furanone (C30) and extracts derived from garlic (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Kociolek, 2009</xref>). Because they are easy to isolate and cultivate and have no detrimental effects on the environment or agricultural productivity, microbes are also an excellent source for the extraction of QS inhibitors (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">John, 2010</xref>). Furthermore, QS inhibitors have the potential to decrease the synthesis of bacterial virulence factors, thereby lowering the possibility of septic shock in the event of an infection (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Dong and Zhang, 2005</xref>).</p><p>Metabolites from natural sources have been verified as effective agents of great importance against various microbes and their biofilms (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Francis and Namasivayam, 2024</xref>), protecting against economically important insect pests (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">Sowmya and Namasivayam, 2024</xref>), along with preventing hypercholesterolemia (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Kokila <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). Bioactive compounds from natural sources have also antioxidant and antimicrobial activities in food applications and the food industry (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Lavanya <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). Furthermore, natural extracts showed inhibition of QS-mediated virulence factors produced by <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">Namasivayam <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). In one study, the environmental isolate <italic toggle="yes">Proteus mirabilis</italic> was found to be a possible producer of QS inhibitory molecules (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">Yu<italic toggle="yes"> et al.,</italic> 2018</xref>). However, the bioactive components of that extract were not analyzed in that investigation. For the purpose of analysis, the technique of gas chromatography-mass spectrometry (GC-MS) is well established and has been used routinely since the early 1980s (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Biermann and McGinnis, 1988</xref>). It uses a tiny amount of plant extracts and is one of the greatest, fastest, and most accurate methods for identifying a wide range of substances, including alcohols, alkaloids, nitro compounds, long-chain hydrocarbons, organic acids, steroids, esters, and amino acids (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Razack <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">Shah and Abdul-Jalil, 2022</xref>). Additionally, it is utilized for analyzing the acquired extracts and can serve as a valuable instrument for quantifying the levels of specific active compounds found in the environment among other sources (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">Uma <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2009</xref>). It is a method that integrates two distinct analytical techniques in order to analyze mixtures of chemical compounds. Gas chromatography is used to separate different components of a mixture, whereas mass spectroscopy is used to evaluate each of these components individually (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Qinghua <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2005</xref>). Thus, the current investigation aimed at analyzing the aqueous crude extract of <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> by GC-MS technique to detect the active ingredients of the extract that might harbor the antimicrobial effect, along with studying the molecular effects of the extract on suppressing the expression of the QS regulatory gene and its phenotypic alteration to the antibacterial resistance.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Bacterial isolates</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Proteus mirabilis</italic>
</p><p>An isolate of<italic toggle="yes"> P. mirabilis</italic> was obtained from the study of <xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Abdul Hussain and Lafta (2024)</xref>. The isolate was confirmed by the Vitek-2 system.</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
</p><p>In total, 8 isolates of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> obtained from Baqubah General Hospital, Baqubah, Iraq, were used in this study. Among the isolates, four were grown from cystic fibrosis patients; the other four were from burn wound infections. These bacteria were cultivated on different agar media, and many biochemical tests were used (data not shown). The assay of polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was applied for the identification of the clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> based on partial amplification of the <italic toggle="yes">recA</italic> gene. Specific primers were designed in this study using Prim3Plus software; their sequences are stated in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The oligonucleotides were provided in a lyophilized form by Macrogen Company (Korea). </p><p>The genomic DNA of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> isolates was extracted by the use of the gSYNC&#8482; DNA Extraction Kit (Geneaid Biotech Ltd., Taiwan) following the procedure specified by the manufacturer. Totally, the volume of the PCR reaction was 25 &#181;l, which included: 12.5 &#181;l of the PCR Master mix (5&#215;), 1 &#181;l of each forward and reverse primer (10 &#181;M), 5 &#181;l of DNA samples, along with 5.5 &#181;l of nuclease-free water. The components of the PCR reaction were then placed in the thermal cycler (Simpliamp, Singapore). First, optimization was done to choose the most appropriate annealing temperature for the primers. Then, the PCR program was set as follows: initial denaturation for one cycle of 1 minute at 95&#176;C, and then 30 cycles of (denaturation at 95&#176;C for 30 seconds, annealing for 30 seconds at 57&#176;C, and extension for 30 seconds at 72&#176;C), and one cycle of 7 minutes for the final extension at 72&#176;C. Eventually, the PCR amplicons were analyzed on a 1% agarose gel stained with Ethidium bromide. No template control was also included in the last lane. Electrophoresis was done for 50 minutes at 65 V, and the gel images were captured by a UV transilluminator connected to the camera (Clraver, UK).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>The nucleotide sequences of the primers specific to the recA gene.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer sequence (5&#8242; to 3&#8242;)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tm</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Product size (bp)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACTGCCTGGTCATCTTCATC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.6</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">104</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGAGGCGTAGAACTTCAGTG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.7</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>Preparation of <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> extracts, including organic and aqueous phases.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2334-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>
<bold>Antibiotic susceptibility test</bold>
</p><p>The Vitek-2 compact system using the AST-N222 card was applied, based on the instructions of the manufacturer, to check the susceptibility of the 8 clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> toward the antibiotics tested<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> The card contained 14 antibacterial agents, including: amikacin, gentamicin, tobramycin, ciprofloxacin, ticarcillin, colistin, ceftazidime, cefepime, imipenem, piperacillin, +mezlocillin, meropenem, piperacillin/tazobactam, and ticarcillin/clavulanic acid. </p><p>
<bold>Preparation of <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> extracts</bold>
</p><p>Organic and aqueous extracts were made from a culture of <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> according to the method of <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Dong and Zhang (2005)</xref>. Briefly, a single colony from an overnight culture of <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> was inoculated into 1 l of Luria Bertani (LB) broth (Liofilchem, Italy) and subjected to incubation at a temperature of 37&#176;C on a shaker incubator (Pars Azma, Iran) for a duration of 2 days. The culture was spun at 4&#176;C for 15 minutes at a speed of 12,000 rpm. Then, after collecting the supernatant, it was filtered via a 0.22 &#181;m membrane. Using an equivalent volume of ethyl acetate (Alpha Chemika, India), the resulting filtrate was extracted twice. The aqueous crude extract was assigned to the aqueous fraction subsequent to the extraction process, whereas the organic crude extract was assigned to the organic phase. Finally, the extracts were subjected to concentration by the use of a rotary evaporator (Buchi-R100, Switzerland) for the aqueous crude extract or by incubation at 40&#176;C for two days in the case of the organic crude extract. <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> shows the organic and aqueous phases of <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> extracts.</p><p>
<bold>GC-MS analysis</bold>
</p><p>Analysis of the aqueous <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> extract by GC-MS was performed by the Central Laboratory, Tehran University, Tehran, Iran. The analysis was conducted via the use of a 6,890 Gas Chromatograph (Agilent, US) connected to Mass Spectrometer model 5973N (Agilent, US). For this analysis, 30 m length, 0.25 mm inner diameter, and 0.25 &#181;m resident layer thickness of an HP-5MS capillary column with a static phase of 5% methylphenyl siloxane were used. The GC Inlet Line&#8217;s temperature was adjusted to 250&#176;C, and a scan range of 20&#8211;600 m/z was applied. The ionization energy was 70 eV, and the carrier gas employed was helium (1.0 ml/min). Based on each component&#8217;s retention index, identification was accomplished, and the supplier&#8217;s MS solution software assisted in controlling the system and data acquisition.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>The nucleotide sequences of the oligomers used in qRT-PCR.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oligonucleotide sequence (5&#8242; to 3&#8242;)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tm (&#176;C)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amplicon size (bp)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">LasI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: 5<bold>&#8242;</bold>-CCGTAGGGGTGGAGAAGAT-3<bold>&#8242;</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">110</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: 5<bold>&#8242;</bold>-ATTGAGTTCGATGCGCAAG-3<bold>&#8242;</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">recA*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: 5<bold>&#8242;</bold>- ACTGCCTGGTCATCTTCATC-3<bold>&#8242;</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.6</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">104</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: 5<bold>&#8242;</bold>-CGAGGCGTAGAACTTCAGTG-3<bold>&#8242;</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.7</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Means the same primer set was used in the conventional PCR for bacterial identification.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Impacts of the P. mirabilis aqueous extract on the QS regulatory gene of P. aeruginosa</title><p>
<bold>RNA extraction and cDNA synthesis</bold>
</p><p>Before the RNA extraction, two <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> isolates (number 1 and 8) were grown separately in nutrient broth (Hi-Media, India), and each was treated with the aqueous <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> extract at sub-MIC at a concentration of 16 &#956;g/ml. Then, the bacterial cells were harvested in a microcentrifuge tube by spinning at 13,000 rpm for 1 minute. This step was repeated to obtain enough amount of the cell pellet. The whole cell RNA was extracted from the bacterial cell pellets, either treated or not with the aqueous extract, by using the TRIzol<sup>TM</sup> RNA extraction kit (Thermo Fisher, USA), and the company&#8217;s instructions were followed. The extracted RNA was stored in the freezer until use. For the cDNA synthesis, the extracted whole-cell RNA was treated with the cDNA ready-to-use kit (Bioneer, Korea). The synthesized cDNA was immediately employed as a template to study gene expression by quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR).</p><p>
<bold>qPCR</bold>
</p><p>The qPCR assay was used in this study to examine the potential impact of the aqueous <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> extract on the expression of the <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">lasI</italic> gene, which is a QS regulator gene<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> For this reason, the qPCR reaction mixture was prepared from the following: 12.5 &#956;l of 2&#215;qPCR Master mix (Tinzyme, China), 2 &#956;l of the cDNA samples with or without treatment with the aqueous extract<italic toggle="yes">,</italic> 1 &#956;l (10 &#956;M) of each forward and reverse primers (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), as well as DNase-free distilled water up to 25 &#956;l. Then, these components were mixed well, put in the qPCR equipment known as Exicycler<sup>TM</sup>96 (Bioneer, Korea), and the qPCR reaction was performed. The setting of the qPCR program was as follows: initial denaturation (95&#176;C, 10 minutes) for 1 cycle, then 40 cycles of denaturation (95&#176;C, 20 seconds), annealing (60&#176;C, 60 seconds), and extension (72&#176;C, 60 seconds). Afterward, the qPCR reaction was pursued by analyzing the melt curve to verify the specificity of the amplified genes and also to exclude the presence of primer dimers or amplified gDNA contaminants.</p><p>To calculate the data of the qPCR assay, first, the Ct values of the target <italic toggle="yes">lasI</italic> gene and the reference or housekeeping <italic toggle="yes">recA</italic> gene were copied to the Excel sheet of Microsoft software. Then, the gene expression fold change was estimated based on the following equations: &#916;Ct<sub>treatment</sub> = Ct<sub>target</sub>&#8211;Ct<sub>reference</sub>, &#916;Ct<sub>control</sub> = Ct<sub>target</sub>&#8211;Ct<sub>reference</sub>, &#916;&#916;Ct = &#916;Ct<sub>treatment</sub>&#8211;&#916;Ct<sub>control</sub>, and Fold change in gene expression = 2<sup>&#8722;&#916;&#916;CT</sup> (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">Schmittgen and Livak, 2008</xref>).</p><p><bold>Effects of the</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic><bold> aqueous extract on the antibacterial response of</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic></p><p>Two <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> isolates (isolate no. 1 from cystic fibrosis and isolate no. 8 from burn wound) were cultivated either with or without the aqueous extract of <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> on Mueller-Hinton agar medium (Hi-Media, India). The bacterial suspension was prepared by mixing a few colonies of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> from a fresh culture with 5 ml of sterile normal saline to yield a suspension equivalent to McFarland tube no. 0.5 (1.5 &#215; 10<sup>8</sup> CFU/ml). Simultaneously, 2 ml of the aqueous crude extract of <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> (32 &#956;g/ml) was mixed with the same volume of bacterial suspension in a sterile tube. By using a sterile cotton swab, the bacterial suspension (with or without <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> extract) was spread in different directions on Mueller-Hinton agar and left for 10 minutes. Subsequently, the antimicrobial discs, including Colistin (CL, 10 &#956;g), Ciprofloxacin (CIP, 5 &#956;g), and Amikacin (AK, 10 &#956;g), were picked by sterile forceps and pushed firmly at suitable distances on the agar surface to confirm their contact with the medium. After that, the plates were inverted and incubated at 37&#186;C for 24 hours. The next day, zones of inhibition were measured in millimeters by a ruler, and compared with the readings stated in <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">CLSI (2020)</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The data were initially subjected to one-way ANOVA to assess the presence of statistically significant differences among the group means. Tukey&#8217;s HSD test was subsequently utilized to compare all possible pairs of means and identify significant differences among the groups at a significance level of <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Identification of P. aeruginosa</title><p>All four cystic fibrosis isolates and the four burn wound bacteria were confirmed at the molecular level as <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, in which a band of approximately 104 bp as the expected size delineated by the designed primers appeared on the agarose gel (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>Agarose gel (1%) shows DNA bands of roughly 104 bp of the partially amplified recA gene of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>. M: 100 bp DNA molecular size marker; lanes 1&#8211;4: DNA of cystic fibrosis isolates; lanes 5&#8211;8: DNA from burn wound isolates; lane 9: the negative control (without the PCR product). Electrophoresis was done at 65 V for 50 minutes.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2334-g002.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>The antibacterial susceptibility of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> clinical isolates.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">No.</th><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Antimicrobial</th><th colspan="8" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIC/In</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIC/In</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIC/In</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIC/In</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIC/In</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIC/In</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIC/In</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIC/In</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ticarcillin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;128/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;128/R</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ticarcillin/clavulanic acid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;8/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;8/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64/S</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+ Mezlocillin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piperacillin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;4/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/R</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piperacillin/Tazobactam</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;4/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;4/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;4/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;4/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;4/S</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ceftazidime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;64/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;64/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;64/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;64/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;64/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;64/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;64/R</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefepime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/I</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;1/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/I</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/I</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/I</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805; 64/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/R</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Imipenem</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805; 16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/R</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meropenem</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;0.25/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;0.25/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;0.25/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;0.25/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;0.25/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;0.25/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;0.25/S</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amikacin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;2/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/R</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gentamicin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;1/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/S</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tobramycin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;1/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;16/R</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ciprofloxacin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;0.25/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/R X</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/R</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colistin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;16/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;16/R</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>MIC: Minimum Inhibitory Concentration; In: Interpretation; R: Resistant; S: Susceptible. All the numbers above refer to &#956;g/ml MIC values.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>
<italic toggle="yes">Antibiotic susceptibility of the isolates</italic>
</p><p>The antibiotic susceptibility of eight isolates of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> is demonstrated in <xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> below. Most of the isolates were MDR. For instance, isolate no. 8 showed resistance to 10 out of 14 antimicrobial agents, followed by isolates no. 6 and 7, which were resistant to 9 out of 14 antibacterial agents. While isolates no. 1, 3, 4, and 5 showed resistance to seven drugs. Nevertheless, isolate no. 2 was susceptible to all of the tested antibiotics. The isolates, regardless of whether they were obtained from burned or cystic fibrosis patients, shared a common resistance profile. In particular, these isolates revealed resistance to each of +mezlocillin, piperacillin, ceftazidime, amikacin, tobramycin, ciprofloxacin, and colistin (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><title>GC-MS chromatogram of the aqueous <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> extract. <italic toggle="yes">X</italic> axis represents time; <italic toggle="yes">Y</italic> axis is the abundance.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2334-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Extracts of P. mirabilis</title><p>Organic and aqueous extracts were made successfully from a culture of <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic>. The aqueous extract was tuned into a powder form with a net weight of 320 mg, while the organic phase was made as a pasty texture in a Petri dish and weighed roughly 1.3 g.</p></sec><sec><title>The GC&#8211;MS analysis</title><p>The GC-MS chromatogram of the aqueous <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> extract yielded 27 peaks, each of which corresponded to a particular bioactive compound (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). The active components with their molecular weights (MWs), retention time (RT), concentration (peak area %), and their nature are presented in <xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. The main compound present in the extract was 1,3-benzodioxole, 4-methoxy-6-(2-propenyl), whose peak area was 37.11%. Additionally, apiol and 1,3-benzodioxole, 4,7-dimethoxy-5-(2-propenyl) also appeared in another area of 12.96%. A third large peak in an area of 10.54% was occupied by dodecane, 1-chloro- and 2-propenamide, and 2-methyl-N-phenyl. Another peak area of 7.98% belonged to benzene, 1,2,3-trimethoxy-5-(2-propenyl). Further compounds were present but in smaller amounts, such as benzene, 1,2,3,4-tetramethoxy-5-(-propenyl), which appeared in the area of 6.56%. Cyclotetradecane, 1-tetradecanol, and 1-dodecanol occurred at a peak area of 5.52%. At the peak area of 4.76%, there were octadecanoic acid and 1H-imidazole-2-methanol, 1-decyl. The compounds succinic acid, 4-methoxy-2-methylbutyl pentadecyl ester, and succinic acid, heptyl pentyl ester, occurred at a peak area of 4.65%. Moreover, other compounds in smaller areas of 1% or less occurred too. Furthermore, numerous substances with antibacterial activities also occurred in the aqueous extract in very small amounts, such as amino acid derivatives (1.09% of N-methyl-dl-leucine), flavonoids (0.64% of 2H-1-benzopyran, 2,2-diphenyl-), quinolines (0.22% of benzo[h]quinoline, 2,4-dimethyl-), and another small peak area of 0.07% of benzo[h]quinoline, 2,4-dimethyl (quinoline).</p><fig position="float" id="fig4" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><title>Fold change in the gene expression of <italic toggle="yes">LasI</italic> of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> (isolates 1 and 8) following treatment with the aqueous extract of <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> compared to the negative control (without treatment). Statistical significance was analyzed by one-way ANOVA, and a significance of <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0001 is indicated by ****.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2334-g004.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig5" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><title>Antibacterial susceptibility test of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, without treatment with the aqueous extract of <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic>, toward Colistin (CL, 10 &#956;g), Ciprofloxacin (CIP, 5 &#956;g), and Amikacin (AK, 10 &#956;g). (A) <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> isolate no. 1 from cystic fibrosis. (B) <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> isolate no. 8 from a burn wound.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2334-g005.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig6" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><title>Antibacterial susceptibility test of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, treated with the aqueous extract of <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic>, toward Colistin (CL, 10 &#956;g) and Amikacin (AK, 10 &#956;g). (A) <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> isolate no. 1 from cystic fibrosis. (B) <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> isolate no. 8 from a burn wound.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-2334-g006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Impacts of the P. mirabilis extract on the expression of the QS regulatory gene</title><p>The qPCR technique analyzed the gene expression of <italic toggle="yes">recA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">lasI</italic> of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> with or without treatment with the aqueous extract of <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic>. Treatment with the aqueous extract of <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> had the capacity to reduce the expression of the QS gene <italic toggle="yes">LasI</italic> in isolates no. 1 and 8 of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> compared to the negative control (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>).</p><p>The one-way ANOVA indicated statistically significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) in gene expression among the three groups (i.e., the control, isolate 1, and isolate 8). Tukey&#8217;s HSD test demonstrated significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) in gene expression between the control group and both isolate 1 and isolate 8 for both comparisons. However, there was no significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.2877) between isolate 1 and isolate 8.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><title>Compounds identified in the aqueous extract of <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> by GC-MS.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak no.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">The compound&#8217;s name</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MW (g/mol)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RT</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peak area %</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">The compound&#8217;s nature</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2E)-2-Methyl-2-Pentenal</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">98.14</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">9.145</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.16</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Aldehyde</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-Pentenal, 2-methyl-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,2-Ethanediamine, N, N-bis(1-methylethyl)-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">186.34</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">11.140</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">1.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diamines</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thiazole, 2-amino-5-methyl-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">114.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterocyclic compounds</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(1H)-Pyridinone-1,3-d2, 4-(hydroxy-d)-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pyridinones</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,4,6-Trimethylboroxin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">125.5</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">15.152</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boron compound</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-ethyl-4-methylthiophene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thiophenes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethanone, 1-(2-thienyl)-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ketones</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-Ethyl-5-Methylthiophene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.175</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thiophenes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Succinic acid, 4-methoxy-2-methylbutyl pentadecyl ester</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">428.6</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">19.079</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">4.65</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Ester compound</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Succinic acid, heptyl pentyl ester</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">286.41</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N-Methyl-dl-leucine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">145.20</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">31.035</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">1.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amino acid derivative</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(E)-2-Methyl-2-penten-1-ol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1H-Indole-3-carboxylic acid, 6-bromo-5-methoxy-1-methyl-2-(4-morpholinylmethyl)-, 2-(dimethylamino)ethyl ester</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">575.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ester derivative</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isobutyramide, N-isobutyl-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">129.20</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">31.058</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amide compound</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propargyl ethyl sulfide</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alkyl sulfides</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-Propanamine, N-methyl-N-(1-methyl ethyl)-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">115.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amines</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dodecane, 1-chloro-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">204.78</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">37.985</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">10.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroalkane</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-Propenamide, 2-methyl-N-phenyl-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">281.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amide</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyclotetradecane</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">196.37</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">38.162</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">5.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cycloalkane</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-Tetradecanol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">214.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohols</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-Dodecanol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">186.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatty alcohol</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,3-Benzodioxole, 4-methoxy-6-(2-propenyl)-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">192.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.174</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterocyclic aromatic compounds</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benzene, 1,2,3-trimethoxy-5-(2-propenyl)-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">208.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenylpropanes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benzene, 1,2,3,4-tetramethoxy-5-(-propenyl)-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">238.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.603</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenylpropanes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-Methyl-1-dodecene</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">182.35</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">43.391</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.76</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Alkenes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-Tridecene</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-Tridecene</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carotol</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">222.37</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">43.683</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">1.11</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Sesquiterpenoids</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3a(1H)-Azulenol, 2,3,4,5,8,8a-hexahydro-6,8a-dimethyl-3-(1-methylethyl)-, [3R (3.alpha.,3a.alpha.,8a.a</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(+)-Calarene Or (+)-.Beta.-Gurjunene</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apiol</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">222.24</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">46.152</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">12.96</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Phenylpropanoids</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,3-Benzodioxole, 4,7-dimethoxy-5- (2-propenyl)-</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-Oxo-4-nitrosomethyl-6-trifluoro-methyl-1,2-dihydropyrimidine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">221.13</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">49.038</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pyrimidines</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,2,3,4-Tetrahydro-1,7-dimethyl-6H-[1,2,4]triazino[4,3-b][1,2,4,5]te trazin-6-one</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">193.24</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Heterocyclic compounds</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-(1-Piperidino)-5-nitropyridine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">217.18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N-(1,1-Dimethyl-3-oxobutyl)-2-methylazetidine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">169.22</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">49.118</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amides</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fumaric acid, 2-ethylhexyl 8-chlorooctyl ester</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">374.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Esters</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4a(2H)-Naphthalenol, octahydro-a-dimethyl-, [4S-(4.alpha.,4a.alph a.,8a.beta.)]-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">182.3025</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpenoids</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palmitic Acid, N-Octyl Ester</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">368.6</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">49.181</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatty acid esters</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4a(2H)-Naphthalenol, octahydro-a-dimethyl-, [4S-(4.alpha.,4a.alph a.,8a.beta.)]-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">182.3025</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpenoids</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,4&#8217;-Bipiperidine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">212.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Piperidines</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Octadecanoic acid</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">284.5</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">62.412</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">4.76</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fatty acids</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1H-imidazole-2-methanol, 1-decyl-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">222.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterocyclic compounds</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2H-1-Benzopyran, 2,2-diphenyl-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">284.3</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">62.532</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavonoids</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetic acid, [4-(1,1-dimethylethyl)phenoxy]-, methyl ester</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">188.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Esters</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adamantane-1-(3,3-dichloropropyn-yl)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128.98</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">62.589</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.72</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Substituted adamantanes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-(3,3-Dichloro-1-Propynyl)Adamantane</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">243.17</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ethanone, 2-(2-benzothiazolylthio)-1-(3,5-dimethylpyrazolyl)-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">303.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ketones</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pyrido[2,3-d]pyrimidine, 4-phenyl-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">207.23</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">64.195</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterocyclic compounds</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-(4-tert-Butylbenzyl)-1,3-propanediol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">224.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohols</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#8217;,4&#8217;-Dimethyloxanilic Acid N&#8217; Veratrylidenehydrazide</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144.21</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">64.224</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hydrazone</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indolizine, 2-(4methylphenyl)-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">207.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterocyclic compounds</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1H-Indole, 1-methyl-2-phenyl-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">235.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indoles</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,3-dimethyl-4 azaphenanthrene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">207.27</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">66.013</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polycyclic aromatic compound</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benzo[h]quinoline, 2,4-dimethyl-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">207.2704</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quinolines</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-methyl-4-phenyl-5-thioxo-1,2,4-triazolidin-3-one</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">207.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thiazolidinones</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pyrido[2,3-d]pyrimidine, 4-phenyl-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">207.23</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">66.053</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heterocyclic compounds</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thymol, TBDMS derivative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">222.3987</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpenoids</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#8217;,4&#8217;-Dimethyloxanilic Acid N&#8217; Veratry lidenehydrazide</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144.21</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">66.093</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hydrazides</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6-(4-Chloro-Phenyl)-5-Nitro-Piperidin-2-One</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">445.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amides</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetic acid, [4-(1,1-dimethylethyl)phenoxy]-, methyl ester</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">188.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Esters</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#8217;,4&#8217;-Dimethyloxanilic Acid N&#8217; Veratry lidenehydrazide</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144.21</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">68.327</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hydrazides</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1H-Indole, 1-methyl-2-phenyl-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">235.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indoles</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benzo[h]quinoline, 2,4-dimethyl-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">207.2704</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quinolines</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>RT = Rtention time.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Impact of the P. mirabilis aqueous extract on the antibiotic susceptibility</title><p>Prior to the aqueous extract treatment, <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> was resistant to amikacin and colistin (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). However, <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> became more susceptible to these antibiotics upon mixing these isolates with the extract of <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic>. A zone of inhibition of 25 mm was seen against Amikacin and 17 mm in the case of Colistin (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>In the current study, eight<italic toggle="yes"> P. aeruginosa</italic> isolates (four from cystic fibrosis and the others from burn wound patients) were included and confirmed by the molecular technique (PCR) based on the partial amplification of the <italic toggle="yes">recA</italic> gene. This gene codes for the RecA protein, which is involved in repairing DNA damage, particularly double-strand breaks, by catalyzing the exchange of DNA strands between homologous sequences (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Del Val <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). When studying the antimicrobial susceptibility of the clinical isolates, this research showed that most of the isolates were multidrug resistant (MDR). This finding agrees with many researchers, who concluded that <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> has multi-resistance toward a wide range of antibiotics, especially beta-lactam antibiotics (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">Mohanty <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). Gaining resistance is common and occurs in bacterial cells either via mutational changes or the acquirement of resistance genes through horizontal gene transfer, and the acquired resistance is highly contributing to the development of MDR strains. This, in turn, augments the complexity of eliminating this microorganism and results in increasing cases of permanent infections (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Munita and Arias, 2016</xref>).</p><p>Among the isolates included in this study, isolates no. 1 and 8, in particular, were chosen for later experiments as they showed resistance to 7 and 10 antibiotics, respectively. Then, an aqueous crude extract of the soil bacterium <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> was made in this study, and its bioactive compounds were identified by the GC-MS analysis. The GC-MS analysis uncovered the occurrence of different groups of composites, including esters, alcohols, alkanes, amides, ketones, aldehydes, terpenoids, heterocyclic compounds, and other derivatives, in the soil bacterial extract. The foremost compound found in the bacterial extract is 1,3-benzodioxole, 4-methoxy-6-(2-propenyl) whose peak area is 37.11%. This compound is also known as myristicin, which is broadly dispersed in the plant kingdom and belongs to the apiole group of compounds, which are known for their synergistic activity. The compound was separated and identified from the hexane portion of Piper mullesua inflorescence alcoholic extract. It demonstrated effective larvicidal efficacy toward fourth-instar larvae of Spilarctia obliqua within 24 hours when applied topically (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">Srivastava <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2001</xref>). According to <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Tisserand and Balacs (1994)</xref>, it was utilized as an antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, and antidepressant. It has also been observed that the chemical myristicin is larvicidal against the Aedes aegypti mosquito<italic toggle="yes"> (</italic><xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">Marston <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1995</xref><italic toggle="yes">)</italic>.</p><p>The second major component present in the extract of the present study is phenylpropanoids, including apiol, as well as 1,3-benzodioxole and 4,7-dimethoxy-5-(2-propenyl) (12.96%). Other phenylpropanes are also present in the bacterial extract; these are represented by benzene, 1,2,3,4-tetramethoxy-5-(-propenyl) (6.56%), and 1,2,3-trimethoxy-5-(2-propenyl) (7.98%). Phenylpropanoids are specific compounds that are often found to have a role in plants&#8217; defense against both living and non-living threats. They can act as a chemical or physical barrier to stop invasions, take part in plant communication that triggers defense responses, or act as a direct toxic weapon against microorganisms or insects (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Ramaroson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). Their mechanism of action on microbes and insects likely stems from disrupting crucial cellular machinery and structures (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Ramaroson <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). Importantly, some chemical compounds found in the bacterial extract of the current study, especially myristicin and apiol, are also present in the essential oil of parsley [<italic toggle="yes">Petroselinum crispum</italic> (Mill) Fuss] (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Linde <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2016</xref>). In addition to its bactericidal action against all tested bacteria, primarily <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, parsley essential oil had bacteriostatic activity against all tested bacteria, primarily <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Listeria monocytogenes</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enterica</italic>. Moreover, this essential oil demonstrated fungicidal and fungistatic efficacy against every tested fungus (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Linde <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2016</xref>). The third chief compound occurring in the aqueous extract of <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> in this study is dodecane, 1-chloro-, which is chloroalkane, and it also belongs to alkyl halides (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">Wiraswati <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). The compound 1-chloro-dodecane was found in Spongia officinalis var ceylonensis extract and demonstrated anti-proliferative properties on three various cancer cell lines (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Ka and Tr, 2021</xref>). Moreover, the plant <italic toggle="yes">Breynia cernua</italic> contains many compounds, including dodecane and 1-chloro-. This medicinal plant shows promise as a possible source of novel plant-derived medications for the treatment of various ailments (smallpox, cervical cancer, breast cancer, and wounds) (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">Wiraswati <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). Dodecane, 1-chloro-has also been isolated from <italic toggle="yes">Streptomyces</italic> spp. and exerted antibacterial and bioactive action (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Al-Rrubaye <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>).</p><p>Importantly, the aqueous extract of the soil bacterium used in the present research contained quinolines (e.g., benzo[h]quinoline, 2,4-dimethyl-) and flavonoids (e.g., 2H-1-benzopyran, 2,2-diphenyl-). Concerning quinolones, they are among the earliest types of artificial antibacterial substances, possessing a wide range of effectiveness against many types of bacteria (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Moussaoui <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). Quinolones have the ability to hinder the activity of two specific enzymes, topoisomerase IV and DNA gyrase, which ultimately prevent bacterial DNA replication (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Hooper, 1999</xref>). These enzymes can be observed in Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria. Based on the Quinolone used for the medication as well as the host, either DNA gyrase or topoisomerase IV can be chosen as the main target in the treatment (<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Pham <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). Regarding flavonoids, they are generally present in flowers, seeds, vegetables, fruits, nuts, stems, tea, wine, propolis, and honey (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Cushnie and Lamb, 2005</xref>). For ages, preparations comprising these chemicals as primary physiologically active ingredients have been utilized for curing human ailments (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Cushnie and Lamb, 2005</xref>). Flavonoids with antifungal, antiviral, and antibacterial properties have garnered attention in anti-infective research, leading to their isolation and structural identification by several research groups. Numerous excellent studies have looked into the relationship between flavonoids&#8217; structural make up and possible antibacterial capabilities (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Cushnie and Lamb, 2005</xref>).</p><p>In addition, succinic acid, 4-methoxy-2-methylbutyl pentadecyl ester, and succinic acid, heptyl pentyl ester were detected in the bacterial extract of this investigation at 4.65%. Both compounds are esters derived from succinic acid, which might possess biological activity, including antimicrobial properties, among others (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Huang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). Succinic acid might act by damaging the structure of bacterial cell membrane as well as disrupting the intracellular structure leading to increased leakage of the cellular components and reducing the cell size. The findings of the aforementioned authors imply that succinic acid can be exploited in the food industry due to its ability to regulate <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas fluorescens</italic> contamination (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Huang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). Other minor elements present in the <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> extract, ranging from 1.16% to 0.04%, are worth mentioning for their known antimicrobial activity. Among the minimal components found in the <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> extract is carotol. Carotol has been reported to exhibit antimicrobial effects versus various fungi and bacteria, and its mechanism of action may involve disruption of microbial membranes and interference with microbial metabolism (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">Mahboubi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). Furthermore, thymol, one of the terpenoids, is also present in the extract of this study. It has been demonstrated to damage microbial cell membranes and reduce the activity of microbial enzymes, and it has been extensively investigated for its antimicrobial properties, particularly against bacteria and fungi (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Nagoor Meeran and Prince, 2012</xref>).</p><p>In the current research, <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> (the MDR isolates 1 and 8) treated with the <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> crude aqueous extract at sub-MIC showed decreased expression of the QS regulatory gene, <italic toggle="yes">LasI,</italic> using the sensitive technique qPCR. This means that the extract successfully interfered with the expression of the QS-regulated gene at the molecular level. These results are in harmony with those observed in the study of Yu and his colleagues (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">Yu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>), in which the filtrate of <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> isolated from soil significantly inhibited QS production by <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>. This finding was further confirmed phenotypically in the current study when the pyocyanin producer isolate of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa,</italic> particularly isolate no. 8 from a burned patient, was treated with the sub-MIC of the <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> aqueous extract, complete disappearance of the greenish dye of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> occurred compared with the same isolate not treated with the extract<italic toggle="yes">.</italic> Importantly, when the same MDR isolates of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> were treated with the extract and then subjected to Amikacin and Colistin, they became susceptible to these antibiotics with zones of inhibition of 25 mm against Amikacin and 17 mm in the case of Colistin. These findings agree with what is stated in <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">CLSI (2020)</xref>, where <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> showing inhibition zones of 11&#8211;17 mm are considered susceptible to Colistin 10 &#956;g. Pertaining to Amikacin 30 &#956;g, zones of 18&#8211;26 mm are considered susceptible according to <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">CLSI, (2020)</xref>. However, in this investigation, a disk of 10 &#956;g Amikacin, which is three times lower than the amount tested in CLSI, was used and exerted a zone of 25 mm. Compared with another study, the aqueous extract of <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> has been shown to exert antagonistic effects on QS-regulated phenotypes, such as the resistance to antibiotics, mainly Kanamycin (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">Yu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>). Overall, the soil bacterium extract applied in this investigation has a powerful effect against pathogenic clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa.</italic></p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, an opportunistic pathogen, is notorious as MDR, producing several acute and long-term infections in those with impaired immune systems. It is well-known that the treatment against <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> infections is very difficult owing to its quick mutations and the rise of resistance to antibiotics. Therefore, studies are needed to attempt new therapeutic targets or antibiotic adjunct agents that can prevent or decrease bacterial resistance to the current drugs. Thus, this study was successful in rendering the MDR clinical <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> isolates to be more susceptible to the tested medications (amikacin and colistin). This occurred due to mixing <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> isolates (MDR) with the crude aqueous extract of the soil <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> isolate. This study is the first to analyze the extract of the <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> soil isolate by GC-MS, which showed the existence of many components with antibacterial activity. Even the compounds found at low percentages in the extract had antimicrobial activities. This means that the crude extract of the soil bacterium might be much more effective than using purified extracts. The data here support the role of the extract as a QS inhibitory agent that had the capacity to decrease the <italic toggle="yes">LasI</italic> gene expression (the QS regulatory gene) at the molecular level. However, one limitation of the study is examining the effect of the extract on two isolates only of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, but not the eight isolates used in this study. Additionally, the effect of the extract on various virulence factors and other QS genes regulating the pathogenicity of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> was not covered. Further future studies are needed to study more characteristics of the extract, such as its interference with other virulence factors genotypically and phenotypically and its impact on QS of other bacteria not only <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>. Moreover, it is necessary to extend the work on the extract by doing <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> evaluation in laboratory and field animals.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The researchers would like to acknowledge everyone who assisted in this study either directly or indirectly.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The researchers declare no conflict of interest is present.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>This work was done privately without any funds.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>IJL put the concept and design of the study and wrote the manuscript. SRA collected the required data and performed the experiments. All authors revised and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data are included in this research article.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdul Hussain</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lafta</surname><given-names>I.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quorum sensing inhibitors as potential mitigators interfering with Pseudomonas aeruginosa pathogenicity</article-title><source>Ph.D. Dissertation, Department of Microbiology/College of Veterinary Medicine, University of Baghdad, Baghdad, Iraq.</source><year>2024</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>N.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baraka</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kabbashi</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arbab</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mubara</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of Lepidium Sativum against multi-drug resistant and sensitive Pseudomonas aeruginosa: a microbiological study from Khartoum State, Sudan</article-title><source>Al-Kindy Col. Med. J.</source><year>2022</year><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>100</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Khazraji</surname><given-names>S.F.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study on tssC1 gene mediating biofilm antibiotics resistance of Pseudomonas aeruginosa</article-title><source>Iraqi J. Sci.</source><year>2023</year><volume>64</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>4356</fpage><lpage>4365</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Rrubaye</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Risan</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Rubaye</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gas chromatography-mass-spectroscopy analysis of bioactive compounds from Streptomyces spp</article-title><source>isolated from Tigris river sediments in Baghdad city. J. Biotechnol. Res. Center.</source><year>2020</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>71</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Biermann</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGinnis</surname><given-names>G.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of carbohydrates by GLC and MS</article-title><source>Boston, MA: CRC press</source><year>1988</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blomquist</surname><given-names>K.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nix</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A critical evaluation of newer &#946;-lactam antibiotics for treatment of Pseudomonas aeruginosa infections</article-title><source>Ann. Pharmacother.</source><year>2021</year><volume>55</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1010</fpage><lpage>1024</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33228374</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1060028020974003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Botelho</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grosso</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peixe</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibiotic resistance in Pseudomonas aeruginosa&#8211;mechanisms, epidemiology and evolution</article-title><source>Drug Resist Updates.</source><year>2019</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>100640</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drup.2019.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31492517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Breidenstein</surname><given-names>E.B.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de la Fuente-N&#250;&#241;ez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>R.E.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pseudomonas aeruginosa: all roads lead to resistance</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>19</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21664819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.tim.2011.04.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>CLSI. Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute</collab><article-title>Performance standards for antimicrobial susceptibility testing</article-title><source>30th ed. Wayne, PA: CLSI Supplement M100.</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cushnie</surname><given-names>T.P.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial activity of flavonoids</article-title><source>Int. J. Antimicrob. Agents.</source><year>2005</year><volume>26</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16323269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2005.09.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7127073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daikos</surname><given-names>G.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Cunha</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossolini</surname><given-names>G.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>G.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baillon-Plot</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tawadrous</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Irani</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Review of ceftazidime-avibactam for the treatment of infections caused by Pseudomonas aeruginosa</article-title><source>Antibiot.</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1126</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antibiotics10091126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8467554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34572708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>del Mar Cendra</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torrents</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pseudomonas aeruginosa biofilms and their partners in crime</article-title><source>Biotechnol. Adv.</source><year>2021</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>107734</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33785375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.biotechadv.2021.107734</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Val</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasser</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abaibou</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reverchon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RecA and DNA recombination: a review of molecular mechanisms</article-title><source>Biochem. Soc. Trans.</source><year>2019</year><volume>47</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1511</fpage><lpage>1531</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31654073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1042/BST20190558</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Y.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quorum sensing and quorum-quenching enzymes</article-title><source>J. Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>43</volume><issue>spc1</issue><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15765063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Namasivayam</surname><given-names>S.K.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combatting microbial biofouling network associated with Chembarambakkam lake water using Acalypha indica derived metabolites</article-title><source>Environ. Qual. Manag.</source><year>2024</year><volume>34</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e22270</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sartelli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKimm</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakar</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health care-associated infections&#8211;an overview</article-title><source>Infect. Drug Resist.</source><year>2018</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2321</fpage><lpage>2333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30532565</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2147/IDR.S177247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6245375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hooper</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mode of action of fluoroquinolones</article-title><source>Drugs</source><year>1999</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10553698</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2165/00003495-199958002-00002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation, identification and antibacterial mechanism of the main antibacterial component from pickled and dried mustard (Brassica juncea Coss</article-title><source>Var. foliosa Bailey). Mol.</source><year>2022</year><volume>27</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2418</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/molecules27082418</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9026341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35458613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jangra</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chhillar</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Therapeutic approaches for combating Pseudomonas aeruginosa infections</article-title><source>Microbes Infect.</source><year>2022</year><volume>24</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>104950</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35139390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.micinf.2022.104950</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural products as lead-structures: a role for biotechnology</article-title><source>Drug Discov. Today.</source><year>2010</year><volume>15</volume><issue>11-12</issue><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20206288</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.drudis.2010.02.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jurado-Mart&#237;n</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sainz-Mej&#237;as</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McClean</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pseudomonas aeruginosa: an audacious pathogen with an adaptable arsenal of virulence factors</article-title><source>Int. J. Mol. Sci.</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>3128</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33803907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ijms22063128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8003266</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ka</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tr</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cultivable bacterial symbionts from the marine sponge with biological activity</article-title><source>Biomed. J. Sci. Tech. Res.</source><year>2021</year><volume>36</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>28635</fpage><lpage>28646</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khudair</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of the antiseptic resistance gene among Pseudomonas aeruginosa isolates</article-title><source>Iraqi J. Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>62</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>82</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kociolek</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quorum-sensing inhibitors and biofilms</article-title><source>Antiinfect. Agents Med. Chem.</source><year>2009</year><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>326</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kokila</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Namasivayam</surname><given-names>S.K.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amutha</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hypocholesterolemic potential of Bacillus amyloliquefaciens KAVK1 modulates lipid accumulation on 3T3-L1 adipose cells and high fat diet-induced obese rat model</article-title><source>World J. Microbiol. Biotechnol</source><year>2024</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>206</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38755297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11274-024-04016-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavanya</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Namasivayam</surname><given-names>S.K.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Developmental formulation principles of food preservatives by nanoencapsulation&#8212;fundamentals, application, and challenges</article-title><source>Appl. Biochem. Biotechnol</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12010-024-04943-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38713338</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Linde</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gazim</surname><given-names>Z.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>B.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jorge</surname><given-names>L.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Te&#353;evi&#263;</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glamo&#269;lija</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sokovi&#263;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colauto</surname><given-names>N.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antifungal and antibacterial activities of Petroselinum crispum essential oil</article-title><source>Genet. Mol. Res.</source><year>2016</year><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>15038538</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4238/gmr.15038538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27525894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahboubi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahdizadeh</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabar</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical composition and antimicrobial activity of Fraxinus excelsior L. seeds essential oil</article-title><source>Jundishapur J. Nat. Pharm. Prod</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e61105</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marston</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hostettmann</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Msonthi</surname><given-names>J.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of antifungal and larvicidal constituents of Diplolophium buchanani by centrifugal partition chromatography</article-title><source>J. Nat. Prod.</source><year>1995</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>128</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7760070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/np50115a019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zgair</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of quorum sensing genes of Pseudomonas aeruginosa isolated from different areas in Iraq</article-title><source>Iraqi J. Sci.</source><year>2022</year><volume>63</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>4665</fpage><lpage>4673</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baliyarsingh</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial resistance in Pseudomonas aeruginosa: a concise</article-title><source>Antimicrob. Resist. One Health Perspect.</source><year>2021</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>192</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moussaoui</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhadane</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sghyar</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Hadrami</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Amrani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ben Tama</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodi</surname><given-names>Y.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chakroune</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salo-Ahen</surname><given-names>O.M.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel amino acid derivatives of quinolines as potential antibacterial and fluorophore agents</article-title><source>Sci. Pharm.</source><year>2020</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>57</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Munita</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arias</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of antibiotic resistance</article-title><source>Microbiol. Spectr.</source><year>2016</year><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/microbiolspec.VMBF-0016-2015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4888801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27227291</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagoor Meeran</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prince</surname><given-names>S.M.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protective effects of thymol on altered plasma lipid peroxidation and nonenzymic antioxidants in isoproterenol-induced myocardial infarcted rats</article-title><source>J. Biochem. Mol. Toxicol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>26</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>368</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22890907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/jbt.21431</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Namasivayam</surname><given-names>S.K.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jerry Angel</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arvind Bharani</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valli Nachiyar</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Terminalia chebula and Ficus racemosa principles mediated repression of novel drug target Las R&#8212;the transcriptional regulator and its controlled virulence factors produced by multiple drug resistant Pseudomonas aeruginosa&#8212;biocompatible formulation against drug resistant bacteria</article-title><source>Microb. Pathog.</source><year>2020</year><volume>148</volume><fpage>104412</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32798672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.micpath.2020.104412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ziora</surname><given-names>Z.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blaskovich</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quinolone antibiotics</article-title><source>Medchemcomm,</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1719</fpage><lpage>1739</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31803393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1039/c9md00120d</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6836748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qinghua</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yangmin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huqiang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preliminary study on chemical composition and insecticidal activity of root bark from Periploca sepium</article-title><source>Acta Agric. Bor. Sin.</source><year>2005</year><volume>14</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>144</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramaroson</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koutouan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helesbeux</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Clerc</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamama</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geoffriau</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Briard</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of phenylpropanoids and flavonoids in plant resistance to pests and diseases</article-title><source>Mol.</source><year>2022</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>8371</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/molecules27238371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9735708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36500459</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Razack</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hemanth Kumar</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nallamuthu</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naika</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khanum</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant, biomolecule oxidation protective activities of Nardostachys jatamansi DC and its phytochemical analysis by RP-HPLC and GC-MS</article-title><source>Antioxid.</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/antiox4010185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4665568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26785345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Razook</surname><given-names>B.R.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-ani</surname><given-names>A.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hematological picture of rabbits immunized with Pseudomonas aeruginosa</article-title><source>Iraqi J. Vet. Med. 44(E0), 64&#8211;68</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>La Rosa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartell</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marvig</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haagensen</surname><given-names>J.A.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sommer</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Molin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>H.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pseudomonas aeruginosa adaptation and evolution in patients with cystic fibrosis</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source><year>2021</year><volume>19</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33214718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41579-020-00477-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analyzing real-time PCR data by the comparative CT method</article-title><source>Nat. Protoc.</source><year>2008</year><volume>3</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1101</fpage><lpage>1108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18546601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nprot.2008.73</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sethupathy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasath</surname><given-names>K.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ananthi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahalingam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balan</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandian</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteomic analysis reveals modulation of iron homeostasis and oxidative stress response in Pseudomonas aeruginosa PAO1 by curcumin inhibiting quorum sensing regulated virulence factors and biofilm production</article-title><source>J. Proteom.</source><year>2016</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jprot.2016.04.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27108548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdul-Jalil</surname><given-names>T.Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Qualitative and quantitative estimation or chemical constituents from leaves and roots of Iraqi Agave Attenuata by GC-MS and RP-HPLC (Conference Paper)</article-title><source>Iraqi J. Pharm. Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>31</volume><issue>Suppl.</issue><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>85</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sowmya</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Namasivayam</surname><given-names>S.K.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pesticidal activity of extra cellular metabolites extracted from the green muscardian fungi Metarhizium anisopliae</article-title><source>Environ. Qual. Manag.</source><year>2024</year><volume>34</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e22235</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prajapati</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sushil Kumar</surname><given-names>Tripathi A.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insecticidal activity of Myristicin from Piper mullesua</article-title><source>Pharm. Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>39</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>229</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tisserand</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balacs</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutmeg: A review of the toxicology and pharmacology of nutmeg and its essential oil</article-title><source>Int. J. Aromather.</source><year>1994</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uma</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prabhakar</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajendran</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lakshmi Sarayu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on GC/MS spectroscopic analysis of some bioactive antimicrobial compounds from Cinnamomum zeylanicum</article-title><source>J. Med. Plants.</source><year>2009</year><volume>8</volume><issue>31</issue><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>131</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiraswati</surname><given-names>H.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fauziah</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pradini</surname><given-names>G.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurnia</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kodir</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berbudi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arimdayu</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laelalugina</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Supandi and Ma&#8217;ruf</surname><given-names>I.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breynia cernua: chemical profiling of volatile compounds in the stem extract and its antioxidant, antibacterial, antiplasmodial and anticancer activity in vitro and in silico</article-title><source>Metabolites</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>281</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36837900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/metabo13020281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9966293</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biofilm inhibition and pathogenicity attenuation in bacteria by Proteus mirabilis</article-title><source>R. Soc. Open Sci.</source><year>2018</year><volume>5</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>170702</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29765621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1098/rsos.170702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5936886</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>