<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2846</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">openvetj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Veterinary Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2226-4485</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2218-6050</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tripoli</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11338614</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11338614.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11338614</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11338614</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39175968</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/OVJ.2024.v14.i7.7</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OVJ-14-1577</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sero epidemiological study on bovine babesiosis in cattle and buffaloes in Sharkia Governorate, Egypt</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yousef</surname><given-names initials="SG">Sarah Gamal</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sobhy</surname><given-names initials="NM">Nader Maher</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gouda</surname><given-names initials="H">Heba</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emam</surname><given-names initials="MH">Mahmoud Helmy</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Animal Medicine, Infectious Diseases, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Zagazig University, Zagazig, Egypt</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Animal Medicine, Internal Medicine, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Zagazig University, Zagazig, Egypt</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Mahmoud Helmy Emam. Department of Animal Medicine, Internal Medicine, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Zagazig University, Zagazig, Egypt. <email>mh5378721@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>7</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">469219</issue-id><fpage>1577</fpage><lpage>1584</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>08</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>22</day><month>08</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-08-29 02:26:00.763"><day>29</day><month>08</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-1577.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Bovine babesiosis represents a serious challenge for animal health, herd production, and profitability. Understanding the epidemiology and risk factors associated with babesiosis is critical to reduce their negative impacts.</p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>Investigation of the seroprevalence and risk factors associated with <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bigemina</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bovis</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic>) in five districts in Sharkia governorate using ELISA.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods:</title><p>Across-sectional research was conducted to determine the seropositivity of babesiosis by collecting a total of 352 blood samples from 250 cattle and 102 buffaloes. A multivariate logistic regression model was implemented to evaluate the strength of the risk factors associated with both Babesia species infection.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>The seroprevalence of <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> was 42.6% and 17.0 %, respectively. The prevalence of babesiosis in cattle was found to be 48.8% for <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and 16.8% for <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic>. Inclusive, in buffaloes, the prevalence was 27.5% for <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and 17.6% for <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic>. Adult animals were more vulnerable to infection with babesia than young animals by 3&#8211;5 times, respectively. Males were more susceptible to <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> than females by 3.7 and 3.5 times. Similarly, the odds of infection in infested animals with ticks were 2&#8211;4 times higher than in animals without ticks.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>The obtained results revealed that age, sex of the animal, and tick infestation were major risk factors for the seropositivity of both Babesia species. Inclusive, there was no evidence to support the premise that seroprevalence of babesiosis is correlated with the season and species.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Babesia bigemina</italic></kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Babesia bovis</italic></kwd><kwd>Egypt</kwd><kwd>Epidemiology</kwd><kwd>Risk factors</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Ticks and tick-borne diseases are considered a global problem because of their detrimental effects on livestock productivity (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Guswanto <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017</xref>). Bovine babesiosis is considered the most prevalent infection detected in cattle and buffaloes, particularly in subtropical and in tropical areas (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Fakhar <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Jaimes-Due&#241;ez <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017</xref>). The clinical findings of bovine babesiosis vary from acute to subacute form (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">G&#243;es <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). The sub-acute form usually occurs in endemic areas with previous exposure and an abundance of tick population; it is manifested only by a slight rise in body temperature (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">Terkawi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2011</xref>). Babesia bovis and <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bigemina</italic> are the most popular species in Egypt because of the abundance of their vector ticks (<italic toggle="yes">Rhipicephalus microplus </italic>and Rhipicephalus annulatus) (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Adham <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Hassan <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017</xref>). In Egypt, Babesia is the most endemic blood parasite in cattle and buffaloes and has a significant impact on milk, meat production, and herd management (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Adham <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Mahmoud <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). Previous studies recorded different prevalence rates of bovine babesiosis among cattle and buffaloes in Egypt (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Ibrahim <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Fereig <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">El-Bahy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2018</xref>). The variation in the infection rate in Egypt is attributed to animal management, climatic changes, immune status, and study place (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Menshawy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>).</p><p>Molecular and serological assays are more sensitive in detection and differentiation between babesia species in carrier animals. Furthermore, Nucleic acid-based techniques are capable of identifying one parasite per 1 million RBCs (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Criado-Fornelio, 2007</xref>). Serological tests such as ELISA and IFA are widely used in large-scale surveillances (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Gul <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2015</xref>). ELISA is an adequate serological method as it is less laborious than IFA and has greater sensitivity and specificity for detection and differentiation between <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Sharma <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2013</xref>).</p><p>Nowadays, understanding the epidemiological features of babesiosis is a critical step toward the managemental control of the disease and improving our ability to detect and predict this health disorder (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Aziz <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Mahmoud <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2015</xref>). To the best of authors knowledge, there is limited information regarding bovine babesiosis in Sharkia governorate, Egypt. Therefore, our study focused on seroprevalence of Babesia species in large ruminants. Moreover, evaluation of the risk factors including seasonal variations, age, species, sex, and tick infestation associated with bovine babesiosis in five districts in the Sharkia governorate.</p></sec><sec><title>Material and Methods</title><sec><title>Study design and sample size calculation</title><p>Our investigation was carried out in Sharkia governorate, particularly in five districts (Zaqaziq, Abu Hammad, Bilbis, Minya Al-Qamh, and Faqus) since April 2023 up to March 2024. Sharkia governorate is located in the northern part of Egypt in the Eastern Nile Delta (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). A cross-sectional study has been conducted in five different districts to investigate the prevalence of babesiosis in the Sharkia governorate. In our investigation, each district was subject to a random selection of smallholder farms. These farms were for meat or milk production. Additionally, the cattle and buffaloes that were used for sampling were chosen at random from each farm (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The minimum sample size was calculated presuming a 95% confidence interval, 50% expected true population and a 0.05 margin of error (&#945;) regarding the following formula (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Thrusfield, 2018</xref>).</p><disp-formula><mml:math id="math1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.33em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.33em"/><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>(</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>.</mml:mi><mml:mn>96</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.33em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">P</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.33em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">exp</mml:mi><mml:mi>(</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#8211;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">P</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.33em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">exp</mml:mi><mml:mi>)</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mfrac></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Where, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = Sample size, P exp = Expected true population, d = Desired margin of error.</p></sec><sec><title>Samples and data collection</title><p>A total of 352 blood samples were collected from apparently healthy 250 cattle and 102 buffaloes for diagnosis of babesiosis infection (<italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic>) in Sharkia governorate. The blood samples were collected from jugular vein in sterile vacutainer tubes without anticoagulant for separation of serum. All samples were transported in an ice box to the laboratory of the Animal Medicine Department, Zagazig University, Egypt. The serum samples were separated and frozen at &#8211;20&#176;C until further examination. The data regarding animals' species, age, sex, housing condition, and feeding management were recorded during sample collection. Moreover, all animals were inspected for the presence of ticks.</p></sec><sec><title>Sandwich ELISA</title><p>Babesia bigemina and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> antibody test kits were obtained from Sinogeneclon Biotech company (Hangzhou, China). The tests were performed according to manufacturer instructions. Briefly, the antigen-coated microtiter plates were incubated with 50 &#181;l of diluted serum samples (10:40) for 30 minutes at 37&#176;C. The plates were washed five times with diluted washing solution and incubated with 50 &#181;l of horseradish peroxidase conjugate for 30 minutes at 37&#176;C. The plates were washed again five times then, and 100 &#181;l of substrate solution was added to each well for 15 minutes. Finally, 50 &#181;l of stop solution was added to stop the reaction. The optical density was measured by a Microtiter plate reader (Biotech 808) at a wavelength of 450 nm. The cut-off value was calculated as the average of negative control well +0.15.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>Map of sampling areas in Sharkia governorate, Egypt. The five districts were Zagazig, Abu Hammad, Bilbis, Faqus and Minya Al Qamh.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-14-1577-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The statistical analysis was performed with the SPSS program (SPSS 25 for Windows, SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). The objected explanatory variables were age, sex and species of the animals, season, location, and tick infestation. The response variable was the serological status of the examined animals (either seronegative or seropositive) for both types of Babesia species. The Univariate logistic regression model was used firstly to evaluate the association between each independent variable and the serological status of <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic>. The predictors with <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> values &#8804; 0.20 were retained in the final multivariate logistic regression model. The predictors with a <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value &lt; 0.05 were considered significant.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>The protocol of animal handling was approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at Zagazig University with protocol number (ZU-IACUC/2/F/74/2024).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Seroprevalence of bovine babesiosis</title><p>The prevalence of babesiosis in the Sharkia governorate was 42.6% and 17.0 % for <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic>, respectively. The number of examined animals and the prevalence of the infection in each district were documented in (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In total, 250 cattle and 102 buffaloes were tested for <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> antibodies. The seroprevalence of <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> in cattle was 48.8% and 16.8%, respectively. In buffaloes, the seroprevalence of <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> was 27.5% and 17.6%, respectively (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Tables 2</xref> and <xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The seroprevalence of <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> was (56.8%, 37.8%) while <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> was (15.9%, 17.4%) for males and females, respectively. The seroprevalence of both Babesia species was higher in the presence of ticks compared to the absence of ticks. Regarding the animal's age, the category (&gt;2&#8211;4 years) represented the highest prevalence for <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> with 57.7% and 24.5%, respectively. <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bigemina</italic> had the highest seroprevalence throughout the summer, with a rate of 47.3%, whereas <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> had the highest seroprevalence during autumn, with a rate of 28.2% (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Tables 2</xref> and <xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The animal-seroprevalence among the studied districts ranged from (28% to 43% for <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic>) and (10%&#8211;20% for <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic>) except for Zagazig that had higher seroprevalence for <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> (61%) (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Univariate regression analysis</title><p>The explanatory variables were evaluated separately for their association with the seropositivity of Babesia species (<italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic>). As shown in <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, age, sex, species, existence of ticks, and locality were considered significant risk factors for infection with <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.20). Both yearling and adult animals (up to 4 years) were more susceptible to infection compared to calves. Females and buffaloes were at a lower level of risk for infection relative to males and cattle. The presence of tick infestation heightened the risk of infection compared to the absence of ticks. Animals from Minya al-Qamh had the highest risk of exposure compared with other districts. Regarding <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic>, the seropositivity was significantly associated with age, sex, and tick infestation (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Animals younger than 6 months were more resistant to infection compared to older ages. Males were more vulnerable than females, and infested animals with ticks were more exhibited to infection than animals free from ticks.</p></sec><sec><title>Multivariate regression analysis </title><p>The final models (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>) revealed that the presence of ticks beside age and sex was significantly associated with babesiosis prevalence (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). The probability of infection increased with age. Adult animals were more exposed to infection with <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> than young animals by 3&#8211;5 times, respectively. The odds of infection in infested animals with ticks were 2&#8211;4 times higher than in animals without ticks. The risk of exposure to both infections was lower in females than in males. The odds of exposure to <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> in males were 3.7 and 3.5 times higher than in females.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>The number of farms and animals selected for the study and subjected to ELISA testing from Sharkia governorate, Egypt, for <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">bovis</italic> antibodies.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">District</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">N of examined farms</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No of examined animals</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemnia</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bilbis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (43.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (10.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Faqus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (33.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (14.3%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minya Al Qamh</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (34.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (20.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abu Hammad</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (28.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (19.0%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zagazig</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (61.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (18.4%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">352</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">150 (42.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (17.0%)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>The univariate logistic regression model for risk factors associated with <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> infection.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No of examined animals</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No of positive animals (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR<sup>1</sup></th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% CI<sup>2</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P-</italic>value<sup>3</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;6 months<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (37.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;6 months&#8211;2years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (40.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.137</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.464</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.786</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;2 years&#8211;4years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (57.7%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.985</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.843</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.676</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;4 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (33.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.676</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.326</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.069</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">264</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (37.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (56.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.158</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.080</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.313</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Species</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cattle<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (48.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Buffalo</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (27.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.397</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.196</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.806</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Tick</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">156</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (32.1%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">196</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (51.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.208</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.189</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Season</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Winter<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (32%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autumn</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (43.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.810</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.657</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.981</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Summer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (47.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.919</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.779</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.727</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spring</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (32%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.991</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.313</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.155</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">location</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Faqus<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (33.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zagazig</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (61.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.263</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.117</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.533</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minya Al Qamh</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (34.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.056</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.364</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.059</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bilbis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (43.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.529</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.480</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.877</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abu Hammad</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (28.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.667</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.171</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.596</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>1</sup>OR: Odds ratio; <sup>2</sup>CI, confidence interval (95%); <sup>3</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &#8804; 0.20 was used to detect which variables will be retained in the final multivariate model; <sup>4</sup>Reference category means the value to which the variable-level is being compared while controlling for the effect of the other predictors in the models.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The objective of this study was to evaluate the prevalence and potential causes of bovine babesiosis in various regions within the Sharkia governorate, Egypt, using ELISA. Sharkia is the second governorate at the level of the Republic in terms of agricultural area after the Al-Behera Governorate in Egypt. This investigation was objected to this area because it is one of the most famous governorates for breeding livestock, and there is a lack of available data regarding the infection with bovine babesiosis.</p><p>In current investigation, the overall seroprevalence for babesiosis in the Sharkia governorate was 42.6% and 17.0 % for <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic>, respectively. The higher occurrence of <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> may be due to the abundance of their main vector tick <italic toggle="yes">(Rhipicephalus annulatus)</italic> in the Sharkia governorate (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Yousef, 2020</xref>) in addition to the diversity of tick species that transmit <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> counter to <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> that is transmitted mainly by <italic toggle="yes">R. microplus</italic> (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Bock <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2004</xref>). Our results agreed with (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Ibrahim <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2013</xref>), who reported a higher prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> compared with <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> in the Behiera and Faiyum governorates, with percentages of 12.5% and 10.12%, respectively. Similarly, <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Mahmoud <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2015)</xref> and <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Fereig <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2017)</xref> reported a higher frequency of <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> compared with <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> in different districts in lower and upper Egypt. On the other hand, a Vietnamese study recorded a higher seroprevalence of <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> (37.4%) than <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> (9.3%) in the studied buffaloes (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). This fluctuation may be attributed to the environmental and managemental differences between Egyptian and other foreign districts and the geographic distribution of tick vectors.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>The univariate logistic regression model for risk factors associated with <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bovis</italic> infection.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No of examined animals</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No of positive animals (%)</th><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR<sup>1</sup></td><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% CI<sup>2</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P-</italic>value<sup>3</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.123</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;6 months<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (10.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;6 months&#8211;2 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (15.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.338</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.347</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.157</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;2 years&#8211;4 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (24.5%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.936</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.224</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;4 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (14.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.146</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.238</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.633</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">264</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (17.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (15.9%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.964</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.439</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.417</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Species</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cattle<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (16.8%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Buffalo</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (17.6%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.061</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.865</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.460</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Tick</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">156</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (22.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">196</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (10.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.684</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.422</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.542</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">Season</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.226</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Winter<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (14.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Autumn</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (28.2%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.259</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.634</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.047</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Summer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (14.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.958</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.281</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.263</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spring</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (12%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.750</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.151</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.732</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1">location</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.602</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Faqus<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (14.3%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zagazig</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (18.4%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.195</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.433</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.123</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minya Al Qamh</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (20.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.612</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.715</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bilbis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (10.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.481</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.247</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.901</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abu Hammad</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (19.0%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.667</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.249</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.133</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>1</sup>OR: Odds ratio; <sup>2</sup>CI, confidence interval (95%); <sup>3</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &#8804; 0.20 was used to detect which variables will be retained in the final multivariate model; <sup>4</sup>Reference category means the value to which the variable-level is being compared while controlling for the effect of the other predictors in the models. </p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The investigated cattle had a higher serological prevalence for <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> than water buffaloes, with percentages of 42.6% and 27.5%, respectively. Meanwhile, both animal species were nearly similar in their seropositivity to <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic>. The variation may be attributed to the thinner skin of cattle compared with buffaloes. Thus, cattle are more preferable to tick vectors and more susceptible to infection with blood parasites than buffaloes <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">Siddique <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., (2020)</xref>. These findings coincide with what was mentioned by <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Jacob <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2020)</xref> in their meta-analysis; they reported that cattle are more susceptible to babesiosis than buffaloes. In the univariable analysis, cattle were more vulnerable to infection with <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> compared to buffaloes. These results came in accordance with (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Ibrahim <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>), who found that water buffaloes revealed a lower percentage of infection with <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> (35.6%) compared with cattle (41.6%). On the other hand, <xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Abas <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2021)</xref> recorded a higher prevalence of babesiosis in buffaloes compared to cattle. The seroprevalence of <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> was higher in males than females. The univariable analysis revealed that the odds of infection in males were 2.15 and 1.9 times higher than in females for <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic>, respectively. The obtained results agreed with <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Fereig <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2017)</xref>, who found that the investigated males had a higher prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> compared to females, with an odds ratio of 4.4. On the contrary, <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Hamsho <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2015)</xref> and <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">Siddique <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2020)</xref> reported that females had a higher risk for infection with bovine babesiosis than males. However, another Egyptian study mentioned that sex did not represent any risk for babesia infection (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Rizk <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2017</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><title>The final multivariate logistic regression model for risk factors associated with <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> infection.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variable</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Level</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">B. Bigemina</italic>
</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR<sup>1</sup> (CI 95%)<sup>2</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p-</italic>value<sup>3</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR<sup>1</sup> (CI 95%)<sup>2</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p-</italic>value<sup>3</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;6 months<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;6 months&#8211;2 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (0.24&#8211;2.10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 (0.21&#8211;3.72)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;2 years&#8211;4 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46 (1.24&#8211;9.66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.25 (1.37&#8211;20.07)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;4 years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 (0.41&#8211;3.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.74 (0.38&#8211;7.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.7 (1.35&#8211;10.21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5 (1.21&#8211;10.16)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Tick</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absent<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35 (1.11&#8211;4.96)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 (1.47&#8211;10.66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.208</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>1</sup>OR: Odds ratio; <sup>2</sup>CI, confidence interval (95%); <sup>3</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05 were considered significant. <sup>4</sup>Reference category means the value to which the variable-level is being compared while controlling for the effect of the other predictors in the models.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In both infections, the animals aged from 2 to 4 years had the highest seroprevalence for <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> with percentages of 57.7% and 24.5%, respectively, followed by the age group (&gt;6 months&#8211;2 years). In the univariate analysis, the animal's age was a significant risk factor associated with exposure to the infection (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.20). These findings were in the same line with <xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">Wesonga <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2017)</xref>, who found that the seroprevalence of <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> was higher in adult animals. Other studies in Pakistan and Sudan by <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Atif (2012)</xref> and <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Shuaib <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2015)</xref> didn&#8217;t detect any association between age and babesiosis. On the other hand, <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Fereig <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2017)</xref> mentioned that younger ages had a higher risk of <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> infection. Regarding tick infestation, the risk of infection to Babesia parasites extended with the presence of ticks. The odds of exposure to both Babesia species were 2.2 and 1.4 times in infested animals related to free animals for both Babesia species. In agreement with our results, previous reports in different governorates in Egypt reported that ticks exaggerated the presence of babesiosis (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Fadly, 2012</xref>).</p><p>In the current study, the highest seroprevalence of <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> was in summer and autumn, respectively. However, there weren&#8217;t any significant seasonal variations regarding the seroprevalence of both Babesia species. These results coincided with <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">El-Moghazy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2014)</xref>, who reported a higher prevalence of bovine babesiosis in summer and autumn without statistical differences between different seasons. In contrast, several studies reported that the risk of exposure to babesia parasites increased significantly during the summer season (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">Siddique <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Ibrahim <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). The close seroprevalence of babesiosis among different seasons may be due to the humid, hot climate in the studied area and the availability of tick vectors most of the year. Moreover, <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Bock <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2004)</xref> mentioned that the antibodies of both Babesia species may be detected for up to 7 months post- natural infection. The highest seroprevalence of <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> was recorded in Zagazig and Minya al-Qamh, respectively. There was no significant difference among the studied districts for the distribution of babesiosis except for Zagazig, which had higher seroprevalence for <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic> (61%). The high prevalence in our investigation may be due to the nature of animal housing in the studied cities, which contributes to tick infestation and impedes effective tick control.</p><p>The final multivariate logistic analysis was used to visualize the combined effect of the significant variables in each babesia species. Interestingly, age, sex, and tick infestation are significant risk factors for the seropositivity of both Babesia species. It is clear from the obtained results that the prevalence increased with age. Adult animals are more exposed to infection with <italic toggle="yes">Babesia</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> than young animals by 3&#8211;5 times, respectively. This observation suggests the accumulated parasite exposure by getting older. Furthermore, the sex and existence of tick vectors are an influential factor in the seropositivity of both babesia species. Males were 3.7 and 3.5 times more likely to be exposed to <italic toggle="yes">B. bovis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic>, respectively, than females. Similarly, the odds of infection in infested animals with ticks were from 2 to 4 times higher than in animals without ticks. In current investigation, most males are fattened and reared in closed houses made from unshelled bricks. Inclusive, these types of houses besides high humidity, are considered a suitable environment for the tick population. Thus, males have a higher risk of exposure to tick infestation and, accordingly, babesia parasites than females which are reared in an open housing system.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>In this study, age, and sex, besides tick infestation, are considerable independent factors that could be used for the prediction of the occurrence of bovine babesiosis in the investigated population. Understanding babesiosis epidemiology can inform future management and control strategies for large ruminants, reducing negative impacts on animal production and profitability. More future studies are recommended for a better understanding of the epidemiological status of bovine babesiosis in Sharkia governorate, Egypt.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank all the animal owners in Sharika governorate for granting access to their animals.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The Authors declare that there is no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>This work didn&#8217;t receive any external funding.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data findings during our investigation are available within the manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Author contributions</title><p>SGY and MHE were involved in data curation, samples collection, formal analysis, discussion of results and prepared the initial draft. NMS and HG were involved in samples collection, discussion of results and review. All authors approved the submitted form.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abas</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd-Elrahman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saleh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bessat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of tick-borne haemoparasites and their perceived co-occurrences with viral outbreaks of FMD and LSD and their associated factors</article-title><source>Heliyon</source><year>2021</year><volume>7</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.heliyon.2021.e06479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7980057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33768176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adham</surname><given-names>F.K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd-El-Samie</surname><given-names>E.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gabre</surname><given-names>R.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>H.E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of tick blood parasites in Egypt using PCR assay I&#8212;<italic toggle="yes">Babesia bovis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bigemina</italic></article-title><source>Parasitol. Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>721</fpage><lpage>730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19415329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00436-009-1443-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Atif</surname><given-names>F.A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of tick-borne diseases in Punjab (Pakistan) and hematological profile of <italic toggle="yes">Anaplasma</italic> marginale infection in indigenous and crossbred cattle</article-title><source>Pakistan J. Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>64</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>15</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>K.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>W.K.B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>M.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>N.H.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mabrouk</surname><given-names>D.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suarez</surname><given-names>C.E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of babesiosis infected cattle: improvement of diagnosis and profiling of the immune response genes expression</article-title><source>Glob. Vet</source><year>2014</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>206</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Vos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Babesiosis of cattle</article-title><source>Parasitology</source><year>2004</year><volume>129</volume><issue>S1</issue><fpage>S247</fpage><lpage>S269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15938514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1017/s0031182004005190</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Criado-Fornelio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review of nucleic acid-based diagnostic tests for Babesia and Theileria, with emphasis on bovine piroplasms</article-title><source>Parassitologia</source><year>2007</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17691606</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Bahy</surname><given-names>N.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menshawy</surname><given-names>S.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goda</surname><given-names>W.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasr</surname><given-names>S.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>AbouLaila</surname><given-names>M.R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bazh</surname><given-names>E.K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abou-Rwash</surname><given-names>A.A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular detection of <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bovis</italic> in cattle in Behaira Governorate</article-title><source>Ejpmr</source><year>2018</year><volume>5</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>446</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El Moghazy</surname><given-names>H.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebied</surname><given-names>M.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelwahab</surname><given-names>M.G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Sayed</surname><given-names>A.A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiological studies on bovine babesiosis and theileriosis in Qalubia governorate</article-title><source>Banha Vet. Med. J</source><year>2014</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>48</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fadly</surname><given-names>R.S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of blood parasites of some farm animals in Behera province</article-title><source>Assiut Vet. Med. J</source><year>2012</year><volume>58</volume><issue>134</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fakhar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajihasani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maroufi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alizadeh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shirzad</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pagheh</surname><given-names>A.S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An epidemiological survey on bovine and ovine babesiosis in Kurdistan Province, western Iran</article-title><source>Trop. Anim. Health Prod</source><year>2012</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22109588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11250-011-0023-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fereig</surname><given-names>R.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>S.G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>H.Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>AbouLaila</surname><given-names>M.R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guswanto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>T.T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishikawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seroprevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bovis</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">B. bigemina</italic>, Trypanosoma evansi, and <italic toggle="yes">Anaplasma</italic> marginale antibodies in cattle in southern Egypt</article-title><source>Ticks Tick-Borne Dis</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27789159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ttbdis.2016.10.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#243;es</surname><given-names>T.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#243;es</surname><given-names>V.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>M.F.B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gontijo</surname><given-names>C.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bovine babesiosis: anti-erythrocyte antibodies purification from the sera of naturally infected cattle</article-title><source>Vet. Immunol. Immunopathol</source><year>2007</year><volume>116</volume><issue>3-4</issue><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17292487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vetimm.2006.12.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gul</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gul</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adnan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shams</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akbar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tropical theileriosis and east coast fever in cattle: present, past, and future perspective</article-title><source>Int. J. Curr. Microbiol. Appl. Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1000</fpage><lpage>1018</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guswanto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allamanda</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mariamah</surname><given-names>E.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sodirun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wibowo</surname><given-names>P.E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Indrayani</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Igarashi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular and serological detection of bovine babesiosis in Indonesia</article-title><source>Parasit. Vectors</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29110723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13071-017-2502-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5674684</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamsho</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tesfamarym</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Megersa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Megersa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A cross-sectional study of bovine babesiosis in Teltele District, Borena Zone, Southern Ethiopia</article-title><source>J. Vet. Sci. Technol</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><issue>230</issue><fpage>2</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>M.I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gabr</surname><given-names>H.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Shafy</surname><given-names>S.O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammad</surname><given-names>K.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mokhtar</surname><given-names>M.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular detection of Borrelia sp. in ornithodorids savignyi and <italic toggle="yes">Rhipicephalus annulatus</italic> by Flab gene and <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bigemina</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">R. annulatus</italic> by 18S rRNA gene</article-title><source>J. Egypt. Soc. Parasitol</source><year>2017</year><volume>47</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>414</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>H.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galon</surname><given-names>E.M.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tumwebaze</surname><given-names>M.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Byamukama</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammed-Geba</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serological Survey of <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bovis</italic> in cattle and water buffaloes from Menoufia Province, Egypt</article-title><source>Acta Parasitol</source><year>2021</year><volume>66</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1458</fpage><lpage>1465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34043120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11686-021-00338-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>H.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moumouni</surname><given-names>P.F.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammed-Geba</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheir</surname><given-names>S.K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashem</surname><given-names>I.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular and serological prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bigemina</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bovis</italic> in cattle and water buffalos under small-scale dairy farming in Beheira and Faiyum Provinces, Egypt</article-title><source>Vet. Parasitol</source><year>2013</year><volume>198</volume><issue>1-2</issue><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24075417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vetpar.2013.08.028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>S.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sengupta</surname><given-names>P.P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paramanandham</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suresh</surname><given-names>K.P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chamuah</surname><given-names>J.K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudramurthy</surname><given-names>G.R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bovine babesiosis: an insight into the global perspective on the disease distribution by systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Vet. Parasitol</source><year>2020</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vetpar.2020.109136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32574977</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaimes-Due&#241;ez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Triana-Ch&#225;vez</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mej&#237;a-Jaramillo</surname><given-names>A.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parasitological and molecular surveys reveal high rates of infection with vector-borne pathogens and clinical anemia signs associated with infection in cattle from two important livestock areas in Colombia</article-title><source>Ticks Tick-Borne Dis</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27956049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ttbdis.2016.12.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Terkawi</surname><given-names>M.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>D.T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>P.T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xuan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular and sero epidemiological survey of <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bovis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bigemina</italic> infections in cattle and water buffaloes in the central region of Vietnam</article-title><source>Trop. Biomed</source><year>2014</year><volume>31</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>406</fpage><lpage>413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25382466</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>H.Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rady</surname><given-names>A.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular detection and characterization of Theileria annulata, <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bovis</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bigemina</italic> infecting cattle and buffalo in southern Egypt</article-title><source>Parasit. Epidemiol. Control</source><year>2024</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>340</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.parepi.2024.e00340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10847785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38333559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>M.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kandil</surname><given-names>O.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasr</surname><given-names>S.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hendawy</surname><given-names>S.H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Habeeb</surname><given-names>S.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mabrouk</surname><given-names>D.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suarez</surname><given-names>C.E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serological and molecular diagnostic surveys combined with examining hematological profiles suggests increased levels of infection and hematological response of cattle to babesiosis infections compared to native buffaloes in Egypt</article-title><source>Parasit. Vectors</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26062684</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13071-015-0928-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4467044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Menshawy</surname><given-names>S.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>AbouLail</surname><given-names>M.R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bessat</surname><given-names>M.N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beder</surname><given-names>N.A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review on Bovine Babesiosis in Egypt</article-title><source>Egypt. Vet. Med. Soc. Parasitol. J</source><year>2020</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>19</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rizk</surname><given-names>M.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Sayed</surname><given-names>S.A.E.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elsify</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Ashkar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Khodery</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Animal level risk factors associated with Babesia and Theileria infections in cattle in Egypt</article-title><source>Acta Parasitol</source><year>2017</year><volume>62</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>796</fpage><lpage>804</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29035848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1515/ap-2017-0096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singla</surname><given-names>L.D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Batth</surname><given-names>B.K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Javed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juyal</surname><given-names>P.D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bigemina</italic> and Trypanosoma evansi in dairy animals from Punjab, India, by duplex PCR: a step forward to the detection and management of concurrent latent infections</article-title><source>BioMed Res. Int</source><year>2013</year><volume>2013</volume><fpage>893862</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24069605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2013/893862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3773408</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shuaib</surname><given-names>Y.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osman</surname><given-names>H.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>M.O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakhiet</surname><given-names>M.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omer</surname><given-names>R.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Nahas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>A.A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seroprevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bigemina</italic> antibodies in cattle in North Kordofan state, the Sudan</article-title><source>ARC J. Anim. Vet. Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siddique</surname><given-names>R.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sajid</surname><given-names>M.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saqib</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of different risk factors with the prevalence of babesiosis in cattle and buffaloes</article-title><source>Pak. J. Agri. Sci</source><year>2020</year><volume>57</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>524</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Terkawi</surname><given-names>M.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huyen</surname><given-names>N.X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shinuo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inpankaew</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maklon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aboulaila</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Igarashi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular and serological prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bovis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bigemina</italic> in water buffaloes in the northeast region of Thailand</article-title><source>Vet. Parasitol</source><year>2011</year><volume>178</volume><issue>3-4</issue><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21324601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vetpar.2011.01.041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thrusfield</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Veterinary epidemiology</article-title><year>2018</year><edition>4th</edition><publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ</publisher-loc><publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wesonga</surname><given-names>F.D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gachohi</surname><given-names>J.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitala</surname><given-names>P.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gathuma</surname><given-names>J.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Njenga</surname><given-names>M.J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seroprevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Anaplasma</italic> marginale and <italic toggle="yes">Babesia bigemina</italic> infections and associated risk factors in Machakos County, Kenya</article-title><source>Trop. Anim. Health Prod</source><year>2017</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27878428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11250-016-1187-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><element-citation publication-type="thesis"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yousef</surname><given-names>S.G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on bovine theileriosis at Sharkia governorate</article-title><year>2020</year><comment>PhD thesis, Zagazig Uni., Zagazig, Egypt</comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>