<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2846</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">openvetj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Veterinary Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2226-4485</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2218-6050</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tripoli</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11910282</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11910282.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11910282</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11910282</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40092196</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/OVJ.2025.v15.i1.13</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OVJ-15-139</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>First molecular detection of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. in domestic goats from Java Island, Indonesia</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dewi</surname><given-names initials="DA">Dias Aprita</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nugraheni</surname><given-names initials="YR">Yudhi Ratna</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Awaludin</surname><given-names initials="A">Aan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ninditya</surname><given-names initials="VI">Vika Ichsania</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Priyowidodo</surname><given-names initials="D">Dwi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nurcahyo</surname><given-names initials="RW">Raden Wisnu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekawasti</surname><given-names initials="F">Fitrine</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prastowo</surname><given-names initials="J">Joko</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Parasitology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Gadjah Mada, Yogyakarta, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Departmenf of Animal Science, Politeknik Pembangunan Pertanian Yogyakarta Magelang, Magelang, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Animal Science, Politeknik Negeri Jember, Jember, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Research Center for Veterinary Science, National Research and Innovation Agency (BRIN), Bogor, Indonesia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Joko Prastowo. Department of Parasitology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Gadjah Mada, Yogyakarta, Indonesia. <email>joko2465@ugm.ac.id</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">484284</issue-id><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>150</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>16</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-03-25 12:25:13.670"><day>25</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-15-139.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Coccidiosis caused by <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria </italic>species (spp.) is a significant global health concern in goats leading to gastrointestinal illness. This condition causes clinical manifestations, including weight loss and diarrhea, resulting in worldwide economic losses. Subclinical symptoms can manifest during <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria </italic>infection. Neglecting this disease can lead to severe morbidity and mortality. Therefore, addressing caprine coccidiosis is imperative. </p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>This study aimed to determine the prevalence and molecular identification related to the natural infection of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. in domestic goats originating from Java Island, Indonesia. </p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods:</title><p>In total, fecal samples from 289 domestic goats were obtained across five provinces on Java Island, Indonesia: East Java, Central Java, D. I. Yogyakarta, West Java, and Banten. Morphological examinations were performed using the modified Whitlock method and saturated sugar flotation. Molecular assays targeting the 18S ribosomal ribonucleic acid have been employed for spp.-specific confirmation. Statistical analysis was performed using the Wilson binomial proportion and chi-square methods implemented in the online software. </p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>A total of 92.7% (268/289) of fecal samples tested positive for <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. Phylogenetic tree analysis demonstrated that <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria christenseni</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria arloingi</italic> closely resembled the reference sequences from China, Australia, and other countries.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>This study identified <italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">E. arloingi</italic> as the goat-infecting spp. of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria </italic>present on Java Island. The specific and accurate molecular identification conducted in this study will contribute to improved coccidiosis control and the development of effectiveness.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Eimera</italic></kwd><kwd>Goat</kwd><kwd>Indonesia</kwd><kwd>Molecular identification</kwd><kwd>18S rRNA</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Small ruminants play a significant role in sustainable agriculture in developing countries and provide numerous socioeconomic advantages (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Anim-Jnr <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2023</xref>). Goats are considered one of the most promising sources of meat and dairy production in Indonesia. Indonesia is a tropical country that has a total goat population of around 18.5 million with various local breeds including Peranakan Ettawa, Jawarandu, Saanen, Boer, and Kacang (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">BPS, 2022</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. are gastrointestinal protozoans belonging to the apicomplexan group (<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Underwood <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). These protozoans infect the digestive tract, causing coccidiosis. Coccidiosis has high morbidity and mortality rates as the condition causes impaired nutrient absorption, which results in decreased quality of life and productivity (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Engidaw <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Several <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria </italic>species (spp.) have been identified in small ruminants, with those frequently infecting goats including <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria caprina, Eimeria ninakohlyakimovae, Eimeria </italic><italic toggle="yes">jolchijevi, Eimeria apsheronica, Eimeria christenseni, Eimeria caprovina, Eimeria alijevi, Eimeria </italic><italic toggle="yes">hirci, </italic>and <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria arloingi</italic> (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Bawm <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). Among these,<italic toggle="yes"> E. arloingi, E. ninakohlyakimovae, </italic>and <italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni</italic> are highly pathogenic and are often associated with significant mortality in goats, especially those under one year of age (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Khodakaram-Tafti <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">Roh <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2023</xref>).</p><p>Clinical symptoms are insufficient for the diagnosis of coccidiosis. This could be misinterpreted as a clinical manifestation of other intestinal disorders. The diagnosis of coccidiosis typically relies on the morphological characteristics of oocysts, including host specificity, aspects of the life cycle, sites of infection, pathogenicity, antigenicity, nucleotide sequencing, clinical symptoms in the animal, and typical macroscopic lesions at necropsy (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Berto <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Information on the morphological characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> in Indonesia remains limited; therefore, the specific <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. present in Indonesia remains unclear. When compared, those spp. identified across different regions of other countries have slightly different morphological and structural variations (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Gondipon and Malaka, 2021</xref>). The identification of different spp. has traditionally relied on the microscopic examination of oocysts, which involves biological assessments, including the size and morphological characteristics of oocysts, absence or presence of residual oocysts, sporulation period, prepatent period, micropyle cap, and site of colonization (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Bawm <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). This method is commonly employed to identify coccidia in goats, particularly in Indonesia (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">Pamungkas <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">Pertiwi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2023</xref>). However, due to the similar morphological characteristics of some spp., relying on physical traits alone is not sufficient for accurately identifying <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. with nearly identical shapes and sizes (morphological resemblance) (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Haug <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). To address this limitation, polymerase chain reaction (PCR) has been used to accurately and rapidly identify <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Jordan <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>).</p><p>Molecular assays are considered precise methods for identifying <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. due to their high sensitivity and reliability (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Al-Habsi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>). Deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) sequences are known to be more consistent than morphological characteristics. In the present study, identification and phylogenetic analyses were performed using ribosomal DNA (rDNA). rDNA in eukaryotic cells consists of tandem arrays containing several hundred to thousand repetitions in each arrangement (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">Hillis and Dixon, 2011</xref>). The 18S ribosomal ribonucleic acid (rRNA) gene is frequently utilized as a molecular marker for genetic analysis. Furthermore, 18S rRNA gene sequences have been used to delineate the inter- and intraspecies phylogenetic relationships among various <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> isolates (<xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">Verma <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>).</p><p>Despite limited knowledge of the genetic characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. in small ruminants, molecular biology methods have the potential for appropriate classification. This study aimed to bridge this gap by isolating genomic DNA from purified oocysts in goats, followed by amplification and sequencing of the 18S rRNA loci. Subsequent phylogenetic analyses of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> using the obtained sequences could contribute to the identification of spp., the epidemiology of molecular biology, and phylogenetic analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Study design and sample collection</title><p>This cross-sectional study was conducted to determine the prevalence of coccidiosis in domestic goats across five provinces on Java Island, Indonesia: East Java, Central Java, D.I. Yogyakarta, West Java, and Banten. In this study, 289 fecal samples were obtained from five provinces. In Banten Province, 15 samples were collected from a single farm, with 15 samples obtained from each farm. A total of 38 samples were collected from two farms located in the West Java Province, with each farm providing between 18 and 20 samples. Central Java Province included 187 samples collected from 11 farms, with each farm providing 18&#8211;20 samples. In East Java, 30 samples were gathered from two farms, with 15 samples being obtained from each farm. In D. I. Yogyakarta, 19 samples were collected from two farms, with each farm contributing between nine and 10 samples. </p><p>The minimum sample size was calculated using the formula <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4PQ/L2 (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Martin <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1987</xref>). The calculation was based on a predicted prevalence of 82%, 95% confidence level, and 5% statistical error (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">de Macedo <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). A total of 289 fecal samples of approximately 15 g (&#177; 15 g) each were obtained at random. Fresh samples were collected directly from the rectum and stored in plastic containers. They were then transported to the Department of Parasitology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Gadjah Mada, for further analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Identification of Eimeria spp. by morphological examination</title><sec><title>Saturated sugar flotation method</title><p>Feces (1 g) from each animal were dissolved in 9 ml of water and left for a few minutes until soft, crushed, stirred homogeneously, and filtered through a steel mesh. The fecal solutions were placed in centrifuge tubes and centrifugated at 1,500 rpm for 5 minutes. The supernatant was discarded, and the tube was then filled with 10 ml saturated sugar float solution with a selected gravity of 1.2 (e.g., 100 g of sugar was added to 120 ml of distilled water). The mixture was mixed until homogenous and then centrifuged for 5 minutes at 1,500 rpm. The centrifuge tube was gently removed from the machine and positioned upright on a test-tube rack. The floating fluid was added dropwise using a Pasteur pipette until the surface formed a convex shape, ensuring that no excess fluid spilled over. After waiting for 5 minutes for the oocysts to float to the surface, a cover glass was placed on the surface of the liquid and attached to the object glass. Oocysts were detected based on their shape and size under a microscope at 400&#215; magnification (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Mohamaden <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Efendi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>McMaster method (Gordon and Whitlock technique)</title><p>This approach was used to count coccidian oocysts. Feces from each animal (up to 3 g) were dissolved in water (up to 17 ml for a few minutes before being crushed and mixed with a saturated salt solution (40 ml to allow the coccidia oocysts to float). Afterward, while stirring, the stool solution was collected containing the filter and was transferred to the Whitlock chamber (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Gordon and Whitlock, 1939</xref>). Coccidia oocysts were assessed using a microscope and multiplied by 40. The number of oocysts was calculated as oocysts per gram (OPG) based on microscopic observations. According to <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Gondipon and Malaka (2021)</xref>, the degree of infection could be classified as light (50&#8211;799), medium (800&#8211;1,200), or high (&gt; 1,200).</p></sec><sec><title>Purification of Eimeria spp. oocysts</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Eimeria </italic>spp. oocysts were purified from goat feces by filtration and centrifugation using a saturated sugar solution to obtain purified oocysts (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Kawahara <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Additionally, <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria </italic>oocysts were isolated from the remaining feces (approximately 5&#8211;10 g). The feces were then diluted with distilled water and filtered through a steel mesh or gauze. After centrifugation at 800 rpm for 5 minutes, the sugar solution was added to the sample, which was then centrifuged at 1,200 rpm for 10 minutes. <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria </italic>oocysts floating on the surface were collected using a Pasteur pipette and rinsed with distilled water. Purified oocysts were suspended in 1&#8211;2 ml distilled water (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Hastutiek <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2022</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Sporulation of Eimeria spp. oocysts</title><p>The purified oocysts were sporulated in 2.5% potassium dichromate solution at 26&#176;C&#8211;33&#176;C for 5 d. A microscope with 400&#215; magnification was employed to identify oocysts and sporocysts. </p></sec><sec><title>Morphological analysis</title><p>Morphological analysis was performed using the identification key developed by <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Eckert <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (1995)</xref>. Sporulation oocysts were observed under a microscope at 400&#215; magnification, and morphological features such as size, shape, and the presence of specific structures including the micropyle and polar cap were evaluated (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Mohamaden <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Efendi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2019</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Identification of Eimeria spp. by molecular examination</title><sec><title>DNA extraction</title><p>Before DNA extraction, purified oocyst samples from goat feces were frozen and thawed to break the oocyst walls mechanically, thereby releasing the genomic DNA (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Lassen and J&#228;rvis, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Gadelhaq <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). The freeze-thawing process was carried out by storing the sample in a freezer at &#8722;20<sup>o</sup>C for 15 minutes, followed by transferring it to a heater at 60<sup>o</sup>C for 15 minutes until it melted. The sample was then spun down, and this cycle was repeated five times (Matsubayashi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009). DNA was extracted using the Geneaid GT100 Genomic DNA Mini Kit (Geneaid, Taiwan).</p></sec><sec><title>Amplification and sequencing of 18S rRNA</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. were identified using PCR targeting the 18S rRNA region. Partial sequences of the 18S rRNA gene were amplified with 630 bp using forward primer 5&#8242;-TACCCAATGAAAACAGTTT-3&#8242; and reverse primer 5&#8242;-CAGGAGAAGCCAA GGTAGG-3&#8242; according to the previous study conducted by <xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">Jinneman <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (1999)</xref>. The PCR reaction was performed in a 25 &#181;l volume, which included 0.75 &#181;l forward and reverse primers (10 &#181;M), 12.5 &#181;l of 2&#215; Buffer (KOD Fx Neo), 0.5&#181;l of Taq Polymerase, DNA template (2 &#181;l), and nuclease-free water. Positive samples used in this study were obtained from samples with very high parasitemia levels, amplified by PCR, and confirmed as <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> by Sanger sequencing. Sterile DNA/RNA-free water was used as the negative control.</p><p>The PCR condition was set with an initial denaturation step (2 minutes at 94&#176;C), followed by 35 cycles of denaturation (10 s at 98&#176;C), annealing (30 s at 51&#176;C), and extension (20 s at 68&#176;C). A final extension step was performed at 68&#176;C for 5 minutes. The PCR products were separated by gel electrophoresis on a 1.5% (w/v) agarose gel in 1&#215; TAE buffer, run at 120 V for 30 minutes, and visualized using an ultraviolet transilluminator. Positive PCR samples were subjected to Sanger sequencing at the Penelitian dan Pengujian Terpadu UGM Laboratorium. Sequencing findings, represented by the nucleotide base sequence in the chromatogram file, were analyzed.</p></sec><sec><title>Sequences analysis</title><p>Sequences from this study and GenBank were aligned using ClustalW in BioEdit version 7 (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Hall, 1999</xref>). After alignment, sequences were compared with GenBank data using BLASTN software. Phylogenetic trees were created using IQtree version 1.6. The trees were visualized using FigTree v1.4.4 (available at <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree/</uri>). All sequences obtained in this study were deposited in GenBank with accession numbers <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide-range" xlink:href="PQ222707:PQ222721">PQ222707&#8211;PQ222721</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The proportion was analyzed using Wilson&#8217;s method with confidence intervals. The chi-square test was employed to investigate the association between coccidia infection, sex, and age. All data were evaluated using a statistical analysis tool incorporated into an epidemiological calculator which is free and accessible at 
<uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://epitools.-ausvet.com.au.">https://epitools.-ausvet.com.au.</uri> The prevalence of samples from each province was statistically analyzed using the Binomial (Clopper&#8211;Pearson) &#8220;exact&#8221; method based on the beta distribution.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>The current study was conceived and performed in accordance with the animal welfare regulations issued by the Research Ethics Committee of the Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Universitas Gadjah Mada, Indonesia. </p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>A total of 289 domestic goat fecal samples were obtained from five provinces on Java Island, Indonesia, including East Java, Central Java, D. I. Yogyakarta, West Java, and Banten, and evaluated for coccidia oocysts using the saturated sugar flotation method for qualitative analysis and the Gordon&#8211;Whitlock method for quantitative analysis. The results demonstrated that 92.7% (268/289) of the fecal samples tested positive for <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. In Banten Province, the OPG ranged from 150 to 3,650, with all samples (100%) testing positive for coccidia infection. Similarly, in West Java Province, the OPG ranged from 50 to 531, with a high proportion of positive samples at 97.4% (37/38). In Central Java Province, the OPG ranged from 50 to 42,500, with 90.9% (170/187) of the samples testing positive for coccidia. Furthermore, in East Java Province, the OPG ranged from 250 to 3,200, with 96.7% (29/30) of the samples testing positive. In D. I. Yogyakarta Province, the OPG ranged from 100 to 1,000, with 89.5% (17/19) of the samples testing positive (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). </p><p><xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> presents the evaluation results, demonstrating the range of OPG in feces, the proportion of positive samples, and corresponding confidence intervals (95%) for each location.</p><p>Variables including sex, age, and breed were associated with the univariate analysis as risk factors for infection in goats. According to an epidemiological study, one of the three variables was significantly related to <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria </italic>infection, namely, age, while the others were not correlated (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><sec><title>Eimeria spp. identification by morphology</title><p>Morphological features were assessed according to the micropyle, polar cap, and oocyst size and shape. The length and width of the oocysts were also evaluated (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Christensen, 1938</xref>).</p><p>In this study, we identified the oocysts of <italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">E. arloingi</italic> based on microscopic observations of sporulated oocysts. The specific characteristics of each spp. are described in detail in <xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Furthermore, <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> illustrates the goat coccidia used in this study.</p></sec><sec><title>Molecular characteristic of Eimeria spp.</title><p>The 18S rRNA gene was used for PCR after extracting DNA from 18 fecal samples that were morphologically positive for <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. All samples produced positive bands, and the PCR product was approximately 630 bp. No amplification products were observed in the negative controls. The 18 PCR-positive samples were sequenced. Unfortunately, three samples were deemed to have low-quality chromatography results. Thus, we excluded these sequences, leaving 15 sequences for molecular and phylogenetic analyses. </p><p>To determine the spp. of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> oocyst using molecular method, 18S rRNA gene sequences were analyzed using BLAST against an extensive non-redundant nucleotide database. After removing low-quality sequences from 18 sequences, 15 high-quality sequences were selected for molecular investigation. Additionally, analysis performed using the BLASTN program employing the 18S rRNA sequences obtained from the sample revealed that they were 100% identical to <italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni</italic> (accession no. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="KX845684">KX845684</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OM328173">OM328173</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OM328172">OM328172</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OM328171">OM328171</ext-link>), meanwhile, <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> 3 was 99.4%&#8211;99.8% identical to <italic toggle="yes">E. arloingi</italic> (accession no. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OM328169">OM328169</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="ON259586">ON259586</ext-link>). </p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>Map depicting sampling site collection in this study. Prevalence rate samples are presented under the arrow, respectively.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-15-139-g001.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>OPG of feces assessed by the Whitlock method.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average OPG (min&#8722;max)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prevalence (Positive/Total) (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower-upper 95% CL</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Banten</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">970 (150&#8211;3,650)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0 (15/15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80&#8211;1.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">West Java</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">531.08 (50-&#8211;31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.4 (37/38)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87&#8211;1.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central Java</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,598.97(50&#8211;42,500)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.9 (170/187)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85&#8211;0.94</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">East Java</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,255.26 (250&#8211;3,200)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.7 (29/30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83&#8211;0.99</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yogyakarta</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">503.13(100&#8211;1,000)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.5 (17/19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69&#8211;0.97</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>OPG = oocyst per gram feces; CL = confidence level.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Univariate analysis of the risk factors associated with <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> infection in goats from Java Island.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prevalence (Positive/Total) (%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower-upper 95% CL</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Sex</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.56 (160/171)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89&#8212;0.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.669</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.52 (108/118)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85&#8212;0.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Age</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804; 12 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.63 (72/73)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93&#8212;1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt; 12 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.74 (196/216)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86&#8212;0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Breed</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> PE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.44 (123/136)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84&#8212;0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.277</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jawarandu</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.91 (94/97)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91&#8212;0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Boer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 (8/8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68&#8212;1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saanen</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.30 (21/23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73&#8212;0.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kacang</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.00 (22/25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70&#8212;0.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Significant association at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.05.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Morphological characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> oocysts obtained from goat feces in this study.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Spp.</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Size (&#956;m)</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Oocyst characteristics</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length <break/>(Min&#8212;Max)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Width<break/>(Min&#8212;Max)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35&#8212;43.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24&#8212;28.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pear-shaped, polar cap, and micropyle caps present</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. arloingi</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24&#8212;36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.2&#8212;26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ellipsoidal, polar cap, and micropyle caps present</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>Sporulated E. <italic toggle="yes">christenseni</italic> (a) and E. <italic toggle="yes">arloingi</italic> (b).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-15-139-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>According to the results of a comparative study of the sequences, 99.4% to 100% of the <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. from goat samples were identified and were similar to <italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">E. arloingi</italic>. Additionally, the sequence similarities between <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria </italic>spp. from goats and <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria ahsata</italic> from sheep ranged from 99.0% to 99.6% (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p><p>A maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree was constructed using the 18S rRNA gene, incorporating <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> isolates and reference <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria </italic>spp. from GenBank. BLAST analysis was performed to match the reference sequences from GenBank with those of the <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> isolates. Our findings revealed a strong correlation between <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> isolates and <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. from Myanmar, China, Iran, and Australia (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><title>Pairwise identities (%) among the 18S rRNA sequences of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> samples with E. <italic toggle="yes">christenseni</italic>, E. <italic toggle="yes">arloingi</italic>, and E. <italic toggle="yes">ahsata</italic>.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample code/species name</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Eimeria 11</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Eimeria 12</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Eimeria 13</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Eimeria 14</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Eimeria 17</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Eimeria 18</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Eimeria 2</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Eimeria 3</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Eimeria 4</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Eimeria 5</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Eimeria6</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Eimeria 7</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Eimeria 8</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Eimeria 9</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Eimeria 10</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="KX845684">KX845684</ext-link></italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OM328173">OM328173</ext-link></italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OM328172">OM328172</ext-link></italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OM328171">OM328171</ext-link></italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. arloingi <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OM328169">OM328169</ext-link></italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. arloingi <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="ON259586">ON259586</ext-link></italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E ahsata <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="KT184334">KT184334</ext-link></italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>A close association between the isolates of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria </italic>spp. was revealed by the phylogenetic tree analysis with high sequence homology to reference strains. The 18S rRNA sequences from China and Australia were completely similar to <italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni</italic> (accession numbers: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="KX845684">KX845684</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OM328173">OM328173</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OM328172">OM328172</ext-link>, and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OM328171">OM328171</ext-link>), forming a distinct clade. Additionally, one sequence clustered with <italic toggle="yes">E. arloingi</italic> (accession numbers <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OM328169">OM328169</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="ON259586">ON259586</ext-link>) from China and displayed 100% sequence homology.</p><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><title>Maximum likelihood tree of the partial 18S rRNA gene for approximately 650 bp. The phylogenetic tree was generated by Bootstrap 1,000, and the best-fit model K2P+I was chosen according to the Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC). <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria bovis</italic> was used as an outgroup. Bootstrap values are indicated at each node.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-15-139-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Goat farming is an important aspect of livestock farming in Indonesia (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">Tenrisanna and Kasim, 2021</xref>). Currently, coccidiosis significantly impacts the production traits of goats, such as milk and meat, leading to substantial economic losses worldwide. This has become a major concern hindering the healthy growth of the goat farming industry and poses a serious threat to the health and productivity of livestock, particularly young goats. Understanding the incidence of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> in a specific region to implement effective control measures and minimize the economic losses associated with the disease is crucial (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">Ruiz <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>).</p><p>Sixteen <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. have been documented to affect goats globally, although the precise number of valid spp. varies depending on the study (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Abo-Shehada and Abo-Farieha, 2003</xref>). Currently, the practical method for identifying spp. within goat coccidia is through morphological observation of oocysts (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Khodakaram-Tafti <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Nonetheless, this approach may prove unreliable due to potential overlap in the quantitative and qualitative morphological characteristics of oocyst between spp. and within spp. of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria.</italic> To address the limitations of traditional methods, molecular techniques have recently been demonstrated to be effective in identifying and classifying <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Matsubayashi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Kawahara <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">Takeo <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Identifying spp. in<italic toggle="yes"> Eimeria </italic>co-infections is difficult because of their morphological similarities, which complicates their differentiation under a microscope. The presence of overlapping life cycle stages complicates identification, as various spp. may exhibit similar characteristics during certain developmental phases. Mixed infections further complicate the evaluation of the contribution of each spp. to the disease severity. These issues underscore the need to integrate multiple diagnostic techniques, including molecular assays, to identify cases of co-infection reliably.</p><p>In Indonesia, morphological and molecular studies focusing on <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. in goats are limited. This study aimed to identify the prevalence and composition of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria </italic>spp. causing coccidiosis in domestic goats in Java, Indonesia, using morphological examination and molecular methods with 18S rRNA sequences. This could contribute to the understanding of the biology, molecular epidemiology, and population diversity of goat <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. Additionally, the analysis will aid in supporting host adaptation of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. in various animals, including goats, sheep, and cattle. This study revealed that two <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. have adapted to goats in different provinces across Java Island. The two different spp. suggests that <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> responds to regional immune systems and farming practices. High infection rates may favor organisms with enhanced infection or treatment resistance.</p><p>The analysis of fecal samples using saturated sugar flotation and Whitlock techniques has enabled the detection and measurement of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> oocysts. These methods are widely used because of their ease and reliability in identifying coccidian infections (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Khodakaram-Tafti <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Our study identified suspected cases of <italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni </italic>and <italic toggle="yes">E</italic><italic toggle="yes">. arloingi</italic>, which are known to have high pathogenicity and are often fatal to goats, especially those under one year of age (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">Roh <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2023</xref>). The sporulation process of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> oocysts in potassium dichromate facilitates morphological characterization and spp. identification (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Gong <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>). Mature sporulated oocysts were subjected to microscopic examination, where morphological features including shape, size, and the presence of specific structures such as the micropyle and polar cap were evaluated (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">Stotish <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1978</xref>). Based on these characteristics, <italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni </italic>and<italic toggle="yes"> E. arloingi</italic> were identified and their morphological differences were noted. </p><p>The current study demonstrated a moderately high prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. in goats (92.7%, 268/289) on Java Island, Indonesia, with varying prevalence rates in each province. Certain regions exhibit higher prevalence rates than those noted in others. Confidence intervals estimate the precision of the proportion of positive samples at each location. The prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">E. arloingi</italic> is widely recognized as the most pathogenic coccidia spp. affecting goats globally (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">Roh <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2023</xref>). A morphological study using microscopic examination of goats in the arid tropical regions of Africa, such as Kenya (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">Kanyari <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>), Somalia (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Harmaya <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>), and Nigeria, revealed a significant prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. infections. Notably, <italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni</italic> (60%) and <italic toggle="yes">E. arloingi</italic> (64%&#8211;80%) were identified as the most prevalent spp. Comparative research from Asian countries, such as Vietnam, India, Myanmar, and China, also demonstrated a low to a high prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">E</italic><italic toggle="yes">. christenseni</italic> (63%&#8211;78%) and <italic toggle="yes">E. arloingi</italic> (21%&#8211;73%) (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Bawm <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">De <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Diao <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2022</xref>; <xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Nguyen-Ho-Bao <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2022</xref>).</p><p>The absence of statistically significant differences in coccidia infection rates between the two variables (sex and breed) suggests that infection may occur in goats indiscriminately based on these factors. In terms of sex, females (93.56%) had a non-significantly higher infection rate than the rate in males (91.52%). Similar results for the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. infection between sexes have been reported previously by <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Dabasa <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2017)</xref> attributing to the similar management systems used to maintain both sexes, which provides an equal likelihood of infection. The animals in this study demonstrated a non-significant difference in the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria spp.</italic> Infections. Moreover, <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Souza <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2015)</xref> reported that<italic toggle="yes"> Eimeria </italic>infection can affect small ruminants of all breeds. All breeds in the region experience the same hot and humid climate, which is conducive to the sporulation of coccidian oocysts. Rehman <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2011) reported that different breeds had no genetic influence on the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic>. According to <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed (2011)</xref>, natural resistance-associated macrophage protein one is associated with factors affecting the susceptibility of goats to developing coccidia; however, no breed effect was detected. Young goats (age &#8804; 12 months) (98.63%) were more affected than adult goats (90.74%). Age is an important risk factor for<italic toggle="yes"> Eimeria</italic> infections in sheep (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Carneiro <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2022</xref>). However, another study reported that animals of different age groups were similarly exposed to <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria spp. </italic>(<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">de Macedo <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). Adult animals can develop parasite immunity through repeated challenges and can eliminate the parasite before the development of the infection (<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">L&#243;pez-Osorio <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). Consequently, coccidiosis is considered a self-limiting disease. Additionally, the disease gradually increases in frequency and severity, peaking just before weaning and then declining in adults. This finding underscores the importance of implementing preventive measures across all goat age groups (Bawm and Htun, 2023). Identifying <italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">E. arloingi</italic> in this study adds to the existing knowledge on <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. diversity in Java, Indonesia. These spp. are highly pathogenic and can produce severe clinical manifestations in goats, leading to significant economic losses in the livestock industry (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">Dai <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Guedes <italic toggle="yes">et al .</italic>, 2024</xref>). Overall, these findings underscore the widespread distribution of coccidia infection among domestic goats on Java, highlighting the need for effective control measures to reduce the effects of disease on the productivity and health of livestock. Therefore, continued surveillance and research efforts are warranted to monitor changes in the prevalence and distribution of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria </italic>spp. and develop targeted control strategies.</p><p>Identifying <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. in goats has historically relied on morphological analysis. In the present study, we employed molecular techniques based on PCR amplification of the parasite to confirm our findings. This study employed 18S rRNA gene sequencing to confirm <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> at the spp. level. The 18S rRNA gene has been extensively used as a molecular marker in phylogenetic analyses due to its high specificity. These sequences have proven effective in differentiating between various closely related <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Matsubayashi <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Pyziel <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2020</xref>). </p><p>Recently, the 18S rRNA gene was used as a target to distinguish closely related spp. of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> and conduct phylogenetic analyses (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">Liang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2022</xref>). In addition, analysis of nucleotide sequences using the maximum likelihood method verified that <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> isolated from goats in this study were genetically grouped with the previously described <italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">E. arloingi.</italic> Phylogenetic analysis revealed a comprehensive overview, indicating that <italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni </italic>and <italic toggle="yes">E. arloingi</italic> formed distinct taxonomic groups, separate from the other <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. in cattle and sheep. The current study contradicts the findings of <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">Liang <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> (2022)</xref>. Their study demonstrated that phylogenetic analysis based on 18S rDNA indicated <italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni</italic> was the most closely related to ovine <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic>, followed by <italic toggle="yes">E. ellipsoidaliss</italic>,<italic toggle="yes"> E. zuernii</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">E. bovis from cattle</italic>. Notably, <italic toggle="yes">E. arloingi</italic> demonstrated 99% similarity to <italic toggle="yes">E. ahsata </italic>based on 18S rRNA (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Khodakaram-Tafti <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>).</p><p>Recognizing certain limitations of this study is imperative. The lack of comprehensive genetic sequences for essential <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. in GenBank for the target gene under study makes it challenging to perform a comparative analysis of coccidia across other goat spp. This gap reduces the accuracy of spp. identification in mixed infections, impede evaluation of genetic diversity, and complicate the development of effective molecular diagnostic tools. The precise diagnosis of the causal agent of coccidia infection is critical for gaining a better understanding of the parasite&#8217;s biology and life cycle. Identifying spp. in<italic toggle="yes"> Eimeria</italic> co-infections is difficult because of their morphological similarities, which complicates their differentiation under a microscope. The presence of overlapping life cycle stages complicates identification, as various spp. may exhibit similar characteristics during certain developmental phases. Mixed infections further complicate the evaluation of the contribution of each spp. to the disease severity. These issues underscore the need to integrate multiple diagnostic techniques, including molecular assays, to reliably identify cases of co-infection.</p><p>This study revealed significant differences in <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> infection rates among various provinces of Java, Indonesia. This study identified that <italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni </italic>and <italic toggle="yes">E. arloingi</italic> were the primary spp. causing caprine coccidiosis. Valuable molecular data for <italic toggle="yes">E. </italic><italic toggle="yes">christenseni</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">E. arloingi </italic>were obtained, which can be utilized for future molecular research. Therefore, the sequence obtained in this study will contribute to expanding our knowledge of the genetic diversity and geographical distribution of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria </italic>spp. that infect small ruminants worldwide.</p><p>Further research on this topic is necessary in regions of Indonesia beyond Java Island, with a significant focus on the molecular identification and characterization of the<italic toggle="yes"> Eimeria</italic> spp. These findings offer important baseline data that can help develop strategies for managing the disease in Indonesia.</p><p>In conclusion, this study provides information regarding the types of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp. in goats in Java, Indonesia, along with their occurrence levels. Additionally, <italic toggle="yes">E. christenseni</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">E. arloingi</italic> were among the spp. identified. These results highlight the epidemiology of coccidiosis in the region and the importance of disease control in goat farms to anticipate economic losses associated with this disease in Java, Indonesia.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>Dias Aprita Dewi received a scholarship from the Agricultural Extension and Human Resource Development Agency, Ministry of Agriculture, while Aan Awaludin was supported by the Center for Higher Education Funding (BPPT) through the Indonesian Education Scholarship/Beasiswa Pendidikan Indonesia program and the Indonesia Endowment Fund for Education (Agency/Lembaga Pengelola Dana Pendidikan).</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p>The authors declare they have no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>This research was supported by a Final Project Recognition/Rekognisi Tugas Akhir (RTA) Grant, Universitas Gadjah Mada (grant number 5286/UN1). P.I/PT.01.03/2024.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>DAD: sample collection, morphological examination, Whitlock examination, DNA sequence analysis, writing the original manuscript; YRN: sample collection, editing sequencing results, molecular data analysis, manuscript editing; AA: sample collection, oocyst measurement and quantification; VIN: DNA extraction, DNA purification, manuscript editing; DP: PCR performance, statistical analysis, morphological examination; RWN: PCR performance, PCR analysis, manuscript editing; FE: morphological data analysis, quantification of OPG in feces; JP: morphological examination, manuscript editing, funding acquisition. </p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All data supporting the findings of this study are available within the manuscript.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abo-Shehada</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abo-Farieha</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of Eimeria species among goats in northern Jordan. Small. Rumin. Res</article-title><year>2003</year><volume>49</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>113</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Factors affecting susceptibility of goats to Coccidia</source><year>2011</year><publisher-loc>Greensboro, NC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>North Carolina Agriculture and Technical State University</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Habsi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphological and molecular characterization of three Eimeria species from captured rangeland goats in Western Australia</article-title><source>Vet. Parasitol. Reg. Stud. Rep</source><year>2017</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vprsr.2017.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31014847</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anim-Jnr</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mabiki</surname><given-names>F.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frimpong</surname><given-names>Y.O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emmambux</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greathead</surname><given-names>H.M.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sustainable small ruminant production in low- and middle-income African countries: harnessing the potential of agroecology</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><year>2023</year><volume>15</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>15326</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bawm</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Htun</surname><given-names>L.L.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kukovics</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Management and control of Eimeria infection in goats. In Goat science-environment, health and economy.</source><year>2021</year><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Intech Open</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bawm</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Win</surname><given-names>T.Z.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Win</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Htun</surname><given-names>L.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakao</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katakura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First detection of Eimeria species in Myanmar domestic goats with both microscopic and molecular methods</article-title><source>Parasite</source><year>2020</year><volume>27</volume><issue>38</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32425155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1051/parasite/2020037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7236540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berto</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mcintosh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>C.W.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on coccidian oocysts (Apicomplexa: Eucoccidiorida)</article-title><source>Rev. Bras. Parasitol. Vet</source><year>2014</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24728354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/s1984-29612014001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>BPS</collab></person-group><source>Populasi Kambing menurut Provinsi (Ekor), 2021&#8211;2023</source><year>2022</year><publisher-loc>Jakarta, Indonesia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>BPS Indonesia</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>P.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasse</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>A.C.D.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Seixas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paschoal</surname><given-names>A.T.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minutti</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cardim</surname><given-names>S.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Rodrigues</surname><given-names>F.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Barros</surname><given-names>L.D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and risk factors of Eimeria spp. natural infection in sheep from northern Paran&#225;</article-title><source>Brazil. Rev. Bras. Parasitol. Vet</source><year>2022</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/S1984-29612022004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9901863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35019027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Species differentiation in the Coccidia from the domestic sheep</article-title><source>J. Parasitol</source><year>1938</year><volume>24</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>453</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dabasa</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shanko</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zewdei</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jilo</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gurmesa</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdela</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of small ruminant gastrointestinal parasites infections and associated risk factors in selected districts of Bale zone, south eastern Ethiopia</article-title><source>J. Parasitol. Vector Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>88</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Y.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathogenic effects of the coccidium Eimeria ninakohlyakimovae in goats</article-title><source>Vet. Res. Commun</source><year>2006</year><volume>30</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16400601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11259-006-3228-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Macedo</surname><given-names>L.O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bezerra-Santos</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Mendon&#231;a</surname><given-names>C.L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>R.A.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Carvalho</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and risk factors associated with infection by Eimeria spp. in goats and sheep in Northeastern Brazil</article-title><source>J. Parasit. Dis</source><year>2020</year><volume>44</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32801513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s12639-020-01235-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7410878</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perumal</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muniswamy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zamir Ahmed</surname><given-names>S.K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sunder</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alyethodi</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ravi</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of coccidiosis in Andaman local goat and its metaphylaxis in tropical island ecosystem</article-title><source>Indian J. Anim. Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>91</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>438</fpage><lpage>442</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diao</surname><given-names>N.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Q.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of Eimeria spp. among goats in China: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Front</article-title><source>Cell. Infect. Microbiol</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fcimb.2022.806085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8924409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35310846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eckert</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shirley</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coudert</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Biotechnology: guidelines on technique in coccidiosis research</source><year>1995</year><publisher-loc>Luxembourg, Europe</publisher-loc><publisher-name>ECSC-EC-EAEC</publisher-name><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>39</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Efendi</surname><given-names>W.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suwanti</surname><given-names>L.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastutiek</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mufasirin</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kusnoto</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalensi dan Identifikasi Protozoa Saluran Pencernaan pada Kambing di Kecamatan Labang Kabupaten Bangkalan</article-title><source>J. Parasite Sci</source><year>2019</year><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Engidaw</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anteneh</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coccidiosis in small ruminants</article-title><source>Afr. J. Appl. Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>319</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gadelhaq</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arafa</surname><given-names>W.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aboelhadid</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of Eimeria species naturally infecting Egyptian baldi chickens</article-title><source>Iran. J. Parasitol</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25904950</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4403544</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gondipon</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malaka</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overview of coccidiosis in sheep: history of disease incidence in the world and life cycle</article-title><source>HAJAS</source><year>2021</year><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>51</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sporulation rate and viability of Eimeria tenella oocysts stored in potassium sorbate solution</article-title><source>Parasitol. Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>120</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2297</fpage><lpage>2301</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34050827</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00436-020-06792-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitlock</surname><given-names>H.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new technique for counting nematode eggs in sheep faeces</article-title><source>J. Council Sci. Ind. Res</source><year>1939</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>52</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guedes</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conde-Felipe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barba</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>del Carmen Mu&#241;oz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrer</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;n</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hermosilla</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taubert</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metaphylactic strategies using toltrazuril against coccidiosis in goat kids</article-title><source>Vet. Parasitol</source><year>2024</year><volume>327</volume><fpage>110133</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38266373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vetpar.2024.110133</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BIOEDIT: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/ NT</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Symp. Ser</source><year>1999</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>98</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harmaya</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zegeye</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alemu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Temesgen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emiru</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amede</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tigre</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feyera</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deressa</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teshome</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tessema</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumsa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naramo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sonkar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Njau</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scholtens</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasali</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiros</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study on prevalance of small ruminant Coccidiosis in and Around Harmaya, Eastern Haraghe Ethiopia study on prevalance of small ruminant Coccidiosis in</article-title><source>Eur. J. Biol. Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastutiek</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lastuti</surname><given-names>N.D.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suwanti</surname><given-names>L.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sunarso</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suprihati</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurniawati</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsubayashi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coproparasitological examinations and molecular determination of Eimeria species in Madura cattle reared on Madura Island, Indonesia. Parasitol. Int</article-title><year>2022</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>102478</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.parint.2021.102478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34626806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haug</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thebo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattsson</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simplified protocol for molecular identification of Eimeria species in field samples</article-title><source>Vet. Parasitol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>146</volume><issue>1&#8211;2</issue><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17386979</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vetpar.2006.12.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillis</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ribosomal DNA:molecular evolution and phylogenetic inference December 1991 ribosomal DNA:molecular evolution and phylogenetic inference</article-title><source>Rev. Lit. Arts Am</source><year>2011</year><volume>66</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>411</fpage><lpage>453</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1086/417338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1784710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jinneman</surname><given-names>K.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wetherington</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>W.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omiescinski</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tenge</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>N.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wekell</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An oligonucleotide-ligation assay for the differentiation between Cyclospora and Eimeria spp. polymerase chain reaction amplification products</article-title><source>J. Food Prot</source><year>1999</year><volume>62</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>682</fpage><lpage>685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10382662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4315/0362-028x-62.6.682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beard</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beharry</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Serrette</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soleyn</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sookhoo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oura</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular identification of Eimeria species in broiler chickens in Trinidad, West Indies</article-title><source>Vet. Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29361806</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/vetsci5010012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5876585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanyari</surname><given-names>P. W.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kagira</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mhoma</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and intensity of endoparasites in small ruminants kept by farmers in Kisumu Municipality, Kenya</article-title><source>Livestock Res. Rural Dev</source><year>2009</year><volume>21</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>202</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mingala</surname><given-names>C.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koiwa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Onuma</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunoya</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis and development of species-specific PCR assays based on ITS-1 region of rRNA in bovine Eimeria parasites</article-title><source>Vet. Parasitol</source><year>2010</year><volume>174</volume><issue>1&#8211;2</issue><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20817404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vetpar.2010.08.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khodakaram-Tafti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashemnia</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Razavi</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharifiyazdi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nazifi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic characterization and phylogenetic analysis of Eimeria arloingi in Iranian native kids</article-title><source>Parasitol. Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>112</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>3187</fpage><lpage>3192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23779225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00436-013-3494-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lassen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>J&#228;rvis</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eimeria and Cryptosporidium in Lithuanian cattle farms</article-title><source>Vet. Med. Zoot</source><year>2009</year><volume>48</volume><issue>70</issue><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of 18S rRNA, ITS-1, ITS-2, and COI from Eimeria christenseni and E. arloingi in goats from Shaanxi Province, Northwestern China</article-title><source>Animals</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1340</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35681805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ani12111340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9179911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#243;pez-Osorio</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaparro-Guti&#233;rrez</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#243;mez-Osorio</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overview of poultry Eimeria life cycle and host-parasite interactions</article-title><source>Front. Vet. Sci.</source><year>2020</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32714951</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fvets.2020.00384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7351014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meek</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willeberg</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Veterinary epidemiology principles and methods</source><year>1987</year><publisher-loc>Ames, IA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Iowa States University Press</publisher-name><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>40</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsubayashi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takami</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimata</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tani</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasai</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of crane Coccidia, Eimeria gruis and E. reichenowi, found in feces of migratory cranes</article-title><source>Parasitol. Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>97</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15940517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00436-005-1404-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamaden</surname><given-names>W.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sallam</surname><given-names>N.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abouelhassan</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of Eimeria species among sheep and goats in Suez Governorate, Egypt</article-title><source>Int. J. Vet. Sci. Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijvsm.2018.02.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6147386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30255081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen-Ho-Bao</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huu Nguyen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on molecular characteristics of Eimeria arloingi in goats (Capra hircus) in Vietnam</article-title><source>Int. J. Eng. Sci. Technol</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pamungkas</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Apsari</surname><given-names>I.A.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Widyastuti</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalensi Infeksi Eimeria spp. yang Tinggi pada Kambing yang Dipelihara di Kota Denpasar</article-title><source>Indonesia. Med. Veterinus</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>861</fpage><lpage>868</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pertiwi</surname><given-names>V.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riffiandi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sofiana</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infeksi Parasit Gastrointestinal pada Kambing (Capra aegagrus hircus) di Desa Rajabasa Lama Kabupaten Lampung Timur</article-title><source>PETERPAN</source><year>2023</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>15</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pyziel</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demiaszkiewicz</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osiska</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolka</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anusz</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laskowski</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Usefulness of PCR. RFLP of 18S rRNA gene for rapid post-mortem diagnostics of highly pathogenic Eimeria spp. (Apicomplexa: Eimeriidae) of European bison, Bison bonasus L. with histopathological correlation</article-title><source>Int. J. Parasitol. Parasites. Wildl</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32368487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijppaw.2020.03.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7190760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehman</surname><given-names>T.U.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sajid</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>R.Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arshad</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of Eimeria and associated risk factors in cattle of district Toba Tek Singh, Pakistan</article-title><source>Parasitol. Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>108</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>11711177</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00436-010-2159-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21110042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roh</surname><given-names>S.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ku</surname><given-names>B.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Case study: pathological and phylogenetic analysis of coccidiosis in two goats with heavy infection of unrecorded Eimeria sp</article-title><source>Parasitol. Int</source><year>2023</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>102662</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36067931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.parint.2022.102662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guedes</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munoz</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hermosilla</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>Y.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matos</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taubert</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Control strategies using diclazuril against coccidiosis in goat kids</article-title><source>Parasitol. Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>110</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2131</fpage><lpage>2136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22193521</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00436-011-2746-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>L.E.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Cruz</surname><given-names>J.F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teixeira Neto</surname><given-names>M.R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melo</surname><given-names>A.D.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tapia</surname><given-names>D.M.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of Eimeria infections in sheep raised extensively in a semiarid region of Brazil</article-title><source>Rev. Bras. Parasitol. Vet</source><year>2015</year><volume>24</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>410</fpage><lpage>415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26648007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1590/S1984-29612015070</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stotish</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyenhofer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and composition of the oocyst wall of Eimeria tenella</article-title><source>J. Parasitol</source><year>1978</year><volume>64</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1074</fpage><lpage>1081</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">739302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takeo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsubayashi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kusakisako</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular and phylogenetic characterizations of an Eimeria krijgsmanni Yakimoff and Gouseff, 1938 (Apicomplexa: Eimeriidae) mouse intestinal protozoan parasite by partial 18S ribosomal RNA gene sequence analysis</article-title><source>Parasitol. Int</source><year>2014</year><volume>63</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>627</fpage><lpage>630</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24780139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.parint.2014.04.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tenrisanna</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasim</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Livestock farming income analysis of farm households in Indonesia. IOP Conf. Ser</article-title><source>Earth Environ. Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>788</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Underwood</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blauwiekel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delano</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillesby</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mischler</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoell</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pritchett-Corning</surname><given-names>K.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whary</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chapter 15.Biology and diseases of ruminants (sheep, goats, and cattle). In Laboratory animal medicine</source><year>2015</year><edition>3rd</edition><publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name><fpage>623</fpage><lpage>694</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>D.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gururaj</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>P.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular epidemiology and point mutations in ITS1 and 18S rRNA genes of Eimeria ninakohlyakimovae and E. christenseni isolated from Indian goats</article-title><source>Vet. Parasitol. Reg. Stud</source><year>2017</year><volume>9</volume><issue>51</issue><fpage>62</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.vprsr.2017.04.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31014842</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>