<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2846</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">openvetj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Veterinary Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2226-4485</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2218-6050</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tripoli</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7703607</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7703607.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7703607</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7703607</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33282701</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/ovj.v10i3.8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OVJ-10-297</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Isolation of enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> harboring <italic toggle="yes">seb</italic> gene and enteropathogenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> (serogroups O18, O114, and O125) from soft and hard artisanal cheeses in Egypt</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hegab</surname><given-names initials="OW">Ola Wagih</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Latif</surname><given-names initials="EF">Eman F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moawad</surname><given-names initials="AA">Ashraf Ahmed</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1">Department of Food Hygiene and Control, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Cairo University, Giza, Egypt</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Ola Wagih Hegab. Department of Food Hygiene and Control, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Cairo University, Giza, Egypt. <email>olawagihvet90@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jul-Sep</season><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">369787</issue-id><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>307</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>08</day><month>6</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>05</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-04-30 01:25:12.957"><day>30</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0"><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-10-297.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Soft and hard artisanal cheeses are regularly consumed in Egypt. These products are usually processed from raw milk which may harbor many pathogenic and spoilage microorganisms.</p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>To evaluate the safety of some artisanal cheeses in Egypt, such as Ras, Domiati, and Mish, through chemical and microbiological examination.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods:</title><p>One hundred and fifty random samples of traditional Ras, Domiati, and Mish cheeses (50 each) were microbiologically and chemically analyzed. Counts of total bacteria, presumptive coliform, staphylococci, yeast, and mold were estimated. Furthermore, isolation of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli and Staphylococcus aureus</italic> was performed, followed by PCR confirmation; isolates of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> were examined for the presence of virulence genes; on the other hand, the detection of the five classical enterotoxin genes of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> was performed using multiplex PCR. Regarding chemical analysis, moisture, salt, and acidity content were measured. Correlations between chemical and microbial findings were investigated.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>Mean counts of total bacteria, presumptive coliform, staphylococci, yeast, and mold were (2 &#215; 10<sup>8</sup>, 3 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup> and 1 &#215; 10<sup>7 </sup>), (3 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup>, 5 &#215; 10 and 5 &#215; 10<sup>2</sup>), (1 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup>, 4 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup>and 1 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup>), (3 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup>, 1 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup> and 5 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup>), and (7 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup>, 4 &#215; 10<sup>3 </sup>and 3 &#215; 10<sup>4</sup>) for Ras, Domiati and Mish cheeses, respectively. Serological identification of suspected <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> revealed that <italic toggle="yes">E. coli </italic>O125 was isolated from Ras and Domiati samples, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O18 was recovered from Ras samples, while <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O114 was isolated from Mish samples. PCR results revealed that all detected isolates of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli </italic>were positive for both iss (increased serum survival) and fimH (type 1 fimbriae) genes. Concerning isolated <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, all examined products were harboring <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> enterotoxigenic strains, with <italic toggle="yes">seb</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sed </italic>genes being the most common. The mean values of moisture, salt, and acidity were (30.03, 56.44, and 58.70), (3.30, 6.63, and 7.56) and (0.65, 0.68, and 0.50) for Ras, Domiati, and Mish cheeses, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>Enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> harboring <italic toggle="yes">seb</italic> gene and enteropathogenic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (serogroups O18, O114, and O125) were frequently isolated from soft and hard artisanal cheeses in Egypt. Therefore, strict hygienic measures should be applied during their manufacture, handing, and distribution.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Domiati</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> virulence genes</kwd><kwd>Mish</kwd><kwd>Ras</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> enterotoxins</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Traditional Egyptian dairy products are an essential part of the daily diet in Egypt. Raw milk is the common factor in making all traditional products, which usually record high sensorial characteristics, as consumers mostly choose their dairy products based on its sensory properties, regardless if it is made from raw or pasteurized milk (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Awad, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">El-Ghaish <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Ewida and Hussein, 2019</xref>). Some traditional products have been traced back to the pharaoh era of 4,000 BC, and is then handed down from one generation to another. There are different types of traditional cheese in Egypt and among them are Ras, Domiati, and Mish (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Benkerroum, 2012</xref>).</p><p>Ras cheese is a hard cheese commonly known in Egypt as &#8220;Romi&#8221;. It is one of the artisan type cheeses, which is produced often in small factories located in rural areas. It is mainly made from raw milk, either cow&#8217;s or a mixture of cow and buffalo milk, mostly without adding a starter culture, and fermentation and ripening occur only due to the native flora of raw milk, then it is kept to ripen for 3&#8211;8 months till a sharp flavor is acquired, similar to the Greek Kefalotyri cheese (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Awad, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">El-Fadaly <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2015</xref>).</p><p>Domiati or Damietta cheese (Gebnah Domiata) is one of the most popular white, soft pickled cheeses. It is named after the Egyptian seaport city &#8220;Dumy&#226;t&#8221;. Typically, it is salty, unlike other pickled cheeses, as the salt is added directly to the raw milk at the proportion of 5%&#8211;14%, which varies according to season and ripening conditions (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">Robinson and Tamime, 1991</xref>).</p><p>Mish is one of the oldest indigenous milk products in Egypt that has a sharp harsh flavor with a relatively higher salt content and is mostly yellowish brown color. Karish cheese is considered as the basic raw material for such a product. Some other ingredients that may be included in Mish are sour milk, buttermilk, morta (a byproduct of ghee), different types of pepper (green, red, and paprika), table salt, and a portion of an old Mish which acts as the starter culture. All ingredients are brined under microaerophilic conditions mostly in earthenware containers for more than 1 year to obtain matured mish, which consists of Mish cheese and Mish slurry (pickling medium), and both are consumed (<xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">Tamime, 2006</xref>).</p><p>Raw milk used in the production of traditional dairy products and harbor a large number of native microflora that may participate in the development of a desirable aroma and an appropriate flavor, but it may also contain pathogenic microorganisms such as <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and others that are considered as public health hazards, causing a serious food illness and may produce lethal toxins in the food (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Awad <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">El-Ghaish <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). Moreover, undesirable spoilage organisms may also be found that cause defects and limits the shelf life of these products, rendering them unmarketable. Many other factors may cause an increase in the microbial load of traditional products, such as manufacture, handling, storage, and even marketing ways, which are still primitive and unhygienic (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Osman <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2011</xref>).</p><p>The current study was conducted to assess the safety of some traditional cheeses in Egypt, such as Ras, Domiati, and Mish, through chemical and microbiological examination.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Samples collection</title><p>One hundred and fifty random samples of Ras, Domiati, and Mish cheeses (50 each) were collected from different Egyptian Governorates. The samples were identified, placed in an ice box, and examined immediately.</p></sec><sec><title>Chemical analysis</title><p>Moisture and acidity were analyzed according to the AOAC guidelines (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Association of Official Analytical Chemists) (2000)</xref> and salt according to the APHA guidelines (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">American Public Health Association) (2004)</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Microbiological examination</title><p>Preparation of food homogenate and decimal dilutions, total bacterial count (TBC; CFU/g), presumptive coliform count (MPN/g), and isolation of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> were carried out according to the APHA guidelines (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">American Public Health Association) (2004)</xref>.</p><p>Biochemical identification of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (microscopic examination, oxidase, urea, IMVC, TSI, L-Lysin decarboxylase, carbohydrate fermentation tests, and confirmed tests for thermotolerant (fecal) coliforms) was carried out according to <xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">Silva <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.&#8217;s (2019)</xref> description.</p><p>Serological identification of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> was done using DENKA SEIKEN CO., LTD. kits. The molecular characterization, and virulence genes detection was performed using PCR, where DNA was extracted from the bacterial isolates using QIAamp&#174; DNA Mini Kit (Catalogue no.51304) according to the instruction manual. PCR was done for characterization of 5 genes of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> using Emerald Amp GT PCR master mix, Takara (Catalogue No. RR310A), using 5 different pair of primers (as uniplex PCR) as mentioned in <xref rid="table1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The PCR products were electrophoresed in 1.5% agarose according to that described in <xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">Sambrook <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.&#8217;s (1989)</xref> study.</p><p>Staphylococci count (CFU/g) and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus </italic>isolation were carried out according to the APHA guidelines (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">American Public Health Association) (2004)</xref>.</p><p>Identification of suspected <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> strains (microscopic examination, catalase activity test, coagulase test, thermostable nuclease, and anaerobic utilization of mannitol) was carried out according to that described in <xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">Silva <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>.&#8217;s (2019)</xref> study. Molecular characterization of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> strains and enterotoxin genes detection was done as in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>. Six genes of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> (5 enterotoxins done by multiplex PCR and 23S rRNA) and six pairs (5 as multiplex and 1 pair as uniplex PCR) were used (<xref rid="table1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>Yeast and mold counts (CFU/g) were conducted according to APHA&#8217;s guidelines (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">American Public Health Association) (2004)</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis </title><p>The collected data were analyzed using Statistical Package for the Social Sciences Statistics 17 for Windows.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>In this study, no experimental live animals were used. All cheese samples were collected directly from the Egyptian local markets.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Chemical analysis</title><p>The chemical analysis of the examined samples, including moisture, salt, and acidity, is illustrated in <xref rid="table2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>; for Ras cheese samples, the mean values were 30.03, 3.30, and 0.65, respectively. The mean values of Domiati cheese samples were 56.44, 6.63, and 0.68, respectively, and were 58.70, 7.56, and 0.50, respectively, for Mish samples.</p></sec><sec><title>Microbiological examination</title><p>As reported in <xref rid="table3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, the TBCs of Ras, Domiati, and Mish samples were 2 &#215; 10<sup>8</sup>, 3 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup>, and 1 &#215; 10<sup>7</sup>, respectively, while coliforms were determined in 44%, 48%, and 92% of that examined in Ras, Domiati, and Mish samples, with a mean values of 3 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup>, 5 &#215; 10, and 5 &#215; 10<sup>2</sup>, respectively. The examined samples were positive for <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> in 8% of Ras cheese samples and in 4% of both Domiati and Mish samples, respectively, as shown in <xref rid="table5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>. The serological identification of the suspected isolated <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> using slide agglutination test (<xref rid="table5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>) revealed that <italic toggle="yes">E. coli </italic>O125 was isolated from Ras and Domiati cheese samples; <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O18 was isolated from Ras samples, while <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O114 was detected in Mish samples. The molecular characterization of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> showed that all <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains isolated from the present study were positive for phoA gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). All isolates of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> lacked both stx1 and tsh genes; on the other hand, all detected isolates were positive for both iss and fimH genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figs. 2</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">5</xref>). Staphylococci were found in 92%, 88%, and 100% of Ras, Domiati, and Mish samples with mean values of 1 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup>, 4 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup>, and 1 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup>, respectively (<xref rid="table3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The incidences of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> in the examined Ras, Domiati, and Mish samples based on biochemical identification were 26%, 36%, and 18%, as presented in <xref rid="table6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>. The number of molecularly identified <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> isolates by using 23S rRNA for the examined Ras, Domiati, and Mish samples was 2, 13, and 6, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Fig. 6</xref>). The detection of the five classical enterotoxin genes of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> revealed that the two strains identified from Ras cheese were enterotoxigenic strains having <italic toggle="yes">seb</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sed</italic> genes; in Domiati samples, 10 strains were enterotoxigenic strains harboring <italic toggle="yes">seb</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">sed</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">see </italic>genes, while the 6 strains from Mish samples were enterotoxigenic strains harboring <italic toggle="yes">seb</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>). The mean values of yeast / mold counts of the examined Ras, Domiati and Mish samples were 3 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup>/7 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup>, 1 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup>/ 4 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup>, and 5 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup>/3 &#215; 10<sup>4 </sup>as reported in <xref rid="table3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="table1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Oligonucleotide primers&#8217; sequences and PCR conditions.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Target agent
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Length of amplified product
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Primer sequence (5&#8217;-3&#8217;)
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Gene
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Reference
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="14" colspan="1">
S. aureus</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
102 bp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGTTATCAATGTGCGGGTGG</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
sea</td><td rowspan="10" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Mehrotra <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>x</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGGCACTTTTTTCTCTTCGG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
278 bp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCAATAATAGGAGAAAATAAAAG</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
sed</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATTGGTATTTTTTTTCGTTC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
209 bp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGGTTTTTTCACAGGTCATCC</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
see</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTTTTTTTTCTTCGGTCAATC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
164 bp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTATGGTGGTGTAACTGAGC</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
seb</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCAAATAGTGACGAGTTAGG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
451 bp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGATGAAGTAGTTGATGTGTATGG</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
sec</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CACACTTTTAGAATCAACCG</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
Primary denaturation: 94&#176;C/5 minutes; secondary denaturation: 94&#176;C/30 seconds; annealing: 57&#176;C/40 seconds; extension: 72&#176;C/45 seconds; No. of cycles: 35; final extension: 72&#176;C/10 minutes.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
1250 bp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AC GGAGTTACAAAGGACGAC</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
23S rRNA</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Straub <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 1999</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGCTCAGCCTTAACGAGTAC</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
Primary denaturation: 94&#176;C/5 minutes; secondary denaturation: 94&#176;C/30 seconds; annealing: 55&#176;C/40 seconds; extension: 72&#176;C/1.2 minutes.; No. of cycles: 35; final extension: 72&#176;C/12 minutes.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="15" colspan="1">
E. coli</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
266 bp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATGTTATTTTCTGCCGCTCTG</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
Iss</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
Yaguchi et al., 2007</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTATTGTGAGCAATATACCC</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
Primary denaturation: 94&#176;C/5 minutes; secondary denaturation: 94&#176;C/30 seconds; annealing: 54&#176;C/30 seconds; extension: 72&#176;C/30 seconds; No. of cycles: 35; final extension: 72&#176;C/7 minutes.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
614 bp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACACTGGATGATCTCAGTGG</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
Stx1</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Dipineto <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, 2006</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTGAATCCCCCTCCATTATG</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
Primary denaturation: 94&#176;C/5 minutes; secondary denaturation: 94&#176;C/30 seconds; annealing: 58&#176;C/40 seconds; extension: 72&#176;C/45 seconds; No. of cycles: 35; final extension: 72&#176;C/10 minutes.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
508 bp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGCAGAACGGATAAGCCGTGG</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
fimH</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Ghanbarpour and Salehi, 2010</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCAGTCACCTGCCCTCCGGTA</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
Primary denaturation: 94&#176;C/5 minutes; secondary denaturation: 94&#176;C/30 seconds; annealing: 50&#176;C/40 seconds; extension: 72&#176;C/45 seconds; No. of cycles: 35; final extension: 72&#176;C/10 minutes.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
620 bp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGT GGT GCA CTG GAG TGG</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
Tsh</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
Delicato et al., 2003</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGT CCA GCG TGA TAG TGG</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
Primary denaturation: 94&#176;C/5 minutes; secondary denaturation: 94&#176;C/30 seconds; annealing: 54&#176;C/40 seconds; extension: 72&#176;C/45 seconds; No. of cycles: 35; final extension: 72&#176;C/10 minutes.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
720 bp</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGATTCTGGAAATGGCAAAAG</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
phoA</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
Hu et al., 2011</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGTGATCAGCGGTGACTATGAC</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
Primary denaturation: 94&#176;C/5 minutes; secondary denaturation: 94&#176;C/30 seconds; annealing: 55&#176;C/40 seconds; extension: 72&#176;C/45 seconds; No. of cycles: 35; final extension: 72&#176;C/10 minutes.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Chemical analysis of examined samples (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 50 each).</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Samples</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Moisture %</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Salt %</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Acidity %</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#177; SE</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#177; SE</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#177; SE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ras cheese</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.03 &#177; 0.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.30 &#177; 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65 &#177; 0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Domiati cheese</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.44 &#177; 0.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.63 &#177; 0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68 &#177; 0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mish</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.70 &#177; 0.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.56 &#177; 0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 &#177; 0.05</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Microbiological evaluation of examined samples (CFU/g) (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 50 each).</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ras cheese</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Domiati cheese</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mish</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Total bacterial count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No. (%) of positive samples</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>50 (100%)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>50 (100%)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>50 (100%)</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 &#215; 10<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 &#215; 10<sup>9</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 &#215; 10<sup>7</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 &#215; 10<sup>8</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#177; SE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 &#215; 10<sup>8</sup> &#177; 0.5 &#215; 10<sup>8</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup> &#177; 0.4 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 &#215; 10<sup>7</sup> &#177; 0.2 &#215; 10<sup>7</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Coliforms count (MPN/g)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. (%) of positive samples</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (44%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (48%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (92%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 &#215; 10<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 &#215; 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 &#215; 10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 &#215; 10<sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#177; SE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup> &#177; 1 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 &#215; 10 &#177; 0.1 &#215; 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 &#215; 10<sup>2</sup> &#177; 0.8 &#215; 10<sup>2</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus</italic> count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. (%) of positive samples</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (92%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (88%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (100%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 &#215; 10<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 &#215; 10<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 &#215; 10<sup>2</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#177; SE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup> &#177; 0.2 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup> &#177; 0.7&#215;10<sup>5</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup> &#177; 0.2 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Yeast count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. (%) of positive samples</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (90%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (100%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (92%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 &#215; 10<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#177; SE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup> &#177; 0.6 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup> &#177; 0.2 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup> &#177; 0.6 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Mold count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. (%) of positive samples</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (50%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (44%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (72%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 &#215; 10<sup>2</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 &#215; 10<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 &#215; 10<sup>4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#177; SE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup> &#177; 0.9 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup> &#177; 0.9 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 &#215; 10<sup>4</sup> &#177; 0.7 &#215; 10<sup>4</sup></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><title>Statistical correlation between chemical and microbiological analyses.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Moisture %</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Salt %</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Acidity %</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pearson correlation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sig.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pearson correlation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sig.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pearson correlation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sig.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Ras cheese</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.215</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.151</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.295</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.171</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.235</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coliforms count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.430<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.394<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.048</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.739</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Staph. count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.182</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.207</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.197</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.170</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.088</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.542</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yeast count </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.644</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.070</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.630</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.169</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.240</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.169</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.241</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.518</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.078</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.589</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Domiati cheese</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.326<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.170</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.237</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.237</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.097</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coliforms count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.229</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.806<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.103</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.475</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Staph</italic>. count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.388<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.267</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.391<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yeast count </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.115</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.427</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.306<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.245</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.668</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.142</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.327</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" rowspan="1">Mish</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.423<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.169</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.381</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.047</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.807</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coliforms count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.788</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.590<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.165</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.215</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Staph. count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.131</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.364</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.315<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.516<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yeast count </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.556<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.221</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.123</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.481<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table4-fn1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.707</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.144</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.317</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.259</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table4-fn1"><label>a</label><p>Correlation is significant at the 0.01 level (2-tailed).</p></fn><fn id="table4-fn2"><label>b</label><p>Correlation is significant at the 0.05 level (2-tailed).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><title>Biochemical, serological, molecular identification, and incidence of virulence genes of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolated from examined samples using PCR.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Types of samples</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">Samples containing <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains identified biochemically</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">Strains identified serologically</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Strains identified by phoA gene</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Strains harbor Stx1 gene</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Strains harbor Tsh gene</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Strains harbor Iss gene</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Strains harbor fimH gene</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">No.</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">No.</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="1">serotype</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">type</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Ras cheese</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">O125</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="4" valign="middle" align="center" colspan="1">Nil</td><td rowspan="4" valign="middle" align="center" colspan="1">Nil</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">O18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Domiati cheese</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">O125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mish</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">O114</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>Agarose gel electrophoresis of the PCR product of <italic toggle="yes">pho</italic>A gene for DNA extracted from analyzed <italic toggle="yes">E. coil </italic>isolates. Lane L: ladder; Lane P: positive control. Lanes 1&#8211;8: showing positive <italic toggle="yes">E. coil </italic>strains at 720 bp.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-10-297-g001.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>Agarose gel electrophoresis of <italic toggle="yes">E. coil </italic>stx1 virulence gene. Lane L: ladder; Lane P: positive control. Lanes 1&#8211;8: showing negative strains at 614 bp.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-10-297-g002.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><title>Agarose gel electrophoresis of <italic toggle="yes">E. coil tsh </italic>virulence gene. Lane L: ladder; Lane P: positive control. Lanes 1&#8211;8: showing negative strains at 620 bp.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-10-297-g003.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><title>Agarose gel electrophoresis of <italic toggle="yes">E. coil iss </italic>virulence gene. Lane L: ladder; Lane P: positive control. Lanes 1&#8211;8: showing positive strains at 266 bp.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-10-297-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Chemical analysis</title><p>The chemical parameters, including moisture, salt, and acidity, are shown in <xref rid="table2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>; for Ras cheese samples, nearly similar results were obtained by <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed (2016)</xref> and <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">El-Refaay <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2016)</xref> concerning salt and acidity, while higher results were recorded by <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Awad <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2003)</xref>, <xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Osman <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2011)</xref>, and <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Dahmash <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2019)</xref> for salt and moisture. For Domiati cheese samples, nearly similar results for salt were obtained by <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Aly <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2007)</xref> and <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">El-Baradei <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2007)</xref>, higher results recorded by <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">El-kholy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2014)</xref>, <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">El-Zahar (2014)</xref>, and <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">El-Refaay <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2016)</xref> for salt and acidity. The results for the Mish samples were in agreement with <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">El-Zahar (2014)</xref> and <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">El-Refaay <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2016)</xref>. The apparent variation among the examined parameters in different examined samples could be attributed to variances in composition, properties of raw milk, and biodiversity of the organisms in each product, as well as other ingredients employed in the manufacture of traditional raw products, especially with lack of Egyptian standards for such products (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Aly <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>).</p><fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><title>Agarose gel electrophoresis of <italic toggle="yes">E. coil fim</italic>H virulence gene. Lane L: ladder; Lane P: positive control. Lanes 1&#8211;8: showing positive strains at 508 bp.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-10-297-g005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Microbiological examination</title><p>Total bacterial, presumptive coliform, yeast and mold counts were considered the most significant indices for the microbial quality (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">APHA (American Public Health Association), 2004</xref>). Nearly similar results of TBC for Ras cheese samples were obtained by <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Awad <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2003)</xref>, <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">El-Zahar (2014)</xref>, and <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">El-Leboudy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2014)</xref>, while lower results were found by <xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Osman <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2011)</xref> and <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Abd El-Halem <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2019)</xref>. The results of TBC for Domiati cheese samples were in agreement with those obtained by <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Aly <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2007)</xref>, <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Sayed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2011)</xref>, and <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Ibrahim <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2015a)</xref>, and higher results were obtained by <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">El Sayed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2011)</xref>, while lower findings were obtained by <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">El-kholy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2014)</xref> and <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Ibrahim <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2015b)</xref>. Nearly similar TBC results for Mish samples were reported by <xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">Zaki and Shokry (1988)</xref> and <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">El-Zahar (2014)</xref>. TBC is not directly related to the presence of pathogens or toxins, but it may be a convenient indicator of poor sanitation, defects in process control systems, and/or contaminated raw ingredients (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">APHA (American Public Health Association), 2004</xref>; <xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">Silva <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). There was a negative correlation between TBC, salt, and acidity in the all examined samples, but was not significant as not all but most microorganisms were suppressed by salt and acidity content (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Aly <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). Nevertheless, there was a positive significant correlation between TBC and moisture in Domiati and Mish cheese samples (<xref rid="table4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The relatively high moisture allows the growth of different types of desirable and undesirable microorganisms that may be introduced through raw milk used or during the processing steps (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Aly <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>).
<table-wrap id="table6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6.</label><caption><title>Biochemical, molecular identification, and incidence of enterotoxin genes of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus </italic>isolated from examined samples using multiplex PCR.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Types of samples</th><th colspan="2" rowspan="2">Samples harbor coagulase positive <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Strains identified by <italic toggle="yes">23S rRNA</italic></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Samples harbor enterotoxigenic strains</th><th colspan="5" rowspan="1">Type of SEs</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">sea</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">seb</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">sec</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">sed</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">see</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ras cheese</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nil</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Domiati cheese</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mish</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nil</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nil</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><title>Agarose gel electrophoresis of the PCR product of 23S rRNA gene for DNA extracted from analyzed <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> isolates. Lane L: ladder; Lane P: positive control. Lanes 1&#8211;21: showing positive <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> strains at 1,250 bp.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-10-297-g006.jpg"/></fig>
<fig id="fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 7.</label><caption><title>Agarose gel electrophoresis showing multiplex PCR amplification products for <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> enterotoxin genes. Lanes L, ladder lane P: positive control. Staphylococcal enterotoxin A (<italic toggle="yes">sea</italic>) positive isolates at 102 bp. Staphylococcal enterotoxin D (<italic toggle="yes">sed</italic>) positive isolates at 278 bp. Staphylococcal enterotoxin E (<italic toggle="yes">see</italic>) positive isolates at 209 bp. Staphylococcal enterotoxin B (<italic toggle="yes">seb</italic>) positive isolates at 164 bp. Staphylococcal enterotoxin C (<italic toggle="yes">sec</italic>) positive isolates at 451 bp.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-10-297-g007.jpg"/></fig>
</p><p>The presence of coliforms in cheese is objectionable as it reflects unsanitary conditions during production, handling, storage, and even distribution (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Sayed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2011</xref>). Its existence may constitute a biological hazard since coliforms are implicated in many reported cases of food poisoning. Moreover, coliforms possess an economic significance as products contaminated with coliforms will be of inferior quality and unmarketable (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Martin <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2016</xref>). Nearly similar results of coliforms for Ras cheese were obtained by <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">El-Zahar (2014)</xref>, lower results were obtained by <xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Osman <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2011)</xref>, <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Awad <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2003)</xref>, and <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Abd El-Halem <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2019)</xref>, while higher results recorded by <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Abd elsalam (2014)</xref> and <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed (2016)</xref>. For Domiati cheese samples, higher findings were introduced by <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Ibrahim <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2015b)</xref> and <xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Abd Allah <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2017)</xref>, while lower results were recorded by <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Sayed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2011)</xref>. For Mish samples, higher results were recorded by <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">El-Zahar (2014)</xref>. There was a positive significant correlation between coliform count and moisture in Ras cheese samples (<xref rid="table4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The comparatively low incidence of coliforms in Ras cheese samples may be related to low moisture content and consequently low water activity that will influence microbial growth (<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">Trm&#269;i&#263; <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2016</xref>). Salt content had a significant negative correlation with coliforms in all examined samples as added salt not only enhances flavor but it also acts as a preservative; the anti-microbial activity of salt is owed to its ability to decrease water activity in food by damaging the microbial cell membrane (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">Ayyash and Shah, 2011</xref>). Concerning <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> incidence rate, higher results for Ras cheese samples were obtained by <xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">Ombarak <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2016)</xref> and <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Abd El-Halem <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2019)</xref>. Nearly similar results in Domiati cheese samples were recorded by <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Sayed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2011)</xref>, while <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">El-kholy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2014)</xref> and <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Ibrahim <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2015b)</xref> obtained higher results. For Mish samples, higher results obtained by <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Dawoud <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2018)</xref>. All isolated <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> serotypes (O125, O18, and O114) belonging to enteropathogenic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli </italic>mainly infect infants younger than 2 years. Acute watery diarrhea, vomiting, and low-grade fever are the most detected symptoms. <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O18 also results in extra intestinal infections as neonatal meningitis, septicemia, pyelonephritis, and pneumonia (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">Stenutz <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Dedei&#263;-Ljubovi&#263; <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Ewida and Hussein, 2019</xref>). The molecular characterization of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> was carried out using phoA gene (alkaline phosphatase) as a target gene for detecting <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">Thong <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2011</xref>) and all <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains were positive for (phoA) gene. <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> bacteria possesses multiple virulence genes from which four genes were detected (stx1, tsh, iss, and fimH); all detected isolates were positive for both (iss) and (fimH) genes. The virulence gene iss encodes a protein associated with increased serum survival of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> in humans and is considered as a protective factor for the pathogen against phagocytosis. <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> acquires this gene to have the ability to cause extra intestinal infections, such as neonatal meningitis and sepsis (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">Sarowska <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). The adhesion criteria of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> are related to fimH virulence gene which is important for both normal ecosystem and pathogenicity of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>. Although 95% of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli </italic>isolates show expression for type 1 fimbriae, the gene is not essential for the presence of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> in the colon. However, it helps <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> to transitory colonize in the oropharyngeal portal which is significant for normal fecal/oral transmission of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> among hosts, as well as it plays an important role in the incidence of urinary tract infections caused by <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">Sokurenko <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">Sarowska <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>).</p><p>Staphylococci are widespread microorganisms that are present everywhere. Staphylococci outbreaks are usually caused by food handlers with bad personal hygiene (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">EL-Kholy <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). Our results (<xref rid="table4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>) showed that there was a significant positive correlation between moisture and staphylococci count and a significant negative correlation between it and acidity in Domiati cheese samples. While staphylococci count significantly decreases with increase in salt and acidity in Mish samples, the growth of staphylococci relies mainly on many parameters, such as temperature, pH, salt, water activity, and oxidation reduction potential; their growth can be decreased by the integration of two or more parameters (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Bellio <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> is incriminated in 9,000 deaths every year; it is regarded as the third most serious pathogen causing foodborne illnesses worldwide (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). The presence of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> in dairy products is regarded as a serious public health hazard as the organism may lose its viability during manufacturing processes but its preformed heat stable enterotoxin will still present and induce vomiting and diarrhea within 1&#8211;6 hours. However, food poisoning is not only the main health problem concerning <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, but it also causes toxic shock syndrome, pneumonia, post-operative wound infection, and skin infections (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">FDA (Food and Drug Administration), 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">EL Malt, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Bellio <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). Large numbers of extracellular proteins and toxins are produced by <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>. The most important toxins are Staphylococcal enterotoxins (SEs), which are SEA, SEB, SEC, SED, and SEE, that cause 95% of staphylococcal food poisoning cases, while only 5% of outbreaks occurred by newly described SEs (SEG-SEI, SEIJ, SEIQ, SER-SET, and SEIU-SEIV) and TSST-1. SEs are soluble in water, stable against most proteolytic enzymes (pepsin and trypsin), especially SEB, and heat-resistant even after boiling for 30 minutes (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Bhunia, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). The detection of the five classical enterotoxin genes of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7">Fig. 7</xref>) revealed that Ras cheese strains harbor the <italic toggle="yes">seb</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sed</italic> genes, while Domiati cheese strains were harboring <italic toggle="yes">seb</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">sed</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">see </italic>genes. Moreover, Mish samples <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> strains harbor the <italic toggle="yes">seb</italic> gene. In Egypt, <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Abolghait <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2020)</xref> recently reported similar results that methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> isolated from chicken meat and giblets often produces staphylococcal enterotoxin B (SEB) in non-refrigerated raw chicken livers. Production of enterotoxins by <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> is influenced by a combination of several factors, such as moisture, water activity, salt, acidity, and temperature as well as microbial competition (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">FDA (Food and Drug Administration), 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Bellio <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2019</xref>).</p><p>The low pH and the high nutritional profile of most cheeses are favorable for the growth of yeasts and molds. Their presence in cheese not only influences the sensory characteristics and decreases the grading of cheese but it also possesses a potential hazard. Some of them have the ability to produce several toxins, such as aflatoxins, and others have the ability to cause human and animal pathogenicity (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Ledenbach and Marshall, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">ELbagory <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">El-Fadaly <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2015</xref>). Nearly similar results of yeast and mold counts for Ras samples were obtained by <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">El-Zahar (2014)</xref> and <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">El-Fadaly <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2015)</xref>, and lower counts were recorded by <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">ELbagory <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2014)</xref>. Nearly similar results in Domiati cheese were obtained by <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Sayed <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2011)</xref>, higher results were obtained by <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Aly <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2007)</xref>, and lower results were recorded by <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Ibrahim <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2015b</xref>). The results of Mish samples are well in line with those reported by <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">El-Zahar (2014)</xref> and <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">El-Refaay <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2016)</xref>. In Mish samples, a significant positive correlation was found between yeast and moisture, as well as a significant negative correlation with acidity. The higher moisture content of the product, the more susceptibility for spoilage, off flavors, and over ripening, which result in more breakdown of acids, sugars, proteins, and lipids (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">Morales <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Aly <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). Corresponding to the relatively high counts of yeasts and molds in the examined samples, using raw milk, poor cleaning practices, and inadequate ripening and storage conditions are the main causes (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">D&#8217;Amico, 2014</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> harboring <italic toggle="yes">seb</italic> gene and enteropathogenic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (serogroups O18, O114, and O125) were frequently isolated from soft and hard artisanal cheeses in Egypt. Therefore, strict hygienic measures should be applied during their manufacture, handing, and distribution. Also, more awareness training programs for producers of dairy products should be conducted about how to produce safe products through the implementation of the recent food safety management systems as good manufacturing practices as well as hazard analysis and critical control points in production sites. Also, consumers should be aware of the correct handling and storage methods in order to maintain product safety.</p></sec></body><back><sec><title>Authors&#8217; contribution</title><p>Ashraf Ahmed Moawad and Eman Fathi Abdel-Latif designed and supervised the study as well as reviewed and approved the final version of the submitted manuscript. Ola Wagih Hegab performed the experiments, analyzed, interpreted the data, and drafted the manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>All authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd Allah</surname><given-names>M.A.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>E.M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Barbary</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>M.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality assessment of soft cheese related to some pathogenic bacteria</article-title><source>M. S. Thesis, Fac. Vet. Med.</source><year>2017</year><publisher-loc>Banha, Egypt</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Benha Univ</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd El-Halem</surname><given-names>S.G.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Derea</surname><given-names>H.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tahoun</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd El Hamed</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Foodborne pathogens in milk and dairy products: prevalence and antibiotic resistance</article-title><source>M. S. Thesis, High Inst. Pub. Health</source><year>2019</year><publisher-loc>Alexandria, Egypt</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Alexandria Univ</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd elsalam</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of biological hazards in milk and some dairy products in Egyptian markets</article-title><source>Ph. D. Thesis, Fac. Vet. Med.</source><year>2014</year><publisher-loc>Giza, Egypt</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cairo Univ</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abolghait</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fathi</surname><given-names>A.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Youssef</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Algammal</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) isolated from chicken meat and giblets often produces staphylococcal enterotoxin B (SEB) in non-refrigerated raw chicken livers</article-title><source>Int. J. Food Microbiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>328</volume><fpage>108669</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2020.108669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32497922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maharik</surname><given-names>N.M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valero</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamal</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incidence of enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> in milk and Egyptian artisanal dairy products</article-title><source>Food Control</source><year>2019</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>27</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>L.I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deteriorating microorganisms in milk and some dairy products</article-title><source>Ph. D. Thesis, Fac. Vet. Med.</source><year>2016</year><publisher-loc>Giza, Egypt</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cairo Univ</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aly</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moawad</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Metwally</surname><given-names>B. N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of moisture, salt content and pH on the microbiological quality of traditional Egyptian Domiati cheese</article-title><source>Assiut Vet. Med. J</source><year>2007</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>81</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>AOAC (Association of Official Analytical Chemists)</collab><source>Official methods of analysis of AOAC international</source><year>2000</year><edition>17th</edition><publisher-loc>Rockville, MD</publisher-loc><publisher-name>AOAC Int</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>APHA (American Public Health Association)</collab><source>Standard methods for examination of dairy products</source><year>2004</year><edition>17th</edition><publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Awad</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Texture and flavour development in Ras cheese made from raw and pasteurised milk</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>394</fpage><lpage>400</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Awad</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Attar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayad</surname><given-names>E.H.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Soda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristic of Egyptian market Ras cheese; 1- sensory evaluation, rheological, physico-chemical properties and microbiological analysis</article-title><source>Egyp. J. Dairy Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>303</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayyash</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>N.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of substitution of NaCl with KCl on chemical composition and functional properties of low-moisture Mozzarella cheese</article-title><source>J. Dairy Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>3761</fpage><lpage>3768</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21787912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3168/jds.2010-4103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellio</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiesa</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallina</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macori</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bossi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nia</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mutel</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Messio</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hennekinne</surname><given-names>J-A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Decastelli</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insight into the distribution of staphylococci and their enterotoxins in cheeses under natural conditions</article-title><source>Front. Microbiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmicb.2018.03233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6330353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30666242</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benkerroum</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional fermented foods of North African countries: technology and food safety challenges with regard to microbiological risks</article-title><source>Comp. Rev. Food Sci. Food Saf</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>89</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhunia</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Foodborne microbial pathogens mechanisms and pathogenesis</article-title><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer Science+Business Media</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#8217;Amico</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbiological quality safety issues in cheese making. In Cheese and microbes</article-title><year>2014</year><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>American Society Microbiol Press</publisher-name><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>309</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dahmash</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nazem</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>R.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histamine producing bacteria and some biogenic amines in Ras cheese</article-title><source>M. S. Thesis, Fac. Vet. Med.</source><year>2019</year><publisher-loc>Alexandria, Egypt</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Alexandria Univ</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawoud</surname><given-names>M.E.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mawgoud</surname><given-names>Y.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezq</surname><given-names>M.A.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of mastitis pathogens by multiplex PCR in raw milk and some dairy products from Menoufia Governorate, Egypt</article-title><source>Curr. Sci. Int</source><year>2018</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>540</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dedei&#263;-Ljubovi&#263;</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huki&#263;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beki&#263;</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zvizdi&#263;</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Frequency and distribution of diarrhoeagenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> strains isolated from pediatric patients with diarrhoea in Bosnia and Herzegovina</article-title><source>Bosnian J. Basic Med. Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.17305/bjbms.2009.2835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5638220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19485948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delicato</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Brito</surname><given-names>B.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaziri</surname><given-names>L.C.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vidotto</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Virulence-associated genes in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> isolates from poultry with colibacillosis</article-title><source>Vet. Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12781478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0378-1135(03)00076-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dipineto</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santaniello</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fontanella</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lagos</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fioretti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menna</surname><given-names>L.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Presence of Shiga toxin-producing <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli </italic>O157:H7 in living layer hens</article-title><source>Lett. Appl. Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16910934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1472-765X.2006.01954.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>EL Malt</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Occurrence of enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">staphylococcus aureus </italic>in some cheese varieties in Aswan city &#8211; Upper Egypt</article-title><source>Assiut Vet. Med. J</source><year>2013</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>70</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El Sayed</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosny</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Kholy</surname><given-names>W.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Dairouty</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>S.H.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbiological evaluation of Egyptian white soft cheeses style</article-title><source>J. Am. Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>526</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>ELbagory</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eid</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammad</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawood</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of fungi in locally produced cheese and molecular characterization of isolated toxigenic molds</article-title><source>Benha Vet. Med. J</source><year>2014</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>20</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Baradei</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delacroix-Buchet</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogier</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biodiversity of bacterial ecosystems in traditional Egyptian Domiati cheese</article-title><source>Appl. Environ. Microbil</source><year>2007</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>1248</fpage><lpage>1255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/AEM.01667-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1828670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17189434</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Fadaly</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Kadi</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamad</surname><given-names>M.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Habib</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and identification of Egyptian Ras cheese (Romy) contaminating fungi during ripening period</article-title><source>J. Microbiol. Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Ghaish</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalgalarrondo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choiset</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sitohy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haertl&#233;</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chobert</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening of strains of lactococci isolated from Egyptian dairy products for their proteolytic activity</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><year>2010</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>758</fpage><lpage>764</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-kholy</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-shinawy</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meshref</surname><given-names>A.M.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Korany</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbiological quality of domiati cheese and the influence of probiotics on the behavior of <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus Escherichia coli</italic> O157:H7 in Domiati cheese</article-title><source>J. Food Saf</source><year>2014</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>406</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Leboudy</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amer</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Youssef</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of sanitary measures of ras cheese in manufacturing dairy plant in alexandria governorate</article-title><source>Alexandria J. Vet. Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>84</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Refaay</surname><given-names>D.G.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salama</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saad</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>J.I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mycological studies on some types of cheese</article-title><source>M. S. Thesis, Fac. Vet. Med</source><year>2016</year><publisher-loc>Ismailia, Egypt</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Suez Canal Univ</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Zahar</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biogenic amines and microbiological profile of Egyptian cheeses</article-title><source>African J. Food Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ewida</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>A.A.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Occurrence of virulent and antibiotic-resistant enteropathogenic and Shiga toxin- producing <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> in some milk products sold in Assiut city, Egypt</article-title><source>J. Adv. Vet. Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>42</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>FDA (Food and Drug Administration)</collab><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lampel</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Khaldi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cahill</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Bad bug book foodborne pathogenic microorganisms and natural toxins</source><year>2012</year><edition>2nd</edition><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>91</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghanbarpour</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salehi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of adhesion encoding genes in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> isolates from omphalitis of chicks</article-title><source>Am. J. Anim. Vet. Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>96</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of multiplex PCR assay for rapid detection of <italic toggle="yes">Riemerella anatipestifer, Escherichia coli, </italic>and<italic toggle="yes"> Salmonella enterica</italic> simultaneously from ducks</article-title><source>J. Microbiol. Methods</source><year>2011</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21791228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.mimet.2011.07.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharaf</surname><given-names>O.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname> and Abd El-Khalek</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbiological quality of commercial raw milk, Domiati cheese and Kareish cheese</article-title><source>Middle East J. Appl. Sci</source><year>2015a</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>176</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>J.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salama</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saad</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Helmy</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbial quality of some dairy products in Ismailia city. In 2nd Conference of Food Safety</article-title><source>Fac. Vet. Med., Suez Canal Univ.</source><year>2015b</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>21</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ledenbach</surname><given-names>L.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>R.T.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sperber</surname><given-names>W.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>M.P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbiological spoilage of dairy products</article-title><source>In Compendium of the microbiological spoilage of foods beverages</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Berlin, Germany</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>67</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>N.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trm&#269;i&#263;</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boor</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiedmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The evolving role of coliforms as indicators of unhygienic processing conditions in dairy foods</article-title><source>Front. Microbiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27746769</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fmicb.2016.01549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5043024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehrotra</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>W.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiplex PCR for detection of genes for <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> enterotoxins, exfoliative toxins, toxic shock syndrome toxin 1, and methicillin resistance</article-title><source>J. Clin. Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>1032</fpage><lpage>1035</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10698991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/jcm.38.3.1032-1035.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC86330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Caseinolysis in cheese by <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae </italic>strains of dairy origin</article-title><source>Lett. Appl. Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>410</fpage><lpage>414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14633113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1046/j.1472-765x.2003.01422.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ombarak</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinenoya</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Awasthi</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iguchi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shima</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elbagory</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamasaki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and pathogenic potential of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> isolates from raw milk and raw milk cheese in Egypt</article-title><source>Int. J. Food Microbiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>221</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26824810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2016.01.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Osman</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahin</surname><given-names>Y.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd El- Galil</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohran</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical and microbiological characteristics of Ras cheese collected from Assiut markets</article-title><source>Assiut J. Agri. Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>54</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamime</surname><given-names>A.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Feta and related cheeses</article-title><year>1991</year><publisher-loc>England, UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Ellis Horwood Limited</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fritscgh</surname><given-names>E.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mentiates</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular coloning. A laboratory manual</article-title><year>1989</year><edition>2nd</edition><publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratotry Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarowska</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Futoma-Koloch</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jama-Kmiecik</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frej-Madrzak</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ksiazczyk</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bugla-Ploskonska</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname> and Choroszy-Krol</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Virulence factors, prevalence and potential transmission of extraintestinal pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli </italic>isolated from different sources: recent reports</article-title><source>Gut Pathog</source><year>2019</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30828388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/s13099-019-0290-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6383261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sayed</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Hameid</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaban</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbiological evaluation of some Egyptian white soft cheeses</article-title><source>Benha Vet. Med. J</source><year>2011</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>N.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taniwaki</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Junqueira</surname><given-names>V.C.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silveira</surname><given-names>N.F.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okazaki</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>R.A.R.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Microbiological examination methods of food and water a laboratory manual p</source><year>2019</year><edition>2nd</edition><publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CRC Press, Taylor &amp; Francis Group</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sokurenko</surname><given-names>E.V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chesnokova</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dykhuizen</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ofek</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krogfelt</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Struve</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schembri</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasty</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathogenic adaptation of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli </italic>by natural variation of the FimH adhesion</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>8922</fpage><lpage>8926</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9671780</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1073/pnas.95.15.8922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC21178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stenutz</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weintraub</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Widmalm</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The structures of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> O-polysaccharide antigens</article-title><source>Fed. Eu. Microbiol. Soc</source><year>2006</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>382</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1574-6976.2006.00016.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16594963</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Straub</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hertel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammes</surname><given-names>W.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A 23S rDNA-targeted polymerase chain reaction&#8211;based system for detection of staphylococcus aureus in meat starter cultures and dairy products</article-title><source>J. Food Prot</source><year>1999</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>1150</fpage><lpage>1156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10528718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4315/0362-028x-62.10.1150</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamime</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Briend cheeses</source><year>2006</year><publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thong</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>M.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teh</surname><given-names>C.S.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous detection of methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic><italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli Klebsiella pneumoniae </italic>and <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa </italic>by multiplex PCR</article-title><source>Trop. Biomed</source><year>2011</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21602765</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trm&#269;i&#263;</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chauhan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ralyea</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>N.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boor</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiedmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coliform detection in cheese is associated with specific cheese characteristics, but no association was found with pathogen detection</article-title><source>J. Dairy Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>6105</fpage><lpage>6120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27289158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3168/jds.2016-11112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yaguchi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogitani</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osawa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawano</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kokumai</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaneshige</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noro</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masubuchi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Virulence factors of avian pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> strains isolated from chickens with colisepticemia in Japan</article-title><source>Avian Dis</source><year>2007</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>656</fpage><lpage>662</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17992922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1637/0005-2086(2007)51[656:VFOAPE]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaki</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shokry</surname><given-names>Y.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical and microbiological changes in Mish cheese and Mish during ripening</article-title><source>Egypt. J. Dairy Sci</source><year>1988</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>129</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>