<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Vet J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2846</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">openvetj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Veterinary Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2226-4485</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2218-6050</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tripoli</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8057210</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8057210.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8057210</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8057210</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33898292</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4314/ovj.v11i1.17</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OVJ-11-112</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>
Histological study of gonadal tissues of adult <italic toggle="yes">Artemia salina</italic> (Linnaeus 1758) and immunohistochemistry by Caspase 3 and HSP70 to detect specific apoptosis markers on gonadal tissues after exposure to TBTCl
</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abushaala</surname><given-names initials="NM">Najla Mohamed</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elfituri</surname><given-names initials="AM">Abdulfattah Mohamed</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zulkifli</surname><given-names initials="SZ">Syaizwan Zahmir</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Zoology Department, Faculty of Science, University of Tripoli, Tripoli, Libya</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Marine Biology Research Centre, Tajoura, Libya</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Biology, Faculty of Science, Universiti Putra Malaysia, 43400 UPM Serdang, Selangor, Malaysia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Najla Mohamed Abushaala. Zoology Department, Faculty of Science, University of Tripoli, Tripoli, Libya. <email>na.abushaala@uot.edu.ly</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><season>Jan-Mar</season><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">380037</issue-id><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>23</day><month>04</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-01-05 19:25:28.300"><day>05</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-11-112.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Several types of research have been recently carried out on the biological effects of TBTs, including investigations of genitals in invertebrates in response to exposure to TBTs in marine water.</p></sec><sec><title>Aim:</title><p>The objective of this research was to investigate the acute effects of tributyltin chloride (TBTCl) on gonads in the adult stage of <italic toggle="yes">Artemia salina</italic> by use normal histology and immunohistochemistry (IHC) (Caspase 3 and HSP70) to see specific apoptosis markers.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods:</title><p>After exposure of <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> to different concentrations of TBTCl (25, 50, 100, 200, and 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>), 50 adult <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> (25 male and 25 female) were selected randomly from each concentration to histologically study the gonads. The gonad tissue was sectioned (5 &#956;m) and some slides were stained with hematoxylin and eosin and others were stained with IHC avidin&#8211;biotin complex, and were examined under a light microscope.</p></sec><sec><title>Results:</title><p>The results showed significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in histological lesions between different concentrations of TBTCl. The histological lesions in the testis and ovary section were undifferentiated cells, degenerating yolk globules, and follicle cells enveloping the oocyte which was then compared with control tissue, and these effects were found to be increased in females more than in males with the highest concentration of TBTCl. Immunohistochemistry (IHC) showed that positive immunostaining was observed in the testis and ovary as brownish deposits to Caspase 3 and HSP70 antibody after exposure to TBTCl, while the testis and ovary section in control tissue had no immunoreactivity to Caspase 3 and HSP70 antibody; these effects were profoundly increased with the highest concentration of TBTCl in females more than in males. Finally, the histological lesions and IHC (Caspase 3 and HSP70) revealed that the apoptosis and immune system stress of <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> gonad tissue damage in females were more sensitive to TBTCl toxicity as compared to white males.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion:</title><p>In general, the present study aimed to observe the effects TBTCl on <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> gonads by using histological sections and IHC (Caspase 3 and HSP70), which were evaluated for the first time and have been proven to possess an important function in apoptosis marker and immune system stress in <italic toggle="yes">Artemia</italic>. Finally, the specific mechanisms through which TBTCl affects <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> Caspase 3 and HSP70 expression need further investigation. </p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic></kwd><kwd>Caspase 3</kwd><kwd>Ecotoxicology</kwd><kwd>Heat shock protein</kwd><kwd>Tributyltin chloride</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The International Program on Chemical Safety (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2020</xref>) documented the presence of TBT at high levels in seawater, estuaries, freshwater, and sediments, as well as in aquatic organisms, such as bivalves, gastropods, and fishes. The levels of TBT in water as low as 2.0 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> have been reported to cause this effect (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">Alzieu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1989</xref>). During 1977&#8211;1983, the oyster population in Arcachon Bay in France was severely affected by TBT contamination, which resulted in a reduction in oyster production because of increased mortality, decreased reproduction, and the presence of shell malformations. Ultimately, this led to substantial economic loss (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Fent, 1996</xref>). This issue needs to be carefully investigated. Tributyltin chloride (TBTCl) is used as an antifouling agent which prohibits the growth of organisms on ship hulls and has been in practice for many years. A large number of methods to preclude biofouling have been tested (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Swain <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1998</xref>) and numerous electrical, chemical, thermal, and radiation techniques have been employed by these methods (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Kiil <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2001</xref>). However, the chemically active antifouling paints have been most successful in fighting biofouling. The active ingredients of the antifouling paints are dispersed in a matrix from which they leach into the water (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Kiil <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2001</xref>), thus forming a thin layer of highly concentrated biocides around the submerged surface and then the toxic concentration kills the organisms which are attached to the surface. </p><p>There are many types of research using <italic toggle="yes">Artemia </italic>sp. to monitor spatial and temporal changes in the concentrations of TBTs (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Ohji <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002a</xref>; <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Abushaala <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>, <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>, <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2020</xref>; <xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Abushaala, 2019</xref>). Nevertheless, only a few previous studies are available on the biological effects of TBTs on features such as growth, survival, reproduction, and the sex ratio of <italic toggle="yes">Artemia</italic> sp. Several studies have been recently carried out on the biological effects of TBT, including investigations into the reproduction and growth rate of caprellids species in response to the exposure of TBT in the ambient marine water (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Ohji <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2003</xref>). It was found that the sex ratio dramatically changed after a brief exposure to TBT during the embryonic stage (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Ohji <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002b</xref>). However, the action mechanism of TBT can differ from one organism to another and the effects of its exposure may also vary according to the developmental stage. </p><p>The reproductive organ which forms the oocytes and sperm are among the important cells. They are used to evaluate the fertility potential of individuals. Infertility and the production of defective gametes may happen because of the failure of germ cells to survive (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Modi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2003</xref>). <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Billig <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (1996)</xref> provided evidence that cell apoptosis plays an important role in the normal functioning of tissues. A healthy person will have balanced cell apoptosis and proliferation. Furthermore, <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Billig <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (1996)</xref> underscored that gonadotrophins serve as survival factors, in both the testis and ovary. In line with this, <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Raff (1992)</xref> argued that in order for the individual to maintain a homeostatic state, the potential for cell suicide appears to be existing in most of the tissues. Death of the apoptotic cells can be diagnosed via morphological changes: membrane blebbing, disruption of the skeleton of the cell, shrinkage of cells, condensation of nuclear acids, disruption of cells into small membrane enclosed fragments known as apoptosis bodies, and phagocytosis by nearby cells to complete degradation of the cell (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Billig <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 1996</xref>). The aim of this research is to study the effects of TBTCl on the histological changes of genital organs of male and female <italic toggle="yes">Artemia salina</italic>, and to see the apoptosis marker and immune system stress on the histological tissues and compare the effects between males and females using Caspase 3 and heat shock protein 70 (HSP70). The results of this study will be important for the discussion of the fluctuation in abundance of marine species in the ecosystem, as well as the biological impacts of TBTCl on marine organisms.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materialsandmethods" id="sec2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>Dilutions of the TBTCl series&#8217; concentrations were 25, 50, 100, 200, and 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> in order to study the effects of TBTCl on gonads of <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> in acute toxicity testing. This range was determined based on previous studies (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Abushaala, 2019</xref>).</p><sec><title>Test organisms</title><p>Culturing of <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> was conducted for hatching approximately 0.5 g of cysts, in a 5 l bottle of artificial seawater having 35% &#177; 1% salinity at 28&#176;C &#177; 1&#176;C for 24 hours under standardized hatching conditions. The feeding capability of <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> was fully developed after 24 hours. Once the feeding capability was reached, food levels were established based on marine green microalgae <italic toggle="yes">Tetrasalims</italic> sp., a single cell organism dominant from the Marine Science LAB, Institute of Bioscience, University Putra Malaysia, and cultured in the Ecotoxicology Laboratory, Department of Biology, University Putra Malaysia. Then, 1 ml of commercial liquid food suspension was added per liter to aquaculture containers every day to provide other food. The inoculation with this food mixture was used for 3 days. Feed application was just enough to cloud the water so that the following application could be done when the water was clear. The application was performed at least twice daily. Identical food concentrations were fed in each growth container. During this period and for the following days, the animals were reared in the laboratory using the same apparatus and conditions. Water was continuously aerated by air stones connected to airline water pumps and the dissolved oxygen was always higher than 7.0 mg.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>. The photoperiod was put in place continuously for illumination purposes using a fluorescent light tube of 60 W. Also, precipitated material (remaining food and dead shrimps) was siphoned out. This procedure prevented ammonia from attaining higher values. After 3 days, the live food was replaced gradually with the food recommended by <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Toi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2013)</xref>. Adult <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> were transferred to new artificial seawater before the toxicity test by using the YSI Model 58 Dissolved Oxygen Meter (Yellow Springs Instrument Co. Inc., Yellow Springs, OH) in the laboratory for measurement purposes (DO 8.0 &#177; 0.5 mg.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, pH 7.5&#8211;8.0 and artificial seawater 35% &#177; 1%). Artificial seawater was prepared by mixing commercial salts with distilled water and ventilation was carried out for 24 hours to be used either for culture procedure or toxicity solution (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Toi <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2013</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Effect of TBTCl on reproductive gonads of male and female tissue staining with hematoxylin and eosin</title><p>Histological analysis of reproductive gonad tissue was carried out on 50 samples of <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> selected randomly from each group (25 male and 25 female), and were fixed with Bouin&#8217;s solution for 24 hours. After that, preparation for histological sections was made for the tissue to be cut into 5 &#956;m thickness. Finally, they were stained with hematoxylin and eosin, following <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Abushaala&#8217;s (2019)</xref> method. All the tissue sections were observed under a light microscope connected to a computer and a camera to measure the scores of gonad structure affected by TBTCl.</p></sec><sec><title>Experimental design of IHC</title><p><bold>Caspase 3 and HSP70 responses in the <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> when exposed to TBTCl</bold></p><p>The Caspase 3 and HSP70 response in the <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> exposed to different concentrations of TBTCl was investigated. In the adult stage experiments (of females and males), they were exposed to 25, 50, 100, 200, and 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> in acute toxicity test for 24 hours. In the histological experiments, <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> was put in Bouin&#8217;s solution for 24 hours preparing for the histology section. The Caspase 3 and HSP70 expressions were determined after the tissue was sectioned (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Cruz-Rodriguez and Chu, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Klepal <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Abushaala, 2019</xref>). IHC avidin&#8211;biotin complex (ABC) was used in this study following the ABC stinging system sc-2017 kit (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.). </p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The statistical analysis for histological study after observing acute toxicity effects of TBTCl on gonads of <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> using means and SE of score system assessing histological effects of TBTCl in the gonad structures of adult stages of males and females, and the scoring methods for pathological lesions were normal (0), mild (&lt;25), moderate (&lt;50), severe (&lt;75), and very severe (above 75). For IHC study, Caspase3 and HSP70 on the gonad structure of males and females using the immunostaining scores for Caspase 3 and HSP70 were normal (0), mild (&lt;5), moderate (&lt;10), and severe (up to 20), and the immunostaining was observed as brownish deposits. The statistical analysis was carrie dout using Kruskal&#8211;Wallis test (<italic toggle="yes">p </italic>&lt; 0.05), and differences were considered significant at <italic toggle="yes">p </italic>&lt; 0.05, observing the relationship between the effect of different concentrations of (TBTCl) on gonad structures in <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> males and females.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical approval</title><p>No ethical approval was needed for this research work.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Effects of TBTCl on gonadal tissues of male and female A. salina stained with hematoxylin and eosin</title><p>The result from the testis section of males (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>) shows that in the predominant lesions undifferentiated cells and degenerating testicular tissue were significantly different, and the results also showed a <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05 between the different concentrations, according to Kruskal&#8211;Wallis test. The result of female <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> gonad exposed to TBTCl is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>. The lesion scores at different concentrations were significantly different from each other at different concentrations showing undifferentiated cells in the head region, vitellogenic oocyte with degenerating yolk globules in the ooplasm, and degenerating yolk globules and follicle cells enveloping the oocyte increasing these effects in the groups exposed to the highest concentration when compared with control tissues (<xref rid="table1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). </p></sec><sec><title>Immunostaining scores of Caspase 3 antibody on gonads of male and female A. salina tissues after exposure to TBTCl</title><p>The mean immunostaining scores of Caspase 3 in adult males are shown in <xref rid="table2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The concentrations of TBTCl in this group were 0, 25, 50, 100, 200, and 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;</sup><sup>1</sup>, respectively, and the tissues stained were from the testis. Positive immunostaining was observed as brownish deposits, indicating the location of the Caspase 3 antigen&#8211;antibody reaction. There were no significant differences between the groups. In the testis of the adult male <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic>, the least immunostaining score of 8.00 &#177; 0.09 was recorded at the exposure concentration of 25 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1 </sup>of TBTCl, while the highest was obtained at the exposure concentration of 200 ng.l<sup>&#8722;</sup><sup>1 </sup>of TBTCl. However, the test recorded the lowest immune score in the male <italic toggle="yes">A. salina </italic>as compared to the gonads in females, which was higher than that in the testis. The effect of immunostaining scores of Caspase 3 on males tissue is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>. The results of immunostaining scores for female <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> to different concentrations of TBTCl is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Figure 4</xref>. Positive immunostaining was observed as brownish deposits, indicating the location of the Caspase 3 antigen&#8211;antibody reaction, and there were significant differences according to Kruskal&#8211;Wallis test, where significant <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values of &lt;0.05 between 25 and 50 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, 25 and 100 ng.l<sup>&#8722;</sup><sup>1</sup>, 25 and 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, and between 200 and 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> exposure groups were observed. The least immunostaining score (11.8 &#177; 0.29) for Caspase 3 in the gonads was obtained from an exposure concentration of 25 ng.l<sup>&#8722;</sup><sup>1</sup> of TBTCl, while the highest score of 22.0 &#177; 0.29 was obtained at the concentration of 200 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> TBTCl (<xref rid="table2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). </p><fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><title>Representative photomicrograph of a section of male testis with a normal histological structure (C: left), and on the right the histological changes are shown following 24-hours exposure to TBTCl at 100 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> concentration, which are shown as undifferentiated cells (black arrow) and degenerating testis tissue (yellow arrow) compared with the control tissue (H&amp;E, &#215;40).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-11-112-g001.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><title>Representative photomicrograph of a section of female ovary of <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> with a normal histological structure of the control showing vitellogeninoocyte (black arrow), yolk globules in the ooplasm (red arrow) (C: on the left), and on the right the histological changes are shown following 24-hours exposure to TBTCl at 100 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> concentration, which are shown as follicle cells enveloping the oocyte (black arrow) and degenerating yolk globules (red arrow) (H&amp;E, &#215;40).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-11-112-g002.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="table1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Hematoxylin and eosin mean scores on the effect TBTCl on gonad structure in adult male and female <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> (n = 5 slides).</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBTCl (ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Testis</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ovary</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20 &#177; 0.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60 &#177; 0.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40 &#177; 1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40 &#177; 1.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80 &#177; 0.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00 &#177; 0.99</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00 &#177; 0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00 &#177; 0.99</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">300</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00 &#177; 0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00 &#177; 0.99</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Scoring methods: 0: Normal; 1&#8211;5: Mild; 5&#8211;10: Moderate; and up to 10: Severe. All data are presented with &#177; SE.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Immunostaining scores of Caspase 3 antibody after the effects of TBTCl on gonad tructure of male and female <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5, five fields/slide).</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBTCl (ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Testis</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ovary</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00 &#177; 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8 &#177; 0.78</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0 &#177; 0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.4 &#177; 1.58</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2 &#177; 0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.6 &#177; 1.60</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2 &#177; 1.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0 &#177; 1.64</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">300</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.00 &#177; 1.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.4 &#177; 1.58</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Scoring methods: 0: Normal; &lt;5: Mild; &lt;10: Moderate; and up to 20: Severe. All data are presented with &#177; SE.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><title>Representative photomicrograph of a section of male testis of <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> of the control (C: on the left) showing no immunoreactivity to Caspase 3 antibody, and at 100 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> of TBTCl concentration showing mild immunoreactivity to Caspase 3 antibody (on the right). Positive immunostaining was observed as brownish deposits (H&amp;E, &#215;40).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-11-112-g003.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><title>Representative photomicrograph of a section of female ovary of <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> of the control (C: on the left) showing no immunoreactivity to Caspase 3 antibody, and at 200 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> concentration showing moderate immunoreactivity to Caspase 3 antibody, following 24-hours exposure to TBTCl (on the right) and the positive immunostaining was observed as brownish deposits (H &amp; E, &#215;40).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-11-112-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Immunostaining scores of HSP70 for male and female A. salina gonad tissues upon exposure to TBTCl</title><p>The findings of immunostaining scores of HSP70 after 24-hours exposure of males <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> to different concentrations of TBTCl is shown in <xref rid="table3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Positive immunostaining was observed as brownish deposits, indicating the location of the HSP70 antigen&#8211;antibody reaction. Significant differences were observed between 25 and 100 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, 50 and 100 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, and between 100 and 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> exposure groups. In male <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic>, the HSP70 immunostaining score was highest at 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> of TBTCl. The generality of the immunostaining score of the HSP70 in males <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> showed that the testis had the highest immunostaining scores, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>. The mean immunostaining scores of HSP70 in female <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> is shown in <xref rid="table3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>. The positive immunostaining was observed as brownish deposits, indicating the location of the HSP70 antigen&#8211;antibody reaction on the ovary. There was a significant difference between 25 and 200 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, 25 and 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, and between 50 and 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> exposure groups. The HSP70 immunostaining score for female <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> was low (20.0 &#177; 1.90) at the exposure concentration of 25 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> TBTCl and the highest immunostaining in the gonads was obtained at the exposure concentration of 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> of TBTCl.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Effects of TBTCl on gonad tissues of male and female A. salina stained with hematoxylin and eosin</title><p>The mean lesion scores post-24-hours exposure of male <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> to different concentrations of TBTCl is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>. The results showed that the predominant lesions such as undifferentiated cells and degenerating testicular tissue were significantly different, according to Kruskal&#8211;Wallis test (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) between the groups. These effects were observed to increase testicular tissues that were exposed to the highest concentration of TBTCl when compared with control tissues. <italic toggle="yes">Artemia salina</italic> female gonads exposed to different concentrations of TBTCl is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>. The lesion scores at the different concentration were significantly different from each other showing undifferentiated cells in the head region, vitellogenic oocyte with degenerating yolk globules in the ooplasm, and degenerating yolk globules and follicle cells enveloping the oocyte increasing these effects in the groups exposed to the highest concentration when compared with control tissues (<xref rid="table1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Zhang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2007)</xref> studied the effect of tributyltin and found that TBT could induce masculinization in marine invertebrates. Their study was conducted to investigate the effects of TBT in environmental marine water on the development of ovaries in females. The result reported that TBT at environmentally realistic concentrations could inhibit the ovarian development in fish. And the few previous studies reported the effect of TBT in fish and crustaceans. In the present research, the effects of TBTCl at different concentrations on the ovary in female and testis in male <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> was investigated. Analysis of the data obtained from our study has shown that TBTCl at environmentally realistic concentrations can inhibit the development of the reproductive gonad in <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> at varying degrees depending on the concentration of TBTCl. This finding is in relative agreement with previous related studies where TBTCl was reported to be highly toxic against several aquatic organisms (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">Zuo <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2014</xref>). This finding is indeed interesting because <italic toggle="yes">Artemia</italic> is commonly used to represent the biotic populations of many aquatic environments (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Ohji <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2002a</xref>) and any chemical that is found to be detrimental to <italic toggle="yes">Artemia</italic> is likely to be detrimental to several other aquatic organisms.</p><table-wrap id="table3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Immunostaining scores of HSP70 on gonad structure of tissues exposed to TBTCl of male and female <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5, five fields/slide).</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TBTCl (ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Testis</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ovary</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.40 &#177; 0.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0 &#177; 1.90</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.20 &#177; 0.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.6 &#177; 2.38</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2 &#177; 0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0 &#177; 1.89</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8 &#177; 0.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.8 &#177; 1.58</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">300</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2 &#177; 1.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.8 &#177; 2.79</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Scoring methods: 0:Normal; &lt;5: Mild; &lt;10: Moderate; and up to 20: Severe. All data are presented with &#177; SE.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><title>Representative photomicrograph of a section of male testis of <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> of the control (C: on the left) showing no immunoreactivity to HSP70 antibody, and at 100 ng.l<sup>&#8722;</sup><sup>1</sup> showing mild immunoreactivity to HSP70 antibody, following 24-hours exposure to concentrated TBTCl (on the right). Positive immunostaining was observed as brownish deposits (H &amp; E, &#215;40).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-11-112-g005.jpg"/></fig><fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><title>Representative photomicrograph of a section of female ovary of <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> showing normal immunoreactivity to HSP70 antibody in the control (C: on the left), and at 25 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> concentration showing moderate immunoreactivity to HSP70 antibody following 24-hour exposure to TBTCl (on the right). Positive immunostaining was observed as brownish deposits (H&amp;E, &#215;40).</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="OpenVetJ-11-112-g006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Immunostaining scores of Caspase 3 antibody on gonad of male and female A. salina tissues after exposure to TBTCl</title><p>Caspase 3 has been demonstrated to possess important functions in apoptosis and immune system of vertebrates. The mean immunostaining scores of Caspase 3; 24-hours after exposure of adult male <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> to different concentrations of TBTCl are shown in <xref rid="table2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The concentrations of the TBTCl in this group were 0, 25, 50, 100, 200 and 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, respectively, and the tissues stained was from the testis. Positive immunostaining was observed as brownish deposits, indicating the location of the Caspase 3 antigen&#8211;antibody reaction. There were no significant differences between the groups. In the testis of the adult male <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic>, the least immunostaining score of 8.00 &#177; 0.09 was recorded at the exposure concentration of 25 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1 </sup>of TBTCl while the highest was obtained at the exposure concentration of 200 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1 </sup>of TBTCl. However, the test has recorded the lowest immune score in the male <italic toggle="yes">A. salina </italic>as compared to the gonad in the female, which was higher than the testis. The effect of immunostaining scores of Caspase 3 on male tissue has been depicted in (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>). The results of immunostaining scores for Caspase 3 after 24 hours exposure of females <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> to different concentrations of TBTCl is shown in (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>). The positive immunostaining was observed as brownish deposits, indicating the location of the Caspase 3 antigen&#8211;antibody reaction, and there were significant differences according to Kruskal&#8211;Wallis test which showed a significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">p &lt; 0.05</italic>) between 25 and 50 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, 25 and 100 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, 25 and 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, and between 200 and 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> exposure groups. The least immunostaining score (11.8 &#177; 0.29) for Caspase 3 in the gonad was obtained from an exposure concentration of 25 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> of TBTCl, while the highest score of 22.0 &#177; 0.29 was obtained at the concentration of 200 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> of TBTCl (<xref rid="table2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Generally, the gonad of the adult female <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> had the highest immune scores as compared to the male organs. But there is less information reported on <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> ovary and testis development with respect to caspase. In the present research, the effects of different concentrations of TBTCl on <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> gonad Caspase 3 were evaluated for the first time. <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Yang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2015)</xref> studied caspase genes on molluscan, named Caspase 2 and 3, which were characterized for the first time from <italic toggle="yes">Crassostrea angulata</italic>. The analysis of their data showed that the Caspase 3 gene has an important function in the loss of velum during larva metamorphosis in <italic toggle="yes">C. angulata</italic>. In this study, Caspase 3 was found to be influenced by the different concentrations of TBTCl following 24 hours exposure of <italic toggle="yes">A. salina.</italic> The specific mechanisms through which TBTCl exposure affects <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> Caspase 3 expression need further investigation.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunostaining scores of HSP70 for male and female A. salina gonad tissues upon exposure to TBTCl</title><p>The findings of immunostaining scores of HSP70 after 24-hours exposure of male <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> to different concentrations of TBTCl is shown in <xref rid="table3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Positive immunostaining was observed as brownish deposits, indicating the location of the HSP70 antigen&#8211;antibody reaction. Significant differences were observed between 25 and 100 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, 50 and 100 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, and between 100 and 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> exposure groups. In male <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic>, HSP70 immunostaining score was highest at 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> of TBTCl. The generality of the immunostaining score of the HSP70 in male <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> showed the testis to have the highest immunostaining scores as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5">Figure 5</xref>. The mean immunostaining scores of HSP70 in female <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> is shown in <xref rid="table3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6">Figure 6</xref>. The positive immunostaining was observed as brownish deposits, indicating the location of the HSP70 antigen&#8211;antibody reaction on the ovary. There was a significant difference between 25 and 200, 25 and 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, and between 50 and 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> exposure groups. The HSP70 immunostaining score for females <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> was low (20.0 &#177; 1.90) at the exposure concentration of 25 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1 </sup>of TBTCl and the highest immunostaining in the gonads was obtained at the exposure concentration of 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> of TBTCl. <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2012)</xref> reported that <italic toggle="yes">Artemia</italic> embryos can endure extreme temperature and other wide variety of stressful environmental conditions. And the embryos can survive these stresses is highly interesting. <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2012)</xref> investigated and analyzed the nucleotide and deduced protein sequence for HSP26, a molecular chaperone specific to <italic toggle="yes">Artemia</italic> embryo development. HSP26 shares sequence similarity with sHSPs (small HSP) from other organisms. The authors (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>., 2012</xref>) observed that HSP26 plays a key role in the resistance of <italic toggle="yes">Artemia</italic> against harsh environmental conditions. Findings from the study by <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Zhou <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2010)</xref> were used to reveal the differential protein expression profiles of acute responses to copper sulfate exposure in larvae of <italic toggle="yes">Artemia sinica</italic>. Three spots were up-regulated and identified as actin, HSP70. The study indicated the involvement of all the differentially expressed proteins in the early responses of protein expression, and in the survival of <italic toggle="yes">A. sinica </italic>in the presence of copper and other heavy metals. </p><p>In this study, exposure of <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> to different concentrations of TBTCl was found to have a significant influence on HSP70 expression. An inverse relationship was found between HSP70 expression and TBTCl concentrations. This shows that exposure of <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> to TBTCl significantly influences the ability of <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> to express HSP70, which could have contributed to the mortality and histopathological changes observed in this study. <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Tanguay <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2004)</xref> studied cysts embryos of the <italic toggle="yes">Artemia</italic> sp. Which provided excellent opportunity for the study to understand how these marine organisms adapt to extremes of environmental stress. One adaptation implicated in the ecological success of <italic toggle="yes">Artemia</italic> sp. is sHSP26, a small HSP that previous evidence indicates plays the role of a molecular chaperone in the embryos. The findings found the contents of three stress proteins (HSP70, Artemin and sHSP26) presented along with data on the cysts of <italic toggle="yes">A. tibetana</italic> collected from the high plateau of Tibet.</p><p>TBTCl is one of the potentially significant sources of pollutants, in the marine environment. The results showed, according to Kruskal-Wallis test <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 a significant increase in HSP70 levels when <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> was exposed to higher concentrations 25, 50, 100, 200 and 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup>. Groups exposed to 100, 200 and 300 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1</sup> of TBTCl were found to significantly express higher levels of HSP70, with those exposed to 25, 50 ng.l<sup>&#8722;1 </sup>TBTCl expressing the highest levels of HSP70. This finding corroborates with the findings of <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Zhou <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. (2010)</xref>, who similarly reported that exposure of <italic toggle="yes">Artemia</italic> to TBTCl significantly influenced the expression of HSP70. Other related studies have similarly reported the effects of TBTCl on different species in the aquatic environment (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">Gallo and Tosti, 2015</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In the present study, the effects of TBTCl on adult gonad of<italic toggle="yes"> A. salina</italic> by using histological sections were onbserved, and IHC (Caspase 3 and HSP70) has been evaluated for the first time on <italic toggle="yes">Artemia</italic>. The testis tissue shows pathological lesions after exposure to TBTCl as undifferentiated cells and degenerating testis tissue when compare with the control tissue. In the female&#8217;s ovaries, the lesion scores at different concentrations are significantly different from each other showing undifferentiated cells of the vitellogenic oocyte with degenerating yolk globules in the ooplasm, and degenerating yolk globules and follicle cells enveloping the oocyte increasing these effects in the groups exposed to the highest concentrations when compared with control tissue. In general, histological lesion and IHC (Caspase 3 and HSP70) revealed the apoptosis and immune system stress of gonad tissue of <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> to be damaged in females which are more sensitive to TBTCl toxicity as compared to white males that have been exposed to TBTCl contaminated water. This study reconfirms the suitability of the <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> for assessing the marine aquatic toxicity profile of any toxicant with simple and reproducible results. Finally, the specific mechanisms through which TBTCl affects <italic toggle="yes">A. salina</italic> Caspase 3 and HSP70 expression need further investigation.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We are grateful to the Department of Biology, Faculty of Science, University Putra Malaysia, and to the Unit of Histology and Serology Faculty of Veterinary, University Putra Malaysia (UPM) for providing facilities and equipment for this investigation. </p></ack><sec><title>Authors&#8217; contribution</title><p>Najla Mohamed Abushaala conducted experiments, analyzed, and wrote the manuscripts. Abdulfattah Elfituri contributed to the experiences that have a relationship with the development of <italic toggle="yes">Artemia salina</italic> (Agriculture microalgae to feed <italic toggle="yes">Artemia</italic>). Syaizwan Zahmir Zulkifli supervised the project and supported it financially (by providing facilities and equipment for this investigation).</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abushaala</surname><given-names>N.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of tributyltin chloride on cell structures of epithelial layer in different stages of <italic toggle="yes">Artemia salina</italic> (Linnaeus, 1758)</article-title><source>Open Vet. J</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>366</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32042660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.4314/ovj.v9i4.15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6971362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abushaala</surname><given-names>N.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zulkifli</surname><given-names>S.Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elftturi</surname><given-names>A.M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hatchability dry cysts and morphological effects of newly hatching nauplii of <italic toggle="yes">Artemia Salina </italic>(Linnaeus, 1758) after exposed to tributyltin chloride</article-title><source>Global J. Med. Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>42</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abushaala</surname><given-names>N.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zulkifli</surname><given-names>S.Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azmai</surname><given-names>M.N.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamat-Yusuff</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selected morphological changes in nauplii of brine shrimp (<italic toggle="yes">Artemia salina</italic>) after tributyltin chloride (TBTCl) exposure</article-title><source>World Appl. Sci. J</source><year>2015</year><volume>33</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1334</fpage><lpage>1340</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abushaala</surname><given-names>N.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zulkifli</surname><given-names>S.Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azmai</surname><given-names>M.N.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamat-Yusuff</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of tributyltin chloride (TBTCl) antifouliong biocide on adult males and females of brine shrimp (<italic toggle="yes">Artemia salina</italic>)</article-title><source>Int. J. Biol. Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>35</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abushaala</surname><given-names>N.M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zulkifli</surname><given-names>S.Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azmai</surname><given-names>M.N.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohamat-Yusuff</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological effects of tributyltin chloride (TBTCl) on Juveniles Stage of Life cycle <italic toggle="yes">Artemia salina</italic></article-title><year>2018</year><comment>Available via <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="www.science.upm.edu.my/ebook-3213">www.science.upm.edu.my/ebook-3213</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alzieu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanjuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreno</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monitoring and assessement of butyltins in Atlantic coastal waters</article-title><source>Mar. Pollu. Bull</source><year>1989</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asaadi</surname><given-names>S.N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pousty</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khah</surname><given-names>D.A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Histological evaluation of the genital tract of <italic toggle="yes">Artemia parthenogenetica</italic> in Urmia Lake Area</article-title><source>European Online J. Nat. Soc. Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>91</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asem</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rastegar-Pouyani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphological differentiation of <italic toggle="yes">Artemia</italic> urmiana G&#252;nther, 1899 (Crustacea: Anostraca) in different geographical stations from the Urmia Lake-Iran</article-title><source>Res. J. Biol. Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>222</fpage><lpage>228</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Billig</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>S.-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisenhauer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsueh</surname><given-names>A.J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gonadal cell apoptosis: hormone-regulated cell demise</article-title><source>Hum. Reprod. Update</source><year>1996</year><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9079407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/humupd/2.2.103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz-Rodr&#305;guez</surname><given-names>L.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>F.-L.E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heat-shock protein (HSP70) response in the eastern oyster, <italic toggle="yes">Crassostrea virginica</italic>, exposed to PAHs sorbed to suspended artificial clay particles and to suspended field contaminated sediments</article-title><source>Aquat. Toxicol</source><year>2002</year><volume>60</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12200083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0166-445x(02)00008-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fent</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecotoxicology of organotin compounds</article-title><source>Crit. Rev. Toxicol</source><year>1996</year><volume>26</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8833456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tosti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ascidian <italic toggle="yes">Ciona intestinalis</italic> as model organism for ecotoxicological bioassays</article-title><source>J. Mar. Sci. Res. Devel</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>000e138</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinell</surname><given-names>C.E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>M.S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dam-Johansen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of self polishing antifouling paints using rotary experiments and mathematical modeling</article-title><source>Ind. Eng. Chem. Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>40</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>3906</fpage><lpage>3920</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klepal</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pflugfelder</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural cyclic degeneration by a sequence of programmed cell death modes in Semibalanus balanoides (Linnaeus, 1767) (Crustacea, Cirripedia Thoracica)</article-title><source>Zoomorph</source><year>2008</year><volume>127</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>58</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Modi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhartiya</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accelerated germ cell apoptosis in sex chromosome aneuploid fetal human gonads</article-title><source>Mol. Hum. Reprod</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12651904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1093/molehr/gag031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of tributyltin exposure in the embryonic stage on sex ratio and survival rate in the caprellid amphipod <italic toggle="yes">Caprella danilevskii</italic></article-title><source>Mar. Ecol. Prog. Seri</source><year>2002a</year><volume>235</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>176</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic effects of tributyltin on the caprellid amphipod <italic toggle="yes">Caprella danilevskii</italic></article-title><source>Mar. Pollu. Bull</source><year>2003</year><volume>46</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1263</fpage><lpage>1272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/S0025-326X(03)00169-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14550339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differences in the acute toxicities of tributyltin between the Caprellidea and the Gammaridea (Crustacea: Amphipoda)</article-title><source>Mar. Pollu. Bull</source><year>2002b</year><volume>44</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0025-326x(01)00146-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11883679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raff</surname><given-names>M.C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Social controls on cell survival and cell death</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1992</year><volume>356</volume><issue>6368</issue><fpage>397</fpage><lpage>400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1557121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/356397a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>G.W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>W.G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Preedeekanit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of biofouling adhesion and biotic disturbance on the development of fouling communities on non-toxic surfaces</article-title><source>Biofoul</source><year>1998</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1&#8211;3</issue><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>269</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanguay</surname><given-names>J.A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>R.C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clegg</surname><given-names>J.S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Habitat diversity and adaptation to environmental stress in encysted embryos of the crustacean <italic toggle="yes">Artemia</italic></article-title><source>J. Biosci</source><year>2004</year><volume>29</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15625404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/BF02712121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toi</surname><given-names>H.T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boeckx</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sorgeloos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bossier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Stappen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacteria contribute to <italic toggle="yes">Artemia</italic> nutrition in algae-limited conditions: a laboratory study</article-title><source>J.Aquacult</source><year>2013</year><volume>388</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cadmium induces hydrogen peroxide production and initiates hydrogen peroxide-dependent apoptosis in the gill of freshwater crab, Sinopotamon henanense</article-title><source>Comp. Biochem. Physiol. C Toxicol. Pharmacol</source><year>2012</year><volume>156</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22692000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.cbpc.2012.05.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>WHO</collab><article-title>International programme on chemical safety. Environmental health criteria</article-title><date-in-citation>15 July 2020</date-in-citation><comment>Available via <uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/ipcs/publications/ehc/en/">https://www.who.int/ipcs/publications/ehc/en/</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular cloning of two molluscan caspases and gene functional analysis during <italic toggle="yes">Crassostrea angulata</italic> (Fujian oyster) larval metamorphosis</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Rep</source><year>2015</year><volume>42</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>963</fpage><lpage>975</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25399080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11033-014-3833-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of tributyltin on the development of ovary in female cuvier (<italic toggle="yes">Sebastiscus marmoratus</italic>)</article-title><source>Aquat. Toxicol</source><year>2007</year><volume>83</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17512063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.aquatox.2007.03.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.-N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>W.-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>A.-L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of HSP60 and HSP70 in white shrimp, <italic toggle="yes">Litopenaeus</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">vannamei</italic> in response to bacterial challenge</article-title><source>J. Invert. Pathol</source><year>2010</year><volume>103</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>170</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jip.2009.12.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20043915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic exposure to tributyltin chloride induces pancreatic islet cell apoptosis and disrupts glucose homeostasis in male mice</article-title><source>Environ. Sci. Technol</source><year>2014</year><volume>48</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>5179</fpage><lpage>5186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24693970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1021/es404729p</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>