<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11666665</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11666665.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11666665</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11666665</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39720404</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2024.1533052</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial: Best practices in clinical research conduct in veterinary medicine</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names initials="TL">Tracy L.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/214480/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names initials="SA">Sarah A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/176223/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brainard</surname><given-names initials="BM">Benjamin M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/399049/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Clinical Sciences, Colorado State University</institution>, <addr-line>Fort Collins, CO</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>BluePearl Science</institution>, <addr-line>Tampa, FL</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Small Animal Medicine &amp; Surgery, University of Georgia</institution>, <addr-line>Athens, GA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited and reviewed by: Ali Mobasheri, University of Oulu, Finland</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Tracy L. Webb <email>tracy.webb@colostate.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">454084</issue-id><elocation-id>1533052</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>24</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-12-25 09:26:22.880"><day>25</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2024 Webb, Moore and Brainard.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Webb, Moore and Brainard</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-11-1533052.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="commentary-article" xml:lang="en" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/61059/best-practices-in-clinical-research-conduct-in-veterinary-medicine"/><kwd-group><kwd>veterinary</kwd><kwd>clinical research</kwd><kwd>consensus statement</kwd><kwd>biobanking</kwd><kwd>recruitment</kwd><kwd>informed consent</kwd><kwd>naturally occurring disease</kwd><kwd>translational research</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare financial support was received for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. TW was partially supported by NIH/NCATS Colorado CTSA Grant Number UM1 TR004399. Contents are the authors' sole responsibility and do not necessarily represent official NIH views.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="20"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="2074"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Comparative and Clinical Medicine</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>The importance of clinical research in improving health outcomes cannot be overstated. However, research design and reports must be of high quality to optimize potential benefits. Veterinary clinical researchers have a moral obligation to perform quality, impactful studies, and targeted research to define best practices in clinical research will promote continued improvement in this space. Such investigations highlight the importance of topics including enrolling a diverse patient population (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), obtaining informed consent (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), adverse event criteria (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), and reporting practices (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) leading to the generation of more clinically and translationally relevant results.</p><p>Interest in and organization around the conduct of veterinary clinical research is increasing (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) and has the potential to play a significant role in improving patient outcomes. The publication of high-quality veterinary research facilitates the use of data in translational contexts to address unmet medical needs of animals and humans. The importance of model selection and benefits of studying naturally occurring disease in target populations (as opposed to studying induced disease under artificial circumstances) is increasingly recognized (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). However, less information is currently available about best practices in veterinary clinical research conduct than what is available in human medicine. Although there is overlap in many areas of clinical research between human and veterinary medicine, there are also significant differences such as the legal status of the patient, regulatory requirements (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), and the role of humane euthanasia and financial decisions on study outcomes.</p><p>This Research Topic was initiated to encourage and support researchers performing needed investigation into the conduct of veterinary clinical research. There are many emerging impactful topics and knowledge gaps in this area such as research regulation and reporting practices, incorporation of adaptive design and artificial intelligence (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), support of multi-site and collaborative projects, equity and diversity in clinical trials, methods of assessing research impact, and sustainable research practices. Included articles investigate the impact of consensus statements, opportunities to improve veterinary biobanking, best practices in study recruitment, and new regulatory guidelines on informed client consent.</p><p>Consensus statements play a key role in medical practice. They represent the combined recommendations of experts in the field, usually when there is a lack of comprehensive evidence available on a topic, and serve to translate available research findings into clinical practice recommendations. Although consensus statements have limitations and biases that should be considered, they can significantly influence patient treatment, health policy, and societal behavior (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). The impact of consensus statements on veterinary prescribing habits in clinical practice has not been fully evaluated, and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1352496" ext-link-type="uri">Sainz et al.</ext-link> investigated the prevalence and appropriateness of omeprazole prescriptions in dogs at a veterinary teaching hospital before and after the publication of the 2018 American College of Veterinary Internal Medicine consensus statement on the rational administration of gastrointestinal protectants (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). The retrospective study compared the prescribing habits for the proton pump inhibitor omeprazole in dogs at an academic veterinary teaching hospital in the 12 months before and after the publication of the consensus statement. Although a small study, the results support the impact of the consensus statement on prescribing patterns for omeprazole in an academic veterinary hospital. Further investigation is needed to evaluate the impact of consensus statements in other practice environments and into other mechanisms to support appropriate medication prescription practices.</p><p>Sample biobanking facilitates impactful research through collection, cataloging, and storage of control and diseased biological samples allowing timely sample analysis. However, biobanking has been associated with controversy (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), and lack of best practices led to a New York Times best-selling book and movie about the generation of HeLa cells&#8212;used widely in research&#8212;without patient consent (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Veterinary biobanks support both human and veterinary clinical research, storing biological samples from animals with naturally occurring disease for future use and distribution to academic researchers and industry. However, informed consent provided by owners for pets contributing to biobanks can be complicated by limited understanding of goals, purpose, and logistics of biobanking. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1359546" ext-link-type="uri">McEnhill et al.</ext-link> performed a survey-based study to investigate pet owner perspectives, motivators, and concerns about veterinary biobanking with the goal of identifying opportunities to improve education, awareness of veterinary biobanking initiatives, and consent processes. Study results suggest veterinary biobanking initiatives are well received by owners, most of whom are willing to allow their pets to participate, and respondent concerns represent opportunities for veterinary biobanks to improve messaging and dissemination of results from work they support.</p><p>A successful clinical trial requires participants, but many factors can impede effective study recruitment. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1418747" ext-link-type="uri">Quigley et al.</ext-link> provide guidelines on best practices for recruitment of patients to veterinary clinical trials. Strategies for recruitment of high-quality subjects for clinical research should utilize a holistic view of recruitment encompassing study design and logistics, representative participation, incentives, personnel resources, advertising, and participant retention. Although human clinical trial resources can provide guidance, effort also needs to be put into evaluating current practices and opportunities for process improvement that are specific to veterinary clinical trials.</p><p>In September 2023, the United States Food and Drug Administration released a draft guidance for comment about how informed client consent for companion animal clinical trials should be obtained (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1426014" ext-link-type="uri">Frederick</ext-link> provides a review of this document, focused on the implications for those conducting veterinary clinical research. The guidance for consent timeframe, language, and specific elements will involve additional efforts by investigators to ensure adherence, yet might lead to increased owner compliance and higher enrollment in clinical studies with subsequent benefits for all.</p><p>The study of naturally occurring disease in populations of companion animals holds tremendous potential for informing the practice and progress in both veterinary and human medicine. Because data generated from these clinical trials may have an outsized impact on clinical treatments and outcomes, it is imperative that studies are conducted using the relevant, available best practice guidelines. The conversation toward the promotion of high quality veterinary clinical research is just beginning, and we hope that the manuscripts included in this Research Topic will promote further introspection that will benefit the animals, owners, researchers, and patients involved in future trials.</p></body><back><ack><p>We thank all the authors and reviewers who have contributed to this Research Topic and the Frontiers editorial team for their support.</p></ack><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>TW: Writing &#8211; original draft, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. SM: Writing &#8211; original draft, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. BB: Writing &#8211; original draft, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. The author(s) declared that they were an editorial board member of Frontiers, at the time of submission. This had no impact on the peer review process and the final decision.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s3"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelsey</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patrick-Lake</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdulai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Broedl</surname><given-names>UC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Inclusion and diversity in clinical trials: actionable steps to drive lasting change</article-title>. <source>Contemp Clin Trials.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>116</volume>:<fpage>106740</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cct.2022.106740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35364292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9133187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenna</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quigley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluating the readability of recruitment materials in veterinary clinical research</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>2125</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.16857</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37759419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10658532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><source>United States Food and Drug Administration Center for Veterinary Medicine Guidance for Industry #282 &#8220;Informed consent forms for studies that enroll client-owned companion animals&#8221;</source> (<year>2023</year>). Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.fda.gov/regulatory-information/search-fda-guidance-documents/cvm-gfi-282-informed-consent-forms-studies-enroll-client-owned-companion-animals" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.fda.gov/regulatory-information/search-fda-guidance-documents/cvm-gfi-282-informed-consent-forms-studies-enroll-client-owned-companion-animals</ext-link> (accessed November 21, 2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sobolewski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duval</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Kell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Readability of consent forms in veterinary clinical research</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>350</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.15462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30793806</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6430880</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>LeBlanc</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atherton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boudreau</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curran</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Veterinary cooperative oncology group-common terminology criteria for adverse events (VCOG-CTCAE v2) following investigational therapy in dogs and cats</article-title>. <source>Vet Comp Oncol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>311</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vco.12677</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33427378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8248125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Butcher</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monsour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mew</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayo-Wilson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Guidelines for reporting outcomes in trial reports: the CONSORT-outcomes 2022 extension</article-title>. <source>JAMA.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>328</volume>:<fpage>2252</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2022.21022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36511921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sargeant</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruple</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selmic</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Connor</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The standards of reporting trials in pets (PetSORT): explanation and elaboration</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1137781</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1137781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37065227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10103631</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCleary-Wheeler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olby</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>London</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>A</surname><given-names>CTSA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>One Health Alliance (COHA) survey of clinical trial infrastructure in North American veterinary institutions</article-title>. <source>BMC Vet Res.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>90</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12917-021-02795-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33632219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7905595</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative oncology: overcoming human cancer through companion animal studies</article-title>. <source>Exp Mol Med.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>725</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s12276-023-00977-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37009802</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10167357</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maina</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Of mice and humans: are they the same?</article-title>&#8211;implications in cancer translational research. <source>J Nucl Med.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>501</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2967/jnumed.109.065706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20237033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arzi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Athanasiou</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nolta</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rebhun</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Companion animals: translational scientist's new best friends</article-title>. <source>Sci Transl Med</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>308ps21</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.aaa9116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26446953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4806851</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beltran</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cideciyan</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewin</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwabe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sumaroka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Gene therapy rescues photoreceptor blindness in dogs and paves the way for treating human X-linked retinitis pigmentosa</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>109</volume>:<fpage>2132</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1118847109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22308428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3277562</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arzi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Volk</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Betts</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cell therapy in veterinary medicine as a proof-of-concept for human therapies: perspectives from the North American Veterinary Regenerative Medicine Association</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>779109</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.779109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34917671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8669438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>LeBlanc</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazcko</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koehler</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Creation of an NCI comparative brain tumor consortium: informing the translation of new knowledge from canine to human brain tumor patients</article-title>. <source>Neuro Oncol</source>. (<year>2016</year>) 14:pii:now051. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/neuonc/now051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27179361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4999002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertout</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baneux</surname><given-names>PJR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson-Plouch</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Recommendations for ethical review of veterinary clinical trials</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>715926</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.715926</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34395581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8355561</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lustgarten</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zehnder</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shipman</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gancher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Veterinary informatics: forging the future between veterinary medicine, human medicine, and One Health initiatives-a joint paper by the Association for Veterinary Informatics (AVI) and the CTSA One Health Alliance (COHA)</article-title>. <source>JAMIA Open.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>306</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jamiaopen/ooaa005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32734172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7382640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blazey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crossley</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ardern</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Middelkoop</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>It is time for consensus on &#8216;consensus statements'</article-title>. <source>Br J Sports Med.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>306</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjsports-2021-104578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34556467</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8899487</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kook</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Papich</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolbert</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willard</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>ACVIM consensus statement: support for rational administration of gastrointestinal protectants to dogs and cats</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1823</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.15337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30378711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6271318</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skloot</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Your Cells. Their Research. Your Permission?</article-title><source>The New York Times</source> (<year>2015</year>). Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.nytimes.com/2015/12/30/opinion/your-cells-their-research-your-permission.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nytimes.com/2015/12/30/opinion/your-cells-their-research-your-permission.html</ext-link> (accessed November 21, 2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skloot</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>The Immortal Life of Henrietta Lacks</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Crown</publisher-name> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>