<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10017982</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10017982.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10017982</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10017982</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36937700</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.1080927</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Epitopes screening and vaccine molecular design of SADS-CoV based on immunoinformatics</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="S">Shinian</given-names></name><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2068767/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yaping</given-names></name><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff><institution>College of Animal Science and Veterinary Medicine, Heilongjiang Bayi Agricultural University, Daqing</institution>, <addr-line>Heilongjiang</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Fangyu Wang, Henan Academy of Agricultural Sciences (HNAAS), China</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Basavaraj S. Mathapati, Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR), India; Ayat Tariq Zawawi, King Abdulaziz University, Saudi Arabia</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Yaping Chen <email>chenyaping0711@163.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Veterinary Infectious Diseases, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn><fn fn-type="present-address" id="fn002"><p>&#8224;Present address: Shinian Li, Shanghai Medicilon Inc., Shanghai, China</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>02</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">400313</issue-id><elocation-id>1080927</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>02</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>17</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-10-18 13:25:17.157"><day>18</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 Li and Chen.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Li and Chen</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-09-1080927.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" xml:lang="en" xlink:title="retraction" vol="10" journal-id="Front Vet Sci" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC10722178"><article-title>Retraction: Epitopes screening and vaccine molecular design of SADS-CoV based on immunoinformatics</article-title><volume>10</volume><date><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date><elocation-id>1342203</elocation-id><source>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1342203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10722178</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38105774</pub-id></related-article><abstract><p>The regional outbreak of the Swine acute diarrhea syndrome coronavirus (SADS-CoV) has seriously threatened the swine industry. There is an urgent need to discover safe and effective vaccines to contain them quickly. The coronavirus spike protein mediates virus entry into host cells, one of the most important antigenic determinants and a potential vaccine target. Therefore, this study aims to conduct a predictive analysis of the epitope of S protein B cells and T cells (MHC class I and class II) by immunoinformatics methods by screening and identifying protective antigenic epitopes that induce major neutralized antibodies and activate immune responses to construct epitope vaccines. The study explored primary, secondary, and tertiary structures, disulfide bonds, protein docking, immune response simulation, and seamless cloning of epitope vaccines. The results show that the spike protein dominant epitope of the screening has a high conservativeness and coverage of IFN-&#947;, IL-4-positive Th epitope, and CTL epitope. The constructed epitope vaccine interacts stably with TLR-3 receptors, and the immune response simulation shows good immunogenicity, which could effectively activate humoral and cellular immunity. After codon optimization, it was highly likely to be efficiently and stably expressed in the <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> K12 expression system. Therefore, the constructed epitope vaccine will provide a new theoretical basis for the design of SADS-CoV antiviral drugs and related research on coronaviruses such as SARS-CoV-2.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Swine acute diarrhea syndrome coronavirus (SADS CoV)</kwd><kwd>spike protein</kwd><kwd>immunoinformatics</kwd><kwd>epitope vaccines</kwd><kwd>antigen epitope</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>This research was supported by the Heilongjiang Postdoctoral Fund (LBH-Z21074).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="11"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="47"/><page-count count="13"/><word-count count="6663"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Swine acute diarrhea syndrome (SADS) is a highly contagious, acute, and fatal respiratory and gastrointestinal infectious disease of pigs caused by Swine acute diarrhea syndrome coronavirus (SADS-CoV) (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). The first outbreak occurred in Qingyuan district, Guangdong Province, China, in 2017, causing severe economic losses to the pig industry in the region (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). The clinical symptoms of diseased pigs were similar to those of other porcine intestinal coronaviruses, and the clinical manifestations were mild diarrhea in infected sows (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Infected newborn piglets within 5 days of age suffer from acute diarrhea and vomiting, resulting in acute death, and the mortality rate can be as high as 90% (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Given is that SADS-CoV was a newly emerged coronavirus in pigs in China, the current understanding and research on SADS-CoV were still shallow. No commercial vaccine was available, bringing challenges to its prevention and control. Therefore, the effect of its antigen characteristics and antigen variation on the host protective immune response needs further clarification.</p><p>Viral antigens, including S protein, have multiple epitopes that have immunoprotective effects and induce the neutralization of antibodies (such as antibodies that inhibit virus replication), effector T cells that inhibit or kill infected cells and assist immune balance response (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). However, the immune response induced by most epitopes does not have the function of neutralizing or inhibiting virus replication (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). On the contrary, it might induce an imbalance of cellular immune response and aggravate inflammatory response, with negative risks such as immunopathological damage and antibody-dependent enhancement (ADE), It might even attenuate the immune protective effect of immunoprotective epitopes (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Immunoinformatics is used to predict antigenic epitopes' characteristics from the gene sequence source, screen the results, and analyze and identify the dominant epitopes with immune protection (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). It could effectively improve protective antibody affinity and cellular immune balance, triggering the immune system to develop immunity to viruses. Therefore, dominant viral epitopes are ideal candidates for vaccine construction (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p><p>The total length of the SADS-CoV genome is about 27.17 kb, encoding four major structural proteins, including spike protein (S), nucleocapsid protein (N), membrane protein (M), and small membrane protein (E) (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Among them, the S protein of SADS-CoV and other coronavirus is a key target for vaccine and antiviral drug development (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Vaccines of S protein could induce the body to produce neutralizing antibodies among all structural proteins located on the surface of virions, cell attachment, receptor-bound, interspecies transmission, mediated viral invasion, and infection. It was the main antigen component responsible for induced host immune response and protected immunity against viral infection (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Therefore, the full-length trimeric S protein usually has high immunogenicity; however, vaccines with full-length S proteins could also induce harmful immune responses that lead to liver damage in vaccinated animals or aggravated infection after homologous virus infection (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). To avoid toxic side effects and enhance the immune effect of the vaccine, in this study, based on immunoinformatics, we screened, identified, and constructed epitope vaccines for the dominant protective epitopes of SADS-CoV S protein and used molecular docking analysis, immune simulation prediction and <italic toggle="yes">silico</italic> clone of epitope vaccine. The purpose was to provide a new method for the design of the SADS-CoV epitope vaccine and a theoretical basis and data support for developing the SADS-CoV epitope vaccine.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>2. Materials and methods</title><p>The workflow summarizing the procedures for the epitope-based candidate vaccine prediction is shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Descriptive workflow for the epitope-based candidate vaccine prediction.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1080927-g0001.jpg"/></fig><sec><title>2.1. Determination of candidate vaccine strains of SADS-CoV</title><p>From the NCBI (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein</ext-link>) database, we collected 31 amino acid sequences of SADS-CoV S protein in fasta file format and used this as a template. The MEGA 7.0 software was used to analyze the sequence conservation, and then the WebLogo server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://weblogo.berkeley.edu/logo.cgi" ext-link-type="uri">http://weblogo.berkeley.edu/logo.cgi</ext-link>) was used to visualize the obtained comparative data set.</p></sec><sec><title>2.2. Prediction and screening of epitopes</title><p>The PEPTIDES (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://imed.med.ucm.es/Tools/antigenic.pl" ext-link-type="uri">http://imed.med.ucm.es/Tools/antigenic.pl</ext-link>) and ABCpred server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://webs.iiitd.edu.in/raghava/abcpred/index.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://webs.iiitd.edu.in/raghava/abcpred/index.html</ext-link>) were used to predict candidate linear B lymphocyte epitopes of the SDS-CoV S protein. The former antigenic peptides are determined used the method of Kolaskar and Tongaonkar. Predictions are based on a table that reflects the occurrence of amino acid residues in experimentally known segmental epitopes. Segments are only reported if the have a minimum size of 8 residues. The reported accuracy of method is about 75%, the latter ABCpred is a recursive neural network based learned algorithm with a default threshold of 0.51 and a tableau length of 16, and its accuracy is 65.93% (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). The NetMHCIIpan-4.0 server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://services.healthtech.dtu.dk/service.php?NetMHCIIpan-4.0" ext-link-type="uri">https://services.healthtech.dtu.dk/service.php?NetMHCIIpan-4.0</ext-link>) was used to predict MHC-II epitopes to select different alleles. The NetMHCIIpan-4.0 server uses the artificial neural network (ANN) to predict the binding of peptides to any MHC II molecule of known sequence. Under the default threshold, different alleles are used to screen, and finally the strong binding sequence with a percentage greater than 10% is selected (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Helper T cell Th1 activates macrophages by releasing (interferon &#947;, IFN-&#947;), recognizes and clears intracellular pathogens; helper T cell Th2 mainly secretes cytokines (interleukin 4, IL-4), which can promote antigen presentation Cell proliferation and differentiation play a key role in various biological activities. Therefore, The combination potential of epitope and MHC-II was realized through the EpiTOP server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.ddg-pharmfac.net/epitop/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.ddg-pharmfac.net/epitop/</ext-link>) evaluation. IFN-&#947; inducible antigen and non-IL-4 inducible antigen epitopes pass through the IFNepitope server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://crdd.osdd.net/raghava/ifnepitope/" ext-link-type="uri">http://crdd.osdd.net/raghava/ifnepitope/</ext-link>) and IL4pred server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://crdd.osdd.net/raghava/il4pred/" ext-link-type="uri">http://crdd.osdd.net/raghava/il4pred/</ext-link>) forecast (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). MHC-I combined CTL epitope prediction by NetMHCpan4.1 server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://services.healthtech.dtu.dk/service.php?NetMHCpan-4.1" ext-link-type="uri">https://services.healthtech.dtu.dk/service.php?NetMHCpan-4.1</ext-link>) and IEDB server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.iedb.org/mhci/" ext-link-type="uri">http://tools.iedb.org/mhci/</ext-link>). The screened method of NetMHCpan4.1 server was the same as that of NetMHCIIpan-4.0 server. The IEDB server uses a consensus recommendation method consisted of ANN, SMM and CombLib, Select different alleles at other default thresholds with lengths of 15 (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). All predicted epitopes were determined by the IEDB server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.iedb.org/immunogenicity/" ext-link-type="uri">http://tools.iedb.org/immunogenicity/</ext-link>). An immunogenicity test was carried out, which is non-toxic, through the ToxinPred server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://webs.iiitd.edu.in/raghava/toxinpred/design.php" ext-link-type="uri">https://webs.iiitd.edu.in/raghava/toxinpred/design.php</ext-link>). Epitopes with immunogenicity score &gt;0.1 and non-toxic were selected as the final prediction (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). At the same time, Pymol software was used to mark the spatial position of each dominant epitope in the tertiary structure of S the (PDB ID:6M39) protein.</p></sec><sec><title>2.3. Identification of protective epitopes and evaluation of antigenic epitope conservation</title><p>To further select the dominant epitope regions for analysis by compared B cell epitopes, Th epitopes and CTL epitopes generated by the server, and the best fragment with high overlap was found. Dominant epitopes were then assessed by the conservation analysis tool on the IEDB server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.iedb.org/conservancy/" ext-link-type="uri">http://tools.iedb.org/conservancy/</ext-link>), According to the determined candidate epitopes and 31 different SADS-CoV S protein sequences, the conservation of antigen epitopes was analyzed (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>2.4. Construction of candidate vaccines and prediction of antigenicity, sensitization, solubility, and physicochemical properties</title><p>Vaccine amino acid sequences were constructed used the above selected CTL, HTL and B lymphocyte dominant epitopes, with the different dominant epitopes linked in tandem using flexible linkers. CTL epitope used GGPPG, HTL epitope used AAY, and B lymphocyte epitope used KK. In order to improve the immunogenicity of candidate vaccines, &#946;- Defensin I, as an immune enhancer, is connected to the N-terminal of the construct through EAAAK linkers (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Through the ANTIGENpro server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://scratch.proteomics.ics.uci.edu/" ext-link-type="uri">http://scratch.proteomics.ics.uci.edu/</ext-link>) and VaxiJen v2.0 server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.ddg-pharmfac.net/vaxijen/VaxiJen/VaxiJen.html" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.ddg-pharmfac.net/vaxijen/VaxiJen/VaxiJen.html</ext-link>) for the final built antigenicity analysis of candidate vaccines (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>); AllerTOPv2.0 server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.ddg-pharmfac.net/AllerTOP" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.ddg-pharmfac.net/AllerTOP</ext-link>), for the final built allergenicity analysis of candidate vaccines (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>); SOLpro server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://scratch.proteomics.ics.uci.edu/explanation.html#SOLpro" ext-link-type="uri">http://scratch.proteomics.ics.uci.edu/explanation.html#SOLpro</ext-link>) for the final built solubility analysis of candidate vaccines (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). In addition, the final candidate vaccine should also pay attention to its physical and chemical properties. Therefore, used the ExPASy Server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://web.expasy.org/protparam/" ext-link-type="uri">https://web.expasy.org/protparam/</ext-link>) for the physicochemical properties of the candidate vaccine were analyzed (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>2.5. Candidate vaccine secondary and tertiary structure modeling, refining, and disulfide engineering</title><p>Candidate vaccine used the PSIPRED4.0 server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://bioinf.cs.ucl.ac.uk/psipred" ext-link-type="uri">http://bioinf.cs.ucl.ac.uk/psipred</ext-link>) and SOPMA server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://npsa-prabi.ibcp.fr/cgi-bin/npsa_automat.pl?page=npsa_sopma.html" ext-link-type="uri">http://npsa-prabi.ibcp.fr/cgi-bin/npsa_automat.pl?page=npsa_sopma.html</ext-link>) completes the prediction of the secondary structure of the final candidate vaccine (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). The trRosetta server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://yanglab.nankai.edu.cn/trRosetta/" ext-link-type="uri">https://yanglab.nankai.edu.cn/trRosetta/</ext-link>) completes the prediction of the tertiary structure of the final candidate vaccine (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). At the same time, used the Galaxy-WEB server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://galaxy.seoklab.org/cgi-bin/submit.cgi?type=REFINE" ext-link-type="uri">https://galaxy.seoklab.org/cgi-bin/submit.cgi?type=REFINE</ext-link>) the quality of the model was improved, and the coarse structure in the model was optimized in this process (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). For this purpose the EBI-PDBSum server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/thornton-srv/databases/pdbsum/Generate.html" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/thornton-srv/databases/pdbsum/Generate.html</ext-link>) a Ramachandran diagram was generated to evaluate the quality of the model before and after optimization (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Before proceeding to the next step, it was necessary to improve the stability of the candidate vaccine model. Therefore, used the DisulfidebyDesign2.0 server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://cptweb.cpt.wayne.edu/DbD2/index.php" ext-link-type="uri">http://cptweb.cpt.wayne.edu/DbD2/index.php</ext-link>) performs disulfide engineered on candidate vaccines (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). After that used the ProSA-web server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://prosa.services.came.sbg.ac.at/prosa.php" ext-link-type="uri">https://prosa.services.came.sbg.ac.at/prosa.php</ext-link>) was used to perform global detection on the model (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>2.6. Tertiary epitope prediction and protein docking analysis</title><p>ElliPro server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tools.iedb.org/ellipro/" ext-link-type="uri">http://tools.iedb.org/ellipro/</ext-link>) conformational B-cell epitopes for prediction of vaccine protein tertiary structure (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Meanwhile, protein interactions are important for understanding cell function and tissue structure. Molecular docking was a method to predict the interaction between a receptor and a ligand in a stable conformation. Therefore, used the PyDockWEB server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://life.bsc.es/pid/pydockweb" ext-link-type="uri">https://life.bsc.es/pid/pydockweb</ext-link>) for the interaction between TLR3 (PDB ID: 2A0Z) as receptor and protein vaccine as ligand is predicted (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). LigPLot+ was used to determine the amino acid residues with hydrogen bonds and hydrophobic interactions after docking.</p></sec><sec><title>2.7. Immune simulation, codon optimization, and silico cloning</title><p>Immunoresponse analysis of the final constructed candidate vaccine by the C-ImmSim server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://150.146.2.1/C-IMMSIM/index.php" ext-link-type="uri">https://150.146.2.1/C-IMMSIM/index.php</ext-link>) was performed to evaluate the immunogenicity characteristics of the candidate vaccine (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). The immunization process was conducted every 7 days, 3 times in total, and the time steps were set as 1, 20, and 40 (each time step was 8 h), where default remained simulation parameters. Back translation of the candidate vaccine's amino acid sequence was conducted on the Gene infinity server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.geneinfinity.org/sms/sms_backtranslation.html" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.geneinfinity.org/sms/sms_backtranslation.html</ext-link>) (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). The Codon Adaptation Index (<italic toggle="yes">CAI</italic>) and GC content of optimized DNA were assessed by the GenScript server (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.genscript.com/tools/rare-codon-analysis" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.genscript.com/tools/rare-codon-analysis</ext-link>) (Genscript Biotech Corporation, China). Finally, the candidate vaccine sequence was inserted into the pET-30a (+) vector by the SnapGene tool.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>3. Result</title><sec><title>3.1. Conservative analysis of SADS-CoV S protein and determination of vaccine strain</title><p>The amino acid sequences of 31 SADS-CoV S proteins downloaded from the NCBI database were analyzed by MEGA 7.0 software. Finally, the relatively conserved SDS-COV S protein (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="ASK51717.1">ASK51717.1</ext-link>) was selected as the template for cell epitope prediction. WebLogo server visualized proteins' full-length amino acid sequence on the comparative data set obtained by MEGA 7.0 software. Protein conservation is shown (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>), indicating that the C-terminal amino acid mutation of the S protein is obvious. The N-terminal amino acid sequence is relatively conserved.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Results of SADS CoV full length S protein conservation analysis.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1080927-g0002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.2. Screening of S protein dominant epitopes of SADS-CoV</title><p>The overlapping epitope regions of B lymphocyte epitopes screened by PEPTIDES server and ABCpred server are shown (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The epitopes screened by NetMHC II panv4.0 EL server, and then, overlapped epitopes were evaluated by the EpiTOP server for binding potential, further obtaining IFN-&#947; and non-IL-4 inducible antigen epitopes. The Th epitopes of MHC class II molecules are shown (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). NetMHCpan4.1 server and IEDB server screened overlapping regions of CTL binding epitopes, CTL epitopes are shown (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). In the epitope screening strategy of this study. To make the results reliable and more confident, all predicted dominant epitopes were tested for immunogenicity by IEDB server and its non-toxicity was confirmed by ToxinPred server. The confirmed dominant epitopes are presented in the table by Percent of protein sequence and Minimum identity conservation analysis. The spatial positions of the dominant epitopes are shown (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Candidate B cell epitopes.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919497"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Name</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sequences</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Length</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Start position</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>End position</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Toxin prediction</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Percent of protein sequence &#8806;100%/%</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Minimum identity/%</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NAFECLIN</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">non-toxin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00% (31/31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WYNDLVRIVFPPTV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">171</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">non-toxin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.77% (30/31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.86%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DFQHLIL</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">316</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">322</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">non-toxin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.77% (30/31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.71%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VNRTIVTPYLKPYECF</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">357</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">372</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">non-toxin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00% (31/31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GDGFCADL</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">531</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">538</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">non-toxin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00% (31/31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIEDLLFS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">675</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">682</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">non-toxin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00% (31/31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTPGLCES</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">931</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">938</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">non-toxin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00% (31/31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TFANVIAVSR</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">975</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">984</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">non-toxin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00% (31/31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p> Candidate Th cell epitopes.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919497"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Name</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sequences</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Allele</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Start position</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>IFN-&#947;</bold><break/>
<bold>inducer</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>IL-4 inducer</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Percent of protein sequence &#8806;100%/%</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Minimum identity/%</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Th-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FNTIFSTH RGLSNTT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRB1_1302; DRB1_0801<break/> DRB1_1301; DRB1_1601</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inducer</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00% (31/31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Th-2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KLRLFDIP PGVYSNS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HLA-DQA10102-DQB10501<break/> HLA-DPA1*02: 01<break/> DPB1*14: 01<break/> HLA-DPA10401-DPB10901</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inducer</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.77% (30/31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.33%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Th-3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VPGFVLRV GRGKAVN</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRB5_0101</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">347</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inducer</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.77% (30/31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.33%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Th-4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NNTITVK TTPGLCES</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DRB1_1501</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">924</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inducer</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00% (31/31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Th-5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NMRVEVE KFQRYVNY</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HLA-DPA10202-DPB10402<break/> HLA-DPA10301-DPB10401<break/> HLA-DPA10103-DPB10401<break/> HLA-DPA10201-DPB10101<break/> HLA-DPA10103-DPB10201</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,052</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inducer</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.55% (29/31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.33%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p> Candidate CTL cell epitopes.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919497"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Name</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sequences</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Allele</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Start position</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Immunogenicity</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Toxin prediction</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Percent of protein sequence 100%/%</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Minimum identity/%</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTL-1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SVDFNLFNTIFSTH</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SLA-1-YDL01</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3763</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">non-toxin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00% (31/31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTL-2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TNLTWELWIHRKWG</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SLA-1-HB02</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7108</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">non-toxin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00% (31/31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTL-3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PVTNERYTEMPLDH</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SLA-6*0104</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">559</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1079</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">non-toxin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00% (31/31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTL-4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IPELNSTFPIEEEF</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SLA-1*0201<break/> SLA-1*1301</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">997</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3618</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">non-toxin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.55% (29/31)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.86%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Epitopes of SADS-CoV Spike protein candidate antigen. Tertiary structure of the spike protein with CTL epitopes marked by red color; HTL epitopes are marked by blue color and IFN-&#947; epitopes marked by green color; showing their surface positions.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1080927-g0003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.3. Construction of SADS-CoV S candidate vaccine</title><p>Based on the dominant epitopes obtained from the immunoinformatics analysis, a flexible linker tandem candidate vaccine was used to prolong the time of protein action <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>,Effectively avoid the introduction of new bound epitopes. Defensin I plays a role as an immunopotentiator through the N-terminal EAAAK linker, promoting a lasting immune response. AAY and GPGPG linkers enhance the recognition of vaccine subunits and KK connectors to enhance the folding, stability, and expression of proteins. Therefore, the constructed vaccine amino acid sequence was as follows: GIINTLQKYYCRVRGGRCAVLSCLPKEEQIGKCSTRGRKCCRRKKEAAAKFNTIFSTHRGLSNTTAAYKLRLFDIPPGVYSNSAAYVPGFVLRVGRGKAVNAAYNNTITVKTTPGLCESAAYNMRVEVEKFQRYVNYGPGPGSVDFNLFNTIFSTHGPGPGTNLTWELWIHRKWGGPGPGPVTNERYTEMPLDHGPGPGIPELNSTFPIEEEFKKNAFECLINKKWYNDLVRIVFPPTVKKDFQHLILKKVNRTIVTPYLKPYECFKKGDGFCADLKKAIEDLLFSKKTTPGLCESKKTFANVIAVSR. The epitope vaccine kit is shown (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>SADS-CoV multi-epitope vaccine kit.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1080927-g0004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.4. Antigenicity, sensitization, solubility, and physicochemical properties analysis of candidate vaccine</title><p>ANTIGENpro server and Vaxijenv2.0 server predicted the antigenicity index of candidate vaccine to be 0.892070 and 0.4974, respectively. And the results were far greater than the default threshold of the server, indicating that the constructed vaccine had good antigenicity. In the AllerTOP V2.0 server prediction of vaccine sensitization, the candidate vaccine was found to be non-allergenic. The SOLpro server predicted a solubility probability of 0.924097 at overexpression, much higher than the server's default threshold of 0.5, indicating a high solubility. ExpasyProtparam server forecast results show that: the number of amino acids of candidate vaccine is 308 aa, molecular weight 34.49 ku, theoretical pI 9.61, the estimated half-life was: 30 h (mammalian reticulocytes, <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>), &gt;20 h (yeast, <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>) and &gt; 10 hours (<italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli, in vivo</italic>). The instability index (II) is computed as 26.43, The instability index (II) was computed to be 72.79, with a grand average of hydropathicity (GRAVY)&#8722;0.390. So the server classifies it as a stable hydrophilic protein. The aliphatic chains in the globular protein structure represent the protein's thermal stability. The elevated aliphatic index indicates that the protein is heat-stable.</p></sec><sec><title>3.5. Candidate vaccine secondary structure prediction</title><p>The prediction results of the PSIPRED and SOPMA servers on the secondary structure show that: In the secondary structure of candidate vaccine, the alpha helix is 29.87%, the Extended strand is 22.40%, the Beta turn is 8.12%, and the random coil is 39.61%. The Secondary structure prediction is shown (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F5" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Secondary structure prediction of SADS-CoV epitopes-based vaccine. Different colors indicate the corresponding information of the secondary structure of the protein.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1080927-g0005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.6. Modeling, elaboration, and evaluation of candidate vaccine tertiary structure</title><p>The results of the best model for the tertiary structure of candidate vaccines predicted by the 3Dpro server are shown (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6F</xref>). The results are shown in <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figures 6A&#8211;E</xref>, that is section visualizes predicted 2D information including: Contact map, which displays the predicted probability of residue pairs being in contact, i.e., the distance between their C-beta (C-alpha for Glycine) atoms is less than 8&#197;. Distance map displays the predicted real distance (4&#8211;20 &#197;) between residue pairs. Orientation maps contains maps of omega (&#8722;180&#176;, 180&#176;), theta (&#8722;180&#176;, 180&#176;) and phi (0&#176;, 180&#176;). The PROCHECK server generates a Ramachandran diagram (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7A</xref>). In the rough model, residues in the most favored regions are 90.3%, 8.5% in the additional allowed regions, 0.8% in generously allowed regions, and 0.4% in the disallowed regions. The Galaxy-Refine server was used to refine the crude model structure in the server-generated five refined models. The parameters of the crude model before refining are GDT-HA (1.0000); RMSD (0.000); MolProbity (1.268); Clash score (3.6); Poorrotamers (00.0); and Rama favored (97.4). After refining, it was confirmed that the first model was the best candidate. The parameters of the model were GDT-HA (0.9440), RMSD (0.430), MolProbity (1.233), Clash score (4.6), Poorrotamers (0.8), and Rama favored (98.7). PROCHECK server generates a Ramachandran diagram (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7C</xref>). In the refining model, residues in the most favored regions are 94.2%, 5.4% in the additional allowed regions, 0.0% in the generously allowed regions, and 0.4% in the disallowed regions. For this purpose, Pymol software was used to plot the comparison results, as shown in <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7B</xref>. To stabilize the protein structure, this study further used the disulfide engineered disulfide by Design 2.0 server to generate disulfide-stabilized proteins. The prediction results show that the B-factor was 0. It was considered that the tertiary structure model of the candidate vaccine after refining was stable enough, and it was not necessary to draw further disulfide bond mutants. Finally, the ProSA web server scored and verified the refined model. The structural accuracy analysis showed that the z value is &#8722;3.33 (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7D</xref>), and the known-based energy is mostly negative (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7E</xref>). The results suggested that the refined model accuracy could meet the requirements for further analysis.</p><fig position="float" id="F6" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Modeling of epitope vaccine tertiary structure. <bold>(A&#8211;E)</bold> Omega, Phi, Distance, Theta and Contact parameters of 2D structures; <bold>(F)</bold> Tertiary structure of candidate vaccine, Red: &#946;-Defensin I molecular adjuvant; Yellow: CTL epitopes; Purple: Th epitopes; Green: B cell epitopes; TM-score: 0. 376.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1080927-g0006.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F7" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Validation of tertiary structure of epitope vaccine. <bold>(A)</bold> Ramachandran plots to validate the tertiary structure; <bold>(B)</bold> For comparison of tertiary protein structure, the crude model and refined model are green and red, respectively; <bold>(C)</bold> The Ramachandran mapping validates the optimized tertiary structure; <bold>(D)</bold> The Z fraction of the ProSA SEB diagram of the refined model is &#8722;3.34; <bold>(E)</bold> The quality of the local model is shown by plotting the energy as a function of the position of the amino acid sequence.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1080927-g0007.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.7. Tertiary structure epitope prediction and protein docking</title><p>The ElliPro server predicted five B-cell linear epitopes based on the refined tertiary structure model of epitope vaccines: 110&#8211;152, 225&#8211;272, 44&#8211;89, 194&#8211;208, and 172&#8211;180, the corresponding scores are: 0.744, 0.735, 0.714, 0.696, and 0.617. 7 B-cell conception epitopes, started from the following locations: 48&#8211;73, 138&#8211;149~151&#8211;152~155&#8211;167, 193&#8211;201, 173~175&#8211;180~233&#8211;272, 74&#8211;86~109&#8211;137, 202&#8211;206, and 226&#8211;232, the corresponding scores are: 0.768, 0.762, 0.751, 0.74, 0.718, 0.637, and 0.629. All scores were above the set threshold of 0.5, confirming that the designed candidate vaccine had good immunogenicity. PyDockWEB server performs protein + protein rigid docking of vaccine ligands and TLR3 receptors. According to the docking result, 101 models were produced, with model name 196 ranking first among all the predicted models from PyDockWEB. The docking result is shown in <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8A</xref>. The prominent hydrogen bond amino acid residue was locally magnified. The results are shown in <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figures 8B</xref>, <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">C</xref>. LigPLot+ was used to determine the two-dimensional interaction diagram, and the results are shown in <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8D</xref>. Candidate vaccine ligands and TLR3 receptors had amino acid residues with hydrogen bonds, respectively: Ala405, His460, Ser372, and Ser315. The amino acid residues with hydrophobic interactions are respectively: Thr623, Phe314, Trp429, His312, Asp347, Thr376, Asn373, Asp348, His432, Phe349, Gln352, His316, Trp353, His319, Asp292, Trp296, Lys272, Ala295, Glu456, Asn291, and Asn265.</p><fig position="float" id="F8" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Complexes of candidate vaccine protein docking with human TLR3 receptor. <bold>(A)</bold> Epitope vaccine structure is shown in blue and TLR3 in green; <bold>(B)</bold> Residue of interaction between docking TLR3 and epitope vaccine; <bold>(C)</bold> Local magnification highlights amino acid residues; <bold>(D)</bold> LigPLot+ determined two-dimensional interaction diagram.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1080927-g0008.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.8. Computer simulation of immune response stimulation</title><p>C-ImmSim server simulates the candidate vaccine immune response, and the simulation generates significantly higher secondary and tertiary responses than the primary response. Secondary and tertiary reactions show decreased antigen concentrations and increased levels of immunoglobulin activity (IgG1+IgG2, IgM, and IgG+IgM antibodies). In addition, various persistent B cell homotypes were found, while the concentration of adjuvant (TH) and cytokines is also increasing. TH (helper cell) and TC (cytotoxic) cell populations showed similarly higher responses to TC preactivation during vaccination, NK (Natural Killing) and dendritic cell activity were found to be consistent with higher macrophage activity, and high levels of IFN-&#947; and IL-2 were also triggered in the simulation. Overall, the entire simulated immune response stimulation conforms to the law of inducing an immune response, has good immunogenicity, and can effectively activate humoral and cellular immunity, and the result is shown in <xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">Figures 9</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="F11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F9" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>B cell and Th counts shown <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> immune simulation. <bold>(A)</bold> B lymphocytes, total count, memory cells, and sub-divided in isotypes IgM, IgG1 and IgG2; <bold>(B)</bold> Plasma B lymphocytes count sub-divided per isotype (IgM, IgG1 and IgG2); <bold>(C)</bold> B lymphocytes population per entity-state (i.e, showing counts for active, presenting on class-II, internalized the Ag, duplicating and anergic; <bold>(D)</bold> CD4 T-helper lymphocytes count. The plot shows total and memory counts; <bold>(E)</bold> CD4 T-helper lymphocytes count sub-divided per entity-state (i.e., acctive, resting, anergic and duplicating); <bold>(F)</bold> CD4 T-regulatory lymphocytes count. Both total, memory and per entity-state counts are plotted here. Act, active; Intern, internalized the Ag; Pres II, presenting on MHC II; Dup, in the mitotic cycle; Anergic, anergic; Resting, not active.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1080927-g0009.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F10" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>CTL, NK, MA, DC, EP cell counts shown <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> immune simulation. <bold>(A)</bold> CD8 T-cytotoxic lymphocytes count, Total and memory shown; <bold>(B)</bold> CD8 T-cytotoxic lymphocytes count per entity-state; <bold>(C)</bold> Natural Killer cells (total count); <bold>(D)</bold> Epithelial cells, Total count broken down to acgive, virus-infected and presenting on class-I MHC molecule; <bold>(E)</bold> Macrophages. Total count, internalized, presenting on MHC class-II, active and resting macrophages; <bold>(F)</bold> Dendritic cells, DC can present antigenic peptides on both MHC class-I and class-II molecules, The curves show the total number broken down to active, resting, internalized and presenting the ag; Act, active; Intern, internalized the Ag; Pres II, presenting on MHC II; Dup, in the mitotic cycle; Anergic, anergic; Resting, not active.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1080927-g0010.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F11" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>Immunoglobulin and immune complex; Change trend of cytokines and interleukins. <bold>(A)</bold> Antigen and immunoglobulins, Antibodies are sub-divided per isotype (&#946;-Defensin I molecular adjuvant including); <bold>(B)</bold> Antigen and immunoglobulins. Antibodies are sub-divided per isotype (&#946;-Defensin I molecular adjuvant not including); <bold>(C)</bold> Concentration of cytokines and interleukins. Inset plot shows danger signal together with leukocyte growthfactor IL-2.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1080927-g0011.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.9. Computer simulation clones of candidate vaccines</title><p>The Gene infinity server conducted back translation of the vaccine construct. GenScript Tool was used for evaluating the gene sequence's key properties, including the Codon Adaptation Index (<italic toggle="yes">CAI</italic>) and GC content. The optimized nucleotide sequence <italic toggle="yes">CAI</italic> value was 1, and the GC content of the optimized sequence was 54.19% in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>. Recognition sites for <italic toggle="yes">BamHI</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">XhoI</italic> restriction enzymes were added to the optimized gene's 5' and 3' ends. The adapted codon sequence was inserted into the pET32a (+) vector using SnapGene software.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>4. Discussion</title><p>Coronavirus had long been considered trivial pathogens, but the recent discovery of a new CoV strain officially named SARS-CoV-2 had sparked a deadly global COVID-19 pandemic (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). As the fourth recently discovered porcine enteric coronavirus, SADS-CoV of the same genus has successively hit several intensive pig farms and brought severe challenges to the prevention and control of swine diseases (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). The results of the metagenomic sequence of the SADS-CoV outbreak in 2019 showed that it had mutated and become more virulent, suggesting that early control and prevention of the epidemic had become necessary (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). However, although the current research results have made some progress in the origin, pathogenicity, diagnostic methods, and detection technologies of viruses, there are still many unsolved problems. For example, there was no report on the research progress of reliable drugs and vaccine preparation for this bat-derived coronavirus. Vaccination has always been an effective measure to prevent and control infectious diseases (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Therefore, in order to prevent the continuous spread of SADS-CoV, there was an urgent need for effective vaccines. Immunoinformatics approaches have helped researchers predict and analyze potential epitopes needed to develop epitope vaccine candidates and screen the viral genome to identify immunogenic epitopes that elicit highly targeted immune responses without reversing the virus pathogenesis (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>).</p><p>Based on this strategy, and to avoid excess antigen load and allergic reactions in the host, this study aims to design an candidate vaccine against SADS-CoV S protein so that the constructed candidate vaccine can generate humoral and cell-mediated immunity, thereby achieving immune balance. In addition to induced neutralized antibodies, the vaccine's protective effect also depends on cytotoxic CD8 T and helper CD4 T cells to eliminate the virus. One of the important features of immune response was the activation of helper T cell subtypes and releasing corresponding specific types of cytokines (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). The antigen epitope on MHC-II could activate Th1 and Th2 helper cells, and Th1 can release interference &#947; (IFN-&#947;), activate macrophages, and recognize and remove pathogens in cells. Helper T cells, Th2 mainly secrete cytokine interleukin 4 (IL-4), which could promote the proliferation and differentiation of antigen-presenting cells (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). MHC-I restricted the transmission of pathogens by secreting unique antiviral cytokines and recognized and destroyed infected cells through the affinity between &#8220;antigenic peptide MHC&#8221; complexes, combined with proteasome processing and transporter associated with antigen processing (TAP) transport (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Memory B cells can respond rapidly to recurred antigenic challenges and have more adaptive antibodies to prevent reinfection while contributing to immunity against homologous or heterologous viral infections (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). Therefore, ideal antigens should be presented by multiple MHC-I and MHC-II alleles and contain linear B cell epitopes related to neutralized antibodies (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). In order to enable animals to quickly cause immune response when they are attacked by SADS CoV again, and provide strong and lasting immune protection for them. The server recognizes the above epitope, but it was worth noting that the Th-5 epitope under the tertiary structure or the epitope is hidden and cannot be displayed. Fortunately, all epitopes are connected in a certain sequence through a flexible linker and introduced into &#946;-defensin I construct epitope vaccine. The corresponding concept has also been used in the research and development of SARS CoV-2 candidate vaccine. From the selected dominant epitope regions, they are randomly distributed on the full length S protein without major concentration regions, which is consistent with previous research results (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). The selected flexible linkers also better avoid the generation of toxic side effects and improve the immune effect of the vaccine. The C-ImmSim server analysis showed that the candidate vaccine has good humoral and cellular immunity and the highest production of IFN-&#947; with a large amount of IL-10 and IL-2 activities. Excessive active immunoglobulins, IgM, IgG, and their possible involvement in isotype switch were also noted. Finally, the multi-epitope vaccine was codon-optimized, the <italic toggle="yes">CAI</italic> value was 1.0, and the GC content (54.19%) was also within the optimal limit, which indicated that the vaccine might be highly expressed in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> K-12 system. SnapGene was used to clone into <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> vector ensures that the candidate vaccine can be accurately translated and stably expressed in the prokaryotic expression vector pET-32a(+). In this study, a series of immunoinformatics tools were used to construct an effective vaccine against SADS-CoV, the candidate vaccine structure has been created. The interaction and binding mode between the receptor and the vaccine protein are stable and can produce immune response to SADS CoV. But experimental verification is still needed to evaluate the immunogenicity and safety of the designed and constructed candidate vaccine. Therefore, this study will next perform high-throughput cloning of the constructed candidate vaccine, express and purify the recombinant protein, immunize animals, and perform an immunological evaluation to ensure the true potential of the designed epitope vaccine against SADS-CoV.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>5. Conclusions</title><p>This study successfully predicted and screened the dominant epitope of SADS-CoV S protein using the immunoinformatics method and constructed an candidate vaccine composed of CTL epitope, Th epitope, and linear B cell epitope that could trigger a strong immune response. This project will provide a new theoretical basis for designing SADS-CoV antiviral drugs and research on coronaviruses such as SARS-CoV-2.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/supplementary material, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s7"><title>Author contributions</title><p>SL and YC came up with and designed the study. SL performed the experiments and wrote the manuscript. YC revised the manuscript. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s9"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Swine acute diarrhea syndrome coronavirus-induced apoptosis is caspase- and cyclophilin D- dependent</article-title>. <source>Emerg Microbes Infect.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>439</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/22221751.2020.1722758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32090691</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7054944</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Retrospective detection and phylogenetic analysis of swine acute diarrhoea syndrome coronavirus in pigs in southern China</article-title>. <source>Transbound Emerg Dis.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>687</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tbed.13008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30171801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7168530</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Re-emergence of severe acute diarrhea syndrome coronavirus (SADS-CoV) in Guangxi, China, 2021</article-title>. <source>J Infect</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>85</volume>:<fpage>e130</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>e133</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2022.08.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36002051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9393104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vlasova</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenney</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saif</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Emerging and re-emerging coronaviruses in pigs</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Virol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>49</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coviro.2018.12.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30654269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7102852</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheatley</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeKosky</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antibody-dependent enhancement and SARS-CoV-2 vaccines and therapies</article-title>. <source>Nat Microbiol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1185</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41564-020-00789-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32908214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12103240</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arvin</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cathcart</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spreafico</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Havenar-Daughton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A perspective on potential antibody-dependent enhancement of SARS-CoV-2</article-title>. <source>Nature.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>584</volume>:<fpage>353</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2538-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32659783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karthik</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Senthilkumar</surname><given-names>TMA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Udhayavel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raj</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Role of antibody-dependent enhancement (ADE) in the virulence of SARS-CoV-2 and its mitigation strategies for the development of vaccines and immunotherapies to counter COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Hum Vaccin Immunother.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>3055</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21645515.2020.1796425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32845733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7484565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Groot</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moise</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Terry</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hindocha</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Better epitope discovery, precision immune engineering, and accelerated vaccine design using immunoinformatics tools</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>442</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2020.00442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32318055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7154102</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parmar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Designing multi-epitope based peptide vaccine targeting spike protein SARS-CoV-2 B1.1.529 (Omicron) variant using computational approaches</article-title>. <source>Struct Chem</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>2243</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11224-022-02027-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36160688</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9485025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Swine enteric alphacoronavirus (swine acute diarrhea syndrome coronavirus): an update three years after its discovery</article-title>. <source>Virus Res.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>285</volume>:<fpage>198024</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2020.198024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32482591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7229464</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sternberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naujokat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Structural features of coronavirus SARS-CoV-2 spike protein: targets for vaccination</article-title>. <source>Life Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>257</volume>:<fpage>118056</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lfs.2020.118056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32645344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7336130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The spike protein of SARS-CoV&#8211;a target for vaccine and therapeutic development</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>226</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro2090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19198616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2750777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Golob</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lugogo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lauring</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lok</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>SARS-CoV-2 vaccines: a triumph of science and collaboration</article-title>. <source>JCI Insight.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e149187</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/jci.insight.149187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33822773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8262277</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchan</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minneci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nugent</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Scalable web services for the PSIPRED protein analysis workbench</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>W349</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>57</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23748958</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3692098</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raghava</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prediction of continuous B-cell epitopes in an antigen using recurrent neural network</article-title>. <source>Proteins.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>40</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/prot.21078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16894596</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynisson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>NetMHCpan-4.1 and NetMHCIIpan-4.0: improved predictions of MHC antigen presentation by concurrent motif deconvolution and integration of MS MHC eluted ligand data</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>W449</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>W454</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkaa379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32406916</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7319546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dimitrov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garnev</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flower</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doytchinova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>EpiTOP&#8211;a proteochemometric tool for MHC class II binding prediction</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>2066</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20576624</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhanda</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vir</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raghava</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prediction of IL4 inducing peptides</article-title>. <source>Clin Dev Immunol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>2013</volume>:<fpage>263952</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/263952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24489573</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3893860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhanda</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vir</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raghava</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Designing of interferon-gamma inducing MHC class-II binders</article-title>. <source>Biol Direct.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>30</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1745-6150-8-30</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24304645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4235049</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andreatta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Gapped sequence alignment using artificial neural networks: application to the MHC class I system</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>511</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26515819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6402319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapoor</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhary</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gautam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Consortium</surname><given-names>OSDD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>In silico approach for predicting toxicity of peptides and proteins</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e73957</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0073957</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24058508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3772798</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bui</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sidney</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fusseder</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sette</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Development of an epitope conservancy analysis tool to facilitate the design of epitope-based diagnostics and vaccines</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>361</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-8-361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17897458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2233646</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qamar</surname><given-names>MTU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahid</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aslam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashfaq</surname><given-names>UA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aslam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fatima</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Reverse vaccinology assisted designing of multiepitope-based subunit vaccine against SARS-CoV-2</article-title>. <source>Infect Dis Poverty.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>132</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40249-020-00752-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32938504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7492789</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sweredoski</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>SCRATCH: a protein structure and structural feature prediction server</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>W72</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gki396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15980571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1160157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doytchinova</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flower</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>VaxiJen: a server for prediction of protective antigens, tumour antigens and subunit vaccines</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-8-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17207271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1780059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dimitrov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bangov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flower</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doytchinova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>AllerTOP v2&#8211;a server for in silico prediction of allergens</article-title>. <source>J Mol Model.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>2278</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00894-014-2278-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24878803</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Magnan</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>SOLpro: accurate sequence-based prediction of protein solubility</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>2200</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19549632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gasteiger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gattiker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoogland</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanyi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Appel</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bairoch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>ExPASy: The proteomics server for in-depth protein knowledge and analysis</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>3784</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkg563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824418</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC168970</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Geourjon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Del&#233;age</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>SOPMA: significant improvements in protein secondary structure prediction by consensus prediction from multiple alignments</article-title>. <source>Comput Appl Biosci.</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>681</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/11.6.681</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8808585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anishchenko</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ovchinnikov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Improved protein structure prediction using predicted interresidue orientations</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>117</volume>:<fpage>1496</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>503</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1914677117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31896580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6983395</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seok</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Galaxyrefine: protein structure refinement driven by side-chain repacking</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>W384</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23737448</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3692086</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laskowski</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>PDBsum: summaries and analyses of PDB structures</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/29.1.221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11125097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC29784</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dombkowski</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Disulfide by Design 2.0: a web-based tool for disulfide engineering in proteins</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>346</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-14-346</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24289175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3898251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lovell</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>IW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arendall</surname><given-names>WB</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Bakker</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Word</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prisant</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Structure validation by Calpha geometry: phi,psi and Cbeta deviation</article-title>. <source>Proteins.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>437</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/prot.10286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12557186</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Location of 'continuous' antigenic determinants in the protruding regions of proteins</article-title>. <source>EMBO J.</source> (<year>1986</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>409</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/j.1460-2075.1986.tb04226.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2423325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1166746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jim&#233;nez-Garc&#237;a</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pons</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#225;ndez-Recio</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>pyDockWEB: a web server for rigid-body protein-protein docking using electrostatics and desolvation scoring</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>1698</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23661696</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rapin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernaschi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castiglione</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Computational immunology meets bioinformatics: the use of prediction tools for molecular binding in the simulation of the immune system</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e9862</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0009862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20419125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2855701</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Badel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Da Cunha</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catchpole</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forterre</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oberto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>WASPS: web-assisted symbolic plasmid synteny server</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>1629</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btz745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31589313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7703779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farzan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanisms of SARS-CoV-2 entry into cells</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41580-021-00418-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34611326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8491763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>QN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>ZX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The re-emerging of SADS-CoV infection in pig herds in Southern China</article-title>. <source>Transbound Emerg Dis.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>2180</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tbed.13270</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31207129</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7168562</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Isolation and characterization of a highly pathogenic strain of Porcine enteric alphacoronavirus causing watery diarrhoea and high mortality in newborn piglets</article-title>. <source>Transbound Emerg Dis.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>119</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tbed.12992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30103259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7168553</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jasny</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petsch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>New vaccine technologies to combat outbreak situations</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1963</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2018.01963</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30283434</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6156540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramana</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehla</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Immunoinformatics and epitope prediction</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>2131</volume>:<fpage>155</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-0716-0389-5_6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32162252</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Skwarczynski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toth</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Peptide-based synthetic vaccines</article-title>. <source>Chem Sci.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>842</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>54</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5SC03892H</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28791117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5529997</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayerhofer</surname><given-names>PU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamp&#233;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antigen translocation machineries in adaptive immunity and viral immune evasion</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>427</volume>:<fpage>1102</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2014.09.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25224907</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bacchetta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gregori</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roncarolo</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>CD4+ regulatory T cells: mechanisms of induction and effector function</article-title>. <source>Autoimmun Rev.</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>491</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.autrev.2005.04.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16214084</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd Albagi</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Nour</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elhag</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tageldein Idris Abdelihalim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Musa Haroun</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adam Essa</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A multiple peptides vaccine against COVID-19 designed from the nucleocapsid phosphoprotein (N) and Spike Glycoprotein (S) via the immunoinformatics approach</article-title>. <source>Inf Med Unlocked.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>100476</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.imu.2020.100476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33200089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7654333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>