<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10687458</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10687458.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10687458</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10687458</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38033638</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1256903</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay on growth performance, rumen microbiota, and untargeted metabolomics of meat in lambs</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="H">Hanning</given-names></name><xref rid="fn0001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1613673/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names initials="L">Lingbo</given-names></name><xref rid="fn0001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2361619/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mi</surname><given-names initials="L">Lan</given-names></name><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/541250/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff><institution>State Key Laboratory of Reproductive Regulation and Breeding of Grassland Livestock, Key Laboratory of Forage and Endemic Crop Biotechnology, Ministry of Education, School of Life Sciences, Inner Mongolia University</institution>, <addr-line>Hohhot</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn id="fn0002" fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Wen-Chao Liu, Guangdong Ocean University, China</p></fn><fn id="fn0003" fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Maghsoud Besharati, University of Tabriz, Iran; Yushan Jia, Inner Mongolia Agricultural University, China</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Lan Mi, <email>lanmi_90@126.com</email></corresp><fn id="fn0001" fn-type="equal"><p><sup>&#8224;</sup>These authors have contributed equally to this work and share first authorship</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">427755</issue-id><elocation-id>1256903</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-08-30 17:25:17.620"><day>30</day><month>08</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 Wang, Meng and Mi.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wang, Meng and Mi</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-10-1256903.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="sec1"><title>Objective</title><p>The objective of this study was to compare the effects of <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay as the roughage on the rumen bacterial and the meat metabolomics in lambs.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Methods</title><p>Fourteen male lambs were randomly assigned to two dietary treatments (one group was fed with concentrate and <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay; another was fed with concentrate and alfalfa hay) with seven replicates per treatment. The feeding experiment lasted for 60&#8201;days. Lambs were slaughtered at the end of the feeding experiment. Growth performance, carcass performance, and weights of various viscera were determined. The longissimus dorsi and rumen contents were collected for untargeted metabolomics and 16S rDNA amplicon sequencing analysis, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Results</title><p>The lambs fed with alfalfa hay showed a significantly increased in average daily gain, carcass weight, dressing percentage, loin-eye area, and kidney weight. Feeding <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay diets resulted in different meat metabolite deposition and rumen bacterial communities in the lambs. The relative abundance of phyla <italic toggle="yes">Fibrobacteres</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Spirochaetes</italic> were greater in the <italic toggle="yes">Leymus Chinensis</italic> hay group, while, the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Proteobacteria</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Fusobacteria</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Verrucomicrobia</italic> were greater in the alfalfa hay group. Based on untargeted metabolomics, the main altered metabolic pathways included alanine, aspartate and glutamate metabolism, D-glutamine and D-glutamate metabolism, phenylalanine metabolism, nitrogen metabolism, and tyrosine metabolism. Several bacteria genera including <italic toggle="yes">BF31</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Alistipes</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Faecalibacterium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Eggerthella</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Anaeroplasma</italic> were significantly correlated with growth performance and meat metabolites.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Alfalfa hay improved growth performance and carcass characteristics in lambs. <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay caused different meat metabolite deposition by modifying the rumen bacterial community. These findings will be beneficial to future forage utilization for sheep growth, carcass performance, and meat quality improvement.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>alfalfa hay</kwd><kwd>growth performance</kwd><kwd>lamb</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay</kwd><kwd>metabolomics</kwd><kwd>rumen bacteria</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn1">Inner Mongolia Autonomous Region Department of Science and Technology</funding-source><award-id award-type="contract" rid="cn1">zdzx2018016</award-id><award-id award-type="contract" rid="cn1">zdzx2018065</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn2">Inner Mongolia Autonomous Region of China</funding-source><award-id award-type="contract" rid="cn2">12000-12102621</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare financial support was received for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This work was supported by the Inner Mongolia Autonomous Region Department of Science and Technology (zdzx2018016 and zdzx2018065), and the Grassland talent innovative team of Inner Mongolia Autonomous Region of China (12000-12102621).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="8"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="51"/><page-count count="14"/><word-count count="7996"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Animal Nutrition and Metabolism</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec5"><label>1.</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Mutton is one of the most widely consumed meats around the world due to its high protein and low cholesterol (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). With the growing requirement for high-quality meat, meat quality has induced more and more attention. Improving animal diets is one of the most effective ways to ameliorate animal growth performance, carcass traits, and meat quality (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Roughage is a necessary nutrient source for ruminants. In particular, types and quality of forage are key factors affecting ruminant productivity, carcass composition, rumen microbiota, and quality of meat nutrition such as amino acids, fatty acids, and mineral elements (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>).</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic>, a perennial species of Gramineae, is widely distributed in the Eurasian Steppe including the eastern Inner Mongolian Plateau and the Songnen Plain in China (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> has been one of the main forages due to its high yield, appropriate nutritional values, and palatability (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). It has been reported that adding <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay in the diet to replace part of the corn silage and alfalfa hay facilitated the improvement of milk yield, milk fat and protein yield, and milk fat concentration (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Enhancing the ratio of <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> silage decreased dry matter and neutral detergent fiber degradability but promoted crude protein degradability in the combinations of <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> silage and corn silage in beef cattle (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Moreover, the <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay diet increased the C15:0 fatty acid contents in lamb meat compared to the mixed forage diet (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). As the average daily gain (ADG) of ewes was higher in the <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay treatment group, <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay was of better quality for ewes than <italic toggle="yes">Vigna radiata</italic> stalk (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p><p>Alfalfa hay is famous for its high quality and widely used as an important dietary roughage for ruminants. Feeding with alfalfa hay increased the growth performance in lambs, such as the ADG, compared with wheat straw diets (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Feeding lactating ewes with alfalfa hay promoted milk production compared with the wheat straw diets (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). A forage diet mixture of alfalfa hay and maize stover in a ratio of 60:40 optimized the growth and carcass traits of lambs (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Additionally, alfalfa hay as an ingredient to supplement the low-energy diet increased omega-3 fatty acids and lowered the omega-6: omega-3 ratio in lamb meat (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), indicating that alfalfa affects the meat metabolites and nutritional quality.</p><p>The rumen is a complex ecosystem containing functional microbiota responsible for the rumen fermentation and an important part in producing nutrient substances and calories in ruminants (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). The ruminal bacteria community is closely correlated with diets (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Interestingly, altering the diet has a cascading effect on the rumen microbiota, which affects animal growth performance and meat quality (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Previous reports have revealed that various forages have a great effect on rumen and fecal microbiota composition (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). For example, lambs fed with alfalfa had a higher relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Akkermansia</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Asteroleplasma</italic> than the mix of purple prairie clover and alfalfa treatment group (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). The alfalfa hay diet elevated the proportion of <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Selenomonas</italic> compared with the cornstalk diet, while cornstalk feeding increased the proportion of <italic toggle="yes">Thermoactimoyces</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Papillibacter</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Anaerotruncus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Streptomyces</italic> compared with the <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay or alfalfa hay feeding in dairy cows (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). It has also been revealed associations between the rumen bacterial community with metabolite deposition. For instance, <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidales_UCG-001_norank</italic> was negatively related to fatty acids including C18:2 and C20:4 in the longissimus dorsi (LD) of sheep (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Amino acids including isoleucine and glycine were positively correlated with <italic toggle="yes">Anaeroplasma</italic> and negatively associated with <italic toggle="yes">Parabacteroides</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Alloprevotella</italic> (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Moryella</italic> was positively associated with fatty acids such as C16:0 and C18:1n9c, and negatively related to C20:4 n6, C20:3 n6, and C20:5 in lamb lumborum muscle (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Moryella</italic> also exhibited a positive relationship with meat metabolites including L-carnosine, N-acetyl-L-histidine, and negatively related to N-acetylaspartylglutamate, L-carnitine, L-citrulline, and Pro-Glu (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Therefore, it is important to characterize the relationship between rumen bacteria and meat metabolites.</p><p>To our knowledge, the comparison of growth performance, carcass characteristics, and meat metabolites of sheep fed with <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay remains poorly defined. The alterations in the rumen bacterial community and interactions between bacteria and metabolites are also lacking. The lack of in-depth evaluation may affect the application of forages in ruminant farming. Therefore, this study focused on investigating the effects of <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay on growth and carcass traits, meat metabolite deposition, and rumen bacterial community in lambs. This study will facilitate assessing growth and carcass performance, and meat quality of sheep fed with forages different forage types, and provide an important reference for improving ruminant growth and carcass performance through manipulating diets in the future.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec6"><label>2.</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec7"><label>2.1.</label><title>Animals and experimental design</title><p>The animal protocol in this study was approved by the Animal Care and Use Committee of Inner Mongolia University (Approval No. IMU-sheep-2020-041).</p><p>Healthy male East Friesian&#8201;&#215;&#8201;Small-tail Han lambs were purchased from Inner Mongolia Lark Biotechnology Co., Ltd. Fourteen lambs with an average age of 60&#8201;days and with body weight of about 22.03&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.08&#8201;kg were selected. The feeding trials were conducted at the Inner Mongolia University Meat Sheep Nutritional Base, where each lamb was housed individually in the same pens. Fourteen lambs were randomly allocated to two dietary treatment groups: one group was feed with concentrate and <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay (Lc group); another was fed with concentrate and alfalfa (<italic toggle="yes">Medicago sativa</italic>) hay (Ms group) with free access to water. The Lc group consumed about 325&#8201;g of concentrate and 803&#8201;g of (<italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay each sheep per day, while the Ms group consumed about 325&#8201;g of concentrate and 925&#8201;g of alfalfa hay each sheep per day. Ingredient and chemical compositions of diets are shown in <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>. Before the experiment, lambs were acclimatized to the environment for about 1&#8201;week. The experiment lasted for 60&#8201;days. At the end of the experiment, lambs were selected for slaughter after fasting for about 12&#8201;h, and the LD and rumen contents samples were collected. Muscle samples were collected using a disposable scalpel at the same location in the LD of each lamb into 50&#8201;mL RNAase-free centrifuge tubes and stored at &#8722;80&#176;C for metabolite analysis. After the rumen was opened, the rumen contents were filtered using 4 layers of sterile gauze, and the rumen contents were collected in a 50&#8201;mL RNAase-free centrifuge tube and stored at &#8722;80&#176;C for 16S rDNA amplicon analysis.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><label>2.2.</label><title>Chemical analysis of roughage (<italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay)</title><p>Dry matter and crushed ash of <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay samples were determined according to Ran et al. (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Crude protein, acid detergent fiber, neutral detergent fiber, and crude fat in the <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay samples were determined using an Automatic Kjeldahl Protein/Nitrogen Analyzer (K1160, Hanon Advanced Technology Group, China), Automatic Fiber Analyser (F2000, Hanon Advanced Technology Group, China) and Automatic Soxhlet Extractor (SOX606, Hanon Advanced Technology Group, China) respectively with reference to Shi et al. (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). The content of mineral elements was determined with using microwave (REVO, LabTech, China) and inductively coupled plasma-optical emission spectrometer (PQ 9000, analytikjena, German) (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><label>2.3.</label><title>Determination of growth and carcass performance and organ index</title><p>Body weight and carcass weight were measured following overnight fasting and evisceration, respectively. Loin-eye area between the 12th and 13th ribs was traced on sulphate papers and calculated (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Dressing percentage&#8201;=&#8201;carcass weight/body weight. Organ index&#8201;=&#8201;organ weight/body weight (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Total weight&#8201;=&#8201;final body weight (FBW)&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;initial body weight (IBW). Average daily gain (ADG)&#8201;=&#8201;total weight gain/total days. Feed to gain ratio (F/G)&#8201;=&#8201;average daily feed intake (ADFI)/ADG.</p></sec><sec id="sec10"><label>2.4.</label><title>16S rDNA amplicon sequencing and bioinformatics analysis</title><p>The rumen contents were collected and stored at &#8722;80&#176;C. Microbial DNA was extracted using a TIANGEN kit. The V3&#8211;V4 region of the bacterial 16S rDNA gene was amplified by PCR (95&#176;C for 3&#8201;min, followed by 30&#8201;cycles at 95&#176;C for 30&#8201;s, 50&#176;C for 30&#8201;s, 72&#176;C for 45&#8201;s, and an extension at 72&#176;C for 10&#8201;min) using the F3 (ACTCCTACGGGAGGCAGCAG) and R4 (GGACTACHVGGGTWTCTAAT) primer pair (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). DNA Library Prep Kit for Illumina following manufacturer&#8217;s recommendations and index codes were added. High throughput sequencing was performed utilizing the Illumina MiSeq PE300 platform to detect the 16S rDNA amplicons according to standard protocols.</p><p>After sequencing, paired-end reads from sequencing were merged by FLASH, and low-quality reads were filtered by Trimmomatic. UPARSE was used to align operational taxonomic units (OTUs) at 97% identity. Taxonomy was assigned to OTUs by searching against the Greengenes database version 13.8. &#945;- and &#946;- diversities were calculated using QIIME2. The biomarkers with statistical differences were screened by Linear discriminant Effect Size (LEfSe) analysis, and the screening criteria were LDA threshold &#8805;4.0 and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt;0.05. The redundancy analysis (RDA) and Spearman&#8217;s rank correlation analysis were performed using the R packages: vegan and pheatmap, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="sec11"><label>2.5.</label><title>Untargeted metabolomics and bioinformatics analysis</title><p>Untargeted metabolomics analysis was referenced to the previous method (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Briefly, 200&#8201;mg LD samples were mixed with 2-chlorophenylalanine (4&#8201;ppm) methanol (&#8722;20&#176;C) and ground by a high-throughput tissue grinder for 90&#8201;s at 60&#8201;Hz. The samples were centrifuged at 4&#176;C for 10&#8201;min at 12,000&#8201;rpm, and the supernatant was filtered through 0.22&#8201;&#956;m membrane to obtain the prepared samples for LC-MS. Twenty microlitre from each sample were taken to the quality control samples, and the rest of the samples were used for LC-MS detection.</p><p>LC-MS detection was referenced against the previous method (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Chromatographic separation was accomplished in a Thermo Ultimate 3000 system equipped with an ACQUITY UPLC<sup>&#174;</sup> HSS T3 column maintained at 40&#176;C. The temperature of the autosampler was 8&#176;C. Gradient elution of analytes was carried out with 0.1% formic acid in water (C) and 0.1% formic acid in acetonitrile (D) or 5&#8201;mM ammonium formate in water (A) and acetonitrile (B) at a flow rate of 0.25&#8201;mL/min. Injection of 2&#8201;&#956;L of each sample was performed after equilibration. An increasing linear gradient of solvent B (v/v) was used as follows: 0&#8211;1&#8201;min, 2% B/D; 1&#8211;9&#8201;min, 2%&#8211;50% B/D; 9&#8211;12&#8201;min, 50%&#8211;98% B/D; 12&#8211;13.5&#8201;min, 98% B/D; 13.5&#8211;14&#8201;min, 98% B/D; 14&#8211;20&#8201;min, 2% D-positive model (14&#8211;17&#8201;min, 2% B-negative model) (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>).</p><p>The ESI-MSn experiments were executed on the Thermo Q Exactive Focus mass spectrometer with the spray voltage of 3.8&#8201;kV and &#8722;2.5&#8201;kV in positive and negative modes, respectively. Sheath gas and auxiliary gas were set at 30 and 10 arbitrary units, respectively. The capillary column temperature was 325&#176;C. The analyzer scanned over a mass range of <italic toggle="yes">m</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">z</italic> 81&#8211;1,000 for a full scan at a mass resolution of 70,000. Data-dependent acquisition (DDA) MS/MS experiments were performed with an HCD scan. The normalized collision energy was 30&#8201;eV. Raw data were converted to the mzXML format by Proteowizard (v3.0.8789), and then processed by the MetaboAnalystR package (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec12"><label>2.6.</label><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>GraphPad Prism was used for statistical analysis. The results of growth performance, carcass performance, and organ index are presented as means&#8201;&#177;&#8201;standard error (SE). All data were considered statistically significant at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05. Statistical significance of organ index, growth and carcass performance, and metabolites were determined by <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test. The statistical significance of &#945;-diversity was performed with Wilcoxon tests.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec13"><label>3.</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec14"><label>3.1.</label><title>Improvement of growth and carcass traits in lambs fed a diet with alfalfa hay</title><p>To investigate the effects of <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay on growth and carcass performance, we first compared IBW, FBW, ADG, carcass weight, and loin-eye area between the two groups. IBW was not significantly distinct, while total weight gain, FBW, and ADG were significantly greater in the Ms. group. Carcass weight, dressing percentage, and loin-eye area were also obviously increased in the Ms. group. However, lambs in the Ms. group had higher ADFI. The F/G was similar between the two groups (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In addition, we analyzed the organ index in lambs. Kidney index was increased in the Ms. group, while others including spleen, lung, liver, and heart index were not significantly affected (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). These data indicated that compared to <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay, alfalfa hay improved growth and carcass traits in lambs.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay on growth and carcass performance of sheep (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;7).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Items</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lc group<xref rid="tfn6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>f</sup></xref> (average&#8201;&#177;&#8201;SE)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms group<xref rid="tfn7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>g</sup></xref> (average&#8201;&#177;&#8201;SE)</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value<xref rid="tfn8" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>h</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IBW<xref rid="tfn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref> (kg)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.63 &#177; 1.58</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.43 &#177; 1.60</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.727</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FBW<xref rid="tfn2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref> (kg)</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.71 &#177; 1.38</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.67 &#177; 1.76</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>*</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADG<xref rid="tfn3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref> (kg)</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 &#177; 0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20 &#177; 0.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>**</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADFI<xref rid="tfn4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref> (kg)</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 &#177; 0.04</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32 &#177; 0.07</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>*</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F/G<xref rid="tfn5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.71 &#177; 4.19</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.66 &#177; 2.46</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.639</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carcass weight (kg)</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.29 &#177; 0.70</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.60 &#177; 1.18</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>*</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dressing percentage, %</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.21 &#177; 0.76</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.69 &#177; 0.58</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0005</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>***</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Loin-eye area (cm<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.39&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.03</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.25&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.35</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>*</sup>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn1"><label>a</label><p>IBW, Initial body weight.</p></fn><fn id="tfn2"><label>b</label><p>FBW, Final body weight.</p></fn><fn id="tfn3"><label>c</label><p>ADG, Average daily gain.</p></fn><fn id="tfn4"><label>d</label><p>ADFI, Average daily feed intake.</p></fn><fn id="tfn5"><label>e</label><p>F/G, Feed to gain ratio.</p></fn><fn id="tfn6"><label>f</label><p>Lc group indicates lambs fed with <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay.</p></fn><fn id="tfn7"><label>g</label><p>Ms group indicates lambs fed with alfalfa hay.</p></fn><fn id="tfn8"><label>h</label><p><sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;0.05, <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;0.01, <sup>***</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;0.001, NS indicates no significant differences.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay on organ index (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;7).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Items</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lc group<xref rid="tfn9" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref> (average&#8201;&#177;&#8201;SE)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms group<xref rid="tfn10" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref> (average&#8201;&#177;&#8201;SE)</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value<xref rid="tfn11" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spleen index, %</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 &#177; 0.01</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 &#177; 0.01</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.538</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung index, %</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 &#177; 0.04</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 &#177; 0.03</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver index, %</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47 &#177; 0.06</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63 &#177; 0.07</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.114</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kidney index, %</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 &#177; 0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 &#177; 0.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>**</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart index, %</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 &#177; 0.02</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43 &#177; 0.02</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.270</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn9"><label>a</label><p>Lc group indicates lambs fed with <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay.</p></fn><fn id="tfn10"><label>b</label><p>Ms group indicates lambs fed with alfalfa hay.</p></fn><fn id="tfn11"><label>c</label><p><sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;0.05, <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;0.01, NS indicates no significant differences.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec15"><label>3.2.</label><title>Alterations of rumen bacterial diversity and composition between two groups</title><p>To investigate the effects of <italic toggle="yes">Lemus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay on rumen microbiota, we performed and analyzed bacterial 16S rDNA sequencing of rumen contents between two groups. The observed OTU and Shannon curves reached the saturation phase, suggesting the sufficient and reliable sequence depth captured in this study (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>). A total of 2,140 OTUs were identified in both groups, among which 3,491 and 3,861 specific OTUs were observed in the Lc and Ms. groups, respectively (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). Shannon and Simpson indexes reflected the bacterial community richness and diversity. No significant differences were observed in the Shannon and Simpson index between the two groups (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref>). The &#946;-diversity presenting as Principal Co-ordinates Analysis (PCoA), Non-metric multidimensional scaling (NMDS), Principal Components Analysis (PCA), and Partial Least Squares Discrimination Analysis (PLS-DA) was further applied to analyze the variation of bacterial structure. The NMDS, PCA, and PLS-DA are in <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>. The Lc group rumen contents (LcRc) formed a different rumen bacterial community clustered separately from the Ms group rumen contents (MsRc) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1D</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The diversity of the rumen microbiota of lambs fed a diet with <italic toggle="yes">Lemus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay. <bold>(A)</bold> Observed OTUs and Shannon curves of rumen microbiota. <bold>(B)</bold> The Venn diagram illustrates the overlap of microbial OTUs between the two groups. <bold>(C)</bold> The &#945;-diversity includes Shannon and Simpson index. <bold>(D)</bold> The &#946;-diversity presents as PCoA. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;7 in each group. LcRc and MsRc indicate rumen contents from lambs fed with <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1256903-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>To further define the composition of rumen microbiota in the LcRc and MsRc, the percentages of bacterial community abundance were analyzed at phylum and genus levels. At the phylum level, <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Spirochaetes</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Fibrobacteres</italic> were the dominant phyla (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). The relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Fibrobacteres</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Spirochaetes</italic> were obviously greater in the Lc group (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S2</xref>); the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Actinobacteria</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Fusobacteria</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Verrucomicrobia</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Proteobacteria</italic> were obviously greater in the MsRc (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). At the genus level, the top 20 genera were present with relatively high abundance (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>). The 17 genera significantly altered between two groups, among which only 5 genera, i.e., <italic toggle="yes">Clostridiu</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Fibrobacter</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Selenomonas</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">BF311</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Treponema</italic>, were greater in the LcRc. Most of the altered bacteria in the MsRc, including <italic toggle="yes">Moryella</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Blautia</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">p_75_a5</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Faecalibacterium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Mogibacteriaceae</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Anaerostipes</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Eggerthella</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">and Collinsella</italic> belong to <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Actinobacteria</italic> (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The composition of the rumen microbiota of lambs fed a diet with <italic toggle="yes">Lemus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay. Taxonomic distribution of rumen bacterial communities of different groups at phylum level <bold>(A)</bold> and genus level <bold>(B)</bold>. LcRc and MsRc indicate rumen contents from lambs fed with <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay, respectively. &#8220;p_&#8221; denotes phylum-level classification, &#8220;f_&#8221; denotes phylum-level classification, and &#8220;g_&#8221; denotes genus-level classification.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1256903-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>The rumen bacterial composition was further compared through LEfSe analysis with 4.0 as the threshold on the LDA score to identify specific species in each group. The constitution of rumen bacteria changed between LcRc and MsRc. A total of 17 taxa sequences were enriched in the LcRc and mainly belonged to <italic toggle="yes">Fibrobacteres</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Spirochaetes</italic> (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). A total of 7 rumen bacteria mainly belonging to <italic toggle="yes">Firmicute</italic> were determined as enriched in the MsRc (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). Taken together, lambs in Lc and Ms. groups had distinct compositions of rumen bacterial community, which may lead to different growth performance, carcass performance, and metabolic profiles.</p><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The effect of <italic toggle="yes">Lemus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay on the taxonomic diversity of the rumen bacteria. The cladogram <bold>(A)</bold> and histogram <bold>(B)</bold> show rumen bacterial taxa with a linear discriminant analysis (LDA) score &gt;4.0 by LEfSe analysis. LcRc and MsRc indicate rumen contents from lambs fed with <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1256903-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec16"><label>3.3.</label><title>Key rumen microbiota associated with ADG, carcass weight, and body weight</title><p>To further investigate the potential relationship between rumen microbiota variation and ADG, carcass weight, and body weight, we performed the RDA and Spearman&#8217;s correlation between differential rumen bacteria and host parameters. According to RDA, the <italic toggle="yes">Lemus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay treatments were distinct and two different clusters were observed. ADG, carcass weight, and body weight showed a significant correlation with bacterial community (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figures 4A</xref>,<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">B</xref>). The Spearman&#8217;s correlation data showed that the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">BF311</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Pseudobutyrivibrio</italic> were negatively related to ADG, carcass weight, and body weight (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4C</xref>). Additionally, most genus-level bacteria such as <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Acidaminococcus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Moryella</italic> belonging to <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> showed a strongly positive correlation with ADG, carcass weight, and body weight (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figures 4C</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Alistipes</italic> belonging to <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Eggerthella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> belonging to <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Anaeroplasma</italic> belonging to <italic toggle="yes">Tenericutes</italic>, were also positively associated with ADG, carcass weight, and body weight (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4C</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Relationship between key rumen bacteria with ADG, carcass weight, and body weight. <bold>(A,B)</bold> RDA was performed on genus-level taxonomic profile and host parameters including ADG, carcass weight, and body weight. Arrows indicate the correlation between community structure and host parameters. <bold>(C)</bold> Correlation analysis of key rumen microbiota with ADG, carcass weight, and body weight. Statistical significance was calculated by Spearman&#8217;s correlation analysis. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;0.05, <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;0.01, <sup>***</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1256903-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec17"><label>3.4.</label><title>Metabolome profiles of longissimus dorsi</title><p>To define similarities and differences between lamb meat fed with <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay, we performed and analyzed the untargeted metabolome profiles of LD samples. PCA score plots with positive and negative ionization modes revealed no significant clustering of the two treatment groups (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5A</xref>), but further analysis revealed significant differences in metabolite composition. These metabolites mainly consisted of peptides, lipids, organic acids, steroids, carbohydrates, nucleic acids, vitamins and cofactors, hormones, and transmitters (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5B</xref>). These two comparisons identified 96 significant differential metabolites (67 in the positive mode and 29 in the negative mode), among which 52 and 44 differential metabolites were elevated in the Lc and Ms. groups, respectively. In detail, organic acid and derivatives including N-Acetyl-L-leucine, Pantetheine, Cysteinyl glycine, Alanyl tyrosine, and Ala-Ile were greater in the Ms group longissimus dorsi (MsLD), while Cinnamoyl glycine, L-arginosuccinate, and Glu-Thr were greater in the Lc group longissimus dorsi (LcLD). Lipids and lipid-like molecules such as 2-methylbutyroylcarnitine, Glycoursodeoxycholic acid, and 2-Hydroxymyristic acid were higher in the LcLD, while Hexadecanediouc acid, prostaglandin F2alpha, and tetradecanedioic acid were higher in the MsLD. Interestingly, LcLD contained higher organoheterocyclic compounds including Momocrotaline, (+)-alpha-lipoic acid, Methyl indole-3-acetate, benzenoids (i.e., hippuric acid), phenylpropanoids, and polyketides (i.e., 2-phenylpropionic acid). MsLD had a higher relative abundance of alkaloids and derivates including ecgonine methyl ester (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figures 5C</xref>,<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">D</xref>). Between <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay treatment, peptides including Ala-Ile, Glu-Thr, N-Acetyl-Asp-Glu, gamma-glutamyl-cysteine, and gamma-glutamyl-L-leucine, significantly changed (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figures 5C</xref>,<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">D</xref>). Furthermore, based on the pathway analysis, we found that these differential metabolites were mainly enriched in alanine, aspartate and glutamate metabolism, D-glutamine and D-glutamate metabolism, phenylalanine metabolism, nitrogen metabolism, and tyrosine metabolism (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figures 6A</xref>,<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">B</xref>). Changed metabolites in these pathways were shown in <xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, indicating that different forages affected amino acid composition and contents, and its metabolism, leading to various meat nutritional qualities.</p><fig position="float" id="fig5" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Lemus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay on metabolites of LD in lambs. <bold>(A)</bold> Scatter plots of the PCA model based on identified metabolite features. <bold>(B)</bold> Composition of metabolites in LcLD and MsLD. <bold>(C)</bold> Volcano plot of differential metabolites between LcLD and MsLD. <bold>(D)</bold> Boxplot of selected differential metabolites. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;7 in each group. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;0.05, <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;0.01, <sup>***</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;0.001. LcLD and MsLD indicate LD from lambs fed with <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1256903-g005.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig6" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Pathway analysis of differential metabolites. <bold>(A)</bold> Enriched KEGG pathways of the comparison between LcLD and MsLD. <bold>(B)</bold> Pathway enrichment and topology analysis.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1256903-g006.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>KEGG pathway enrichment of the changed metabolites for LcLD vs. MsLD.<xref rid="tfn12" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KEGG pathway</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Changed metabolite</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upregulation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Alanine, aspartate, and glutamate metabolism</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Glutamine</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.0004</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LcLD</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-Oxoglutaric acid</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LcLD</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adenylosuccinic acid</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LcLD</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">D-Glutamine and D-glutamate metabolism</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Glutamine</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.0022</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LcLD</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-Oxoglutaric acid</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LcLD</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Phenylalanine metabolism</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Phenylalanine</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="3" colspan="1">0.0029</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MsLD</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phenylacetylglycine</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MsLD</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hippuric acid</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LcLD</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Nitrogen metabolism</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Phenylalanine</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.0266</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MsLD</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Glutamine</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LcLD</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Tyrosine metabolism</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Dopa</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.0376</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MsLD</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homovanillic acid</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MsLD</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biotin metabolism</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Lysine</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0449</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MsLD</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn12"><label>a</label><p>LcLD and MsLD indicate LD from lambs fed with <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay, respectively.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To facilitate the identification of potential biomarkers between the two groups, PLS-DA and OPLS-DA were applied to identify the major differences in metabolites. PLS-DA score plots showed the best separation of LcLD and MsLD samples (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S2A</xref>). Several potential biomarkers with VIP &gt;2 including Monocrotaline, Hippuric acid, 6-Hydroxytestosterone, N-Acetyl-L-leucine, LysoPE 18:0, Ala-Ile, Methadone-d9, Cysteinylglycine, Cinnamoylglycine, Pilocarpine, and 2-Phenylpropionic acid and were highlighted in the volcano plots (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S2B</xref>). To minimize overfitting in the PLS-DA model, we further explored potential markers using OPLS-DA between groups. The analysis presented a cross-validated score plot (R2X&#8201;=&#8201;0.311, R2Y&#8201;=&#8201;0.993, Q2&#8201;=&#8201;0.737, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value&#8201;=&#8201;0.01) of the discriminating model between LcLD and MsLD in positive ionization mode. The cross-validated score plot (R2X&#8201;=&#8201;0.454, R2Y&#8201;=&#8201;0.995, Q2&#8201;=&#8201;0.526, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value&#8201;=&#8201;0.05) was shown in negative ionization mode. Identified biomarkers were the same as those identified by PLS-DA as having a trend toward being distinct between the two groups (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>). Additionally, random forest showed top differential metabolites including N-Acetyl-L-leucine, Hippuric acid, (+)-alpha-lipoic acid, and 2-Phenylpropionic acid (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S4</xref>).</p><p>Differential metabolites and potential biomarkers have been clarified as mentioned above. The correlation of potential biomarkers with growth performance was further analyzed. A total of 30 differential metabolites were significantly associated with ADG, carcass weight, and body weight. Among them, 14 metabolites including N-Acetyl-L-leucine, Methadone-d9, Hexadecanedioic acid, and alanyltyrosine were positively related to ADG, carcass weight, and body weight. Sixteen metabolites such as LysoPE 18:0, Cinnamoylglycine, and 2-Methylbutyroylcarnitine exhibited a negative relationship with growth performance (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig7" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Correlation analysis of differential metabolites with ADG, carcass weight, and body weight. Statistical significance was calculated by Spearman&#8217;s correlation analysis. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;0.05, <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;0.01, <sup>***</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1256903-g007.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec18"><label>3.5.</label><title>Correlation of key rumen microbiota with differential metabolites</title><p>The 16S rDNA sequencing revealed that lambs with the consumption of dietary <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay exhibited distinct rumen microbiota communities. The metabolomics analysis indicated that exposure to <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay resulted in different metabolic profiles of LD. Therefore, we explored the correlations between the rumen microbiota and the altered LD metabolites through Spearman&#8217;s correlation analysis, revealing high correlations between key rumen microbiota with differential metabolites (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref>). In detail, <italic toggle="yes">Fibrobacter</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Selenomonas</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">BF311</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Treponema</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium</italic> exhibited a strong positive relationship with organic acid and derivatives such as Glu-Thr, benzenoids including hippuric acid, phenylpropanoids and polyketides including 2-phenylpropionic acid, and organoheterocyclic compounds including Methyl indole-3-acetate, Momocrotaline, and (+)-alpha-lipoic acid. And they were negatively associated with other differential metabolites including Ala-Ile, N-Acetyl-L-leucine, Tetradecanedioic acid, and Methadone-d9. Other genera including <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Faecalibacterium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Blautia</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Roseburia</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Moryella</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">[Ruminococcus]</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Odoribacter</italic>, showed an obviously opposite correlation trend with the five genera mentioned above (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref>). These results indicated that the rumen bacterial compositions obviously and specifically impacted host LD metabolites.</p><fig position="float" id="fig8" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Correlation analysis of key rumen microbiota with differential metabolites. Statistical significance was calculated by Spearman&#8217;s correlation analysis. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;0.05, <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;0.01, <sup>***</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1256903-g008.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec19"><label>4.</label><title>Discussion</title><p>The forage is one of the main factor affecting ruminant production, rumen microbiota community, and meat quality. Previous studies explored ratios of various forages such as alfalfa hay, <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay, <italic toggle="yes">Vigna radiata</italic> stalk, and corn stalk, which had a greater effect on the ruminants (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). To our knowledge, few studies have systematically compared the growth and carcass traits of lambs fed <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay. In this study, we found that feeding with alfalfa hay increased lamb carcass weight, FBW, ADG, loin-eye area, and dressing percentage compared to those in the Lc group, supporting that those lambs fed with the alfalfa hay exhibited better carcass characteristics and growth performance.</p><p>The composition and diversity of rumen bacteria exhibit a close relationship with the host. Diet is one of the key factors that triggers changes in rumen microbial communities, alongside different environmental factors (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). To investigate the impacts of <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay on the host rumen bacterial community, 16S rDNA amplicon sequencing was performed and analyzed. Obviously, there was no significant difference in Shannon and Simpson indexes in the LcRc and MsRc. This indicates no significant altered in the diversity of rumen bacteria.</p><p>Exploring changes in rumen microbiota, which are closely related to muscle metabolites, can help to investigate the mechanisms for improving lamb meat quality under different roughage conditions. At the phylum level, <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> were the major bacterial phyla in the rumen as reported (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), whose relative abundances were significantly distinct in the LcRc and MsRc. <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> are dominant across rumen bacterial communities and consist of various fibrolytic and cellulolytic bacterial genera (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> are beneficial for digesting carbohydrates (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Then, we analyzed differences in key rumen bacteria at the genus level between the two groups and their correlation with metabolite deposition in the LD. <italic toggle="yes">Unspecified bacteroidales</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> were the dominant bacterial genera in both groups. Based on the LEfSe analysis, lambs in the Lc group have a higher relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic>, which plays an important role in polysaccharide and protein metabolism, and utilization of hemicelluloses (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Fibrobacter</italic> was also higher in the LcRc, which is a cellulolytic bacteria in the rumen of ruminants (<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). This may be related to the higher fiber intake of lambs in the Lc group, while we found that they positively regulate Glu-Thr levels in the LD. Dipeptides are important flavor precursors in lamb meat (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>), suggesting that rumen microorganisms may influence lamb meat quality by regulating flavor substances in muscle after feeding <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay. It has been reported that <italic toggle="yes">Fibrobacter</italic> was able to synthesize oligosaccharides and contributed to rapidly adapting to sudden environmental changes (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). In addition, three genera mainly belonging to the fibrolytic bacteria, such as <italic toggle="yes">Selenomonas</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">BF311</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Treponema</italic> were obviously elevated in the LcRc. <italic toggle="yes">Treponema</italic> is closely related to pectin treatments due to its ability to degrade pectin, which shares mutual interaction with <italic toggle="yes">Fibrobacter</italic> (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Selenomonas</italic> can oxidize lactate and produce propionic acid as a main fermentation product (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). And the correlation between these three fibrolytic bacteria and the metabolite levels of the LD had the same trend as <italic toggle="yes">Fibrobacter</italic>, suggesting that they may have the same mechanism of action. Most of the significant differential bacteria, such as <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Faecalibacterium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Mogibacterium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Anaerostipes</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Alistipes</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Blautia</italic>, were elevated in the MsRc. A previous study has shown that <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> is saccharolytic bacteria can generate acetate and lactate (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Faecalibacterium</italic> is one of the butyrate-producing bacteria linked to higher weight gain, and displays anti-inflammatory action (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Anaerostipes</italic> is also a butyrate-producing bacterium (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). In the present study also the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Faecalibacterium</italic> was found to be positively correlated with body weight and carcass weight. Changes in <italic toggle="yes">Mogibacterium</italic> are associated with feed efficiency in ruminants (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Additionally, <italic toggle="yes">Blautia</italic> has been proven to enhance beneficial anti-inflammatory effects of hosts (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). These results suggested that alfalfa hay may have altered feed efficiency, influenced volatile fatty acid production, and also facilitated rumen resistance to inflammation. Taken together, the forage types, i.e., <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay, resulted in different rumen bacterial compositions of lambs.</p><p>The compositions of nutrient metabolites have a direct impact on meat quality (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Thus, meat metabolic profiles aroused great public concern. Amino acids are important ingredients for the nutritional value of mutton (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). According to the analysis of untargeted metabolomics, we found significant differences in amino acid-related metabolites in meat between Lc and Ms. groups. Some amino acid metabolism, including alanine, aspartate, and glutamate metabolism, phenylalanine metabolism, D-glutamine, and D-glutamate metabolism, and tyrosine metabolism were changed, suggesting forages regulated amino acid contents and metabolism, and thus affected the nutritional quality of meat. Free amino acids and dipeptides are important flavor precursors in meat (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Importantly, some peptides have bioactive properties (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Cysteinylglycine belonging to the dipeptide is a structural component of glutathione (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>), which was higher in the MsLD. Between <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay treatment, peptides including Ala-Ile, Glu-Thr, N-Acetyl-Asp-Glu, gamma-glutamyl-cysteine and gamma-glutamyl-L-leucine changed significantly. The gamma-glutamyl peptide, gamma-glutamyl-L-leucine, has been recognized as a kokumi-imparting molecule (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). Another gamma-glutamyl peptide, gamma-glutamyl-cysteine, can activate the calcium-sensing receptor and then impart the kokumi peptide-induced responses (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>).</p><p>Rumen microorganisms provide energy for muscle metabolism to the host mainly in the form of volatile fatty acids (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Feeding <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay not only altered the substrates available for rumen fermentation but may have also altered the distribution of various fatty acids in the rumen, thereby affecting the composition of the rumen microbiota and the levels of LD muscle metabolites (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). For example, Du et al. (<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>) found that <italic toggle="yes">Ruminiclostridium_6</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">U29-B03</italic> might be participating in carbohydrate metabolism to produce volatile fatty acids, which promote IMF deposition affecting tenderness in muscles. The significant changes in the relative abundance of the associated bacteria in the Lc and Ms. groups in the present study may similarly cause alterations in the levels of metabolites in muscle via the volatile fatty acid pathway. However, more research would be required to reveal the connection between different roughages and changes in rumen microbiota and muscle metabolites.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec20"><label>5.</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>Compared to lamb with the <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay diet, lambs fed with alfalfa hay exhibited better growth performance and carcass performance. <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay led to the enrichment of the genera <italic toggle="yes">Fibrobacter</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Treponema</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Selenomonas</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">BF311</italic>. Alfalfa hay led to the enrichment of <italic toggle="yes">Blautia</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Anaerostipes</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Faecelibacterium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Alistipes</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic>, and other genera. Ruminal bacteria after feeding different roughages affect the quality of lamb meat by influencing the metabolism of several amino acids and polypeptides in lamb meat. It was also demonstrated that alanine, aspartate and glutamate metabolism, D-glutamine and D-glutamate metabolism, phenylalanine metabolism, nitrogen metabolism, and tyrosine metabolism were the key metabolic pathways involved after feeding <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay and alfalfa hay. In addition, conjoint analysis of rumen microbes and metabolomics indicated a close relationship between rumen microbial composition and muscle metabolites. These results have important significance for the future adequate and rational utilization of pasture to improve the quality of lamb meat.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec21"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The datasets presented in this study can be found in online repositories. The names of the repository/repositories and accession number(s) can be found at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject</ext-link>; PRJNA995904.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="sec22"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The animal study was approved by Animal Care and Use Committee of Inner Mongolia University (Approval No. IMU-sheep-2020-041). The study was conducted in accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="sec23"><title>Author contributions</title><p>HW: Writing &#8211; original draft. LiM: Data curation, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. LaM: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Data curation.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We express our gratitude to the diligent and committed researchers at our laboratories for their unwavering dedication and hard work. Additionally, we extend our sincere appreciation to all individuals who have contributed to the realization of this thesis.</p></ack><fn-group><title>Abbreviations</title><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>Lc, <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic>; Ms, <italic toggle="yes">Medicago sativa</italic>; LD, Longissimus dorsi; OTUs, Operational taxonomic units; ADG, Average daily gain; FBW, Final body weight; IBW, Initial body weight; F/G, Feed to gain ratio; ADFI, Average daily feed intake.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec25"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec100"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec26"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2023.1256903/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2023.1256903/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diao</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of urea supplementation on performance and safety in diets of Dorper crossbred sheep</article-title>. <source>J Anim Physiol Anim Nutr</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>902</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jpn.12417</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27611109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of dietary sea buckthorn pomace supplementation on skeletal muscle mass and meat quality in lambs</article-title>. <source>Meat Sci</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>166</volume>:<fpage>108141</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2020.108141</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32302933</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linden</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonagh</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Understanding the impact of sire lean meat yield breeding value on carcass composition, meat quality, nutrient and mineral content of Australian lamb</article-title>. <source>Meat Sci</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>170</volume>:<fpage>108236</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2020.108236</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32688223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Meat quality, fatty acid composition of tissue and gastrointestinal content, and antioxidant status of lamb fed seed of a halophyte (<italic toggle="yes">Suaeda glauca</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Meat Sci</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2014.09.005</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25282041</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of substitution of mixed grass hay with <italic toggle="yes">Urtica cannabina</italic> hay and/or <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay on blood biochemical profile, carcass traits, and intramuscular fatty acid composition in finishing lambs</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>272</volume>:<fpage>114780</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2020.114780</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Transcriptome analysis in sheepgrass (<italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic>): a dominant perennial grass of the Eurasian Steppe</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e67974</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0067974</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23861841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3701641</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> degradability of corn silage and <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> silage and evaluation of their mixed ratios on performance, digestion and serum parameters in beef cattle</article-title>. <source>J Anim Physiol Anim Nutr</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>104</volume>:<fpage>1628</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jpn.13392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32525268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Undersander</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Short communication: effects of replacing part of corn silage and alfalfa hay with <italic toggle="yes">Leymus chinensis</italic> hay on milk production and composition</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>3605</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2010-3536</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21700048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Forage intake and weight gain of ewes is affected by roughage mixes during winter in northeastern China</article-title>. <source>Anim Sci J</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>1058</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/asj.12747</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27925352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Obeidat</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Subih</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Obeidat</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Alfalfa hay improves nursing performance of Awassi ewes and performance of growing lambs when used as a source of forage compared with wheat straw</article-title>. <source>Trop Anim Health Prod</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>581</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11250-018-1735-z</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30338426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gentu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Feeding forage mixtures of alfalfa hay and maize stover optimizes growth performance and carcass characteristics of lambs</article-title>. <source>Anim Sci J</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>359</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/asj.12928</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29024312</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ponnampalam</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunshea</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Use of lucerne hay in ruminant feeds to improve animal productivity, meat nutritional value and meat preservation under a more variable climate</article-title>. <source>Meat Sci</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>170</volume>:<fpage>108235</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2020.108235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32688224</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgavi</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rathahao-Paris</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Popova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boccard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boudra</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rumen microbial communities influence metabolic phenotypes in lambs</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1060</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2015.01060</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26528248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4601264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Y&#225;&#241;ez-Ruiz</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mele</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Serra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luciano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Bacterial and protozoal communities and fatty acid profile in the rumen of sheep fed a diet containing added tannins</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>76</volume>:<fpage>2549</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.02583-09</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20173064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2849217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zened</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Combes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cauquil</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mariette</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klopp</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchez</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Microbial ecology of the rumen evaluated by 454 Gs Flx pyrosequencing is affected by starch and oil supplementation of diets</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>83</volume>:<fpage>504</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>14</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1574-6941.12011</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22974422</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petri</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKinnon</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McAllister</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of rumen bacterial diversity and fermentation parameters in concentrate fed cattle with and without forage</article-title>. <source>J Appl Microbiol</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>112</volume>:<fpage>1152</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2012.05295.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22533638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huws</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MRF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muetzel</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scollan</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Forage type and fish oil cause shifts in rumen bacterial diversity</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>73</volume>:<fpage>396</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>407</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6941.2010.00892.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20491929</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>QQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holman</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Fecal microbiota of lambs fed purple prairie clover (<italic toggle="yes">Dalea purpurea</italic> vent.) and alfalfa (<italic toggle="yes">Medicago sativa</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Arch Microbiol</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>200</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00203-017-1427-5</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28864945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of dietary forage sources on rumen microbiota, rumen fermentation and biogenic amines in dairy cows</article-title>. <source>J Sci Food Agr</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>1886</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.6508</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24375419</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rumen bacteria and meat fatty acid composition of Sunit sheep reared under different feeding regimens in China</article-title>. <source>J Sci Food Agric</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>101</volume>:<fpage>1100</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.10720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32767556</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Microbiome-metabolomics analysis of the impacts of long-term dietary advanced-glycation-end-product consumption on C57bl/6 mouse fecal microbiota and metabolites</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>8864</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>75</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.8b01466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30037223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Untargeted and targeted metabolomics profiling of muscle reveals enhanced meat quality in artificial pasture grazing tan lambs via rescheduling the rumen bacterial community</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>846</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>58</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.0c06427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33405917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ran</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saleem</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beauchemin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Penner</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Processing index of barley grain and dietary undigested neutral detergent Fiber concentration affected chewing behavior, ruminal pH, and total tract nutrient digestibility of heifers fed a high-grain diet</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>skab011</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jas/skab011</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33523183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7850052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of increasing neutral detergent Fiber level through different fiber feed ingredients throughout the gestation of sows</article-title>. <source>Animals</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>415</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani11020415</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33561988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7914734</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubio-Armend&#225;riz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guti&#233;rrez</surname><given-names>&#193;J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes-Furtado</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez-Weller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Revert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardisson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Essential metals and trace elements in cereals and their derivatives commercialized and consumed in Cape Verde</article-title>. <source>Biol Trace Elem Res</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>201</volume>:<fpage>444</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>54</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12011-022-03158-x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35226277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9823067</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A comparative analysis of carcass and meat traits, and rumen bacteria between Chinese Mongolian sheep and Dorper&#8201;&#215;&#8201;Chinese Mongolian crossbred sheep</article-title>. <source>Animal</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>100503</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.animal.2022.100503</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35378496</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>ZZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of residual superdoses of phytase on growth performance, tibia mineralization, and relative organ weight in ducks fed phosphorus-deficient diets</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>3926</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pez114</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30938806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomita</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishioka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hisada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishijima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Development of a prokaryotic universal primer for simultaneous analysis of bacteria and archaea using next-generation sequencing</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e105592</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0105592</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25144201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4140814</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ponnusamy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Microbial community and metabolomic comparison of irritable bowel syndrome faeces</article-title>. <source>J Med Microbiol</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>60</volume>:<fpage>817</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.028126-0</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21330412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3167923</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sangster</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Major</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plumb</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A pragmatic and readily implemented quality control strategy for Hplc-Ms and Gc-Ms-based metabonomic analysis</article-title>. <source>Analyst</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>131</volume>:<fpage>1075</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/b604498k</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17003852</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Want</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gika</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Theodoridis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plumb</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shockcor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Global metabolic profiling procedures for urine using Uplc-Ms</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1005</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2010.50</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20448546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Metaboanalystr: an R package for flexible and reproducible analysis of metabolomics data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>4313</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bty528</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29955821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6289126</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Persistence of cellulolytic bacteria <italic toggle="yes">Fibrobacter</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Treponema</italic> after short-term corn stover-based dietary intervention reveals the potential to improve rumen Fibrolytic function</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1363</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.01363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29997589</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6029512</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Getty</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Birtles</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of novel bovine gastrointestinal tract <italic toggle="yes">Treponema</italic> isolates and comparison with bovine digital dermatitis Treponemes</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>138</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>47</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00993-10</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21057019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3019712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of the primary starch utilization operon in the obligate anaerobe <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroides fragilis</italic>: regulation by carbon source and oxygen</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>188</volume>:<fpage>4663</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>72</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00125-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16788175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1482989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daugherty</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hance</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genomic differences between <italic toggle="yes">Fibrobacter succinogenes</italic> S85 and <italic toggle="yes">Fibrobacter intestinalis</italic> Dr7, identified by suppression subtractive hybridization</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>987</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/Aem.02514-07</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18156324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2258565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaczmarska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piyasiri</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Flavor and metabolite profiles of meat, meat substitutes, and traditional plant-based high-protein food products available in Australia</article-title>. <source>Foods</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>801</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/foods10040801</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33917948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8068397</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pectin induces an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> rumen microbial population shift attributed to the pectinolytic Treponema group</article-title>. <source>Curr Microbiol</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>67</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00284-014-0672-y</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25178631</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vidra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemeth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bio-produced propionic acid: a review</article-title>. <source>Period Polytech Chem Eng</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>62</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>67</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3311/PPch.10805</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oikonomou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foditsch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bicalho</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bicalho</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fecal microbial diversity in pre-weaned dairy calves as described by pyrosequencing of metagenomic 16s rDNA. Associations of <italic toggle="yes">Faecalibacterium</italic> species with health and growth</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e63157</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0063157</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23646192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3639981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Metagenomic sequencing reveals that high-grain feeding alters the composition and metabolism of cecal microbiota and induces cecal mucosal injury in sheep</article-title>. <source>mSystems</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e0091521</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSystems.00915-21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34609166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8547435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McLoughlin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spillane</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Claffey</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Rourke</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diskin</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rumen microbiome composition is altered in sheep divergent in feed efficiency</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1981</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.01981</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32983009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7477290</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenq</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taur</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Devlin</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ponce</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahr</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Intestinal Blautia is associated with reduced death from graft-versus-host disease</article-title>. <source>Biol Blood Marrow Transplant</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1373</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>83</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbmt.2015.04.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25977230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4516127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A large-scale comparison of meat quality and intramuscular fatty acid composition among three Chinese indigenous pig breeds</article-title>. <source>Meat Sci</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>168</volume>:<fpage>108182</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2020.108182</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32497959</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Z-W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X-F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X-L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y-C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>N-Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <source>Comparison of muscle amino acid and fatty acid composition of castrated and uncastrated male pigs at different slaughter ages</source>(<year>2010</year>) <source>Ital J Anim Sci</source>. <volume>9</volume>, <fpage>e33</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4081/ijas.2010.e33</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oestreicher</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Glutathione: subcellular distribution and membrane transport<sup>1</sup></article-title>. <source>Biochem Cell Biol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>97</volume>:<fpage>270</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>89</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/bcb-2018-0189</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30427707</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Biocatalytic synthesis of &#947;-glutamyl-L-leucine, a Kokumi-Imparting Dipeptide, by <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus licheniformis</italic> &#947;-Glutamyltranspeptidase</article-title>. <source>Food Biotechnol</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>130</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>47</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08905436.2018.1444636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohsu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagasaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takeshita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Involvement of the calcium-sensing receptor in human taste perception</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>285</volume>:<fpage>1016</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M109.029165</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19892707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2801228</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nathani</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mootapally</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lunagaria</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of roughage on rumen microbiota composition in the efficient feed converter and sturdy Indian Jaffrabadi Buffalo (<italic toggle="yes">Bubalus bubalis</italic>)</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1116</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-015-2340-4</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26714477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4696265</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghimire</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohn</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gregorini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanigan</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Representing interconversions among volatile fatty acids in the Molly cow model</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>3658</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2016-11858</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28259412</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary energy levels affect carbohydrate metabolism-related Bacteria and improve meat quality in the longissimus Thoracis muscle of yak (<italic toggle="yes">Bos grunniens</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>718036</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.718036</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34631849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8492897</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>