<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10565034</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10565034.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10565034</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10565034</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37829355</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1236635</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Early supplementation with zinc proteinate does not change rectal microbiota but increases growth performance by improving antioxidant capacity and plasma zinc concentration in preweaned dairy calves</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="J">Junhao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn0002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names initials="X">Xin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn0002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names initials="F">Fengtao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wo</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yeqianli</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1853033/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuhang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashem</surname><given-names initials="NM">Nesrein M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names initials="P">Peng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/664370/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>State Key Laboratory of Animal Nutrition and Feeding, Institute of Animal Science, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Animal and Fish Production, Faculty of Agriculture, Alexandria University</institution>, <addr-line>Alexandria</addr-line>, <country>Egypt</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0003"><p>Edited by: Bangyuan Wu, China West Normal University, China</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0004"><p>Reviewed by: Houqiang Luo, Wenzhou Vocational College of Science and Technology, China; Adham Al-Sagheer, Zagazig University, Egypt</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Peng Sun, <email>sunpeng02@caas.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn0002"><p><sup>&#8224;</sup>These authors have contributed equally to this work and share first authorship</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">427755</issue-id><elocation-id>1236635</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>08</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>9</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-08-29 01:25:29.363"><day>29</day><month>08</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 Liu, Yu, Ma, Wo, Jin, Hashem and Sun.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Liu, Yu, Ma, Wo, Jin, Hashem and Sun</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-10-1236635.pdf"/><abstract><p>The present study evaluated the effects of early supplementation with zinc proteinate (ZnP) or zinc oxide (ZnO) for 2&#8201;weeks on the growth performance, redox status, plasma trace element concentrations, and rectal microbiota of preweaned dairy calves. A total of 60 newborn healthy female Holstein dairy calves, with initial body weight (BW): 41.33&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.62&#8201;kg, were randomly allocated to 5 groups of 12 each: a control group (CON); three groups supplemented with 261 (L-ZnP), 523 (M-ZnP), and 784 (H-ZnP) mg/day ZnP, equivalent to 40, 80, and 120&#8201;mg/day zinc, respectively; and one group supplemented with 232&#8201;mg/day ZnO, equivalent to 180&#8201;mg/day zinc (ZnO). Zinc supplements were administered on days 1&#8211;14, and the calves were followed up until day 70. Zinc supplementation increased total dry matter intake (DMI) and starter DMI compared with the CON group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01). The final BW, average daily gain, and feed efficiency were higher in the M-ZnP, H-ZnP, and ZnO groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The incidence of diarrhea on days 1&#8211;28 was reduced by zinc administration (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01), whereas the incidence on days 29&#8211;56 was lower in the M-ZnP and ZnO groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Serum glutathione peroxidase activity, total antioxidant capacity, immunoglobulin G and plasma zinc concentrations were increased linearly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05), while the serum concentration of malondialdehyde was decreased linearly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01), as the dose of ZnP increased. ZnP yielding 80&#8201;mg/day zinc had similar effects as ZnO yielding 180&#8201;mg/day zinc, except that final BW was higher in the ZnO group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). At the phylum level, ZnO decreased the relative abundance of Firmicutes while increasing the abundance of Bacteroidetes (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). At the genus level, ZnO increased the relative abundances of <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Subdoligranulum</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Odoribacter</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). These findings indicated that early supplementation with ZnP did not affect the rectal microbiota of preweaned dairy calves but increased their growth performance, antioxidant capacity, and plasma zinc concentration. In summary, ZnP is an organic zinc source with greater bioavailability than ZnO for preweaned dairy calves. Early dietary supplementation with ZnP yielding 80&#8201;mg/day zinc is recommended.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>zinc proteinate</kwd><kwd>zinc oxide</kwd><kwd>growth performance</kwd><kwd>antioxidant capacity</kwd><kwd>plasma zinc concentration</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn1"><institution-wrap><institution>National Key Research and Development Program of China</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100012166</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id award-type="contract" rid="cn1">2022YFD1300505</award-id><award-id award-type="contract" rid="cn1">2022YFD1301101</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn2">China Agriculture Research System</funding-source><award-id award-type="contract" rid="cn2">CARS-37</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn3"><institution-wrap><institution>Agricultural Science and Technology Innovation Program</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100012421</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id award-type="contract" rid="cn3">cxgc-ias-07</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="7"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="59"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="8048"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Animal Nutrition and Metabolism</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><label>1.</label><title>Introduction</title><p>The health of calves is of great importance in maintaining optimal lactation performance of adult dairy cows and the sustainable development of pastures. In traditional breeding, the lactation period of calves is generally 3&#8211;6&#8201;months; weaning earlier than 6&#8201;weeks has been found to reduce average daily gain (ADG) and increase morbidity, thus reducing the lifespan of dairy cows (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). To shorten the lactation cycle, most farms have begun to implement early weaning. However, the high levels of stress caused by early weaning may have lasting effects on calf health, which may reduce future production parameters, including growth, lactation, and reproductive performance, and in severe cases may lead to calf death (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>).</p><p>Efforts are therefore required to minimize the adverse effects of weaning, such as reducing stress associated with weaning or disease risk, and improving feed conversion efficiency. Antibiotics once played important roles in these areas (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). However, the intensive use of synthetic antibiotics raises global concerns due to the increased health risks related to antimicrobial resistance (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Therefore, it is imperative to seek appropriate feed additives to reduce the possible damage caused by weaning.</p><p>Zinc is an essential nutrient element and is involved in many physiologic functions in the body (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Dietary zinc supplementation has been found to increase growth performance, promote antioxidant and immune activities, improve the intestinal microflora, and reduce the incidence of diarrhea (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8&#8211;10</xref>). Although oral administration of large amounts of zinc oxidant (ZnO) was often used to promote growth and reduce diarrhea in young animals (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), unabsorbed zinc secreted in feces may post a threat to the environment. Thus, in 2017, the Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs of China banned the supplementation of animal diets with high levels of ZnO and mandated that the level of zinc in calf diets not exceed 180&#8201;mg/kg.</p><p>Organic zinc has a higher bioavailability than inorganic zinc (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). There are many commercial sources of organic zinc such as zinc methionine, zinc polysaccharide, zinc lysine, zinc amino acid chelate, and zinc proteinate, etc. Ma et al. (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) suggested that zinc methionine supplementation lowers the incidence of diarrhea in postnatal Holstein dairy calves by reducing intestinal permeability, which confirms the effectiveness of organic zinc as a potential treatment for diarrhea during early life calf rearing. Comparable to the same dose of zinc from zinc methionine, our previous study showed that supplementation with ZnP to yield 80&#8201;mg/day zinc also reduced the incidence of diarrhea and increased the growth performance and immune function of dairy calves (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). It is known that ZnP is a novel form of organic zinc prepared from soybean protein isolate and feed-grade inorganic zinc (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). The ZnP supplementation was found to significantly enhance humoral immunity, and superoxide dismutase (SOD) activity in red blood cells (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Therefore, we hypothesized that early supplementation with ZnP during the first 2&#8201;weeks of life may alleviate diarrhea and improve the growth performance of preweaned dairy calves by improving their antioxidant capacity, immune function, and rectal microbial microbiota. The present study was designed to determine the optimal dose of ZnP for dairy calves and compare that dose of ZnP with ZnO yielding 180&#8201;mg/day zinc. Outcomes analyzed included growth performance, the incidence of diarrhea, serum concentrations of antioxidants and immune indicators, plasma concentrations of trace elements, and rectal microbiota of preweaned Holstein dairy calves, which might achieve the most optimal dose of ZnP that can maintain calf health and minimize the release of zinc into the environment.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><label>2.</label><title>Materials and methods</title><p>This study was performed at the Yanqing Breeding Farm of the Beijing Dairy Cattle Center (Beijing, China). The calves were maintained according to the standards of the Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences Animal Care and Use Committee.</p><sec id="sec3"><label>2.1.</label><title>Animals and diet</title><p>The study included 60 newborn healthy female Holstein dairy calves of initial mean body weight (BW) 41.33&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.62&#8201;kg. Each calf was fed 4&#8201;L of colostrum from a bottle within 1&#8201;h of birth, followed by 1.5&#8201;L of raw milk three times per day from a bottle at 0600, 1400, and 1800 on days 2&#8211;4, and 4&#8201;L of raw milk twice per day from a bottle at 0600 and 1800 on days 5&#8211;70. Based on their growth condition, all calves were removed from their dams at age 4&#8211;7&#8201;days, housed in individual pens, and then fed with granulated starter produced by the Feed Branch of Beijing Shounong Animal Science and Technology Development Co., Ltd. (Beijing, China). The crude protein (CP; AOAC International, 2000; method 976.05), ether extract (EE; AOAC International, 2003; method 4.5.05), and dry matter content (DM; AOAC International, 2005; method 930.15) of starter was measured using the standard procedures of AOAC International (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18&#8211;20</xref>). The neutral detergent fiber (NDF) and acid detergent fiber (ADF) contents were determined according to Van Soest et al. (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). The density, milk protein, milk fat, lactose, total solids (TS), and solids non-fat (SNF) were determined by a milk composition analyzer (MilkoScanTM FT6000, FOSS Corporation, Denmark). The nutrient compositions of the milk and starter are presented in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The concentrations of zinc in water, milk, and starter were 0, 3.35&#8201;mg/kg and 175&#8201;mg/kg DM, respectively.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Nutrient composition of the milk and starter.<xref rid="tfn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Item</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Milk</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Starter (DM basis)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP, %</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ether extract, %</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ash, %</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDF, %</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADF, %</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DM, %</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zinc, mg/kg</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.35</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Milk protein, %</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Milk fat, %</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.02</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total solids, %</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.56</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lactose, %</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.91</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Density, g/mL</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>CP, crude protein; NDF, neutral detergent fiber; ADF, acid detergent fiber; DM, dry matter.</p><fn id="tfn1"><label>a</label><p>Analyzed value.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>2.2.</label><title>Experimental design and sample collection</title><p>The calves were randomly allocated to 5 groups of 12 using a random number generator (Microsoft Corp., WA, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> =&#8201;12 each): a negative control group without extra zinc supplementation (CON group); three groups supplemented with 261 (L-ZnP group), 523 (M-ZnP group), and 784 (H-ZnP group) mg/day ZnP, equivalent to 40, 80, and 120&#8201;mg/day zinc, respectively; and one group supplemented with 232&#8201;mg/d ZnO, equivalent to 180&#8201;mg/day zinc (ZnO group). These doses were based on previous studies (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). The ZnP (<italic toggle="yes">Q</italic><sub>f</sub> =&#8201;327) was donated by the Mineral Nutrition Research Division, Institute of Animal Science, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences (Beijing, China). The ZnO or ZnP was administered from birth until 14&#8201;days of age. The appropriate amounts of ZnO or ZnP were mixed with 200&#8201;mL of raw milk and fed to the calves, followed by feeding with additional raw milk. The calves were monitored from birth to 70&#8201;days of age, during which time they had free access to water and starter.</p><p>Blood samples were collected from the external jugular vein of each calf using vacutainer tubes, with or without heparin sodium (BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA), before morning feedings on days 15, 29, 43, 57, and 71 after birth. Serum and plasma were prepared by centrifugation at 3000&#8201;&#215;&#8201;g for 15&#8201;min at 4&#176;C and then stored at &#8722;20&#176;C for subsequent analyses.</p><p>Fecal samples were randomly collected from the rectum of 8 calves in each group on the morning of day 71. About 0.2&#8201;g of fecal sample from each animal was collected in a 2&#8201;mL tube and stored at &#8722;80&#176;C for subsequent analysis of the microbiota.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>2.3.</label><title>Growth performance and incidence of diarrhea</title><p>The BW of each calf was recorded before morning feedings on days 1, 15, 29, 43, 57, and 71 after birth. ADGs were calculated for these time intervals and for the entire length of the study. Daily intake of milk and starter was recorded, and the total dry matter intake (DMI), starter DMI, and feed to gain ratio (F:G) were calculated for each calf.</p><p>During the trial period, the feces of each calf were monitored twice daily, in the morning and evening, and scored. Normal and cylindrical feces were scored as 1 point; slight, thin, soft, and tangible feces as 2 points; shapeless stools with high moisture content as 3 points; and liquid, shapeless, watery feces as 4 points (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Scores of 3 and 4 for 2 consecutive days were defined as diarrhea, and the incidence of diarrhea was recorded as described (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><label>2.4.</label><title>Concentrations of serum immunoglobulins, antioxidant indicators and plasma trace elements</title><p>The concentrations of serum immunoglobulin (Ig) A, IgG, and IgM were measured using bovine ELISA kits (Wuhan ColorfulGene Biological Technology; Wuhan, China) according to the manufacturer&#8217;s instructions.</p><p>Glutathione peroxidase (GSH-Px) and SOD activities, and total antioxidant capacity (T-AOC) and malondialdehyde (MDA) concentrations, were analyzed by radioimmunoassays using commercially available kits (Nanjing Jian Cheng Bioengineering Institute, Nanjing, China) in accordance with the manufacturer&#8217;s instructions.</p><p>The concentrations of copper (Cu), iron (Fe), zinc (Zn), calcium (Ca), and magnesium (Mg) in plasma were determined by inductively coupled plasma optical emission spectroscopy (ICP-OES), according to the Chinese National Standards (GB 5009.268, China, 2016) with some modifications (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><label>2.5.</label><title>Extraction of total DNA from rectal microbes and <italic toggle="yes">16S rRNA</italic> gene sequencing</title><p>The DNA was extracted from rectal contents using M5635-02 Mag-Bind Soil DNA kits (Omega Biotek, United States), according to the manufacturer&#8217;s instructions. The quality of the extracted DNA was determined by 0.8% agarose gel electrophoresis, and the quantity of the DNA were assessed using a NanoDrop NC2000 spectrophotometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA).</p><p>DNA sequences were PCR amplified using Applied Biosystems<sup>&#8482;</sup> 2,720 Thermal Cycler (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA), Pfu high-fidelity DNA polymerase (Beijing Quanshijin Biotechnology Co., Ltd., China), and the primers 338F (5&#8242;-ACTCCTACGGGAGGCAGCA-3&#8242;) and 806R (5&#8242;-GGACTACHVGGGTWTCTAAT-3&#8242;) (Personalbio Biotechnology Co., Ltd.; Shanghai, China). Each 25&#8201;&#956;L PCR reaction mixture contained 5&#8201;&#956;L of 5&#8201;&#215;&#8201;reaction buffer, 5&#8201;&#956;L of 5&#8201;&#215;&#8201;GC buffer, 2&#8201;&#956;L of dNTPs (2.5&#8201;mM each), 1&#8201;&#956;L each of the forward and reverse primers (10&#8201;&#956;M each), 2&#8201;&#956;L of template DNA, 8.75&#8201;&#956;L of ddH<sub>2</sub>O, and 0.25&#8201;&#956;L of Q5 DNA polymerase. The sequencing area was &#8220;16s-V3-V4,&#8221; and all samples were assayed in triplicate.</p><p>The amplification protocol consisted of an initial denaturation at 98&#176;C for 2&#8201;min, followed by 25&#8211;30&#8201;cycles of denaturation at 98&#176;C for 15&#8201;s, annealing at 55&#176;C for 30&#8201;s, and extension at 72&#176;C for 5&#8201;min, followed by a final extension at 72&#176;C for 5&#8201;min. The amplification products were electrophoresed on 2% agarose gels, and the target fragments were extracted from the gels using a DNA purification kit (Axygen, Biosciences, Union City, CA). Depending on the results of electrophoresis, the PCR products were amplified using Quant-iT PicoGreen dsDNA Assay Kits and quantified using a microplate reader (BioTek, FLx80). According to the fluorescent quantitative results, the samples were mixed in equal quantities and used to construct a sequencing library using an Ilumina Truseq Nano DNA LT Library Prep Kit. Finally, the V3&#8211;V4 amplicons were sequenced using the paired-end method on an Illumina Miseq at Majorbio (Shanghai personalbio, Shanghai, China). The sequences have been registered at GenBank under accession number SRP320638.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><label>2.6.</label><title>Sequence analysis</title><p>The DADA2 method was used for primer removal, mass filtering, denoising, splicing, and chimera removal (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>), followed by detailed processing (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Richness was estimated using the Chao1 and observed species indices, and community diversity was assessed using the Shannon and Simpson indices. Beta diversity was analyzed using Bray&#8211;Curtis distance and visualized by principal coordinates analysis (PCoA).</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><label>2.7.</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The incidence of diarrhea was compared among groups using the chi-squared contingency test. Growth performance and blood indices were compared using the MIXED procedure in SAS software (version 9.4, SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC). A repeated measures model evaluated the random effect of calf and the fixed effects of treatment, day, and their interaction was used. Contrasts were performed to evaluate treatment effects, ZnP supplementation levels, and zinc source (M-ZnP vs. ZnO). The data are expressed as the least squares means and the standard error of the mean (SEM). Differences between treatment groups were evaluated using Tukey&#8217;s multiple range tests. Differences in rectal microbial alpha diversity and the relative abundances of species at different levels were analyzed by Kruskal-Wallis tests using SPSS 20 software. The range of <italic toggle="yes">R</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values selected by the correlation heat map was &gt;0.3 and &lt;0.05, respectively. Correlations of the populations of the principal fecal microbes with growth performance, antioxidant indicators, and plasma zinc concentrations on day 70 were analyzed by Spearman&#8217;s correlation method on Genescloud.<xref rid="fn0001" ref-type="fn"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values &lt;0.05 were defined as statistically significant, whereas <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values of 0.05&#8211;0.10 were considered significant tendencies.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec10"><label>3.</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec11"><label>3.1.</label><title>Growth performance and incidence of diarrhea</title><p>The effects of different zinc sources on growth performance and incidence of diarrhea in preweaned Holstein dairy calves are presented in <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. At baseline, BW was similar in the five groups of calves. However, supplementation with ZnP or ZnO increased starter DMI and total DMI compared with the CON group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01). As the level of ZnP supplementation increased, starter DMI and total DMI increased linearly and quadratically, and peaked in the M-ZnP group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The final BW, ADG, and feed efficiency also increased linearly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05), being significantly higher in the M-ZnP, H-ZnP, and ZnO groups than in the CON group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Growth performance was not affected by zinc source except for the final BW, which was significantly higher in the ZnO than in the M-ZnP group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Supplementation with ZnP or ZnO reduced the incidence of diarrhea on days 1&#8211;28 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01), whereas, on days 29&#8211;56, the incidence of diarrhea was lower in the M-ZnP and ZnO groups than in the CON group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The growth performance of the calves varied significantly with age, with day and the treatment&#8201;&#215;&#8201;day interaction having significant effects on total DMI and feed to gain ratio (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effects of different zinc sources and concentrations on growth performance and incidence of diarrhea of preweaned Holstein dairy calves.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Item<xref rid="tfn2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th align="center" valign="middle" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Treatment<xref rid="tfn3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">SEM</th><th align="center" valign="middle" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CON</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-ZnP</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M-ZnP</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-ZnP</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZnO</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linear</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quadratic</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trt</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trt&#8201;&#215;&#8201;day</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial BW (kg)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.08</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.08</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.11</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.42</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.00</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.461</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Final BW (kg)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.19<sup>c</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.81<sup>c</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.35<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.53<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.99<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.681</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average daily gain (ADG; g/d)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">826.19<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">852.98<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">872.62<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">888.69<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">893.45<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.26</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.157</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.983</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total dry matter intake (total DMI; g/d)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1320.78<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1369.88<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1373.78<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1370.35<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1371.39<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.21</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.875</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Starter dry matter intake (starter DMI; g/d)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">343.18<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">383.54<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">387.00<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">386.42<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">382.51<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.25</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.725</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feed to gain (F:G; g of DMI/g of gain)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.386</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.771</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incidence of diarrhea (1&#8211;28 days; %)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.2<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.55<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.57<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.27<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.17<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incidence of diarrhea (29&#8211;56 days; %)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.17<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.08<sup>abc</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60<sup>c</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.98<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49<sup>bc</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.048</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incidence of diarrhea (57&#8211;70 days; %)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.17</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.57</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.98</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.616</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a,b,c</sup>Significant differences within the same row (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05).</p><fn id="tfn2"><label>a</label><p>BW, body weight; ADG, average daily gain; total DMI, total dry matter intake; starter DMI, starter dry matter intake; F:G, feed to gain.</p></fn><fn id="tfn3"><label>b</label><p>CON, control group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, no zinc proteinate or zinc oxide supplementation); L-ZnP, low-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, 261&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); M-ZnP, medium-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, 523&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); H-ZnP, high-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, 784&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); ZnO, zinc oxide group, (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, 232&#8201;mg/day of zinc oxide).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec12"><label>3.2.</label><title>Concentrations of serum immunoglobulins, antioxidant indicators and plasma trace elements</title><p>The effects of different zinc sources on serum immune indices are shown in <xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. Neither zinc supplementation nor zinc source affected the serum IgA, IgG, and IgM concentrations in these dairy calves. However, serum IgG concentration increased linearly with increasing ZnP dose (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Effects of different zinc sources and concentrations on serum immune indices of preweaned Holstein dairy calves.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Item<xref rid="tfn4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th align="center" valign="middle" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Treatment<xref rid="tfn5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">SEM</th><th align="center" valign="middle" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CON</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-ZnP</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M-ZnP</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-ZnP</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZnO</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linear</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quadratic</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trt</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trt&#8201;&#215;&#8201;day</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgA, &#956;g/mL</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.19</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.89</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.37</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.20</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.77</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.625</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.369</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.401</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.823</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.972</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgG, mg/mL</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.60</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.75</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.26</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.23</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.864</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.529</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.223</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.874</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgM, mg/mL</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.77</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.88</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.77</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.752</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.077</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.159</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.302</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.428</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn4"><label>a</label><p>IgA, immunoglobulin A; IgG, immunoglobulin G; IgM, immunoglobulin M.</p></fn><fn id="tfn5"><label>b</label><p>CON, control group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, no zinc proteinate or zinc oxide supplementation); L-ZnP, low-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, 261&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); M-ZnP, medium-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, 523&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); H-ZnP, high-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, 784&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); ZnO, zinc oxide group, (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, 232&#8201;mg/day of zinc oxide).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p><xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> shows the effects of different zinc sources on serum antioxidant indices. The activities of serum GSH-Px (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01) and T-AOC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) increased linearly, whereas the serum concentrations of MDA (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01) decreased linearly, as the dose of ZnP increased. Furthermore, serum GSH-Px activity was higher in the ZnP and ZnO groups than in the CON group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01), whereas the activity of SOD was higher in the M-ZnP and ZnO groups than in the CON and H-ZnP groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Zinc source did not significantly affect the serum antioxidant indices.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Effects of different zinc sources and concentrations on antioxidant indices in the sera of preweaned Holstein dairy calves.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Item<xref rid="tfn6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th align="center" valign="middle" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Treatment<xref rid="tfn7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">SEM</th><th align="center" valign="middle" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CON</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-ZnP</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M-ZnP</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-ZnP</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZnO</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linear</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quadratic</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trt</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trt&#8201;&#215;&#8201;day</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDA, nmol/mL</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.30</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.24</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.13</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.04</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.11</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.872</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.849</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.068</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.632</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOD, U/mL</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.23<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.50<sup>abc</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.74<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.28<sup>bc</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.06<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.134</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.088</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.332</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.991</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSH-Px, U/mL</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">126.10<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">129.82<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">132.31<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">132.72<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">132.23<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.181</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.992</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.755</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-AOC, U/mL</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.86</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.08</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.05</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.07</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.958</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.930</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a,b,c</sup>Significant differences within the same row (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05).</p><fn id="tfn6"><label>a</label><p>MDA, malondialdehyde; SOD, superoxide dismutase; GSH-Px, glutathione peroxidase; T-AOC, total antioxidant capacity.</p></fn><fn id="tfn7"><label>b</label><p>CON, control group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, no zinc proteinate or zinc oxide supplementation); L-ZnP, low-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, 261&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); M-ZnP, medium-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, 523&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); H-ZnP, high-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, 784&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); ZnO, zinc oxide group, (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, 232&#8201;mg/day of zinc oxide).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The effects of different zinc sources on plasma trace element concentrations are presented in <xref rid="tab5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>. Neither zinc source nor zinc dose affected plasma Ca, Cu, Fe, and Mg concentrations. However, plasma zinc concentrations increased linearly as the dose of ZnP increased (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01). Plasma concentrations of zinc were significantly higher in the M-ZnP, H-ZnP, and ZnO groups than in the CON and L-ZnP groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Effects of different zinc sources and concentrations on plasma trace element concentrations of preweaned Holstein dairy calves.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Item</th><th align="center" valign="middle" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Treatment<xref rid="tfn8" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">SEM</th><th align="center" valign="middle" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CON</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-ZnP</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M-ZnP</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-ZnP</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZnO</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linear</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quadratic</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trt</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trt&#8201;&#215;&#8201;day</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zinc, mg/L</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.53<sup>bc</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.89<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.852</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcium, mg/L</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">118.21</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">119.93</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">119.45</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">116.34</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">119.52</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.487</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.232</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.977</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.702</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.113</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Copper, mg/L</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.813</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.981</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.986</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.074</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iron, mg/L</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.64</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.533</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.531</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.339</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.285</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.779</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Magnesium, mg/L</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.38</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.13</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.83</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.93</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.34</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.630</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.118</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.323</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.814</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a,b,c</sup>Significant differences within the same row (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05).</p><fn id="tfn8"><label>a</label><p>CON, control group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, no zinc proteinate or zinc oxide supplementation); L-ZnP, low-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, 261&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); M-ZnP, medium-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, 523&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); H-ZnP, high-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, 784&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); ZnO, zinc oxide group, (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12, 232&#8201;mg/day of zinc oxide).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec13"><label>3.3.</label><title>Rectal microbial diversity</title><p>The effects of different zinc sources on rectal microbial diversity on day 70 are presented in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figures 1</xref>, <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. Indicators of &#945; diversity showed that neither zinc supplementation nor zinc source affected the Chao1, Observed species, Shannon, and Simpson indices on day 70 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). A plot of PCoA scores showed shifts of principal component between the CON and L-ZnP groups (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.13, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.048), the L-ZnP and ZnO groups (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.24, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.012), and the H-ZnP and ZnO groups (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.21, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.023) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Effects of different zinc sources on rectal microbial &#945;-diversity of Holstein dairy calves on day 70. CON, control group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, no zinc proteinate or zinc oxide supplementation); L-ZnP, low-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, 261&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); M-ZnP, medium-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, 523&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); H-ZnP, high-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, 784&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); ZnO, zinc oxide group, (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, 232&#8201;mg/day of zinc oxide).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1236635-g001.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Principal coordinates analysis (PCoA) of the effects of different zinc sources on rectal microbiota of Holstein dairy calves on day 70. CON, control group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, no zinc proteinate or zinc oxide supplementation); L-ZnP, low-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, 261&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); M-ZnP, medium-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, 523&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); H-ZnP, high-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, 784&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); ZnO, zinc oxide group, (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, 232&#8201;mg/day of zinc oxide).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1236635-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec14"><label>3.4.</label><title>Rectal microbiota composition at the phylum level</title><p>The effects of different zinc sources on the rectal microbial composition at the phylum level on day 70 are shown in <xref rid="tab6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>. Firmicutes and Bacteroidetes were the dominant phyla, followed by Actinobacteria, Proteobacteria, Cyanobacteria, and Fusobacteria. The relative abundance of Firmicutes was lower in the ZnO group than in the CON and H-ZnP groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). In contrast, the relative abundance of Bacteroidetes was higher in the ZnO group than in the CON and L-ZnP groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Analysis of the principal rectal phyla in preweaned Holstein dairy calves on day 70.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Phylum, %</th><th align="center" valign="middle" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Treatment<xref rid="tfn9" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">SEM</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CON</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-ZnP</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M-ZnP</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-ZnP</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZnO</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Firmicutes</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.43<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.57<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.46<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.14<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.81<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.048</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bacteroidetes</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.54<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.69<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.63<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.43<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.05<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Actinobacteria</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.987</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proteobacteria</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.342</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyanobacteria</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.128</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fusobacteria</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.411</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a,b</sup>Significant differences within the same row (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05).</p><fn id="tfn9"><label>a</label><p>CON, control group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, no zinc proteinate or zinc oxide supplementation); L-ZnP, low-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, 261&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); M-ZnP, medium-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, 523&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); H-ZnP, high-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, 784&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); ZnO, zinc oxide group, (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, 232&#8201;mg/day of zinc oxide).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec15"><label>3.5.</label><title>Rectal microbiota composition at the genus level</title><p>The effects of different zinc sources on the rectal microbial composition at the genus level on day 70 are shown in <xref rid="tab7" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>. <italic toggle="yes">Faecalibacterium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidaceae_Bacteroides</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Blautia</italic> were the dominant genera, followed by <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Oscillospira</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Subdoligranulum</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Odoribacte</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Dorea</italic> (<xref rid="tab7" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>). Early supplementation with ZnO increased the relative abundances of <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05), <italic toggle="yes">Subdoligranulum</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05), and <italic toggle="yes">Odoribacter</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) compared with the CON group. There were no differences in the composition of rectal microflora at the genus level among the three ZnP groups and the CON group, except that the relative abundance of Odoribacter was higher in the H-ZnP group than in the CON group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab7" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Analysis of rectal microflora composition at the genus level in preweaned Holstein dairy calves on day 70.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Genus, %</th><th align="center" valign="middle" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Treatment<xref rid="tfn10" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">SEM</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CON</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-ZnP</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M-ZnP</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H-ZnP</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZnO</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Faecalibacterium</italic>
</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.76</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.50</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.27</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.85</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.535</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidaceae_Bacteroides</italic>
</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.29</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.38</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.35</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.26</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.077</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic>
</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.92<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.36<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.66<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.51<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.46<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Blautia</italic>
</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.14</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.92</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.06</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.83</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.96</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.533</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic>
</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.38</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.57</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.795</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Oscillospira</italic>
</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.08</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.18</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.34</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.34</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Subdoligranulum</italic>
</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.32<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Odoribacter</italic>
</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Dorea</italic>
</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.842</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a,b</sup>Significant differences within the same row (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05).</p><fn id="tfn10"><label>a</label><p>CON, control group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, no zinc proteinate or zinc oxide supplementation); L-ZnP, low-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, 261&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); M-ZnP, medium-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, 523&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); H-ZnP, high-zinc proteinate group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, 784&#8201;mg/day of zinc proteinate); ZnO, zinc oxide group, (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;8, 232&#8201;mg/day of zinc oxide).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec16"><label>3.6.</label><title>Correlation of rectal microbiota with growth performance, antioxidant indicators, and plasma zinc concentrations</title><p>Analyses of the correlation of rectal microbiota with the growth performance, antioxidant indicators, and plasma zinc concentrations of calves on day 70 showed that the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Subdoligranulum</italic> was positively associated with ADG (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Interaction heatmaps showing the associations between the relative abundances of rectal bacterial phyla and genera and the growth performance, antioxidant indicators, and plasma zinc concentrations of Holstein dairy calves on day 70. ADG, average daily gain; total DMI, total dry matter intake; starter DMI, starter dry matter intake; F:G, feed to gain; final BW, final body weight; IgG, immunoglobulin G.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1236635-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussions" id="sec17"><label>4.</label><title>Discussion</title><p>Zinc is an essential trace mineral for humans and animals with effective antidiarrheal and growth promotion activities (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Lower doses of zinc, especially in organic forms, can reduce diarrhea and promote the growth of young animals (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). In agreement with these findings, the present study found that dietary supplementation with ZnP linearly increased total DMI, ADG, and feed efficiency, thus increasing the final BW of preweaned dairy calves. Furthermore, compared with the control group, supplementation with ZnP to yield 80&#8201;mg/day of zinc significantly enhanced the growth performance of dairy calves (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). In the present study, supplementation with ZnP to yield 80&#8201;mg/day zinc exhibited growth promotion effects similar to that of ZnO yielding 180&#8201;mg/day zinc, except for the final BW. Besides, the incidence of diarrhea is also a factor in evaluating the health status of calves. Diarrhea occurs frequently during the first month of life (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). The present study found that the incidence of diarrhea declined as the calves grew older. The incidence of diarrhea in the CON group fluctuated from 4.17 to 18.2 during the experimental period and peaked during the first 28&#8201;days of life, during which supplementation with ZnP and ZnO significantly reduced the incidence of diarrhea. Notably, calves in the M-ZnP and ZnO groups showed significant reductions in the incidence of diarrhea compared with the CON group on days 1&#8211;28, and 29&#8211;56. Overall, considering the source and concentrations of ZnP, the study suggests that dietary zinc supplementation to preweaned dairy calves in the form of ZnP (80&#8201;mg/day zinc), can positively boost their growth performance by reducing the occurrence of diarrhea.</p><p>Zinc is essential for the function of the immune system, thus affecting cells of both the innate and adaptive immune systems (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Zinc deficiency has been shown to impair immune function, which can be restored and even improved by zinc supplementation, especially during early life (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Supplementation with ZnO was found to increase serum concentrations of IgG in piglets 14&#8201;days after weaning but did not affect serum antibody concentrations 28&#8201;days after weaning (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Similarly, in the present study, dietary supplementation with ZnP or ZnO did not affect immunoglobulin indices of preweaned dairy calves. This may be due to the relatively long experimental period of the present study. However, the antidiarrheal effect of dietary zinc has been associated with its immune effect (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>), and dietary zinc supplementation has been reported to improve immune function by increasing the serum IgG content of calves (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). The findings of the present study, showing that serum IgG concentrations increased linearly with ZnP dose, were consistent with these earlier results.</p><p>Reactive oxygen species, which are generated during normal cellular respiration, can be scavenged by the free radical scavenging system (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Zinc acts as an antioxidant by promoting the free radical scavenging system in the body (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). The SOD is involved in the cellular scavenging of free radicals and reactive oxygen species (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). In this study, serum SOD activities were higher in the M-ZnP and ZnO groups than in the CON group. This aligned with the results showing that dietary supplementation with 30&#8201;mg/kg zinc DM in the form of ZnP or zinc sulfate (ZnSO<sub>4</sub>) enhanced serum SOD activities in lambs (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Furthermore, the harmful effects of reactive oxygen species accumulation can be prevented by GSH-Px (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), which metabolizes hydrogen peroxide and lipid peroxides to water and harmless oxy compounds (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). The present study found that serum GSH-Px activities were increased by dietary supplementation with ZnP or ZnO, with increasing levels of ZnP supplementation associated with a linear increase in serum GSH-Px activity. T-AOC is an antioxidant biomarker (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>), whereas MDA is an end-product of lipid peroxidation regarded as a marker of oxidative stress and antioxidant status (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). In the present study, supplementation with ZnP linearly increased serum T-AOC activity and decreased serum MDA concentration, indicating that ZnP enhanced antioxidant activity in dairy calves.</p><p>Plasma trace element concentration is the most direct reflection of body trace element status, with alterations in plasma zinc concentration being highly sensitive to changes in dietary zinc content (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Dietary supplementation with Zn-Met or ZnO during the first 2&#8201;weeks of life increased plasma zinc concentrations in calves (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). The present study found that increases in plasma zinc concentrations in dairy calves correlated with increasing doses of ZnP supplement, and that supplementation with ZnP to yield &#8805;80&#8201;mg/day zinc was associated with significantly higher plasma zinc concentrations compared with the CON group. Although different sources of zinc did not affect plasma zinc concentrations, the dose of ZnO was relatively higher than that of ZnP, suggesting that the bioavailability of ZnP was higher than that of ZnO. This finding was in good agreement with previous studies showing that organic zinc had higher bioavailability than inorganic zinc (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>).</p><p>Zinc has been shown to alter the structure of gut microbes (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47&#8211;49</xref>). In the present study, the dominant phyla in the rectum of dairy calves from birth to day 70 were Firmicutes and Bacteroidetes, consistent with previous findings (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Furthermore, the relative abundance of Firmicutes in the ZnO group was lower on day 70, which may be due to the bacteriostatic effects of zinc ions in the intestinal lumen (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). Zinc proteinate was absorbed in its intact form and therefore did not affect Firmicutes (<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Interestingly, some bacteria have strong tolerance to zinc ions (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroides</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic>, belong to Bacteroidetes) (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>), which may explain the greater relative abundance of Bacteroidetes in the ZnO group on day 70. Bacteroidetes generally produce butyrate, which has antitumor properties, presents the main energy source for enterocytes, and enhances intestinal health by maintaining mucosal integrity (<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). In the present study, supplementation with ZnO increased the abundance of Bacteroidetes, improving intestinal health. <italic toggle="yes">Faecalibacterium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidance-Bacteroides</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> were the main intestinal genera from day 1 to day 70, a finding consistent with previous results (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> protects mucosal and epithelial tissues by inducing lymphocytes to secrete cytokines (<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Subdoligranulum</italic> is contributing to increasing ADG, with the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Subdoligranulum</italic> positively correlating with ADG (<xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). Consistent with these reports, the present study found that the relative abundances of <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Subdoligranulum</italic> were higher in the ZnO group than in the CON group, which may have contributed to the higher ADG in ZnO-treated dairy calves. ZnP supplementation increased the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Odoribacter</italic>, which may help improve the intestinal health of dairy calves, as <italic toggle="yes">Odoribacter</italic> is a type of beneficial bacterium that can also produce butyrate (<xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec18"><label>5.</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>The present study showed that early supplementation with ZnP or ZnO to yield more than 80&#8201;mg/day zinc during the first 2&#8201;weeks of life reduced neonatal diarrhea from day 1 to day 28, and increased the DMI, ADG, and feed efficiency of preweaned dairy calves. Furthermore, supplementation with ZnP linearly increased serum IgG concentration, GSH-Px and T-AOC activities, and plasma zinc content but reduced serum MDA concentration. The effects of supplementation with ZnP to yield 80&#8201;mg/day zinc were similar to the effects of supplementation with ZnO to yield 180&#8201;mg/day zinc, except that the final BW of calves was higher in the ZnO group. Early supplementation with ZnP did not affect rectal microbial diversity or composition, whereas ZnO reduced the relative abundance of the phylum Firmicutes while increasing the relative abundance of the phylum Bacteroidetes, and enhanced the abundance of the genera <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Subdoligranulum</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Odoribacter</italic>. This study demonstrated that ZnP is a potential organic source of zinc with greater bioavailability than ZnO for preweaned dairy calves. Zinc proteinate yielding doses of 80&#8201;mg/day zinc is recommended for early dietary supplementation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec19"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The datasets presented in this study can be found in online repositories. The names of the repository/repositories and accession number(s) can be found in the article/supplementary material.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="sec20"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The animal study was approved by the Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences Animal Care and Use Committee. The study was conducted in accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements.</p></sec><sec id="sec21"><title>Author contributions</title><p>JL and PS designed the experiment. JL, XY, FM, YW, and YJ carried out the experiment. JL and XY wrote the manuscript. NH and PS revised the manuscript. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="sec22"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was financially supported by the National Key Research and Development Program of China (2022YFD1300505 and 2022YFD1301101), the earmarked fund for China Agriculture Research System (CARS-37), and the Agricultural Science and Technology Innovation Program (cxgc-ias-07, Beijing, China).</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec23"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec100"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors thank Zhu Ma and Kangkang Chu in Beijing Dairy Cattle Centre, Beijing, China for their support on the animal experiment.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="fn0001"><p>
<sup>1</sup>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.Genescloud.cn" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.Genescloud.cn</ext-link>
</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klotz</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heitmann</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rumen development, intestinal growth and hepatic metabolism in the pre- and postweaning ruminant</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>87</volume>:<fpage>E55</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(04)70061-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinrichs</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinrichs</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A prospective study of calf factors affecting first-lactation and lifetime milk production and age of cows when removed from the herd</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>336</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2010-3170</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21183043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dystrophinopathies</article-title>. <source>Handb Clin Neurol</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>101</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>39</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-08-045031-5.00002-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21496622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Constable</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial use in the treatment of calf diarrhea</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1892/0891-6640(2004)18&amp;#x0003c;8:auitto&amp;#x0003e;2.0.co;2</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14765726</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7197454</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Binversie</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruegg</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Combs</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ollivett</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Randomized clinical trial to assess the effect of antibiotic therapy on health and growth of preweaned dairy calves diagnosed with respiratory disease using respiratory scoring and lung ultrasound</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>103</volume>:<fpage>11723</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2019-18044</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33222860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashem</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosny</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Desoky</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soltan</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elolimy</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sallam</surname><given-names>SMA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Alginate nanoencapsulated synbiotic composite of pomegranate peel phytogenics and multi-probiotic species as a potential feed additive: physicochemical, antioxidant, and antimicrobial activities</article-title>. <source>Animals</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>2432</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani13152432</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37570241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10417444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luan</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of montmorillonite-zinc oxide hybrid on performance, diarrhea, intestinal permeability and morphology of weanling pigs</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>177</volume>:<fpage>108</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2012.07.028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grilli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tugnoli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vitari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Domeneghini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morlacchini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Low doses of microencapsulated zinc oxide improve performance and modulate the ileum architecture, inflammatory cytokines and tight junctions expression of weaned pigs</article-title>. <source>Animal</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1760</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1751731115001329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26189883</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Juste Contin Gomes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stampini</surname><given-names>DMH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tako</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of iron and zinc biofortified foods on gut microbiota <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Gallus gallus</italic>): a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Nutrients</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>189</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu13010189</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33435398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7827887</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>FAM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kishawy</surname><given-names>ATY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moustafa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roushdy</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Growth performance, tissue precipitation, metallothionein and cytokine transcript expression and economics in response to different dietary zinc sources in growing rabbits</article-title>. <source>J Anim Physiol Anim Nutr</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>105</volume>:<fpage>965</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jpn.13550</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33871882</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valenzano</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mercado</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zurbach</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mullin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Zinc supplementation modifies tight junctions and alters barrier function of CACO-2 human intestinal epithelial layers</article-title>. <source>Dig Dis Sci</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>77</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>87</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10620-012-2328-8</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22903217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muszy&#324;ski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomaszewska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwiecie&#324;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobrowolski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomczyk-Warunek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Subsequent somatic axis and bone tissue metabolism responses to a low-zinc diet with or without phytase inclusion in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>e0191964</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0191964</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29373588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5786321</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of zinc methionine supplementation on laying performance, zinc status, intestinal morphology, and expressions of zinc transporters&#8217; mRNA in laying hens</article-title>. <source>J Sci Food Agric</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>6582</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.9941</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31328268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wo</surname><given-names>YQL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Zinc-methionine acts as an anti-diarrheal agent by protecting the intestinal epithelial barrier in postnatal Holstein dairy calves</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>270</volume>:<fpage>114686</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2020.114686</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Supplementation with zinc proteinate increases the growth performance by reducing the incidence of diarrhea and improving the immune function of dairy calves during the first month of life</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>911330</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.911330</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35847636</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9284037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll1">AAFCO</collab></person-group>. <source>Official publication</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, IN</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Association of American Feed Control Officials, Inc.</publisher-name> (<year>2000</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagalakshmi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhanalakshmi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Himabindu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of dose and source of supplemental zinc on immune response and oxidative enzymes in lambs</article-title>. <source>Vet Res Commun</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>631</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11259-009-9212-9</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19214767</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll2">AOAC International</collab></person-group>. <source>Official methods of analysis</source>. <edition>17th</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Arlington, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>AOAC International</publisher-name> (<year>2000</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll3">AOAC International</collab></person-group>. <source>Official methods of analysis</source>. <edition>17th</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Gaithersburg, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>AOAC International</publisher-name> (<year>2003</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll4">AOAC International</collab></person-group>. <source>Official methods of analysis</source>. <edition>18th</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>AOAC International</publisher-name> (<year>2005</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Soest</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Methods for dietary fiber, neutral detergent fiber, and nonstarch polysaccharides in relation to animal nutrition</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci</source>. (<year>1991</year>) <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>3583</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>97</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(91)78551-2</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1660498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puschner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossow</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lehenbauer</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Champagne</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A double-blind block randomized clinical trial on the effect of zinc as a treatment for diarrhea in neonatal Holstein calves under natural challenge conditions</article-title>. <source>Prev Vet Med</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>112</volume>:<fpage>338</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>47</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.prevetmed.2013.09.001</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24074841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7114245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of differing amounts of zinc oxide supplementation on the antioxidant status and zinc metabolism in newborn dairy calves</article-title>. <source>Livestock Sci</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>230</volume>:<fpage>103819</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.livsci.2019.103819</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Divers</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stokol</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bicalho</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of crofelemer extract on severity and consistency of experimentally induced enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> diarrhea in newborn Holstein calves</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>8035</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2015-9513</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26298758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of different types of zinc supplement on the growth, incidence of diarrhea, immune function, and rectal microbiota of newborn dairy calves</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>103</volume>:<fpage>6100</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2019-17610</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32307167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wo</surname><given-names>YQL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of the source of zinc on the tissue accumulation of zinc and jejunal mucosal zinc transporter expression in Holstein dairy calves</article-title>. <source>Animals</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1246</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani10081246</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32707966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7459842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Callahan</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McMurdie</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>DADA2: high-resolution sample inference from Illumina amplicon data</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>581</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.3869</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27214047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4927377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonaventura</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benedetti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albar&#232;de</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miossec</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Zinc and its role in immunity and inflammation</article-title>. <source>Autoimmun Rev</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>277</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>85</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.autrev.2014.11.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25462582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feldmann</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Champagne</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lehenbauer</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aly</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness of zinc supplementation on diarrhea and average daily gain in pre-weaned dairy calves: a double-blind, block-randomized, placebo-controlled clinical trial</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>e0219321</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0219321</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31291305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6619766</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Seedy</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abed</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yanni</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd El-Rahman</surname><given-names>SAA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> in neonatal diarrheic calves</article-title>. <source>Beni Suef Univ J Basic Appl Sci</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bjbas.2015.11.010</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32363209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7185456</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maares</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haase</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Zinc and immunity: an essential interrelation</article-title>. <source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>611</volume>:<fpage>58</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.abb.2016.03.022</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27021581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wessels</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maywald</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rink</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Zinc as a gatekeeper of immune function</article-title>. <source>Nutrients</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1286</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu9121286</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29186856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5748737</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ackland</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michalczyk</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Zinc and infant nutrition</article-title>. <source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>611</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.abb.2016.06.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27317042</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of prepartum zinc-methionine supplementation on feed digestibility, rumen fermentation patterns, immunity status, and passive transfer of immunity in dairy cows</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>103</volume>:<fpage>8976</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>85</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2019-17991</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32713690</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of nano zinc oxide as an alternative to pharmacological dose of zinc oxide on growth performance, diarrhea, immune responses, and intestinal microflora profile in weaned piglets</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>258</volume>:<fpage>114312</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2019.114312</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of dietary zinc oxide nanoparticles supplementation on growth performance, zinc status, intestinal morphology, microflora population, and immune response in weaned pigs</article-title>. <source>J Sci Food Agric</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>1366</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.9312</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30094852</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomasi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Volpato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>WAB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Debastiani</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bottari</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morsch</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Metaphylactic effect of minerals on the immune response, biochemical variables and antioxidant status of newborn calves</article-title>. <source>J Anim Physiol Anim Nutr</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>102</volume>:<fpage>819</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jpn.12890</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29603406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Zinc: an antioxidant and anti-inflammatory agent: role of zinc in degenerative disorders of aging</article-title>. <source>J Trace Elem Med Biol</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>364</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtemb.2014.07.019</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25200490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Critical role of zinc as either an antioxidant or a prooxidant in cellular systems</article-title>. <source>Oxidative Med Cell Longev</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>2018</volume>:<fpage>9156285</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2018/9156285</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29743987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5884210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fridovich</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Superoxide radical and superoxide dismutases</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source>. (<year>1995</year>) <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>112</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.bi.64.070195.000525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7574505</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alimohamady</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aliarabi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruckmaier</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of different sources of supplemental zinc on performance, nutrient digestibility, and antioxidant enzyme activities in lambs</article-title>. <source>Biol Trace Elem Res</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>189</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12011-018-1448-1</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30032401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Handy</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loscalzo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of glutathione peroxidase-1 in health and disease</article-title>. <source>Free Radic Biol Med</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>188</volume>:<fpage>146</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2022.06.004</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35691509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9586416</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aktas</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kandemir</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirbas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanedan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aydin</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of oxidative stress in sheep infected with <italic toggle="yes">Psoroptes ovis</italic> using total antioxidant capacity, total oxidant status, and malondialdehyde level</article-title>. <source>J Vet Res</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>197</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>201</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/jvetres-2017-0025</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29978073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5894390</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gawe&#322;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wardas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niedworok</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wardas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Malondialdehyde (MDA) as a lipid peroxidation marker</article-title>. <source>Wiad Lek</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>453</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15765761</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wieringa</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dijkhuizen</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiorentino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laillou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Determination of zinc status in humans: which indicator should we use?</article-title><source>Nutrients</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>3252</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu7053252</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25954900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4446750</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaeffer</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spears</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bioavailability of zinc hydroxychloride relative to zinc sulfate in growing cattle fed a corn-cottonseed hull-based diet</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>232</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2017.07.013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vahjen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pieper</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zentek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Increased dietary zinc oxide changes the bacterial core and enterobacterial composition in the ileum of piglets</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>2430</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/jas.2010-3270</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21383037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Starke</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pieper</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zentek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vahjen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of high dietary zinc oxide on the development of the intestinal microbiota in weaned piglets</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Ecol</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>87</volume>:<fpage>416</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1574-6941.12233</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24118028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pieper</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dadi</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pieper</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vahjen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reinert</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Concentration and chemical form of dietary zinc shape the porcine colon microbiome, its functional capacity and antibiotic resistance gene repertoire</article-title>. <source>ISME J</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>2783</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41396-020-0730-3</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32747713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7784847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jami</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Israel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kotser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizrahi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Exploring the bovine rumen bacterial community from birth to adulthood</article-title>. <source>ISME J</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1069</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>79</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ismej.2013.2</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23426008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3660679</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malmuthuge</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Regulation of rumen development in neonatal ruminants through microbial metagenomes and host transcriptomes</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>172</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-019-1786-0</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31443695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6708143</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liedtke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vahjen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> antibacterial activity of zinc oxide on a broad range of reference strains of intestinal origin</article-title>. <source>Vet Microbiol</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>160</volume>:<fpage>251</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2012.05.013</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22673319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>XG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Organic zinc absorption by the intestine of broilers <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic></article-title>. <source>Br J Nutr</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>117</volume>:<fpage>1086</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007114517001040</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28528581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milner</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary modulation of colon cancer risk</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>137</volume>:<fpage>2576S</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9S</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jn/137.11.2576S</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17951506</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cosgrove</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lockett</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Head</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Topping</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A review of the potential mechanisms for the lowering of colorectal oncogenesis by butyrate</article-title>. <source>Br J Nutr</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>108</volume>:<fpage>820</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007114512001948</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22676885</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Enjalbert</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Combes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cauquil</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchez</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monteils</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Establishment of ruminal bacterial community in dairy calves from birth to weaning is sequential</article-title>. <source>J Appl Microbiol</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>116</volume>:<fpage>245</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>57</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.12405</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24279326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The immune response to <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> bacteria in chronic inflammatory disease</article-title>. <source>Immunology</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>151</volume>:<fpage>363</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/imm.12760</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28542929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5506432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>QL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Drinking water supplemented with acidifiers improves the growth performance of weaned pigs and potentially regulates antioxidant capacity, immunity, and gastrointestinal microbiota diversity</article-title>. <source>Antioxidants</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>809</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antiox11050809</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35624673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9138078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hiippala</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barreto</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burrello</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz-Basabe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suutarinen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kainulainen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Novel <italic toggle="yes">Odoribacter splanchnicus</italic> strain and its outer membrane vesicles exert immunoregulatory effects <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic></article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>575455</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.575455</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33281770</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7689251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>