<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">iScience</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">iScience</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">3532</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">isci</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>iScience</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2589-0042</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12182317</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12182317.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12182317</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12182317</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40546954</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.isci.2025.112709</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2589-0042(25)00970-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">112709</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Light quality and time in shelter modulate behavior and cortisol in the domestic cat (<italic toggle="yes">Felis catus</italic>)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yaw</surname><given-names initials="AM">Alexandra M.</given-names></name><email>yawalexa@msu.edu</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">2</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#8727;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardella</surname><given-names initials="ME">Mary E.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names initials="J">Jacquelyn</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names initials="HM">Hanne M.</given-names></name><email>hanne@msu.edu</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor2" ref-type="corresp">&#8727;&#8727;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Animal Science, Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI 48824, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#8727;</label>Corresponding author <email>yawalexa@msu.edu</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2"><label>&#8727;&#8727;</label>Corresponding author <email>hanne@msu.edu</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>2</label><p id="ntpara0010">Lead contact</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>20</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>28</volume><issue>6</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">489934</issue-id><elocation-id>112709</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>25</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>20</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>21</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-06-24 15:25:17.200"><day>24</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2025 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="main.pdf"/><abstract id="abs0010"><title>Summary</title><p>Light is a principal synchronizer of behavior, circadian rhythms, and hormone release patterns, including stress responses. High stress in domestic cats (<italic toggle="yes">Felis catus</italic>) increases risk of disease, promotes undesirable behaviors, and is associated with reduced adoptions from shelters. To determine how light properties impact stress and behavioral activity patterns in cats, the effects of light intensity and composition were tested in 101 male and female cats using standard, dim, and dim, blue-depleted light during the initial five days in a shelter environment. Cats exhibited circadian locomotor activity, peaking at lights on, in all light conditions. Cortisol levels decreased under dim, blue-depleted light versus standard light on day 5. Probability of hiding was only increased in the dim light condition. A behavioral approach test showed declined behavioral stress markers over time in the shelter. Here, we demonstrate that indoor light conditions and length of time in shelter modulate stress in cats.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015"><title>Graphical abstract</title><fig id="undfig1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fx1.jpg"/></fig></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="abs0020"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="ulist0010"><list-item id="u0010"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0010">Light intensity, light composition, and time in shelter modulated urinary cortisol levels</p></list-item><list-item id="u0015"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0015">Behavioral markers of stress in cats decreased over the first five days in the shelter</p></list-item><list-item id="u0020"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0020">All cats had circadian activity patterns, with peak activity when the lights turned on</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0025"><p>Molecular biology; Neuroscience</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Subject areas</title><kwd>Molecular biology</kwd><kwd>Neuroscience</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><p id="misc9010">Published: May 20, 2025</p></notes></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0025">As organisms evolved to the Earth&#8217;s 24-h day/night cycles, species have adapted to fit temporal niches.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> The timing of behaviors and physiological functions to specific times of day not only aids survival by predicting changes in the environment, reducing predation, and increasing reproductive success, but also contributes to overall health. Light is a primary signal that entrains circadian rhythms in mammals and is a complex variable comprising several qualities, including intensity, spectral composition (wavelength), duration (photoperiod), and time of day of exposure. Each quality contributes to an organism&#8217;s ability to synchronize physiological functions and behaviors to external time of day.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> Not only are light qualities essential to the maintenance of robust circadian rhythms, but in mammals, both light intensity and composition are established modulators of mood, stress responses, sleep-wake cycles, and locomotor activity.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> Many mammals, including humans and laboratory rodents, respond to light properties such that bright light and short (blue) wavelengths act as more powerful stimulatory cues to entrain circadian rhythms compared to dim light and longer (red) wavelengths.<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> While light has well-established roles modulating circadian rhythms, including stress responses, the impact of light on animal wellbeing in captive environments has been understudied.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref></p><p id="p0030">The domestic cat (<italic toggle="yes">Felis catus</italic>) is a species of particular interest due to their roles as companion animals and biomedical research subjects for translational and veterinary studies.<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> Additionally, domestic cats have a high degree of conserved genetic and behavioral similarities with wild cats in the Felidae family.<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> Domestic cats are used as a research model for wild cats, commonly focused on reproduction, which has led to essential insights for overcoming breeding difficulties in wild felid species.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> Not only is understating how domestic cats respond to light important for informing housing conditions in research facilities and shelters, but this information can also provide a starting point for determining the impacts of light qualities on other Felidae species housed in captivity and may be of particular relevance for Felidae species that are involved to conservation breeding programs.</p><p id="p0035">Stress is broadly defined as actual or anticipated threats to wellbeing and/or threats to the disruption of homeostasis.<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> In domestic cats, high stress is linked to increased health risks, increased aggressive and compulsive behaviors<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> and reduced adoptions.<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> Stress-related information is relayed to the brain via sensory input, which in turn relays neural and endocrine signals to adapt to a perceived threat or homeostatic imbalance.<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> These adaptations include both autonomic nervous system responses, which provide immediate reflexive responses to stressor exposures, and hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenocortical axis activation, which results in neuroendocrine release of glucocorticoids. Light information modulates autonomic nervous system responses in cats, including autonomic nervous system&#8211;driven pupillary reflexes;<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> however, our understating of light&#8217;s impact on hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenocortical activation in domestic cats is less established. In other mammals, such as humans and laboratory rodents, light information is translated from the eye to the suprachiasmatic nucleus,<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> a brain region essential for coordinating timekeeping and circadian rhythms. The suprachiasmatic nucleus then projects to the paraventricular nucleus, which is a major stress regulation center,<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> providing a link between light and hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenocortical axis stress responses. In domestic cats, light is translated from the eye to the suprachiasmatic nucleus,<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> but the connections between light, stress, and circadian rhythms in this species are still not well understood.</p><p id="p0040">In terms of circadian timekeeping, the temporal niche of the domestic cat is highly variable, with reports of domestic cats exhibiting circadian<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> and polyphasic<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> and a lack of circadian rhythms.<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> When domestic cats display circadian rhythms, multiple chronotypes (diurnal, nocturnal, and crepuscular)<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref> are found, suggesting that the environment strongly influences the expression of locomotor activity patterns in cats.<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref> It is currently hypothesized that cats exhibit weak endogenous circadian activity rhythms that are highly entrainable to environmental conditions, including social interactions with humans and conspecifics, food availability, and light.<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref> Despite this knowledge, the capacity of light qualities to modulate physiology and behavior in domestic cats remains largely unknown. The Association of Shelter Veterinarians&#8217; Guidelines for Standards of Care in Animal Shelters recommends lighting that promotes a safe work environment for the staff and effective observation of animals.<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref> This recommendation suggests designing facilities to incorporate as much natural sunlight as possible and, if artificial lighting is necessary, to approximate natural light duration and intensity. These guidelines are largely based on research in non-feline mammals, primarily humans and rodents, that have well characterized circadian (24h) rhythms that are strongly modulated by light.<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr"><sup>43</sup></xref> However, it is important to note that indoor artificial lighting is very different from sunlight, where indoor lighting intensity is much lower and has a reduced spectrum of emitted wavelengths.<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr"><sup>44</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr"><sup>45</sup></xref> Increasing our understanding of how light properties modulate domestic cat circadian rhythms and stress in captive environments, such as animal rescues, shelters, catteries, and research laboratories, is important for both animal welfare and academic rigor in veterinary and biomedical research.</p><p id="p0045">Given the importance of light in regulating circadian rhythms and stress, our goals were to (1) determine how light intensity and composition modulate cat stress and (2) characterize behavioral circadian rhythms of cats in a shelter environment in response to the studied light conditions. We hypothesized that reducing room light intensity and removing blue light wavelengths would reduce cat stress compared to standard white, LED lighting.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>Light conditions and time in the shelter impact cortisol, hiding, and overall activity levels</title><p id="p0050">While the impacts of light quality on domestic cats are largely unknown, light quality has begun to emerge as a new target for improving the welfare of animals used for production and in zoo and aquarium settings.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr"><sup>46</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr"><sup>47</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr"><sup>48</sup></xref> In collaboration with a Midwestern animal control and shelter, we evaluated the impact of three light conditions on intact cats admitted to the shelter over 19 months (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>A). As multiple aspects of light quality are known to modulate physiology and behavior,<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr"><sup>49</sup></xref> we analyzed both light intensity and composition in three types of lighting (standard, dim, and dim, blue-depleted; the latter will be referred to as orange based on the human perception of the blue-depleted light in the cat holding room (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figures 1</xref>B and 1C).<fig id="fig1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Diagrams of experimental timelines and shelter housing</p><p>(A) Experimental timeline of data collection and lighting conditions over 19 months. Box color indicates lighting conditions with light gray for standard lighting, dark gray for dim lighting, and orange for dim, blue-depleted lighting.</p><p>(B) The dimensions and layout for the shelter housing room and cat housing units. Smaller cat housing units are indicated by &#8220;&#8727;&#8221; and the location of the door to enter the room is indicated on the upper left.</p><p>(C) Individual cat units comprised two levels that cats were able to freely move between. The upper level was left empty and a litter pan, towels, and a stool covered with a towel (covered hiding spot) were placed on the lower level.</p><p>(D) Cats were enrolled into the study between 1300 and 1700h within the first 24h after they arrived at the shelter. Following enrollment, daily data for the approach test, urine collection, and PetPace data monitoring were collected through the date of unenrollment.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr1.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0055">To determine how standard, dim, and orange lighting altered physiological stress levels, we collected daily urinary cortisol for at least three days in 43 cats (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>D). Unaltered shelter overhead LED lighting (standard) was used as the control. Both dim and orange (dim, blue-depleted) lighting conditions were achieved through attaching light filters to the overhead lighting. Blue wavelengths (orange condition) were targeted for their importance in regulating both circadian rhythms and mood in mammals.<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr"><sup>50</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr"><sup>51</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr"><sup>52</sup></xref> Differences in the type of light are reflected in the representative spectral power distributions, 24h room light intensity, in-unit peak and dominant wavelengths, and in-unit intensity (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>A&#8211;2H). As the light filters for the orange condition significantly reduced the light intensity of the room (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>B and 2E), and light intensity also impacts circadian rhythms and stress,<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr"><sup>53</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr"><sup>54</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr"><sup>55</sup></xref> a dim light condition was included. There was a significant interaction of light condition and time in day (hours) on room light intensity, F(46, 138) = 22.33; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>B). Room light intensity did not differ during times of lights off (0000&#8211;0700h and 1700&#8211;2300h), but both dim and orange light had reduced intensity compared to standard light from 0800h to 1500h, while only orange differed from standard light at 1600h. Inside the cat units, orange lighting had a reduced peak in the blue-light portion (450&#8211;495nm; <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>F&#8211;2H) that is not present in standard or dim spectral power distributions, and standard light intensity (1.24 mW/m<sup>2</sup>) is higher than both dim (0.93 mW/m<sup>2</sup>) and orange light (0.82 mW/m<sup>2</sup>).<fig id="fig2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Cat unit lighting conditions for standard, dim and orange overhead lighting</p><p>(A) CIELUV 1976 chromaticity diagram displaying average cat unit perceived hue. Standard light is indicated by black square, dim light is indicated by white triangle, and orange light is indicated by white circle.</p><p>(B) Average cat room light intensity (lux) in standard, dim, and orange light conditions across time of day. &#8220;&#8727;&#8221; indicates significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) between both dim and orange light compared to standard and &#8220;#&#8221; indicates significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) between orange and standard light.</p><p>(C) Average peak wavelength (&#955;p), (D) dominant wavelength (&#955;d), and (E) light intensity from inside cat units were analyzed via two-way Analysis of Variance (n = 2&#8211;3 per light condition). Independent light measures are shown as circles, with white indicating standard light, gray indicating dim light, and orange indicating dim, blue-depleted (orange perceived) light. Data are represented as mean &#177; SEM. Different letters indicate significant differences, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05. Spectral power distribution for (F) standard, (G) dim, and (H) orange conditions.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr2.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0060">As previous studies have established that stress levels decrease across days as cats habituate to a new environment<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr"><sup>56</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr"><sup>58</sup></xref> and that sex differences are found in many species in both stress responses<xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr"><sup>59</sup></xref> and activity patterns,<xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr"><sup>60</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr"><sup>61</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr"><sup>62</sup></xref> we included day in the shelter and sex as variables in addition to light condition. There were no significant three-way interactions for urinary cortisol or PetPace activity scores (mixed model ANOVA, <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Urinary cortisol levels (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>A) were dependent on both light condition and day in shelter (F[6,100.43] = 2.22, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 15&#8211;20 per light condition, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.047). Cats in orange light on day 5 (1730 &#177; 349 pg/mL) had reduced cortisol (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.019) compared to cats in standard lighting (9861 &#177; 2093 pg/mL). In addition to cortisol levels, we measured cat hiding behavior (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>B), an established behavioral response to stress in cats.<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr"><sup>63</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr"><sup>64</sup></xref> Bayesian logistic regression with random intercepts for each individual cat to account for repeated measures (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) was used to predict the probability of hiding behavior as a function of sex, light condition, and day (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Under standard and orange light, the predicted probabilities of hiding were low (standard: 0.00&#8211;0.002; orange: &lt;0.002), with most estimates close to zero. Hiding probabilities were higher under dim lighting, with male cats demonstrating increased probabilities across days, peaking at day 4 (Estimate = 0.013, 95% Cl: [0, 0.083]) and day 5 (Estimate = 0.011, 95% Cl: [0, 0.087]). Female cats also had higher probabilities of hiding under dim light, in particular on day 5 (Estimate = 0.029, 95% Cl: [0, 0.191]), suggesting increased hiding in dim light, especially during later days in the shelter.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Mixed model ANOVA table (Type 3 tests, KR-method) for sex, day in shelter, and sex differences for cortisol (n = 4&#8211;12 per group), and PetPace activity score (n = 2&#8211;7 per group) for each light condition</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Effect</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">df</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="7" colspan="1">Cortisol</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex:Light:Day</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">6, 100.43</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.354</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Light:Day</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>6, 100.43</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.22</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.047</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex:Day</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3, 100.53</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.04</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.378</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex:Light</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2, 44.57</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.87</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.166</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Day</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3, 100.53</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>6.30</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2, 44.57</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.42</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.252</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1, 44.51</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.27</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.139</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7" colspan="1">PetPace Activity Score</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex:Light:Day</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3, 47</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.54</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.655</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light:Day</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4, 47</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.08</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.989</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex:Day</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2, 47</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.48</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.620</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex:Light</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2, 25.16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.47</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.249</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Day</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2, 47</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>5.68</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.006</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2, 24.8</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.87</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.431</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1, 25.05</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.28</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.604</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Significant data (p &lt; 0.05.) are bolded.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Light and/or time in shelter impact cortisol, hiding behavior, and activity levels in shelter cats</p><p>(A) Male and female cat urinary cortisol by day in shelter in standard, dim, and orange overhead lighting were analyzed via mixed model ANOVA (Type 3 tests, KR-method) for sex, day in shelter and sex differences, n = 4&#8211;12 per group. Data are represented as mean &#177; SEM.</p><p>(B) Percentage of male and female cats hiding during daily care by day in shelter in standard, dim, and orange lighting. Probability of hiding was analyzed via Bayesian logistic regression model, n = 4&#8211;19 per group.</p><p>(C) Male and female PetPace Activity scores by day in shelter in standard, dim, and orange lighting were analyzed via mixed model ANOVA (Type 3 tests, KR-method) for sex, day in shelter and sex differences, n = 2&#8211;7 per group. Individual cats are represented by circles with color indicating light condition. Data are represented as mean &#177; SEM. &#8220;&#8727;&#8221; indicates significant differences with <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr3.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Bayesian logistic regression model of posterior mean estimate, standard error, 95% credible interval (CI) and R-hat statisic for all main effects and interactions between sex, light condition, and day in shelter, as well as random intercepts for each individual cat to account for repeated measures in cat hiding behavior (n = 4&#8211;19 per group)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Term</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Estimate</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Est. Error</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI (Lower)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% CI (Upper)</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">R-hat</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Intercept</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;10.06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;14.57</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;6.49</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex Female (SexF)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.28</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.47</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;2.65</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Light Dim</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.51</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.46</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&#8722;0.34</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>5.34</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>1.00</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light Orange</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.46</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.59</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;2.68</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.48</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.62</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.31</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;3.21</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.87</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.51</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;3.15</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.08</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;2.74</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.59</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.09</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.40</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;2.85</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.52</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SexF:Light Dim</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.68</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.57</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;1.49</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.79</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SexF:Light Orange</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.69</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;3.17</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.45</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SexF:Day 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.19</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.44</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;2.69</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.98</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SexF:Day 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.73</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.49</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;3.81</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.17</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SexF:Day 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;1.20</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.49</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;4.19</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.73</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SexF:Day 5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.88</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.53</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;3.91</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.02</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light Dim:Day 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.38</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;2.52</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.89</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light Orange:Day 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.14</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.58</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;3.21</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.98</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light Dim:Day 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.39</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;1.34</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light Orange:Day 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;1.26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.73</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;4.74</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light Dim:Day 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.96</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.41</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.79</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.83</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light Orange:Day 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;1.37</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.68</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;4.74</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.86</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light Dim:Day 5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.52</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.48</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;1.30</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.43</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light Orange:Day 5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;1.06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.69</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;4.45</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SexF:Light Dim:Day 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.32</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.56</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;3.26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.83</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SexF:Light Orange:Day 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.91</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.67</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;2.45</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4.24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SexF:Light Dim:Day 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.16</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.55</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;2.87</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.24</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SexF:Light Orange:Day 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.73</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.84</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;4.46</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.88</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SexF:Light Dim:Day 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.31</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.52</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;3.28</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.68</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SexF:Light Orange:Day 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.67</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.84</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;4.34</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.84</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SexF:Light Dim:Day 5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.15</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.58</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;2.92</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">3.33</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">SexF:Light Orange:Day 5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.81</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.85</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;4.43</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.81</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.00</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>The reference group for the intercept was male cats on day 1 in standard light.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Predicted probabilities and mean estimates, standard errors, and 95% credible intervals (Cl) of hiding for each combination of sex, light condition, and day in shelter using the Bayesian logistic regression model&#8217;s posterior distributions (n = 4&#8211;19 per group)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Estimate</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Est. Error</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.5% CI</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">97.5% CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Standard</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00058</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Standard</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00076</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Standard</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00072</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Standard</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00098</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Standard</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00116</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Standard</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00096</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Standard</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00251</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Standard</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00093</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Standard</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00116</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Standard</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00283</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dim</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00513</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.014</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dim</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00557</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.014</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dim</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.006</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.01255</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.037</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dim</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.013</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02650</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.083</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dim</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.011</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02737</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.087</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dim</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.014</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02898</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.092</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dim</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.009</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.02136</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.059</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dim</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.018</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03478</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.118</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dim</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.020</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.03790</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.131</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dim</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.029</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.05622</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.191</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Orange</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00185</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Orange</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00334</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Orange</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00136</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Orange</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00206</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">M</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Orange</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00280</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Orange</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 1</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00439</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.010</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Orange</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 2</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00838</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.017</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Orange</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 3</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00138</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Orange</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 4</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00120</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Orange</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day 5</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.00207</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.002</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0065">To understand if increased hiding in the dim light may be limited to when human experimenters were present in the room or if increased hiding was persistent across each day, we analyzed overall activity levels via PetPace collars (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>C; <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). PetPace activity scores were only dependent on day in shelter (F[2, 47] = 5.68, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.006), with increased activity scores on day 3 (30.0 &#177; 3.19; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0014) and day 4 (29.7 &#177; 2.33; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0027) compared to day 2 (21.1 &#177; 2.41). To understand if changes in activity level were linked with stress response, we conducted correlation analyses of urinary cortisol levels with PetPace activity scores for each light condition (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). PetPace activity and cortisol were only correlated under standard light, where reduced activity was linked to increased cortisol levels, with no significant relationship in dim or orange light (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Pearson correlation data for urinary cortisol concentration with cat stress scores (CSS) and PetPace activity score for each light condition</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light Condition</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Pearson r</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">95% confidence interval</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">R<sup>2</sup></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">PetPace Activity Score</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Standard</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&#8722;0.40</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&#8722;0.62 to -0.11</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.16</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.0084</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dim</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.042</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.34 to 0.27</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0017</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.79</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Orange</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.53 to 0.12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.052</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">3 Feet</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Standard</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.45</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.18 to 0.70</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.21</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.0018</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dim</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.39</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.12 to 0.60</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.15</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.0055</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Orange</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.056</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.21 to 0.31</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0031</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.68</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Approach</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Standard</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.53</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.28 to 0.71</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.28</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.0002</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dim</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.41</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.15 to 0.62</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.17</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.0028</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Orange</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.0055</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.25 to 0.26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.97</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Hand Extended</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Standard</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.62</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.40 to 0.77</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.39</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.0001</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Dim</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.48</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.23 to 0.67</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.23</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.0004</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Orange</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.0095</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&#8722;0.27 to 0.25</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.094</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Males and females are combined. Significant data (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05.) are bolded, n = 45&#8211;60 per group.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Pearson correlations between cortisol and PetPace activity score</p><p>(A&#8211;C) Pearson correlations examining the relationship between cortisol and PetPace activity scores in (A) standard, (B) dim and (C) orange light. Individual cats are shown as circles, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 45-60 per group. R<sup>2</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> values are indicated next to linear regression lines. Dashed curves indicate 95% confidence intervals.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr4.jpg"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Shelter cats exhibited circadian rhythms in locomotor activity that did not depend on light condition</title><p id="p0070">As the PetPace-generated activity scores and hiding behavior only represent an averaged or singular point in time, we wanted to gain a higher resolution of locomotor activity patterns across individual cats&#8217; adaptation to the shelter environment. We exported raw data from the PetPace collars to analyze circadian rhythms using ClockLab Analysis 6 (Actimetrics, Wilmette, IL). All cats (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 29) were rhythmic (representative actograms: <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figures 5</xref>A&#8211;5F) and displayed circadian periods ranging from 21.5h to 24.83h (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>G). Period (Male: W = 0.96; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.62; Female: W = 0.87; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.29), Chi<sup>2</sup> amplitude (Male: W = 0.81; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.15; Female: W = 0.99; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.77), and activity profile (Male: W = 0.78; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.06; Female: W = 0.93; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.48) data passed Shapiro&#8211;Wilk test for normality. There were no interactions or main effects of light condition or sex (statistics reported in <xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>) on circadian period, Chi<sup>2</sup> amplitude (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>H), or activity profile amplitude (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>I). Representative Chi<sup>2</sup> periodograms depicting peaks of rhythmic activity (Qp values), with the highest peak corresponding to the estimated true period of the time series<xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr"><sup>65</sup></xref> and activity profiles are reported for males (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S1</xref>A&#8211;S1F) and females (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figures S1</xref>G&#8211;S1L) for each light condition.<fig id="fig5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Cat actigraphy under standard, dim, and orange lighting</p><p>Representative actograms for (A, C, and E) male and (B, D, and F) female cats over days 1&#8211;5 in the shelter.</p><p>(G) Circadian period (H) Chi<sup>2</sup> amplitude, and (I) activity profile amplitude were analyzed via two-way ANOVAs in standard, dim, and orange lighting, n = 2&#8211;7 per group. Data are represented as mean &#177; SEM. Individual cats are represented by circles (males) or diamonds (females). Acrophase plotted in radians for J all cats, n = 2&#8211;7 per group, (K) males, n = 2&#8211;6 per group, and (L) females, n = 4&#8211;7 per group, in standard (black circle), dim (gray square), and orange (orange square) lighting. Rayleigh tests of uniformity revealed clustering of acrophase, indicated by arrowheads crossing the dashed circle (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr5.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Two-way ANOVA for sex differences and light condition for actigraphy data, n = 2&#8211;7 per group</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light Condition</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Interaction</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Period</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F (2, 23) = 0.45</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.65</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F (1, 23) = 0.10</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.75</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F (2, 23) = 0.75</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.49</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Chi<sup>2</sup> Amplitude (Qp)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F (2, 23) = 1.65</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.21</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F (1, 23) = 3.66</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.07</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F (2, 23) = 1.55</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Activity Profile Amplitude</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F (2, 23) = 0.88</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.42</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F (1, 23) = 0.015</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.90</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">F (2, 23) = 2.97</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.07</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0075">As it is important to understand the activity patterns of domestic cats in a shelter environment as a first step toward understanding how the timing of entraining cues, such as caretaking activities (e.g., feeding, introducing enrichment toys, or social interactions), may impact activity patterns, we determined the chronotype of cats in our study by identifying the acrophase (timing of peak activity), in each light condition. Notably, in the shelter environment for this study, several timing cues (zeitgebers) were present, including shelter staff manually turning on the lights each day at approximately 0800h and off at approximately 1700h, shelter staff administered medications to cats at 0830h (if a second dose was required, it was administered at 1500h), shelter staff cleaned all housing units and fed each cat at 1030h, daily enrichment was given to each cat at 1300&#8211;1400h, and researchers conducted daily data collection between 1300 and 1700h. Cat acrophase for males and females combined (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>J) was significantly clustered in standard (2.09rad &#177;0.59; Rayleigh = 0.72, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.001), dim (2.08rad &#177;0.67; Rayleigh = 0.70, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.003), and orange light (2.06rad &#177;0.44; Rayleigh = 0.87, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.005), corresponding to the time of lights on (ZT0, &#8764;0800h) in the room, and did not differ between light conditions. Watson&#8217;s two-sample tests of homogeneity did not reveal differences between acrophase in each light condition (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.10). When each sex was examined independently (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figures 5</xref>K&#8211;5L), acrophase clustering was limited to standard light in males (1.94rad &#177;0.54; Rayleigh = 0.89, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.001), dim light in females (1.94rad &#177;0.54; Rayleigh = 0.82, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.001), and orange light in females (2.05rad &#177;0.46; Rayleigh = 0.84, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.048), with all others groups failing to cluster (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>Cat stress scores were reduced by type of lighting and time in shelter</title><p id="p0080">High stress, as measured by physiological and behavioral outputs, is associated with reduced adoptions in cats<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> and increased health risks, including respiratory, gastrointestinal, dermatological, and feline interstitial cystitis, among others.<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr"><sup>63</sup></xref> To increase our understanding of cat stress behavior in response to human presence, human approach, and human-initiated interaction, we used a 3-task behavioral approach test (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figures 6</xref>A&#8211;6C). In brief, an experimenter video recorded the cat as the experimenter 1: stood 3 feet away directly in front of the housing unit for 2 s (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>A; 3-Feet), 2: approached the cat unit at a slow and steady pace (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>B; Approach), and 3: reached a hand toward the cat within the unit, with palm down and fingers extended (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>C; Hand Extended). Cat behavior was scored at all three time-points using a modified version of the validated cat stress score, where 1 is fully relaxed and 7 is terrified (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>).<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref> There were no significant three-way interactions for 3 Feet, Approach, or Hand Extended tasks (mixed model ANOVA, <xref rid="tbl6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>).<fig id="fig6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Cat stress score by day in shelter in standard, dim and orange overhead lighting in the 3-task behavioral approach test</p><p>Cat stress scores (A and D) three feet from the unit, (B and E) approaching the unit, and (C and F) with hand extended, analyzed mixed model ANOVA (Type 3 tests, KR-method), <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 10&#8211;15 per group. (G) Cat latency to approach in response to an extended hand, measured in seconds, by day in shelter in standard, dim and orange light, analyzed via repeated measures mixed-effects model with Geisser-Greenhouse correction; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 27&#8211;41 per group. Data are represented as mean &#177; SEM. Individual cats are represented by circles. &#8220;&#8727;&#8221; indicates significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr6.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Mixed model ANOVA table (Type 3 tests, KR-method) for sex, day in shelter, and sex differences for each task in the Behavioral Approach Test, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 10&#8211;15 per group</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Variable</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">Effect</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">df</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">F</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="7" colspan="1">3 Feet</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex:Light:Day</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8, 266.93</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.33</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Light:Day</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>8, 266.93</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>2.94</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.004</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex:Day</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4, 267.36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.26</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.91</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex:Light</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2, 79.76</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.76</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.18</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Day</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4, 267.36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.12</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.079</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2, 79.76</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.29</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.75</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1, 79.94</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.54</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.46</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7" colspan="1">Approach</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex:Light:Day</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8, 243.00</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.56</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.81</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light:Day</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8, 243.00</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.78</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.082</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex:Day</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4, 243.40</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.06</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.99</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex:Light</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2, 72.64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.68</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.51</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Day</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>4, 243.40</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>4.07</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.003</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2, 72.64</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.80</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.45</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1, 72.79</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.36</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.55</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7" colspan="1">Hand Extended</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex:Light:Day</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8, 266.90</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.45</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.89</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light:Day</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">8, 266.90</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.49</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex:Day</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">4, 267.37</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.92</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex:Light</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2, 80.23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.27</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.29</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>Day</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>4, 267.37</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>3.72</bold></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><bold>0.006</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Light</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">2, 80.23</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.74</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.48</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sex</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">1, 80.48</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.52</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.47</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Significant data (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05.) are bolded.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0085">For males and females combined, the 3-Feet task (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>D) revealed a significant interaction of both lighting and day in shelter (F[8, 266.93] = 2.94, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.004). In standard light, cat stress scores were reduced on day 2 (1.89 &#177; 0.22, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0083), day 3 (1.82 &#177; 0.23, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0019), and day 5 (2.00 &#177; 0.21, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.010), compared to day 1 (2.46 &#177; 0.29). Cat stress scores were increased on day 3 (2.36 &#177; 0.18, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.025) compared to day 2 (1.90 &#177; 0.14) in dim light, and there were no differences in 3 Feet cat stress scores in orange light. There were no significant interactions for the approach (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>E) or hand extended (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>F) tasks, and light condition alone did not impact approach or hand extended tasks (<xref rid="tbl6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). However, there was a main effect of day in shelter for both the approach (F[4, 243.4] = 4.07, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.003) and hand extended (F[4, 267.37] = 3.72, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.006) tasks. In the approach task, cat stress scores were higher on day 1 (2.61 &#177; 0.16, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.013) and day 2 (2.46 &#177; 0.13, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.010) compared to day 5 (2.04 &#177; 0.13).</p><p id="p0090">In the hand extended task, cat stress scores were higher on day 2 (2.58 &#177; 0.13) compared to day 4 (2.22 &#177; 0.11, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.049) and day 5 (2.23 &#177; 0.14, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.050). To validate the 3-task behavioral approach test, we compared the cat stress scores to urinary cortisol levels via correlation analyses (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Higher cat stress scores were positively correlated with increased urinary cortisol levels for all 3 tasks in the behavioral approach test in standard and dim, but not orange light (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>).<fig id="fig7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Pearson correlations between cortisol and cat stress scores from the 3-Task Behavioral Approach Test</p><p>Pearson correlations examining the relationship between cortisol compared to cat stress scores in the (A&#8211;C) 3 Feet, (D&#8211;F) Approach, and (H&#8211;J) Extended Hand tasks. Individual cats are shown as circles, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 45-60 per group. R2 and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> values are indicated next to linear regression lines. Dashed curves indicate 95% confidence intervals.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="gr7.jpg"/></fig></p><p id="p0095">As social affiliation toward humans is a strong indicator of successful adoption, we also measured latency to approach an extended human hand. Light condition did not impact latency to approach (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.73). As cats spent increased time in the shelter, the latency to approach decreased (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.05), such that cats had reduced approach latencies on day 3 (mean = 1.52, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 77) compared to day 1 (mean = 1.94, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 77) in the shelter (mean difference = 0.42, standard error of difference = 0.18, 95% CL of difference = &#8722;0.0434 to 0.875, adjusted <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.09).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0100">This study investigated the ability of light intensity and composition as well as length of time in the shelter to modulate cat stress and locomotor circadian rhythms. A major focus of the field of circadian biology has been advancing human health; however, increasing our understanding of circadian mechanisms guiding health across species has important implications beyond humans, including the potential to improve non-human animal health and welfare, recently reviewed by Farag et al., 2024.<xref rid="bib66" ref-type="bibr"><sup>66</sup></xref> Here, we found that both male and female shelter cats had short (22-23h) circadian rhythms in locomotor activity that peaked at the time of lights on, independent of light condition. Additionally, light intensity, light composition, and the length of time spent in the shelter, interreacted to modulate cortisol, stress behaviors, and overall activity patterns. Surprisingly, we did not observe any sex differences, although it is possible that sex-specific effects might emerge with increased sample sizes. Together, the data presented here characterize circadian locomotor activity patterns in shelter cats and demonstrate that both lighting conditions and number of days in the shelter can reduce physiological and behavioral measures of cat stress.</p><p id="p0105">Understanding the circadian rhythms in physiology and behavior of cats in a shelter environment is an important first step toward determining how the timing of care, such as food, social interactions with staff and conspecifics, and medications, should be coordinated to ensure peak health of the cats. Studies examining circadian rhythms in domestic cats have been conducted since the early 1960s, where male cats were found to have a circadian peak in mean heart rate at the time of lights on.<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref> However, there are varying reports on the activity patterns in domestic cats, ranging from evidence suggesting a lack of circadian activity patterns to reports of nocturnal, crepuscular, and diurnal circadian activity rhythms.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> Previous work found that cats in constant darkness exhibit free-running circadian rhythms,<xref rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr"><sup>67</sup></xref> but there are mixed reports that include circadian,<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr"><sup>68</sup></xref> polyphasic,<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> and a lack of circadian rhythms<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr"><sup>69</sup></xref> in standard light dark cycles. Here, we find that shelter cats displayed circadian rhythms in behavioral activity with &#8764;22-23h periods in all light conditions. Our data support the current hypothesis that cats exhibit a high variability in activity patterns in controlled housing conditions<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> and that the environment exerts a strong influence on the expression of cat locomotor activity patterns.<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref> Notably, in our study, cats were housed under an extended dark period (9h light: 15h dark). Photoperiod has not been found to modulate cortisol levels in cats,<xref rid="bib70" ref-type="bibr"><sup>70</sup></xref> making it unlikely that the extended dark phase alone impacted stress hormone levels. However, others have shown that cats can rapidly adapt their activity patterns to light cycles in a laboratory environment,<xref rid="bib68" ref-type="bibr"><sup>68</sup></xref> and it is possible that the shorter activity periods found here are driven by re-entrainment as the cats adapt to a new lighting schedule in their shelter environment. This work was limited by the shelter&#8217;s designated quarantine/holding period for all intact cats, as spay/neuter procedures occurred after 5 days in the shelter, but it will be of interest for future studies to lengthen the time of observation to understand if the less-than-24h periods are innate or a function of re-entrainment.</p><p id="p0110">Two of the main factors guiding cat activity patterns are proximity to humans and feeding, with several reports documenting circadian activity pattern entrainment to both human activity and feeding schedules.<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> Interestingly, our data find that shelter cat acrophase occurs at the time of lights on. This suggests that cats may be entrained to the timing of lights on compared to the timing of food availability, which occurred approximately 2.5 h after cat peak activity. However, one limitation of our study is the inability to tease apart the potential interactions of shelter cat activity patterns in relation to zeitgeber availability. Notably, the shelter lights were not coordinated by an automatic timing system, instead the lights were manually turned on by shelter staff as they entered the room for morning health checks. It is possible that acrophase is impacted not only by the timing of light, but is also influenced by human staff presence, although additional work will be needed to discern how these variables impact the cat&#8217;s temporal niche. Importantly, this work suggests that daytime care (feeding, interactions with staff, medication administration) is not likely to introduce health risks associated with desynchrony, as cats in this cohort adapted activity patterns to correspond with these activities. However, more controlled studies are needed to determine if specific timing of care and enrichment, such as a consistent feeding and treat schedule, is more beneficial compared to scattered care, which would provide a more naturalistic environment. This is a potentially important advancement for the timing of care for other environments that house domestic cats, such as boarding, veterinary, and research facilities.</p><p id="p0115">In addition to locomotor activity patterns, light quality has been demonstrated to impact mood and stress in mammals.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> In domestic cats, both transition-related increases in stress, including entering a new housing enviornment,<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref> and the animal shelter environment<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> are well-established stressors, making the initial days following intake into an animal shelter an especially vulnerable time. Here, we examined cats housed in the shelter&#8217;s windowless quarantine and holding room that was used to house recently admitted cats, separate from the shelter&#8217;s cat adoption room and not open to the public. This allowed for a highly controlled environment to understand how light qualities impact a cat&#8217;s transition into a shelter. Our study confirms prior work that time in a new housing location is a critical factor for stress reduction in cats,<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr"><sup>71</sup></xref> as we found that both physiological stress (urinary cortisol) and behavioral indicators of stress (cat stress scores, 3-task behavioral approach test) decreased across days in the shelter in all light conditions. A longer length of time in shelter (i.e., the more days) could increase the likelihood of a cat to become habituated to their surroundings, including their housing unit, other cats in the room, and shelter staff. The reduced cat stress scores across the 3-task behavioral approach test reported here are consistent with previous work that found significant reductions in behavioral cat stress scores after 5 days in a cattery<xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref> or animal shelter.<xref rid="bib71" ref-type="bibr"><sup>71</sup></xref> We found that like cortisol and locomotor activity, cat latency to approach an extended human hand depended on the length of time in the shelter. Specifically, cats under all light conditions had decreased latency to approach on day 3 in the shelter.</p><p id="p0120">Interestingly, while urinary cortisol decreased across days in both standard and dim lighting conditions, the dim, orange (blue-depleted) light condition decreased urinary cortisol concentration in both male and female cats to a greater extent than standard light on later days (days 5). This could indicate faster adjustment to the shelter housing conditions, but more work, such as including an extended duration of data collection greater than 5 days, will be necessary to better understand if these effects are due to habituation or potential downregulation of cortisol as a result of chronic stress.<xref rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr"><sup>72</sup></xref> Interestingly, stressed cats are known to suppress active exploratory and play behaviors,<xref rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr"><sup>73</sup></xref> making it possible that increases in activity levels were linked to reduced stress; however, increased activity and reduced urinary cortisol were only significantly correlated under standard light (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>). This demonstrates an important avenue for future work to examine the mechanisms driving changes in locomotor and stress behaviors and the nuances in light qualities that may modulate such stress-related behaviors.</p><p id="p0125">In addition to reduced activity, cats naturally hide as a stress response and will even overturn litter boxes to create hiding spaces if there are no other alternatives.<xref rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr"><sup>63</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr"><sup>64</sup></xref> In the present study, all cats were provided with a hiding space within their unit. We found that light impacted cat hiding behavior, where cats had an increased probability of hiding under the dim light, but not during standard or dim, orange lighting. This provides additional evidence that light can modulate stress-related behaviors in cats, where dim light is less effective at reducing cat stress, compared to standard light and dim, orange light. While hiding boxes have been a significant stress-reduction intervention for shelter cats, hiding boxes do not prevent physiological results of stress such as weight loss<xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr"><sup>74</sup></xref> or improve a cat&#8217;s chances of adoption,<xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr"><sup>75</sup></xref> suggesting that cats may need multiple stress-reduction interventions to be fully comfortable in shelter environments. While additional investigation is needed to tease apart the complex relationships between the stress variables examined here, taken together our data suggest that urinary cortisol, locomotor activity, hiding, and approach behaviors depend on both light manipulation and time spent in the shelter. As such, care should be taken in the design and documentation of lighting conditions in domestic cat housing facilities and research studies. Additionally, given the high genetic and behavioral overlap of domestic cats and their wild relatives,<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> this work is likely to be relevant for conservation research. Light quality may be especially important to consider for wild Felidae species that are undergoing captive breeding and assisted reproductive efforts, where precise circadian timekeeping is essential for successful reproduction, and high stress can impair breeding efforts.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref></p><p id="p0130">Together this work demonstrates for the first time that room light manipulation, in conjunction with the length of a shelter stay, may help shelters enact easy and inexpensive changes that make the adjustment period shorter and less stressful for incoming cats. Here, we also define the activity patterns of male and female domestic cats in a shelter environment as a first step toward developing recommendations for the timing of caretaking activities. These results highlight the importance of considering light quality as an important factor for stress management when designing or modifying cat housing.</p><sec id="sec3.1"><title>Limitations of the study</title><p id="p0135">In addition to the limitations of this study characterized throughout the Discussion, cat ownership history prior to study enrollment was not available, making it impossible to distinguish between cats that were surrendered by owner or entered the shelter as strays, which might impact stress levels upon arrival at the shelter. It is possible that variability in our data could be explained by combinations of feral and non-feral cats, or that some of our findings, such as increased activity profile amplitude in female under dim light, might reflect an instinctual hunting response from feral populations. To generate sufficient data for analysis, we enrolled cats ranging from 8 months to 6 years, which encompasses two age ranges, junior and prime,<xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr"><sup>76</sup></xref> and thus it is possible that our data may be complicated by potential age effects. A limitation of the 3-task behavioral approach test is that the cat stress scoring system does not discriminate between stress (negative high arousal) and &#8220;excitement&#8221; (positive high arousal). For example, a cat with high affiliation for humans, a desirable trait for adoption, that stood and approached an experimenter could not be categorized as &#8220;fully relaxed&#8221;. To account for this, we included the latency to approach dataset, which measures a cat&#8217;s motivation to interact with a human and is an established marker of feline affiliation toward humans.<xref rid="bib75" ref-type="bibr"><sup>75</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib77" ref-type="bibr"><sup>77</sup></xref> In an effort to minimize interactions between researchers and enrolled cats, we did not collect light data from underneath the covered stool in each cat unit; however, it is possible that variations in blanket/towel thickness, resulting in a range of dim-dark hiding spaces, coupled with the amount of time cats spent hiding (not tracked in this study), could impact the results. Sample sizes vary between different analyses due to missing data and technical challenges. Several cats did not use the litter pan, and animals that did not give three samples of urine during the testing period were excluded from cortisol analyses. Cats were sometimes not present in their unit at the time of behavioral data collection due to removal from their unit by shelter staff, and no behavioral task data for those days were collected. Missing data from the PetPace collars, included data lost via Wi-Fi disconnection, cat collar self-removal, and inability of experimenters to safely place a collar on a cat. It is also important to note that for unknown reasons the shelter had reduced intake of male cats during the data collection periods for orange lighting (July&#8211;August 2021 and April&#8211;October 2022), which resulted in lower sample size for some datasets. Efforts were made to distribute data collection across seasons; however, due to the reduced intake of male cats during the second timepoint for orange lighting, there is a significant overlap of summer months. It is possible that our results may be linked to time-of-year or seasonal effects, although more work is needed to confirm this.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Resource availability</title><sec id="sec4.1"><title>Lead contact</title><p id="p0140">Requests for further information and resources should be directed to and will be fulfilled by the Lead Contact, Alexandra Yaw (<email>yawalexa@msu.edu</email>).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.2"><title>Materials availability</title><p id="p0145">This study did not generate new unique reagents.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec4.3"><title>Data and code availability</title><p id="p0150">
<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0015"><list-item id="u0025"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0155">All data reported in this paper will be shared by the <xref rid="sec4.1" ref-type="sec">lead contact</xref> upon request.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0030"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0160">This paper does not report original code.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0035"><label>&#8226;</label><p id="p0165">Any additional information required to reanalyze the data reported in this paper is available from the <xref rid="sec4.1" ref-type="sec">lead contact</xref> upon request.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p id="p0170">Thank you to our partners at the Ingham County Animal Control and Shelter and undergraduate researchers Grace Jaksen, Jessica Crane, Kathryn Hurt, Skyler Mack, and Eleanor Vondette for their assistance in data collection. Research reported in this publication was supported in part by grants from <funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100011138</institution-id><institution>MSU AgBioResearch</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> and <funding-source id="gs2"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100007709</institution-id><institution>Michigan State University</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> to J.J. and H.M.H. A.M.Y. was supported by the <funding-source id="gs3"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100009633</institution-id><institution>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health &amp; Human Development of the National Institutes of Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> under Award Numbers <award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs3">F32HD107852</award-id> and <award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs3">K99HD113843</award-id>, and the Resident/Fellow Award from the <funding-source id="gs4">MSU&#8217;s College of Veterinary Medicine (CVM) Feline Health Endowment</funding-source>, with additional support of training to A.M.Y. by <award-id award-type="grant" rid="gs4">T32HD087166</award-id>. The content is solely the responsibility of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official views of the supporting institutions.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Author contributions</title><p id="p0175">Conceptualization: A.M.Y., J.J., and H.M.H.; methodology: A.M.Y., M.E.G., J.J., and H.M.H.; investigation: A.M.Y. and M.E.G.; writing &#8211; original draft: A.M.Y. and M.E.G.; writing &#8211; reviewing and editing: A.M.Y., M.E.G., J.J., and H.M.H.; funding acquisition: J.J. and H.M.H.; resources: J.J. and H.M.H.; supervision: A.M.Y., J.J., and H.M.H.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec7"><title>Declaration of interests</title><p id="p0180">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>STAR&#9733;Methods</title><sec id="sec8.1"><title>Key resources table</title><p id="p0185">
<table-wrap position="float" id="undtbl1" orientation="portrait"><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">REAGENT or RESOURCE</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">SOURCE</th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1">IDENTIFIER</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>Experimental models</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Domestic Cats (<italic toggle="yes">Felis catus</italic>)</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Ingham County Animal Control and Shelter</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>Software and algorithms</bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">CIELUV chromaticity diagram 1976</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">E H H Hasabeldaim 2021</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://sciapps.sci-sim.com/CIE1976.html" id="intref0015">https://sciapps.sci-sim.com/CIE1976.html</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">ClockLab</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Actimetrics, Lafayette Instrument Company</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://actimetrics.com/products/clocklab/" id="intref0020">https://actimetrics.com/products/clocklab/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">PetPace</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">PetPace LLC</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://petpace.com" id="intref0025">https://petpace.com</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">Prism</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1">GraphPad, Dotmatics</td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.graphpad.com" id="intref0030">https://www.graphpad.com</ext-link></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="sec8.2"><title>Experimental model and subject details</title><p id="p0190">All animal procedures were performed according to protocols approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Michigan State University. We tested 101 domestic cats (<italic toggle="yes">Felis catus</italic>; 48 male and 53 female), residing at a Midwestern animal control and shelter from March 2021 through October 2022 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>C). Intact healthy cats between the ages of 8 months &#8211; 6 years, corresponding to junior (7 months-2 years; 59 cats, 21 male) and prime (3-6 years; 42 cats, 27 male) aged cats, according to the American Animal Hospital Associate and American Association of Feline Practitioners (AAHA/AAFP) Feline Life Stage Guidelines,<xref rid="bib76" ref-type="bibr"><sup>76</sup></xref> that were housed individually and under ownership by the shelter were enrolled in the study. No cats underwent surgical procedures while they were enrolled in the study, including spay/neuter procedures. Cat exclusion criteria included: documented injuries, including eye damage or blindness, pregnancy or recent birth (&#8764;10 weeks), or co-housing. Cat ownership history prior to study enrollment was not available. All sample and animal behavior data were collected at Ingham County Animal Control and Shelter located in Mason, Michigan. Subjects were housed in the shelter&#8217;s quarantine and holding room that was used to house recently admitted cats, separate from the shelter&#8217;s cat adoption room and not open to the public. The housing room (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>A) was 17.6 m<sup>2</sup> and windowless, with accessibility by one door. The housing room was located on the interior keycard access portion of the building, away from dog adoption kennels and associated outdoor spaces. The housing room shared walls with the adoption lobby, office spaces, and a dog quarantine and holding room. Ambient noise levels were 62.7-74.5dB measured by a TOPTES (TS-501A) Sound Level Meter (Guangzhou Zhongguoqi Technology Co., Ltd., Guangdong, China). The room housed 22 units (10 on one wall, 12 on opposite wall) for cat containment. There were two sizes of housing units, large units were 0.68 m<sup>3</sup> and small units 0.55 m<sup>3</sup> (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>A). Cats were placed in individual housing units at random by the shelter staff. Each unit contained an upper and lower level (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>B). The upper level was left empty as open housing space. The lower level contained: food and water bowls, bedding (blankets or towels), a litter pan, and a stool covered by fabric allowing cats more privacy and a hiding space. Shelter staff provided a variety of daily enrichment activities for the cats, including toys, handling, and/or treats and enrichment type was varied as resources permitted. The holding room was only accessed by shelter staff (for feeding, enrichment, cleaning, medical checks, moving cats) and our researchers (for data collection). Lights were turned on and off manually daily by shelter staff, with lights on at approximately 0800h and off at approximately 1700h. Each day, staff administered medications to cats at 0830h (if a second dose was required, it was administered at 1500h). At 1000h the staff then cleaned all kennels and fed every cat. Finally, cats received daily enrichment around 1300-1400h. Researchers conducted all enrollment and data collection between 1300-1700h. Interactions between researchers and cats were minimal. Researchers were instructed to act as neutral observers, and only interacted (physical or verbal) with cats during PetPace collars application and removal in addition to litter pan exchanges. Animal health was monitored regularly by on-site veterinary staff.</p><p id="p0195">Light conditions in the shelter room were varied across the 19 months of testing (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>C) and cats were assigned to a light condition if they maintained the same light for all days of testing. Enrolled cats were monitored with data collection for five days (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>D). Cat&#8217;s enrollment occurred within the first 24h in the shelter. On the day of enrollment, initial approach test videos were filmed before cats were given a new litter pan containing hydrophobic litter and fitted with a PetPace collar (PetPace, Burlington, MA). For the next four days, activity data were continuously collected via PetPace smart collars, the approach test was conducted and filmed each day prior to urine samples collection. Cats were unenrolled on the fifth full day in the study.</p><sec id="sec8.2.1"><title>Apparatus/materials</title><p id="p0200">There were three light conditions: standard (control, unaltered shelter LED lighting), dim, and orange (dim, blue-depleted) light (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). Light filters (B &amp; H Foto &amp; Electronics Corp, New York, NY) were placed over the LED overhead lights (standard light) to achieve dim (BH #ROE250S: MFR #102302502124) and orange lighting (BH #ROE204S: MFR #102302042124). Light qualities in cat units (both upper and lower levels) were measured with UV Illuminance Spectrophotometer SRI-2000 UV (Allied Scientific Pro&#8482;, Qu&#233;bec, Canada) at1300h. The CIELUV chromaticity diagram 1976 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>A) was created through online open-source software.<xref rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr"><sup>78</sup></xref> As multiple aspects of light quality are known to modulate physiology and behavior,<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> we analyzed both light intensity and composition (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). As light composition can impact mood, a CIELUV 1976 chromaticity diagram for the average human-perceived lighting color in each of the light conditions was generated (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>A). Both human perceived wavelength (&#955;p; main effect of lighting F(2, 5) = 59.22, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0003) and dominant wavelength (&#955;d; main effect of lighting F(2, 5) = 465.6, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) were increased in dim, orange lighting compared to both standard and dim (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>C&#8211;2E). Light intensity (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>B and 2E) was reduced in both dim and orange lighting compared to standard (main effect of lighting F(2,10) = 7.783, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.009) and the lower level of the cat unit had reduced light intensity compared to the upper level (main effect of unit level F(2,10) = 18.34, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.002). To monitor room light timing, a three-day continuous recording with sampling every 5 min were collected in each lighting condition via HOBO Pendant MX2202 Temperature/Light Data Recorder (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>B). Light condition differences are reflected in the representative spectral power distributions (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>F&#8211;2H), where orange lighting has a reduced peak in the blue-light portion (450-495nm) that is not present in standard or dim spectral power distributions and standard light intensity (1.24 mW/m<sup>2</sup>) is higher than dim (0.93 mW/m<sup>2</sup>) and orange light (0.82 mW/m<sup>2</sup>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec8.3"><title>Method details</title><sec id="sec8.3.1"><title>Urinary cortisol</title><p id="p0205">Cortisol was used as a physiological indicator of stress. Urine was the chosen medium for obtaining this hormone, as drawing blood may have imparted more stress on the cats. Cats received a fresh litter pan containing hydrophobic cat litter, Nosorb (Catco Vet Products Inc., Florida, USA) or Kit 4Kat (Coastline Global Inc., Pennsylvania, USA), daily. Urine was collected once daily from litter pans, as previous work demonstrated that litter urine samples collected 24h following a stressor reflect increases in cortisol levels similar to needle drawn serum and urine.<xref rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr"><sup>79</sup></xref> Urine samples were immediately frozen at &#8722;20&#176;C. Cortisol was analyzed via Cortisol ELISA kit, ADI-900-071; RRID: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.antibodyregistry.org/AB_3697107" id="PC_linkpoyRW4Fp4i">AB_3697107</ext-link>, (ENZO Life Sciences INC., Farmingdale, NY). Urine samples were thawed at room temperature for 24h before steroid displacement and added to the plate at a 1:10 dilution and run in duplicate. Animals that did not give three samples of urine for the 4-day testing period were excluded from analysis. Data include n = 4&#8211;12 per group.</p></sec><sec id="sec8.3.2"><title>Locomotor actigraphy</title><p id="p0210">PetPace SmartCollars (PetPace LLC, Massachusetts, USA) were used to record activity data every two minutes for the length of a cat&#8217;s enrollment. All data were stored wirelessly in the online PetPace Health Monitoring Portal. PetPace Activity scores were calculated through a proprietary scale within the PetPace software and represented the combined calculated values of activity intensities, activity frequency and duration.<xref rid="bib80" ref-type="bibr"><sup>80</sup></xref> Individual activity counts were exported from the Health Monitoring Portal and converted to be compatible with ClockLab Analysis 6 (Actimetrics, Wilmette, IL). Data were analyzed in 10 min bins and daily onset and offset of activity, defined as a period of 4h of activity following 4h of inactivity (onset) or a period of 4h of inactivity following 4h of activity (offset). Chi<sup>2</sup> periodograms<xref rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr"><sup>81</sup></xref> were generated from 19 to 28h, reflecting the general biological designation for circadian rhythms<xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr"><sup>82</sup></xref> with significance set at 0.005. All cats that exhibited a significant peak were deemed rhythmic, with the maximum amplitude reported as Qp. Activity profiles were generated using the circadian period (tau) estimated from the Chi<sup>2</sup> periodogram for the same testing dates. Acrophase was generated using at least three days of activity. Missing data included data lost via Wi-Fi disconnection, cat collar self-removal, and inability of experimenters to safely place a collar on a cat. Data include n = 2-7 per group.</p></sec><sec id="sec8.3.3"><title>3-Task Behavioral Approach Test and approach latency</title><p id="p0215">The daily 3-Task Behavioral Approach Test (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>, <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>) was conducted prior to all other daily sample collections (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>D) and was recorded via GoPro HERO7 Black camera (GoPro Inc., San Mateo, California). Each task of the approach test (3 feet, approach, hand extended) took place for 3 sec., with a total of &#8764;9sec. to complete the test, similar to the approach test in Arhant &amp; Troxler, 2017.<xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr"><sup>83</sup></xref> To begin, the experimenter stood 3 feet away (&#8764;91cm) and directly in front of the housing unit and began video recording the cat while remaining still. After 3 sec, the experimenter approached the cat unit at a slow and steady pace (&#8764;1 ft/s; &#8764;0.3 m/s) to complete the approach task. Next, the experimenter reached a hand towards the cat within the unit, with palm down and fingers extended, and the hand remained extended for 3sec. before finishing the recording.</p><p id="p0220">Videos were scored for stress using an adapted cat stress score (CSS) system<xref rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr"><sup>56</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr"><sup>57</sup></xref> by experimenters who were blind to the groups. The CSS (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Table S1</xref>) identifies behavioral signs of stress on a scale of one to seven, with a score of one equating to a fully relaxed cat (laid out on back or side, eyes closed or half open, resting or sleeping) while a score of seven describes a terrified cat (fast breathing, shaking, dilated pupils, ears flattened back). Cats located beneath the stool and towel during any task of the behavioral approach test were deemed &#8220;not visible&#8221; for that portion of the task. Cats that remained under the stool and towel during all three tasks were deemed &#8220;hiding,&#8221; not included in CSS data, and were used to calculate the percentage of cats hiding. Approach latency was defined as the number of seconds a cat took to approach the front of the cat unit during the hand extended portion of the test. Data from cats removed from their unit by shelter staff during the time of behavioral data collection were not included. Data include n = 4-19 per group.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec8.4"><title>Quantification and statistical analysis</title><p id="p0225">Data were analyzed using GraphPad Prism 8 (Version 10.4.1 (532), Graph Pad Software, La Jolla, CA) and RStudio (Version 2024.12.1 + 563 (2024.12.1 + 563)). Significant differences were designated as <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 and data are reported as mean &#177; standard error mean (SEM). In unit light quality data (peak wavelength, dominant wavelength, and light intensity), approach latency, and hiding data were analyzed by two-way Analysis of Variance (ANOVA). Room light intensity was analyzed via a two-way repeated-measures ANOVA, followed by Tukey&#8217;s multiple comparison test. Cortisol, PetPace activity scores, and cat stress scores (3-Trial Behavioral Approach Test) were analyzed by linear mixed-effects models with sex, light condition, and day as within subject factors. Cat IDs were included as a random effect to account for repeated measures across conditions and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values were computed with Kenward-Roger approximation for degrees of freedom to account for missing data. Hiding behavior was analyzed via Bayesian logistic regression model using the brms package in R, which interfaces with Stan for Bayesian inference via Hamiltonian Monte Carlo sampling. The model included all main effects and interactions between sex, light condition, and day in shelter, as well as random intercepts for each individual cat to account for repeated measures. Model convergence was assessed via the R-hat statistic (all values = 1.00), and the effective sample size for each parameter was sufficient. Posterior predictive checks were performed to ensure model fit. Predicted values and 95% credible intervals for hiding were calculated for each combination of sex, light condition, and day in shelter using the model&#8217;s posterior distributions. Chi<sup>2</sup> amplitude and activity profile amplitude were analyzed by two-way ANOVA. Correlation analyses were completed using Pearson r. Post hoc tests were completed using Tukey&#8217;s multiple comparison test. All data passed normality testing. Acrophase data were analyzed in R Studio via Rayleigh test of uniformity and 1-criterion analysis of variance for circular data, followed by pairwise comparisons, and Watson&#8217;s 2-sample test of homogeneity using Bonferroni&#8217;s correction to accommodate familywise error rate, where appropriate. Phase data were reported in radians with circular mean deviation. Statistical analyses for outliers (Grubbs&#8217; test) were conducted on all datasets, and no outliers were identified. All data except for period passed testing for equal standard deviations.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Refinetti</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The diversity of temporal niches in mammals</article-title><source>Biol. Rhythm Res.</source><volume>39</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>192</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Czeisler</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Effect of Light on the Human Circadian Pacemaker</article-title><source>Ciba Found Symp.</source><volume>183</volume><year>1995</year><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/9780470514597.ch14</pub-id><comment>discussion 290-302</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7656689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirota</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukada</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resetting mechanism of central and peripheral circadian clocks in mammals</article-title><source>Zool.. Sci.</source><volume>21</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2108/zsj.21.359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15118222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Best</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maywood</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastings</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid resetting of the mammalian circadian clock</article-title><source>J. Neurosci.</source><volume>19</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>828</fpage><lpage>835</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9880602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.19-02-00828.1999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6782190</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandrashekaran</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singaravel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Subbaraj</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship between light intensity and phase resetting in a mammalian circadian system</article-title><source>J. Exp. Zool.</source><volume>283</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9919688</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/(sici)1097-010x(19990201)283:2&lt;181::aid-jez8&gt;3.0.co;2-i</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boivin</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kronauer</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Czeisler</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dose-response relationships for resetting of human circadian clock by light</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>379</volume><year>1996</year><fpage>540</fpage><lpage>542</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8596632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/379540a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindheimer</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#700;Connor</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCully</surname><given-names>K.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dishman</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of light-intensity cycling on mood and working memory in response to a randomized, placebo-controlled design</article-title><source>Psychosom. Med.</source><volume>79</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27551990</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/PSY.0000000000000381</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedrosian</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of the modern light environment on mood</article-title><source>Mol. Psychiatr.</source><volume>18</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>757</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/mp.2013.70</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23711982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vardi-Naim</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sagiv</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kronfeld-Schor</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fitness consequences of chronic exposure to different light pollution wavelengths in nocturnal and diurnal rodents</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>12</volume><year>2022</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">16486</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/s41598-022-19805-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9526750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36182961</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peirson</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pothecary</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisk</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Light and the laboratory mouse</article-title><source>J. Neurosci. Methods</source><volume>300</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28414048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jneumeth.2017.04.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5909038</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebihara</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuji</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Entrainment of the circadian activity rhythm to the light cycle: effective light intensity for a Zeitgeber in the retinal degenerate C3H mouse and the normal C57BL mouse</article-title><source>Physiol. Behav.</source><volume>24</volume><year>1980</year><fpage>523</fpage><lpage>527</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7375573</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0031-9384(80)90246-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>A.J.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vidafar</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGlashan</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajaratnam</surname><given-names>S.M.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lockley</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cain</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High sensitivity and interindividual variability in the response of the human circadian system to evening light</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><volume>116</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>12019</fpage><lpage>12024</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1901824116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31138694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6575863</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>P.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Someren</surname><given-names>E.J.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mainster</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of environmental light in sleep and health: effects of ocular aging and cataract surgery</article-title><source>Sleep Med. Rev.</source><volume>14</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20056462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.smrv.2009.11.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duffy</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Czeisler</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of light on human circadian physiology</article-title><source>Sleep Med. Clin.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20161220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jsmc.2009.01.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2717723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Binding</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krusin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Status of animal welfare research in zoos and aquariums: Where are we, where to next?</article-title><source>J. Zool. Aquar. Res.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>174</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lantermino</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lapuente</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>P.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gobello</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of artificial light in the female domestic cat reproduction: What we know so far?</article-title><source>Anim. Reprod. Sci.</source><volume>248</volume><year>2023</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">107173</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.anireprosci.2022.107173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36592522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Domestic cats as laboratory animals</article-title><source>Lab. Anim. Med.</source><volume>459</volume><year>2007</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Precision medicine in cats&#8212;The right biomedical model may not be the mouse</article-title><source>PLoS Genet.</source><volume>16</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e1009177</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pgen.1009177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7723241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33290388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitchener</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Valkenburgh</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macdonald</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loveridge</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Felid form and function</part-title><source>Biology and Conservation of Wild Felids 2010</source><year>2010</year><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>106</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Brien</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>W.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Big cat genomics</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Genomics Hum. Genet.</source><volume>6</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>429</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16124868</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1146/annurev.genom.6.080604.162151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative endocrinology of domestic and nondomestic felids</article-title><source>Theriogenology</source><volume>66</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16620933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2006.03.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>W.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The challenge of assisted reproduction for conservation of wild felids-A reality check</article-title><source>Theriogenology</source><volume>197</volume><year>2023</year><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36502591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2022.11.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pelican</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wildt</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pukazhenthi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ovarian control for assisted reproduction in the domestic cat and wild felids</article-title><source>Theriogenology</source><volume>66</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16630653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2006.03.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulrich-Lai</surname><given-names>Y.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neural regulation of endocrine and autonomic stress responses</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Neurosci.</source><volume>10</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>397</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19469025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrn2647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4240627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amat</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Camps</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manteca</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stress in owned cats: behavioural changes and welfare implications</article-title><source>J. Feline Med. Surg.</source><volume>18</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>586</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26101238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1098612X15590867</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10816390</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stella</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Croney</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental aspects of domestic cat care and management: implications for cat welfare</article-title><source>Sci. World J.</source><volume>2016</volume><year>2016</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">6296315</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1155/2016/6296315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5059607</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27774506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szabadi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional organization of the sympathetic pathways controlling the pupil: light-inhibited and light-stimulated pathways</article-title><source>Front. Neurol.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1069</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30619035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fneur.2018.01069</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6305320</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McDougal</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gamlin</surname><given-names>P.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Autonomic control of the eye</article-title><source>Compr. Physiol.</source><volume>5</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25589275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/cphy.c140014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4919817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Groos</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The visual properties of rat and cat suprachiasmatic neurones</article-title><source>J. Comp. Physiol.</source><volume>135</volume><year>1980</year><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>356</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalsbeek</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van der Spek</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Endert</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buijs</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fliers</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circadian rhythms in the hypothalamo&#8211;pituitary&#8211;adrenal (HPA) axis</article-title><source>Mol. Cell. Endocrinol.</source><volume>349</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21782883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.mce.2011.06.042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuwabara</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circadian, sleep and brain temperature rhythms in cats under sustained daily light-dark cycles and constant darkness</article-title><source>Physiol. Behav.</source><volume>38</volume><year>1986</year><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3797494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0031-9384(86)90164-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circadian rhythms in food intake and activity in domestic cats</article-title><source>Behav. Neurosci.</source><volume>99</volume><year>1985</year><fpage>1162</fpage><lpage>1175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3843546</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1037//0735-7044.99.6.1162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Serra</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deputte</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ract-Madoux</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faustin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Challet</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of locomotor and feeding rhythms between indoor and outdoor cats living in captivity</article-title><source>Animals.</source><volume>12</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>2440</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36139300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ani12182440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9494968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Refinetti</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wassmer</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cherukalady</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>V.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singaravel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giannetto</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piccione</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variability of behavioral chronotypes of 16 mammalian species under controlled conditions</article-title><source>Physiol. Behav.</source><volume>161</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27090227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.physbeh.2016.04.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cerutti</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scaglione</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sciabarrasi</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piccione</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pennisi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giannetto</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of light/dark schedules on daily pattern of total locomotor activity in wild and domestic felids</article-title><source>J. Vet. Behav.</source><volume>50</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>35</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Macdonald</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Apps</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The social behaviour of a group of semi-dependent farm cats, Felis catus: a progress report</article-title><source>Carniv. Genet. Newsl.</source><volume>3</volume><year>1978</year><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>268</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kavanau</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Locomotion and activity phasing of some medium-sized mammals</article-title><source>J. Mammal.</source><volume>52</volume><year>1971</year><fpage>386</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4996451</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szymanski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activity and rest in animals and human</article-title><source>Z. Allg. Physiol.</source><volume>18</volume><year>1919</year><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>162</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>FOLK</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Observations on the Daily Rhythms of Body Temperature-Labile Mammals</article-title><source>Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci.</source><volume>98</volume><year>1962</year><fpage>954</fpage><lpage>968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13945770</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/j.1749-6632.1962.tb30611.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Piccione</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marafioti</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giannetto</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panzera</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fazio</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Daily rhythm of total activity pattern in domestic cats (Felis silvestris catus) maintained in two different housing conditions</article-title><source>J. Vet. Behav.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>194</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeTar</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Quin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berliner</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradley-Seimens</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Association of Shelter Veterinarians&#8217; Guidelines for Standards of Care in Animal Shelters</article-title><source>J. Shelter Med. Commun. Animal Health</source><volume>2</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>76</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boubekri</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>I.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.-H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zee</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of windows and daylight exposure on overall health and sleep quality of office workers: a case-control pilot study</article-title><source>J. Clin. Sleep Med.</source><volume>10</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>611</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24932139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.5664/jcsm.3780</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4031400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>V.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoults</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Practical Guide to Veterinary Hospital Design: From Renovations to New Builds</part-title><year>2018</year><publisher-name>AAHA Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thorne</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Archer</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dijk</surname><given-names>D.-J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Daily and seasonal variation in the spectral composition of light exposure in humans</article-title><source>Chronobiol. Int.</source><volume>26</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>854</fpage><lpage>866</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19637047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/07420520903044315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guillemette</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#233;bert</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paquet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dumont</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural bright light exposure in the summer and winter in subjects with and without complaints of seasonal mood variations</article-title><source>Biol. Psychiatry</source><volume>44</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>622</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9787887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0006-3223(97)00543-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Erensoy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sar&#305;ca</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noubandiguim</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dur</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aslan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of light intensity and stocking density on the performance, egg quality, and feather condition of laying hens reared in a battery cage system over the first laying period</article-title><source>Trop. Anim. Health Prod.</source><volume>53</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>320</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33987733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s11250-021-02765-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>J.-R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belal</surname><given-names>S.-A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Na</surname><given-names>C.-S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>K.-S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of LED lighting intensity on productivity, blood parameters and immune responses in dairy cows</article-title><source>Korean J. Org. Agric.</source><volume>27</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>171</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref48"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hjalmarsson</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferneborg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agen&#228;s</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ternman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of low light intensity at night on cow traffic in automatic milking systems</article-title><source>Anim. Prod. Sci.</source><volume>54</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>1784</fpage><lpage>1786</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref49"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of preferred natural stimuli on humans&#8217; affective states, physiological stress and mental health, and the potential implications for well-being in captive animals</article-title><source>Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev.</source><volume>83</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28916271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2017.09.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref50"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tosini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsubota</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of blue light on the circadian system and eye physiology</article-title><source>Mol. Vis.</source><volume>22</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26900325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4734149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref51"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monochromatic blue light activates suprachiasmatic nucleus neuronal activity and promotes arousal in mice under sevoflurane anesthesia</article-title><source>Front. Neural Circ.</source><volume>14</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>55</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fncir.2020.00055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7461971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32973462</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref52"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gui</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blue light insertion at night is involved in sleep and arousal-promoting response delays and depressive-like emotion in mice</article-title><source>Biosci. Rep.</source><volume>41</volume><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1042/BSR20204033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7938454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33624794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref53"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lonstein</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linning-Duffy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low daytime light intensity disrupts male copulatory behavior, and upregulates medial preoptic area steroid hormone and dopamine receptor expression, in a diurnal rodent model of seasonal affective disorder</article-title><source>Front. Behav. Neurosci.</source><volume>13</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>72</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31031606</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fnbeh.2019.00072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6473160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref54"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leach</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adidharma</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Depression-like responses induced by daytime light deficiency in the diurnal grass rat (Arvicanthis niloticus)</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>8</volume><year>2013</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e57115</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0057115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3577787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23437327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref55"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lonstein</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunez</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Light as a modulator of emotion and cognition: Lessons learned from studying a diurnal rodent</article-title><source>Horm. Behav.</source><volume>111</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yhbeh.2018.09.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30244030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6456444</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref56"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of Density and Cage Size on Stress in Domestic Cats (Felis Sil Vestris Catus) Housed in Animal Shelters and Boarding Catteries</article-title><source>Anim. Welf.</source><volume>8</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>267</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref57"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stress and adaptation of cats (Felis silvestris catus) housed singly, in pairs and in groups in boarding catteries</article-title><source>Anim. Welf.</source><volume>6</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>254</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref58"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCobb</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patronek</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marder</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinnage</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of stress levels among cats in four animal shelters</article-title><source>J. Am. Vet. Med. Assoc.</source><volume>226</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>548</fpage><lpage>555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15742695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2460/javma.2005.226.548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref59"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bale</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Epperson</surname><given-names>C.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sex differences and stress across the lifespan</article-title><source>Nat. Neurosci.</source><volume>18</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>1413</fpage><lpage>1420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26404716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nn.4112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4620712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref60"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fountain</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wijnen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Control of daily locomotor activity patterns in Drosophila suzukii by the circadian clock, light, temperature and social interactions</article-title><source>J. Biol. Rhythms</source><volume>34</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>463</fpage><lpage>481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31436123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/0748730419869085</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref61"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krizo</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mintz</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sex differences in behavioral circadian rhythms in laboratory rodents</article-title><source>Front. Endocrinol.</source><volume>5</volume><year>2014</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">234</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fendo.2014.00234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4288375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25620955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref62"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolaides</surname><given-names>N.C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chrousos</surname><given-names>G.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sex differences in circadian endocrine rhythms: clinical implications</article-title><source>Eur. J. Neurosci.</source><volume>52</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>2575</fpage><lpage>2585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32012359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/ejn.14692</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref63"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gourkow</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of housing and handling practices on the welfare, behaviour and selection of domestic cats (Felis sylvestris catus) by adopters in an animal shelter</article-title><source>Anim. Welf.</source><volume>15</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>377</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref64"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rochlitz</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Podberscek</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Broom</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Welfare of cats in a quarantine cattery</article-title><source>Vet. Rec.</source><volume>143</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9699249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1136/vr.143.2.35</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref65"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Refinetti</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corn&#233;lissen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halberg</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Procedures for numerical analysis of circadian rhythms</article-title><source>Biol. Rhythm Res.</source><volume>38</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23710111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/09291010600903692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3663600</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref66"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farag</surname><given-names>H.I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Templeman</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanlon</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joshua</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>T.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niel</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoveller</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedecarrats</surname><given-names>G.Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellison</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilcockson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>One Health: Circadian Medicine Benefits Both Non-human Animals and Humans Alike</article-title><source>J. Biol. Rhythm.</source><volume>143</volume><year>2024</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">07487304241228021</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/07487304241228021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11141112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38379166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref67"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Freerunning and entrained circadian rhythms in activity, eating and drinking in the cat</article-title><source>Biol. Rhythm Res.</source><volume>14</volume><year>1983</year><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>327</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref68"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delmar Cerutti</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rizzo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alberghina</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cristina Scaglione</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piccione</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Locomotor activity patterns of domestic cat (Felis silvestris catus) modulated by different light/dark cycles</article-title><source>Biol. Rhythm Res.</source><volume>50</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>838</fpage><lpage>844</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref69"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Piccione</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marafioti</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giannetto</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Pietro</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quartuccio</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fazio</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of daily distribution of rest/activity in companion cats and dogs</article-title><source>Biol. Rhythm Res.</source><volume>45</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>623</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref70"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>LEYVA</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>ADDIEGO</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>STABENFELDT</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of different photoperiods on plasma concentrations of melatonin, prolactin, and cortisol in the domestic cat</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><volume>115</volume><year>1984</year><fpage>1729</fpage><lpage>1736</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6436007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1210/endo-115-5-1729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref71"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janke</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giacinti</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Behavior and adoptability of hoarded cats admitted to an animal shelter</article-title><source>J. Feline Med. Surg.</source><volume>24</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>e232</fpage><lpage>e243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35722998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1177/1098612X221102122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9315195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref72"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rich</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exposure to chronic stress downregulates corticosterone responses to acute stressors</article-title><source>Am. J. Physiol. Regul. Integr. Comp. Physiol.</source><volume>288</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>R1628</fpage><lpage>R1636</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15886358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1152/ajpregu.00484.2004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref73"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlstead</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strawn</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Behavioral and physiological correlates of stress in laboratory cats</article-title><source>Appl. Anim. Behav. Sci.</source><volume>38</volume><year>1993</year><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>158</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref74"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Der Leij</surname><given-names>W.J.R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selman</surname><given-names>L.D.A.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vernooij</surname><given-names>J.C.M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vinke</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of a hiding box on stress levels and body weight in Dutch shelter cats; a randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>14</volume><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0223492</object-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0223492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6791553</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31609987</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref75"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kry</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of hiding enrichment on stress levels and behaviour of domestic cats (Felis sylvestris catus) in a shelter setting and the implications for adoption potential</article-title><source>Anim. Welf.</source><volume>16</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>383</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref76"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodan</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buffington</surname><given-names>C.A.T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forman</surname><given-names>M.J.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neilson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sparkes</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Feline life stage guidelines</article-title><source>J. Feline Med. Surg.</source><volume>12</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20123486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jfms.2009.12.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10845473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref77"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stella</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Croney</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coping styles in the domestic cat (Felis silvestris catus) and implications for cat welfare</article-title><source>Animals.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>370</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31216726</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3390/ani9060370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6616962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref78"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasabeldaim</surname><given-names>E.H.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CIELUV chromaticity diagram 1976</article-title><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://Sciapps.Sci-Sim.Com/CIE1976.Html" id="intref0040">https://Sciapps.Sci-Sim.Com/CIE1976.Html</ext-link><year>2021</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref79"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlstead</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monfort</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Killens</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wildt</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Urinary monitoring of adrenal responses to psychological stressors in domestic and nondomestic felids</article-title><source>Zoo Biol.</source><volume>11</volume><year>1992</year><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>176</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><label>80</label><element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref80"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>PetPace</collab></person-group><article-title>Quantifying Activity and Caloric Needs</article-title><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://Petpace.Com/Petpace-Collar-Instrumental-Weight-Loss-Management-Dog/" id="intref0045">https://Petpace.Com/Petpace-Collar-Instrumental-Weight-Loss-Management-Dog/</ext-link><year>2023</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><label>81</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref81"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sokolove</surname><given-names>P.G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bushell</surname><given-names>W.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The chi square periodogram: its utility for analysis of circadian rhythms</article-title><source>J. Theor. Biol.</source><volume>72</volume><year>1978</year><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">566361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/0022-5193(78)90022-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><label>82</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref82"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Refinetti</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>Ultradian and Infradian Rhythms</part-title><source>Circadian physiology</source><edition>3rd ed.</edition><year>2019</year><publisher-name>CRC press</publisher-name><fpage>123</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib83"><label>83</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref83"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arhant</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Troxler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is there a relationship between attitudes of shelter staff to cats and the cats&#8217; approach behaviour?</article-title><source>Appl. Anim. Behav. Sci.</source><volume>187</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>68</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec2" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplemental information</title><p id="p0235">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Document S1. Figures S1 and Table S1</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="mmc1.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="appsec1" fn-type="supplementary-material"><p id="p0230">Supplemental information can be found online at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isci.2025.112709" id="intref0035">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isci.2025.112709</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article></pmc-articleset>