<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10185883</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10185883.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10185883</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10185883</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37205227</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1203702</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial: <italic toggle="yes">Lawsonia intracellularis</italic>: a problem well understood is a problem half solved</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karuppannan</surname><given-names initials="AK">Anbu Kumar</given-names></name><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1440650/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff><institution>Department of Veterinary Microbiology, Bioinformatics Centre, Madras Veterinary College, Tamil Nadu Veterinary and Animal Sciences University</institution>, <addr-line>Chennai</addr-line>, <country>India</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited and reviewed by: Michael Kogut, United States Department of Agriculture, United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Anbu Kumar Karuppannan <email>anbukumar.k@tanuvas.ac.in</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>02</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">427755</issue-id><elocation-id>1203702</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>4</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>4</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>17</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-05-21 09:25:09.617"><day>21</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 Karuppannan.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Karuppannan</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-10-1203702.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="commentary-article" xml:lang="en" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/25064/lawsonia-intracellularis-a-problem-well-understood-is-a-problem-half-solved"/><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Lawsonia intracellularis</italic></kwd><kwd>vaccine</kwd><kwd>pathogenesis</kwd><kwd>microbiome</kwd><kwd>microbiota</kwd><kwd>genome</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="14"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="1864"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Veterinary Infectious Diseases</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Porcine proliferative enteropathy (PE) or proliferative hemorrhagic enteritis (PHE), or commonly &#8220;ileitis&#8221;, is a severe intestinal disease of domestic pigs and wild boars. It is caused by the bacterium <italic toggle="yes">Lawsonia intracellularis</italic>, which infects the cells lining the ileum and infrequently cells in the large intestine, and it causes inflammation, hemorrhages, and thickening of the intestinal wall (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). The disease can be fatal, particularly in young pigs, and causes significant economic loss (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> also infects and causes pathogenesis in horses, rabbits, and hamsters (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). The etiological role of <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> in ileitis was unraveled after much effort, due to the initial difficulty in the axenic culture of the organism, by Lawson et al. at the University of Edinburgh (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> is an obligate intracellular microaerophilic organism that requires a reduced O<sub>2</sub> concentration of 8%. The establishment of culture procedures opened avenues for further research on <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Now, the infection has been recorded in many host species (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). The estimation of genome copies of the organism shed in the feces by quantitative PCR has been a reliable indicator of the infection load. The <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> strains are thought to have developed host species-specific adaptation, as strains derived from one host species show decreased pathogenicity in experimental cross-species infections (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). A multi-locus variable number tandem repeat (VNTR) analysis based on four sets of primers has been reported for discriminating porcine and equine isolates (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). A cross-sectional study by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2023.1058113" ext-link-type="uri">Yeh et al.</ext-link> reported in this collection, from South Korea, estimated a seropositivity of 12.3% to <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> in farmed rabbits in 163 farms. The study detected <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> genomic DNA from rabbit rectal swabs in 3.8% of rabbit farms. The presence of pigs or horses in or near the rabbit farm was a risk factor for seropositivity, indicating the potential cross-species spread of infection. The first commercial live attenuated <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> vaccine for pigs administered orally was available in 2001, and an inactivated parenteral vaccine was available from 2015 (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). The administration of the oral live attenuated vaccine requires a 7-day window free of antibiotic administration to pigs. In addition, interference due to maternal antibodies in the gut of piglets is a concern with the live attenuated vaccine (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). The vaccines have reduced the disease burden of <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> infection in pigs. Interestingly, an experimental infection, by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2022.994147" ext-link-type="uri">Hansen et al.</ext-link> with porcine circovirus 2 (PCV2) prior to a combined <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic>/PCV2 infection mitigated the clinical signs, lesions, and level of shedding of <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> infection. Prior PCV2 exposure also led to higher <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> antibody titers after the combined infection, which warrants further research into the cross-talk between the immune response to viral infections and <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> infection. The microbiota of the pig's ileum is known to influence the susceptibility to <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic>, and the infection also adversely affects the gut microbiota (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). In this Research Topic collection, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2021.692521" ext-link-type="uri">Leite et al.</ext-link> have elaborated dysbiosis in the small and large intestine caused during <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> infection by analyzing the gut microbiome (microbiota). Particularly, an increase of pathobionts, including <italic toggle="yes">Collinsella, Campylobacter, Chlamydia</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Fusobacterium</italic>, was observed in the gut during <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> infection. Interestingly, the live attenuated <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> vaccine, in addition to decreasing the <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> shedding, significantly decreased the relative abundance of pathobionts, highlighting the role of the broader gut microbiome composition in the pathogenesis caused by <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic>. Another article in this collection by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2022.1004506" ext-link-type="uri">Hankel et al.</ext-link>, which is based on their analysis of fecal microbiota in pigs naturally infected with <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> that were varying in their vaccination status (with live attenuated oral vaccine) and clinical conspicuity, found the influence of the microbiota on the severity of disease. The causal role of the microbiota in the pathogenesis of <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> infection is yet to be completely unraveled.</p><p>The reference genome of <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> consists of a 1.46 Mb chromosome and three plasmids of 0.03, 0.04, and 0.19 Mb (NCBI Refseq IDs <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide-range" xlink:href="NC_020127:NC_020130">NC_020127 to NC_020130</ext-link>). A complete genome dataset of at least nine strains of <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> from around the world [US (PHE/MN1-00, E40504), UK (N343, LR189), Japan (Ni/JPN, Ib2/JPN, Fu/JPN), South Korea (CBNU010), and China (PPE-GX01-2022)] are available in the public domain at the end of March 2023. Notably, the E40504 strain was isolated from a horse. The genome data have led to the development of several semi-quantitative and quantitative PCR assays for the diagnosis of <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic>. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2021.753610" ext-link-type="uri">Xiao et al.</ext-link> expressed the outer membrane protein (Omp2) of <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> from a synthetic gene based on sequence information. Monoclonal antibodies specific to Omp2 were produced and found to be efficient in detecting <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> in Western blots, immunohistochemistry, and immunofluorescence assays. Moreover, a comparison of the gene expression profiles of the pathogenic low-passage and non-pathogenic high-passage isolate of <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> revealed that there were only 401 genes expressed by the pathogenic bacteria (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Notably, one of the plasmids (A) was entirely repressed in the non-pathogenic bacteria. Transcriptomic profiling of the host ileum tissue in <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic>-infected pigs revealed the molecular signature of cellular proliferation and inflammation (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). The stimulation of Notch-1 signaling and inhibition of the &#946;-catenin/Wnt pathway in ileum crypt cells during the peak of infection by <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> has been implicated in the molecular pathogenesis (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). In addition, the apoptosis and autophagy pathways in the ileum cells were found to be dysregulated (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). These altered signaling and cellular mechanisms are thought to influence the inhibition of goblet cell maturation and enhance crypt cell proliferation, leading to decreased mucin secretion and thickening of the ileum wall in <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> infection. The genome of <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> encodes for a type III secretion system (T3SS), which is commonly found in pathogenic bacteria to secrete effector proteins into host cells. Through a yeast expression array expressing hypothetical genes from <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic>, it has been identified that LI1035 interacts with the mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) pathway and regulates actin organization in yeast (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2023.1005676" ext-link-type="uri">Pereira et al.</ext-link> reported in this collection on the role of clathrin in the endocytosis of <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> into cultured porcine intestinal epithelial cells (IPEC-J2). They found that <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> is endocytosed by both clathrin-dependent and -independent mechanisms, but the internalization of heat-killed bacteria is decreased in the clathrin-depleted cells. This suggests potential active mechanisms, involving a secretion apparatus, effected by <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic> during endocytosis, as observed in many pathogenic intracellular bacteria. Given the wealth of knowledge on the genome of <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic>, potential effector proteins or virulence factors remain to be characterized. With the current level of information on the biology of <italic toggle="yes">L. intracellularis</italic>, a promising outlook prevails over the efforts for a comprehensive understanding of the pathogenesis of this fastidious organism, which may require uncharacterized inciting factors to cause disease.</p><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>The author confirms being the sole contributor of this work and has approved it for publication.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The author declares that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s2"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karuppannan</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Opriessnig</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Lawsonia intracellularis</italic>: revisiting the disease ecology and control of this fastidious pathogen in Pigs</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>181</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2018.00181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30140680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6095029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Advances in ileitis control, diagnosis, epidemiology and the economic impacts of disease in commercial pig herds</article-title>. <source>Agriculture.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>536</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/agriculture3030536</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>GHK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rowland</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacIntyre</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Demonstration of a new intracellular antigen in porcine intestinal adenomatosis and hamster proliferative ileitis</article-title>. <source>Vet Microbiol.</source> (<year>1985</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>303</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-1135(85)90001-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2412336</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McOrist</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jasni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mackie</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Intracellular bacteria of porcine proliferative enteropathy: cultivation and maintenance <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic></article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol.</source> (<year>1993</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>1136</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jcm.31.5.1136-1142.1993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8501214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC262892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vannucci</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pusterla</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mapes</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evidence of host adaptation in Lawsonia intracellularis infections</article-title>. <source>Vet Res.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>53</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1297-9716-43-53</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22715937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3443049</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckler</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapur</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gebhart</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular epidemiologic typing of Lawsonia intracellularis</article-title>.In: <source>Proceedings of the Conference of Research Workers in Animal Disease</source>. <publisher-loc>Chicago, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ellis RP. 2004, Blackwell Publishing</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holyoake</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donahoo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lising</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Identifying obstacles to reducing the use of antibiotics to control porcine proliferative enteropathy</article-title>. <source>Aust Vet J.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>87</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1751-0813.2008.00372.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19178474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Opriessnig</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karuppannan</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ait-Ali</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cubas-Atienzar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halbur</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bacillus pumilus probiotic feed supplementation mitigates <italic toggle="yes">Lawsonia intracellularis</italic> shedding and lesions</article-title>. <source>Vet Res.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>85</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13567-019-0696-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31640784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6806562</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muwonge</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karuppannan</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Opriessnig</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Probiotics mediated gut microbiota diversity shifts are associated with reduction in histopathology and shedding of Lawsonia intracellularis</article-title>. <source>Anim Microbiome.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>22</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s42523-021-00084-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33663618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7931366</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vannucci</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gebhart</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative transcriptional analysis of homologous pathogenic and non-pathogenic Lawsonia intracellularis isolates in infected porcine cells</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e46708</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0046708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23056413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3463550</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leite</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrahante</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasquez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vannucci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gebhart</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Winkelman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cell Proliferation and Inflammatory Signature Is Induced by Lawsonia intracellularis Infection in Swine</article-title>. <source>mBio.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e01605</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.01605-18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30696739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6355989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huan</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacIntyre</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guthrie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finlayson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Lawsonia intracellularis exploits &#946;-catenin/Wnt and Notch signalling pathways during infection of intestinal crypt to alter cell homeostasis and promote cell proliferation</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e0173782</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0173782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28323899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5360247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salvesen</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sargison</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Archibald</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ait-Ali</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterisation of autophagy disruption in the ileum of pigs infected with Lawsonia intracellularis</article-title>. <source>Vet Res Commun.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>585</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11259-021-09847-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34669106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9165227</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>LI1035, a putative effector secreted by Lawsonia intracellularis, targets the MAPK pathway and regulates actin organizationin yeast and mammalian cells</article-title>. <source>Vet Microbiol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>235</volume>:<fpage>127</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2019.06.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31282370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>