<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1103</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jvetsci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JVS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1229-845X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1976-555X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Korean Society of Veterinary Science</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10694368</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10694368.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10694368</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10694368</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37904638</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4142/jvs.23163</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="subheading"><subject>Oncology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Palmar&#8211;plantar erythrodysesthesia syndrome resulting from toceranib phosphate in a dog with apocrine gland anal sac adenocarcinoma: a case report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2649-1824</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="E">Eunjoo</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9480-8163</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="SS">Sung-Soo</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5614-9846</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names initials="MO">Min-Ok</given-names></name><xref rid="A1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="A2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>VIP Animal Medical Center KR, City Place Bld., Seoul 02830, <country>Korea</country>.</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Laboratory of Internal Medicine, Department of Veterinary Clinical Science, College of Veterinary Medicine, Seoul National University, Seoul 88082, <country>Korea</country>.</aff><author-notes><corresp>Corresponding author: Min-Ok Ryu. Laboratory of Internal Medicine, Department of Veterinary Clinical Science, College of Veterinary Medicine, Seoul National University, 1 Gwanak-ro, Gwanak-gu, Seoul 88082, Korea. <email>apple963@snu.ac.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>04</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><issue>6</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">450250</issue-id><elocation-id>e76</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>26</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>05</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-01-28 17:25:10.717"><day>28</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2023 The Korean Society of Veterinary Science</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Korean Society of Veterinary Science</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0</ext-link>) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jvs-24-e76.pdf"/><abstract><p>An 11-year-old neutered male Miniature Poodle with a stage 3 apocrine gland adenocarcinoma was started on chemotherapy with toceranib phosphate after surgery. Beginning on day 10 of toceranib, the dog&#8217;s foot pads became erythematous and hyperkeratinized. The dog complained of pain, inability to walk, depression, and loss of appetite. The symptoms resolved when toceranib was discontinued and reappeared when toceranib was resumed. Grade 3 palmar&#8211;plantar erythrodysesthesia was identified as an adverse event of toceranib based on the VCOG-CTCAE and Naranjo scale. Although very rare in veterinary medicine, clinicians should consider that palmar&#8211;plantar erythrodysesthesia can occur after toceranib administration.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Case reports</kwd><kwd>hand-foot syndrome</kwd><kwd>tyrosine protein kinase inhibitor</kwd><kwd>canine diseases</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Toceranib phosphate is an anticancer drug approved by the FDA for canine mast cell tumors. Although approved for grades 1 and 2 canine mast cell tumors, it has been used widely for various cancers [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Recent studies showed that chemotherapy with toceranib phosphate improved the progression-free interval and median survival time for canine apocrine gland anal sac adenocarcinoma (AGASACA) [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref><xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>Palmar&#8211;plantar erythrodysesthesia, also known as hand&#8211;foot syndrome, is a relatively common side effect of chemotherapy in humans. It is a disorder characterized by redness, marked discomfort, swelling, and tingling of the palms of the hands or the soles of the feet [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. According to the CTCAE, it is classified into three grades based on the severity of skin changes, the presence or absence of pain, and the degree of limitation of activities of daily living [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. It has been reported to occur with various anticancer agents, including sorafenib, sunitinib, cediranib, docetaxel, doxorubicin, cytarabine, and capecitabin [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. On the other hand, its manifestation in veterinary practice is relatively rare. This case report presents an exceptional case of palmer&#8211;plantar erythrodysesthesia in a dog after treatment with toceranib phosphate for a stage 3 apocrine gland adenocarcinoma, shedding light on this infrequently reported adverse effect in veterinary medicine.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>CASE PRESENTATION</title><p>An 11-year-old neutered male Miniature Poodle with a history of surgery for removing a perianal mass three months ago was presented for evaluation of metastasis and a general annual check-up. The histopathology of the resected mass revealed AGASACA. A physical examination showed no remarkable findings except for several subdermal soft masses. The blood analysis results, including complete blood count (CBC), serum chemistry, venous blood gas, and urinalysis, were normal. Diagnostic imaging, including thoracic and abdominal radiography, abdominal ultrasound, and echocardiogram, showed no remarkable findings.</p><p>Computed tomography (CT) revealed a soft tissue mass with ill-defined margins around the left external anal sphincter muscle (21.1 &#215; 11.6 &#215; 18.2 mm) and mild to moderate enlargement of the left sacral and left hypogastric lymph nodes. An epithelial malignancy was suspected on cytology via fine needle aspiration, and surgery resecting the mass and the left sacral and hypogastric lymph nodes was performed. On histopathology, the soft tissue mass around the anal sphincter muscle was identified as apocrine adenocarcinoma, and the sacral lymph node was interpreted as metastatic adenocarcinoma. No neoplasia was observed in the hypogastric lymph node. The dog was diagnosed as stage 3 AGASACA based on the Polton and Brearley clinical staging system [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>For treatment purposes, toceranib phosphate (Palladia, Pfizer Inc., Italy) was administered at 25 mg (3.2 mg/kg) every other day with the owner&#8217;s informed consent. One week later (day 7), a physical examination revealed erythema and scaling around the mouth, and the owner complained of pruritus. On day 10, the foot pads were changed to erythema (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). Toceranib was discontinued on day 11 because of suspected drug toxicity. After discontinuing toceranib, the erythema was mildly reduced, but the foot pads appeared depigmented.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Gross lesions of each foot. (A) on day 10; pictures of front feet after 10 days of toceranib treatment; (B) left front foot on day 18 and bilateral hind feet on day 21; lesion after seven and 10 days of first drug withdrawal, respectively. (C) On day 42, pictures of all feet were taken 21 days after re-introducing the toceranib. (D) On day 56, pictures after 14 days of 2<sup>nd</sup> drug withdrawal (E) on day 98, pictures after seven weeks of 2<sup>nd</sup> drug withdrawal.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jvs-24-e76-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>On day 21, toceranib was reinitiated in consultation with the owners. After seven days, the owner complained of generalized erythema and scaling. After 12 days, the foot pads showed erythema, and the dog was depressed and anorectic. The erythema is a symptom of allergic dermatitis, but despite PDS administration, the erythematous lesion on the pads widened. The pads became edematous, and hyperkeratosis occurred from the pads to the metacarpal/metatarsal lesion. Finally, the dog stopped walking because of the pain, and toceranib was stopped (day 42).</p><p>After discontinuing toceranib, the dog had a good appetite and was no longer in pain or lame. The foot pads became black and normalized over time, starting 14 days after discontinuing toceranib. The Naranjo adverse drug reaction probability scale [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] was used to determine if a specific medication caused the side effects. The total score was 9, indicating a definite adverse drug reaction. Although the histopathology of the dermal lesions could not be performed because the owners did not give their consent, based on the history, clinical examination, Naranjo scale, and VCOG-CTCAE [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], a diagnosis of grade 3 plantar-palmar erythrodysesthesia was made as an adverse reaction secondary to toceranib phosphate.</p><p>Melphalan was prescribed after discontinuing toceranib, and the dog underwent several examinations, including CBC, serum chemistry panels, ionized calcium level, thoracic/abdominal X-ray, abdominal and perineal ultrasound monthly, and thoracic/abdominal CT every three months to evaluate metastasis, chemotherapy-induced side effects, and paraneoplastic syndrome. Five months after the start of melphalan, CT revealed a metastasis in the lung and the left sublumbar lymph node. Based on current reports that toceranib was effective in stage 3&#8211;4 AGASACA [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], a lower dose and lower frequency toceranib protocol (2.5 mg/kg PO every Tuesday, Thursday, and Saturday) was initiated, and the dermatologic change was closely evaluated. After taking toceranib twice, the dog began to show the same skin problem as before (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>), and the doxorubicin/carboplatin protocol was initiated as an alternative to toceranib. Gene analysis was performed to differentiate mutations of the MDR1 gene, but no mutations were detected. All the diagnostic procedures and therapeutic interventions were performed with the informed consent of the owners.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Gross skin lesion of the left forefoot four days after low-dose toceranib.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jvs-24-e76-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>In human medicine, skin toxicity has been reported in 70&#8211;90% of patients receiving an epidermal growth factor receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitor (EGFR-TKI) [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The observed cutaneous effects include xerosis, pruritus, papulopustular eruption, paronychia, and hand-foot syndrome (palmar&#8211;plantar erythrodysesthesia) [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref><xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref><xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref><xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref><xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Several studies investigated the underlying mechanisms of these EGFR-TKI-induced skin toxicities, but they are not completely understood. Several studies suggest that skin toxicity may be associated with EGFR inhibition-induced keratinocyte apoptosis, inflammation or capillary endothelial damage, and the drug concentration of papillary dermis [<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The skin toxicity may be associated with EGFR inhibition, vascular EGF-PDGFR inhibition, and inhibition of EGFR downstream signals, such as STAT3 [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><p>In dogs, the skin toxicity of tyrosine kinase inhibitors was not frequently determined and was not as severe as human toxicity. The common side effects of toceranib include gastrointestinal signs, such as vomiting and diarrhea, neutropenia, anorexia, anemia, elevated liver enzymes, and lameness [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. There are few reports of skin toxicity caused by toceranib in dogs. One case report of skin depigmentation and one case of foot pad thinning and depigmentation have been published [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. To the best of the authors&#8217; knowledge, this case report is the first to describe the presentation of palmar&#8211;plantar erythrodysesthesia as an adverse effect of toceranib in dogs.</p><p>In this case, the skin toxicity of toceranib appeared similar to the skin toxicity of tyrosine kinase inhibitors reported in humans, and the mechanisms are believed to be similar. Despite the recent widespread use of toceranib in canine oncology, clinicians often do not recognize cutaneous toxicity as an adverse effect. Nevertheless, cutaneous adverse reactions with tyrosine kinase inhibitors, including toceranib, may occur in dogs. Considering this case and the other two reported cases [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], the skin toxicity of toceranib phosphate may occur within three days to three weeks after initiating the drug and resolve within one or a few weeks after discontinuation of the drug.</p><p>In the previously reported clinical trial, a dog with mild hand-foot syndrome tolerated a lower dose of toceranib after the side effects resolved [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In this case, however, the same side effect occurred only after two administrations at a 25% reduced dose, suggesting that it was not dose-dependent. In human medicine, there are guidelines for managing skin-related toxicities of EGFR TKIs [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref><xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Mild symptoms can be managed with topical ointments while continuing the anticancer treatment, while severe symptoms may warrant dose reduction or discontinuation. Similar approaches could be considered in dogs.</p><p>The 'rash-dosing,' the intentional use of a dose that induces mild symptoms of skin toxicity, is believed to enhance the anticancer efficacy based on some studies in humans [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Although veterinary evidence is lacking in this regard, if the symptoms are mild and can be managed with topical ointments without affecting the quality of life significantly, the continuation of toceranib may be beneficial despite the potential skin toxicity.</p><p>One limitation of this case report is the absence of a histopathological examination of the dermal lesions because the owners did not give their consent, and they disappeared after drug discontinuation. Histopathology could have provided valuable insights into the specific changes and characteristics of the affected skin tissues, further supporting the diagnosis of palmar&#8211;plantar erythrodysesthesia. In this case, however, the characteristics of the dermatologic lesions and the temporal relationship between drug administration and clinical signs are considered sufficient to diagnose palmar&#8211;plantar erythrodysesthesia.</p><p>In conclusion, this case report highlights the occurrence of palmar&#8211;plantar erythrodysesthesia as a rare adverse event in a dog receiving toceranib phosphate to treat stage 3 apocrine gland anal sac adenocarcinoma. The temporal relationship between the administration of toceranib and the development of symptoms supports the diagnosis of drug-induced palmar&#8211;plantar erythrodysesthesia. Clinicians should consider this potential adverse effect when using tyrosine kinase inhibitors in veterinary oncology. Further research will be needed to understand the underlying mechanisms and management strategies for such drug toxicities in dogs.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold> The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><bold>Author Contributions:</bold>
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Conceptualization:</bold> Ryu MO.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Supervision:</bold> Kim SS.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Writing - original draft:</bold> Ryu MO, Kim E.</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>Writing - review &amp; editing:</bold> Ryu MO.</p></list-item></list></p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernabe</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Portela</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kisseberth</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pennell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yancey</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the adverse event profile and pharmacodynamics of toceranib phosphate administered to dogs with solid tumors at doses below the maximum tolerated dose</article-title><source>BMC Vet Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>190</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24079884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1746-6148-9-190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3850926</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Response and outcome following toceranib phosphate treatment for stage four anal sac apocrine gland adenocarcinoma in dogs: 15 cases (2013&#8211;2017)</article-title><source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source><year>2019</year><volume>254</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>960</fpage><lpage>966</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30938616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2460/javma.254.8.960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heaton</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jark</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of toceranib for treatment of apocrine gland anal sac adenocarcinoma in dogs</article-title><source>J Vet Intern Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>34</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>873</fpage><lpage>881</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31977135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jvim.15706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7096647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Setser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anadkat</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cotliar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garden</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Grading dermatologic adverse events of cancer treatments: the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events Version 4.0</article-title><source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source><year>2012</year><volume>67</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1025</fpage><lpage>1039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22502948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.jaad.2012.02.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipworth</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>AX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hand-foot syndrome (hand-foot skin reaction, palmar-plantar erythrodysesthesia): focus on sorafenib and sunitinib</article-title><source>Oncology</source><year>2009</year><volume>77</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19923864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1159/000258880</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikolaou</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Syrigos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saif</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incidence and implications of chemotherapy related hand-foot syndrome</article-title><source>Expert Opin Drug Saf</source><year>2016</year><volume>15</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1625</fpage><lpage>1633</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27718746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1080/14740338.2016.1238067</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Polton</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brearley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical stage, therapy, and prognosis in canine anal sac gland carcinoma</article-title><source>J Vet Intern Med</source><year>2007</year><volume>21</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17427388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1892/0891-6640(2007)21[274:cstapi]2.0.co;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naranjo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Busto</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sellers</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandor</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Naranjo ADR probability scale</article-title><source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source><year>1981</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7249508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/clpt.1981.154</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Common terminology criteria for adverse events (VCOG-CTCAE) following chemotherapy or biological antineoplastic therapy in dogs and cats v1.1</article-title><source>Vet Comp Oncol</source><year>2016</year><volume>14</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28530307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/vco.283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of tyrosine kinase inhibitor therapy on skin toxicity and skin-related quality of life in patients with lung cancer: An observational study</article-title><source>Medicine (Baltimore)</source><year>2020</year><volume>99</volume><issue>23</issue><elocation-id>e20510</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32501998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1097/MD.0000000000020510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7306373</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borgonovo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cabiddu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lonati</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship between skin rash and outcome in non-small-cell lung cancer patients treated with anti-EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitors: a literature-based meta-analysis of 24 trials</article-title><source>Lung Cancer</source><year>2012</year><volume>78</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22795701</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.lungcan.2012.06.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Skin rash could predict the response to EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitor and the prognosis for patients with non-small cell lung cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e55128</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23383079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1371/journal.pone.0055128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3559430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Califano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tariq</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Compton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harwood</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expert consensus on the management of adverse events from EGFR tyrosine kinase inhibitors in the UK</article-title><source>Drugs</source><year>2015</year><volume>75</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1335</fpage><lpage>1348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26187773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s40265-015-0434-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4532717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacouture</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of cutaneous toxicities to EGFR inhibitors</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>812</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16990857</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1038/nrc1970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Terada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inui</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of dose variability and side effects for individualized cancer pharmacotherapy with tyrosine kinase inhibitors</article-title><source>Pharmacol Ther</source><year>2015</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25976912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/j.pharmthera.2015.05.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavalcanti</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasbach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dange</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saavedra</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Skin depigmentation associated with toceranib phosphate in a dog</article-title><source>Vet Dermatol</source><year>2017</year><volume>28</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>e95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28164401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/vde.12422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacouture</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anadkat</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bensadoun</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryce</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical practice guidelines for the prevention and treatment of EGFR inhibitor-associated dermatologic toxicities</article-title><source>Support Care Cancer</source><year>2011</year><volume>19</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1079</fpage><lpage>1095</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21630130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/s00520-011-1197-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3128700</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>