<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12075875</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12075875.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12075875</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12075875</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40370836</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2025.1511289</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Human papillomavirus in canine serum: evidence from a Chinese study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yumeng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn0004" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1750846/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/visualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names initials="L">Lulu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn0004" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yimin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn0004" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names initials="L">Lin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn0004" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2870204/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bi</surname><given-names initials="J">Jingshan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names initials="M">Min</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/566365/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lan</surname><given-names initials="T">Tian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/funding-acquisition/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names initials="W">Wenchao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1727294/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/funding-acquisition/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Institute of Virology, Wenzhou University</institution>, <addr-line>Wenzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>College of Animal Science and Technology, Guangxi University</institution>, <addr-line>Nanning</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Guangxi Centre for Animal Disease Control and Prevention</institution>, <addr-line>Nanning</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0005"><p>Edited by: Christopher Hamilton-West, University of Chile, Chile</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0006"><p>Reviewed by: Zhangyu Bu, Hangzhou First People&#8217;s Hospital, China</p><p>Jos&#233; Pizarro-Lucero, University of Chile, Chile</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Tian Lan, <email>827002151@qq.com</email>; Wenchao Sun, <email>sunwenchao131@163.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn0004"><p><sup>&#8224;</sup>These authors have contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">480746</issue-id><elocation-id>1511289</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-05-15 09:25:47.373"><day>15</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2025 Liu, Xie, Zhou, Zhou, Bi, Zheng, Lan and Sun.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Liu, Xie, Zhou, Zhou, Bi, Zheng, Lan and Sun</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-12-1511289.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Human papillomaviruses (HPVs) are well-known for causing both benign and malignant epithelial growths in humans, but their occurrence in non-human species is rarely reported. Expanding the understanding of HPV&#8217;s host range is essential for assessing its ecological and public health implications.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>We investigated serum samples from dogs collected in Guangxi, China, between 2014 and 2020. PCR screening was performed to detect HPV DNA, followed by sequencing and phylogenetic analysis of the positive amplicons.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>HPV DNA was unexpectedly detected in 2 out of 1,226 canine serum samples, yielding a detection rate of 0.16%. Phylogenetic analysis revealed that the sequences clustered with alpha2-HPV78 (GX-70-related) and alpha2-HPV94 (GX-47-related), respectively. Interestingly, both sequences displayed multiple amino acid variations in viral proteins. However, virus isolation was not achieved.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The detection of HPV nucleic acids in canine serum suggests a potential presence of HPV in canine hosts. These findings provide new insights into the possible host range of HPV, underscoring the need for further research to assess the virus&#8217;s infectivity, transmission dynamics, and implications for both animal and human health.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>papillomavirus</kwd><kwd>human papillomavirus</kwd><kwd>canine serum</kwd><kwd>phylogenetic analysis</kwd><kwd>public health</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that financial support was received for the research and/or publication of this article. This study is supported by the National Key Research and Development Program of China (No. 2023YFD1800400), Guangxi Agricultural Science and Technology project (No. Z201986), and Guangxi Natural Science Foundation project (No. 2022JJA130228).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="25"/><page-count count="7"/><word-count count="4433"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Veterinary Epidemiology and Economics</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Papillomaviruses (PVs) are a large and diverse group of DNA viruses that infect a broad range of vertebrate species, from benign warts to malignant cancers, with human papillomaviruses (HPVs) being particularly well-known for their association with such conditions in humans (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1&#8211;3</xref>). While more than 200 human papillomavirus (HPV) types have been identified and extensively studied for their role in human health (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), papillomaviruses have been detected across a broad range of animal species, reflecting their evolutionary adaptability to diverse hosts (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>) (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Papillomavirus infections have been documented in species as varied as cattle, horses, cats (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), dogs, avian (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), and even more exotic animals such as giant pandas, pangolins, and whales (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Despite their generally host-specific nature, the detection of papillomaviruses in a wide variety of animals suggests significant evolutionary diversification within the Papillomaviridae family (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). While HPV has been extensively studied in humans, reports of papillomavirus infections in non-human species are relatively scarce, and few studies have explored the presence of papillomaviruses in other mammals.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>This figure provides a comprehensive view of papillomavirus diversity. Phylogenetic tree of papillomavirus (PV) L1 gene sequences. The L1 nucleotide sequences of all papillomavirus types currently available in the Papillomavirus Episteme (PaVE) database were aligned using MAFFT. A maximum likelihood tree was constructed using PhyML, implementing the GTR&#8239;+&#8239;I&#8239;+&#8239;G substitution model to account for among-site rate variation and variable substitution rates. This model was selected based on jModeltest analysis. The resulting phylogenetic tree was visualized and displayed using phylotree.js.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1511289-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>While infection models for HPV in dogs and mice have recently been established (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), reports of natural HPV infections in non-human species remain limited. Papillomaviruses have traditionally been regarded as highly host-specific, with minimal evidence of cross-species transmission (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). However, bovine papillomavirus (BPV) has demonstrated its ability to infect a wide range of species beyond cattle (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). BPV infections have been documented in wild animals such as tapirs, giraffes, antelopes, and zebras, as well as domestic animals like horses and donkeys, where it causes equine sarcoids (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Furthermore, molecular detection of BPV DNA in the placenta and blood of healthy mares and their foals suggests potential vertical transmission, further supporting the notion that PV can cross species barriers (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Moreover, systematic studies on HPV in domestic animals, particularly dogs, are scarce, despite the close interaction between dogs and humans. Investigating the potential presence of HPV in dogs could provide important insights into the ecological complexity and host range of papillomaviruses.</p><p>In this study, we examined canine serum samples collected in Guangxi, China, from 2014 to 2020 and detected HPV DNA in two serum samples. To our knowledge, this is the first report of naturally occurring HPV detected in dogs outside of experimental models, raising important questions about the potential for papillomaviruses to infect a broader range of hosts in natural environments. Although contamination cannot be entirely ruled out, the detection of HPV nucleic acid in canine samples highlights a previously unexplored aspect of HPV ecology. These findings underscore the need for further investigation into the infectivity, transmission dynamics, and broader implications of papillomaviruses for both animal and human health.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec3"><label>2.1</label><title>Papillomavirus DNA detection and PCR</title><p>From 2014 to 2020, an extensive surveillance program was conducted in China to monitor rabies antibody prevalence across various species, including domestic pets (dogs and cats), rural dogs, and wild animals such as foxes and raccoons. Serum samples were collected from pets diagnosed in veterinary hospitals and from rural dogs undergoing rabies antibody testing at the Guangxi Animal Disease Prevention and Control Center, China. Serological testing was first conducted to detect antibodies against rabies virus. Subsequently, DNA was extracted from the serum samples, and PCR assays were performed to identify the presence of CPV viral DNA. We unexpectedly detected sequence fragments corresponding to papillomaviruses (PVs) in several serum samples. This unexpected discovery prompted us to perform additional PCR assays specifically targeting conserved regions of the PV genome. The primer sequences used for full-length genome amplification are provided in <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Tables S1, S2</xref>. The applied primer sequences and amplification conditions are shown in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The PCR mixture consisted of 2&#8239;&#956;L extracted DNA, 2&#8239;&#956;L of the primer pair (10&#8239;&#956;M), 25&#8239;&#956;L of 2&#8239;&#215;&#8239;Phanta Max Master Mix (Vazyme, Nanjing, China), and 21&#8239;&#956;L DNase/RNase-free water. PCR amplification was performed under the following cycling conditions: initial denaturation at 95&#176;C for 3&#8239;min; 35&#8239;cycles of 95&#176;C for 15&#8239;s, 62&#176;C for 15&#8239;s, and 72&#176;C for 1&#8239;min; followed by a final extension at 72&#176;C for 5&#8239;min. After amplification, 15&#8239;&#956;L of the PCR products were analyzed by 1.0% agarose gel electrophoresis, and the target bands were purified using a gel extraction kit. Each fragment was amplified and analyzed in triplicate to ensure reproducibility. The PCR products of the three fragments were cloned into the pMD18-T Easy vector (Takara Biotechnology Co., Ltd., Dalian, China) and submitted for Sanger sequencing by Sangon Biotech (Shanghai, China). Among these, those with the highest quality and concentration of viral DNA were chosen to ensure accurate and complete genome assembly. Subsequently, the assembly and editing of viral sequences were carried out using BioEdit software.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Overview of the different ORFs of the HPVs GX-47 and GX-70, their position in the genome, the length of the proteins they encode, and the other features they contain at the nucleotide (nt) or amino acid (aa) level.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gene</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Positions (nt)</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Fragment length</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Number of encoded amino acids (aa)</th><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Amino acid differences</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Function</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GX-47</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GX-70</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GX-47</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GX-70</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GX-47</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GX-70</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GX-47 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AJ620211">AJ620211</ext-link>)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GX-70 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AB793779">AB793779</ext-link>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E6</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57&#8211;482</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">188&#8211;508</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">426</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">321</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R47H</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Associated with the development of epithelial malignancies</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">485&#8211;736</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">532&#8211;783</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">267</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">252</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H56P</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Re-entry into S-phase cell cycle</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E1</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">749&#8211;2,791</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">796&#8211;2,775</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2043</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1980</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">681</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">660</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G220H, R501X, I502X, P503X, I581M</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D42E, K598T</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viral DNA replication and transcription</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,736&#8211;3,854</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,720&#8211;3,841</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,119</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,122</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">373</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">374</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S220R</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N247D, W251R, Q291R, N292H</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viral DNA replication, apoptosis, transcriptional repressor of E6/E7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E4</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,340&#8211;3,627</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,324&#8211;3,614</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">288</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">291</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A21E</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A51V, K94D</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Viral DNA replication</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,380&#8211;5,672</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,372&#8211;5,721</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,293</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,350</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">431</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">450</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S13F</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A61S, P96A, T112S, N260D, R285K, G296X, G297X, V333I, S349A, A370T, D380N, S381N, V451I</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Major capsid protein</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L1</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,731&#8211;7,242</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,741&#8211;7,195</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,862</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,455</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">954</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">485</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S487W, T502P</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I107V, T118S, P180S, N274S</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>2.2</label><title>Sequence assembly and phylogenetic analysis</title><p>Open reading frames (ORFs) of the complete genomes were predicted using the ORF Finder tool<xref rid="fn0001" ref-type="fn"><sup>1</sup></xref>. Multiple sequence alignments were conducted between the papillomavirus (PV) genomes identified in this study and reference PV sequences from different hosts using the Clustal W method. Percent pairwise identities, based on nucleotide and deduced amino acid sequences, were calculated using SDT3.4. Phylogenetic analysis was performed on the two canine-origin HPV strains as well as 433 reference sequences, which were obtained from the Papillomavirus Episteme (PaVE) database<xref rid="fn0002" ref-type="fn"><sup>2</sup></xref>. The E6 and L1 gene sequences from the GX-70 (HPV-78) and GX-47 (HPV-94) canine HPVs were aligned with reference genomes using ClustalW. Subsequently, maximum-likelihood phylogenetic trees were constructed with MEGA7, using midpoint rooting, and visualized with iTOL<xref rid="fn0003" ref-type="fn"><sup>3</sup></xref>. The best-fit model of nucleotide substitution, determined based on the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC), was GTR&#8239;+&#8239;G&#8239;+&#8239;I. Both maximum-likelihood and neighbor-joining trees were generated with a bootstrap value of 1,000 (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). All phylogenetic analyses were conducted using MEGA 7.0.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec5"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec6"><label>3.1</label><title>PV discovery and genome annotation</title><p>We detected two HPV-positive samples from 1,226 canine serum samples, yielding a detection rate of 0.16% (2/1226). Whole-genome sequencing of these samples revealed two distinct viral genomes, GX-70 (7,776&#8239;bp) and GX-47 (7,830&#8239;bp). Using the NCBI ORF prediction tool, we identified key papillomavirus open reading frames (ORFs), including early genes (E6, E7, E1, E2, E4) and late genes (L1, L2). The genome structures of GX-70 and GX-47 are illustrated in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>, depicting the positions and sizes of each ORF, which provides a comprehensive comparison of the genomic organization of the two viral strains.</p><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Genome organization of the two papillomaviruses identified in this study. <bold>(A)</bold> Circular genome organization of GX-47 (HPV-94); <bold>(B)</bold> Circular genome organization of GX-70 (HPV-78). The scale inside the circles represents nucleotide positions of the viral genome.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1511289-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>Detailed analysis of the open reading frames (ORFs) revealed multiple key amino acid substitutions between the two strains, including R47H in the E6 gene of GX-47 and H56P in the E7 gene of GX-70. These substitutions may have profound effects on viral replication, transcriptional regulation, and host-pathogen interactions, given the critical roles of E6 and E7 in the viral life cycle. <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> summarizes these mutations alongside the nucleotide positions, fragment lengths, and number of encoded amino acids for each ORF. The data indicate potential functional divergence between GX-47 and GX-70, laying a foundation for future studies to explore the implications of these mutations on viral behavior and pathogenicity.</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><label>3.2</label><title>Phylogenetic analysis</title><p>To understand the evolutionary relationships of GX-70 and GX-47, we conducted a maximum-likelihood phylogenetic analysis based on their whole-genome sequences. The analysis revealed that GX-70 clusters closely with HPV-78, while GX-47 shows slight divergence from HPV-94. Both strains are positioned within the Alphapapillomavirus 2 clade, aligning with their closest human relatives (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>). For further validation, we also analyzed the L1 and E6 genes. The L1 gene encodes the viral capsid protein, and the phylogenetic tree for L1 mirrored the overall whole-genome phylogeny (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref>). Similarly, the E6 gene, which is associated with epithelial malignancies, showed consistent evolutionary patterns with the full genome and L1-based trees (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C</xref>). This consistency across different gene segments supports the close evolutionary relationship between GX-70, GX-47, and their related strains, reinforcing their classification within the Alphapapillomavirus lineage.</p><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> The maximum likelihood (ML) tree of papillomavirus based on whole-genome sequences (downloaded from PAVE database), with a tree visualized with iTOL (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://itol.embl.de" ext-link-type="uri">https://itol.embl.de</ext-link>) and midpoint rooted. Two Chinese canine-origin HPV GX-47 and GX-70 strains (marked with a red circle) in the study. The red box highlights the clade belonging to the Alphapapillomavirus genus. <bold>(B)</bold> Phylogenetic trees generated with L1 regions of the papillomaviruses in canine serum. <bold>(C)</bold> Phylogenetic trees generated with E6 regions of the papillomaviruses in canine serum. The red lines in <bold>(B)</bold> and <bold>(C)</bold> indicate the Alphapapillomavirus genus. (BPV &#8211; <italic toggle="yes">Bos taurus</italic> papillomavirus; CPV &#8211; canine papillomavirus; EaPV &#8211; <italic toggle="yes">Equus asinus</italic> papillomavirus; EcPV &#8211; <italic toggle="yes">Equus caballus</italic> papillomavirus; FcaPV &#8211; Felis domesticus papillomavirus; HPV &#8211; human papillomavirus; MnPV &#8211; <italic toggle="yes">Mastomys natalensis</italic> papillomavirus; OaPV &#8211; <italic toggle="yes">Ovis aries</italic> papillomavirus; SsPV &#8211; <italic toggle="yes">Sus scrofa</italic> papillomavirus; SfPV &#8211; <italic toggle="yes">Sylvilagus floridanus</italic> papillomavirus).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1511289-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec8"><label>3.3</label><title>Canine-origin HPV sequence identity and amino acid mutations</title><p>The comparative genomic analysis revealed that the genomes of the two HPV-positive canine samples shared a nucleotide identity of 82.1%. The nucleotide identity of GX-47 with the reference strain <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AJ620211">AJ620211</ext-link> was as high as 99.4%. In contrast, the nucleotide identity between the GX-70 strain and the reference gene HPV-78 (No. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AB793779">AB793779</ext-link>) was 98.4% (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). However, the amino acid sequence homology between these two strains and canine papillomavirus (CPV) ranged from 44.7 to 49%.</p><fig position="float" id="fig4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of amino acid substitutions identified in the GX-47 <bold>(A)</bold> and GX-70 <bold>(B)</bold> strains of papillomavirus compared with their respective reference genomes (HPV 94 [<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AJ620211">AJ620211</ext-link>] and HPV 78 [<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AB793779">AB793779</ext-link>], respectively). Colored boxes represent viral open reading frames (ORFs), with corresponding positions and amino acid changes shown below each gene. Mutations are mapped to their respective positions in the viral proteins, highlighting potential differences in functional domains.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1511289-g004.jpg"/></fig><p>The closest related sequence in GenBank, HPV-94 (No. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AJ620211">AJ620211</ext-link>), exhibited multiple amino acid differences when compared to GX-47 and GX-70. As illustrated in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>, the GX-47 strain contains a key substitution in the E6 gene (R47H) as well as notable changes in the E2 (S220R) and L2 (S13F) proteins, which may impact viral replication and host-pathogen interactions. These substitutions may indicate a potential adaptation mechanism within GX-47. Similarly, in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B</xref>, the GX-70 strain is shown to have 13 novel substitutions in the L2 protein at positions 61, 96, 112, 260, 285, 296, 297, 333, 349, 370, 380, 381, and 451, as well as mutations in E7 (H56P) and E1 (D42E, K598T). These mutations, especially in the L2 protein, could affect capsid stability, immune evasion, and viral DNA packaging. Substitutions in the N-terminal region of L2 (positions 1&#8211;200) may impact capsid assembly and immune recognition, while mutations in the central and C-terminal regions (positions 200&#8211;450) could alter receptor interactions and viral entry mechanisms. These observed differences, presented in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>, suggest that GX-70 may have undergone evolutionary adaptations specific to the canine host.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec9"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>This study presents the first molecular evidence of human papillomavirus (HPV) strains in canine serum, revealing an unexpected dimension of papillomavirus (PV) biology. Serum has proven to be a valuable sample for detecting viral nucleic acids and antibodies in various canine virus studies. Previous research has identified several novel viruses in canine serum, such as canine bufaviruses (CBuVs) (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), porcine circovirus 3 (PCV3) (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), Torque teno canis virus (TTCaV) (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), and canine circovirus (CanineCV) (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). The detection of papillomaviruses in serum, however, is particularly noteworthy, as PVs are traditionally associated with epithelial tissues, primarily being detected in skin or mucosal lesions. The presence of HPV nucleic acids in dogs suggests either a viremic phase or a broader tissue tropism, challenging the current understanding of PV biology (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>).</p><p>While infection models for HPV in dogs have been established, these experimental models have primarily focused on viral pathogenesis under controlled conditions. Our detection of HPV in naturally collected canine serum highlights a previously unexplored aspect of HPV ecology, suggesting the potential for systemic infection beyond these experimental settings. This finding raises important questions about whether HPV can establish natural infections in dogs, a species that shares close proximity with humans.</p><p>Environmental contamination from human-derived HPV cannot be entirely excluded. However, the detection of papillomavirus DNA in blood across other species, including horses and cattle, supports the hypothesis of a viremic phase in certain PV infections (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). This finding prompts further investigation into whether HPV may circulate beyond epithelial tissues in non-human hosts, potentially expanding the virus&#8217;s transmission routes.</p><p>Our findings also mirror the well-documented cases of cross-species transmission involving bovine papillomavirus (BPV), which infects animals such as horses, zebras, and donkeys, and is implicated in the development of equine sarcoids (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). BPV&#8217;s ability to cross species boundaries suggests that HPV may similarly possess this potential under certain conditions, though such cross-species transmission of HPV remains speculative. The detection of viral strains in dogs&#8212;animals in close, regular contact with humans&#8212;raises significant questions about zoonotic risk and potential viral adaptation to new hosts (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>).</p><p>A significant limitation of this study is the inability to isolate live virus or confirm replication in canine cells. Although HPV DNA was detected in serum samples, without evidence of viral replication or protein expression in host cells, we cannot conclusively determine whether these viruses established productive infections. We attempted virus isolation using conventional cell culture techniques with multiple cell lines, but no cytopathic effects or viral replication were observed. This may be due to the lack of appropriate permissive cell models or the possibility that HPV does not actively replicate in canine blood cells. To address this limitation, future studies should explore the use of primary canine epithelial cells, organoid systems, or <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> models to assess viral infectivity, tissue tropism, and replication competence. These approaches will help clarify whether the presence of HPV DNA in canine serum represents a transient exposure, systemic spread, or a true active infection.</p><p>Despite these limitations, the detection of HPV DNA in canine serum raises important questions regarding viral transmission dynamics and host range. Given the increasing evidence of PVs in various animal species and the close interaction between dogs and humans, further research is essential to explore the possibility of interspecies transmission. Established HPV infection models in dogs provide a valuable platform for studying viral replication, immune responses, and the broader health implications in canine hosts.</p><p>While evaluating host immune responses is critical for understanding virus&#8211;host interactions, our study did not include serological analysis. This was primarily due to the lack of validated serological assays for detecting antibodies against HPV L1 or E6 proteins in dogs. Currently, no standardized protocols or reliable canine-specific secondary antibodies are available to facilitate such measurements. We acknowledge this limitation and propose that future studies prioritize the development of species-specific serological tools to enable comprehensive assessment of humoral immune responses in exposed animals.</p><p>In conclusion, this study provides the first molecular evidence of HPV in canine serum, suggesting that papillomaviruses may have a broader host range than previously recognized. Further research is critical to clarify the mechanisms of HPV transmission in dogs and assess the potential health risks for both canines and humans.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="fn0001"><p>
<sup>1</sup>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/orffinder/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/orffinder/</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn id="fn0002"><p>
<sup>2</sup>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://pave.niaid.nih.gov/" ext-link-type="uri">https://pave.niaid.nih.gov/</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn id="fn0003"><p>
<sup>3</sup>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://itol.embl.de" ext-link-type="uri">https://itol.embl.de</ext-link>
</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec10"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The datasets generated and analyzed during this study are publicly available in the GenBank repository. The complete genome sequences of the two canine-origin human papillomavirus (HPV) strains have been deposited under the following accession numbers: GX-47 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="PV384155">PV384155</ext-link>) and GX-70 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="PV384154">PV384154</ext-link>). Additional data supporting the findings of this study are provided in the <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Material</xref>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="sec11"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The animal studies were approved by Animal Ethics Committees of both Guangxi Centre for Animal Disease Control and Prevention and Guangxi University, China. The studies were conducted in accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements. Written informed consent was not obtained from the owners for the participation of their animals in this study because the Institutional Review Board (IRB) of Guangxi Centre for Animal Disease Control and Prevention has reviewed and approved the research study and has granted a waiver of the informed consent process. This waiver was granted based on the nature of the study, which involves minimal risk. As a result, animal owners were not required to sign a formal informed consent document. However, all ethical guidelines were followed to ensure the confidentiality of owner information and the integrity of the data.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="sec12"><title>Author contributions</title><p>YL: Visualization, Writing &#8211; original draft, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. LX: Methodology, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. YZ: Investigation, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. LZ: Data curation, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. JB: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. MZ: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. TL: Funding acquisition, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. WS: Funding acquisition, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec14"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ai-statement" id="sec15"><title>Generative AI statement</title><p>The author(s) declare that no Gen AI was used in the creation of this manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec16"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec17"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2025.1511289/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2025.1511289/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM2" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_2.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vergara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balanda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MH</surname><given-names>RFS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Detection and quantitation of human papillomavirus DNA in peripheral blood mononuclear cells from blood donors</article-title>. <source>J Med Virol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>91</volume>:<fpage>2009</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmv.25551</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31317547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alizon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murall</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saulnier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sofonea</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Detecting within-host interactions from genotype combination prevalence data</article-title>. <source>Epidemics</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>100349</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.epidem.2019.100349</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31257014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6899502</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McBride</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Human papillomaviruses: diversity, infection and host interactions</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>108</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-021-00617-5</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34522050</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bravo</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Felez-Sanchez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Papillomaviruses: viral evolution, cancer and evolutionary medicine</article-title>. <source>Evol Med Public Health</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>2015</volume>:<fpage>32</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emph/eov003</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25634317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4356112</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Unveiling the multifaceted realm of human papillomavirus: a comprehensive exploration of biology, interactions, and advances in cancer management</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1430544</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2024.1430544</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39176086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11338918</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>DCR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peleteiro</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pires</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DiMaio</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An update on canine, feline and bovine papillomaviruses</article-title>. <source>Transbound Emerg Dis</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>1371</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tbed.12555</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27615361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Canuti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munro</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kroyer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ojkic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>New insight into avian papillomavirus ecology and evolution from characterization of novel wild bird papillomaviruses</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>701</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.00701</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31031718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6473165</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agius</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phalen</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eden</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>New insights into Sauropsid Papillomaviridae evolution and epizootiology: discovery of two novel papillomaviruses in native and invasive island geckos</article-title>. <source>Virus Evol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>vez51</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ve/vez051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6874027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31798966</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Willemsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bravo</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Origin and evolution of papillomavirus (onco)genes and genomes</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>374</volume>:<fpage>20180303</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2018.0303</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30955499</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6501903</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Totain</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Misseri</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iche</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Birling</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Development of HPV16 mouse and dog models for more accurate prediction of human vaccine efficacy</article-title>. <source>Lab Anim Res</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>14</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s42826-023-00166-3</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37308929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10258489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodarzi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mosayebi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ganji</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raoufi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadelaji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Babaei</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>HPV16 mutant E6/E7 construct is protective in mouse model</article-title>. <source>BMC Biotechnol</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12896-024-00893-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39350162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11443707</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angeletti</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A human papillomavirus-independent cervical Cancer animal model reveals unconventional mechanisms of cervical carcinogenesis</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>2636</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2650.e5</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2019.02.004</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30840887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6812687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wenker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoby</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steck</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramsauer</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blatter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tobler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Equine SARCOIDS in captive wild equids: diagnostic and clinical management of 16 cases-a possible predisposition of the EUROPEAN cohort of SOMALI wild ass (<italic toggle="yes">Equus Africanus Somaliensis</italic>)?</article-title><source>J Zoo Wildl Med</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>28</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>37</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1638/2020-0166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33827158</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Virus diversity, wildlife-domestic animal circulation and potential zoonotic viruses of small mammals, pangolins and zoo animals</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>2488</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-38202-4</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37120646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10148632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Falco</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cutarelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marcus</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roperto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Vertical intrauterine bovine and ovine papillomavirus coinfection in pregnant cows</article-title>. <source>Pathogens</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>453</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/pathogens13060453</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38921751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11206582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>First identification of a novel parvovirus distantly related to human bufavirus from diarrheal dogs in China</article-title>. <source>Virus Res</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>265</volume>:<fpage>127</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2019.03.020</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30914299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>An epidemiological investigation of porcine circovirus 3 infection in dogs in the Guangxi Province from 2015 to 2017, China</article-title>. <source>Virus Res</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>270</volume>:<fpage>197663</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2019.197663</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31301332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7114628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular detection and genomic characterization of torque Teno canis virus in domestic dogs in Guangxi Province, China</article-title>. <source>J Biotechnol</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>252</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2017.05.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28483442</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Canine circovirus genome cloning and sequence analysis</article-title>. <source>Bing Du Xue Bao</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>429</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>. PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29979554</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiological and evolutionary analysis of canine circovirus from 1996 to 2023</article-title>. <source>BMC Vet Res</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>328</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12917-024-04186-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39033103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11264901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tisza</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pastrana</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peretti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Starrett</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Discovery of several thousand highly diverse circular DNA viruses</article-title>. <source>eLife</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e51971</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.51971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32014111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7000223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanat</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ataseven</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Babaeski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Derelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dogan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Equine and bovine papillomaviruses from Turkish brood horses: a molecular identification and immunohistochemical study</article-title>. <source>Vet Arhiv</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>601</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.24099/vet.arhiv.0507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Otten</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Tscharner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lazary</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antczak</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>DNA of bovine papillomavirus type 1 and 2 in equine sarcoids: PCR detection and direct sequencing</article-title>. <source>Arch Virol</source>. (<year>1993</year>) <volume>132</volume>:<fpage>121</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01309847</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8394687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasir</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campo</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bovine papillomaviruses: their role in the aetiology of cutaneous tumours of bovids and equids</article-title>. <source>Vet Dermatol</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>243</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>54</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3164.2008.00683.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18927950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>MEGA7: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis Version 7.0 for Bigger Datasets</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>, (<year>2016</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>1870</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1874</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msw054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27004904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8210823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>