<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11220278</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11220278.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11220278</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11220278</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38962702</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2024.1397051</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> tratt residue as an alternative feed for improving growth, blood metabolites, rumen fermentation, and slaughter performance in Hu sheep</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="H">Huijie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>11</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2631566/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names initials="X">Xinyu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2556029/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="W">Wenxuan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1712768/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names initials="C">Chuanshe</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1572793/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/funding-acquisition/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Key Lab of Animal Genetics, Breeding and Reproduction in the Plateau Mountainous Region, Ministry of Education, College of Animal Science, Guizhou University</institution>, <addr-line>Guiyang</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Institute of New Rural Development, Guizhou University</institution>, <addr-line>Guiyang</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Key Lab of Agro-Ecological Processes in Subtropical Region, Institute of Subtropical Agriculture, Chinese Academy of Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Changsha</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0001"><p>Edited by: Davide Pravettoni, University of Milan, Italy</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0002"><p>Reviewed by: Matteo Dell&#8217;Anno, University of Milan, Italy</p><p>Maghsoud Besharati, University of Tabriz, Iran</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Wenxuan Wu, <email>wxwu@gzu.edu.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">454084</issue-id><elocation-id>1397051</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>3</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>03</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-07-04 17:25:13.820"><day>04</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2024 Li, Song, Wu and Zhou.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Li, Song, Wu and Zhou</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-11-1397051.pdf"/><abstract><p>The utilization of agro-industrial by-products, such as fruit residues, presents a promising strategy for providing alternative feed to ruminants amidst rising prices and limited availability of traditional roughage. In this study, we investigated the effects of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> tratt residue, a local fruit residue in Guizhou province of China, on the growth, blood metabolites, rumen fermentation, and slaughter performance of Hu sheep. Ninety-six sheep were randomly divided into four groups, namely control, treatment 1, treatment 2, and treatment 3, and fed diets containing 0, 10, 20, and 30% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue, respectively. Feeding varying levels of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue showed no significant differences in dry matter intake, average daily gain, or the ratio of dry matter intake to average daily gain. However, sheep in the group fed with 30% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue showed the highest gross profit. Plasma albumin content was lower in groups fed with <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue-containing diets compared to the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Additionally, diet treatment 3 decreased plasma creatinine levels compared to control and treatment 1 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Sheep in treatment 2 and treatment 3 exhibited higher plasma high-density lipoprotein level than control and treatment 1 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05), as well as increased total cholesterol levels compared to control (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). There were no significant differences in other plasma metabolites. Rumen pH, N-NH<sub>3</sub>, volatile fatty acids, and methane levels did not differ significantly among the four groups. However, feeding diets treatment 2 and treatment 3 resulted in decreased water holding capacity and increased shear force compared to control and treatment 1 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Furthermore, pH, red chromaticity (a*), yellowness index (b*), and luminance (L*) were unaffected among the four groups of sheep. In conclusion, the inclusion of up to 30% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue had no adverse effects on growth performance, allowing for feed cost savings without impacting rumen fermentation parameters. <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> tratt residue also showed benefits in improving plasma protein efficiency and enhancing lipid metabolism, albeit with limited effects on meat quality. Considering its affordability, <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue presents a practical choice for low-cost diets, ensuring economic returns.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue</kwd><kwd>growth</kwd><kwd>blood metabolites</kwd><kwd>rumen fermentation</kwd><kwd>Hu sheep</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that financial support was received for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This study was financially funded by National Natural Science Foundation of China (31960674 and U20A2057), Science and Technology Project of Guizhou Province [(2020)1Y081], Key Project of Education Department of Guizhou Province [KY(2021)40], the Scientific Research Project of Forestry Bureau of Guizhou Province [(2019)007], and the &#8220;Ph.D. Village Chief&#8221; Project at Guizhou University in 2023.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="6"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="40"/><page-count count="9"/><word-count count="6606"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Animal Nutrition and Metabolism</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>To meet the increasing demand for cattle and sheep, exploring alternatives to traditional roughage is crucial. Utilizing agro-industrial by-products, particularly fruit residues, holds promise in this regard. Fruit residue, a by-product of fruit processing or crushing, offers advantages such as high production levels, low cost, and moderate nutrient content, making it a viable ingredient for ruminants (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Several studies have demonstrated its potential as a substitute for conventional feed, showing no adverse effects on growth performance. For instance, Massod et al. (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) fed crossbred calves varying amounts of apple residue as a substitute for corn, observing no significant differences in growth performance or nutrient digestibility. Similarly, Sharif et al. (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>) found that feeding orange pulp to lambs did not affect their feed intake or growth performance negatively. Molosse et al. (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) reported that grape residues could enhance the growth rate of lambs. Another study by Hao et al. (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) found that adding sea-buckthorn residue increased metabolizable protein supply and the average daily gain of sheep, although it was advisable to limit the addition level to 16% to avoid negative impacts on nutrient digestion. These findings collectively support the effective utilization of fruit residue by ruminants, offering a practical and scientifically backed approach to alternative feeding strategies.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt is a perennial wild deciduous shrub with a slightly sour taste, astringent flavor, strong aroma, and crisp texture (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Guizhou Province is the pioneering region in cultivating, developing, and utilizing RRT resources, making it the sole province in China and globally to engage in large-scale planting and industrial development (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). RRT earned its reputation as the &#8216;king of VC&#8217; due to its exceptionally high concentration of Vitamin C in its juice. Each 100 grams of RRT juice contains up to 3,500&#8201;mg of Vitamin C, making it 500 times higher than apple and pear juice, 100 times higher than citrus juice, and 40 times higher than lemon juice (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Moreover, RRT also contains <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt polysaccharide, which possesses various beneficial functions such as antioxidation, immune enhancement, anti-coagulation, anti-tumor (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) properties, blood glucose reduction, and improvement of anti-oxidative stress ability in mice (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt extract demonstrates effectiveness in human medicine by reducing blood sugar (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>) and blood lipid levels (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), inhibiting tumor development (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), and protecting liver function (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>).</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue is the by-product of fresh <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt physical juicing, mainly generated over a 45-day period from mid-August to late September. <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue exhibits high moisture content ranging from 62.1 to 69.5%, rendering it susceptible to decay and contributing to resource wastage and environmental pollution. Regrettably, a significant quantity of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue has been indiscriminately discarded during <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt production seasons until now. Hence, there is an imperative to explore practical means of utilizing <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue.</p><p>We hypothesized that <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue may be fed to meat sheep without having an adverse effect on their growth and metabolism because of its comparatively rich nutritional composition. In order to investigate the effects of varying quantities of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue on the growth performance, blood metabolites, rumen fermentation, and slaughter performance of Hu sheep, we tested our hypothesis by providing meat sheep feed containing <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue. The findings of this study aim to provide a theoretical foundation for the scientific utilization of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue in ruminants.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec3"><label>2.1</label><title>Animal care</title><p>The present experiment received approval from the Animal Ethics Committee of Guizhou University (EAE-GZU-2023-E042).</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>2.2</label><title>Experimental design and animal management</title><p>The <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue was obtained from a large-scale <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt juice processing factory in Longli county, Guizhou province, China. The proximate chemical compositions of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue were determined as follows: dry matter 31.50%, gross energy 18.19&#8201;MJ/kg dry matter, crude protein 11.99% dry matter, ether extract 1.43% dry matter, neutral detergent fiber 53.71% dry matter, acid detergent fiber 47.22% dry matter, and organic matter 97.03% dry matter, respectively.</p><p>Ninety-six male finishing twins of Hu sheep, averaging 60 (&#177;1.4) days in age and 24.22 (&#177;1.26) kg in body weight (mean&#8201;&#177;&#8201;standard difference), were randomly divided into four blocks: control, treatment 1, treatment 2, and treatment 3. Each block consisted of three replicates with eight individual sheep in each replicate. Animals were provided one of four diets differing in <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue level. The control sheep were fed a basal diet without <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue, while treatment 1, treatment 2, and treatment 3 sheep received diets containing 10, 20, and 30% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue on a dry matter basis, respectively. <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue replaced the corresponding level of peanut vine (on a dry matter basis) for treatment 1, treatment 2, and treatment 3. The consumed diet by sheep was in the form of pelleted total mixture ration. The ingredients and chemical composition of the diet fed to the sheep are presented in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Ingredients and chemical composition of diets fed to sheep (air-dried basis).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Item</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment 1</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment 2</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment 3</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ingredients</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stevia residue</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peanut vine hay powder</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peanut hull powder</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corn</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean meal</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean hull</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat bran</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palm oil granules</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NaCl</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CaHPO<sub>4</sub></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Premix<sup>1</sup></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chemical composition</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dry matter</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolizable energy</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crude protein</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.9</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organic matter</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.9</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral detergent fiber</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acid detergent fiber</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.9</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>One kilogram of premix contained Fe 100.0&#8201;mg, Cu 17.0&#8201;mg, Mn 72.5&#8201;mg, Zn 122.0&#8201;mg, Co 0.50&#8201;mg, Se 0.30&#8201;mg, I 0.80&#8201;mg, V<sub>A</sub> 13000&#8201;IU, V<sub>E</sub> 68.5&#8201;mg, V<sub>D</sub> 700&#8201;IU.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Before the trial, the sheep were dewormed to ensure body hygiene and underwent a 7-day adaptation period for regrouping. Animals were then subjected to a 10-day pre-feeding period followed by a 35-day trial duration. The diet was formulated according to the nutrient requirements of meat-type sheep and goats (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Sheep were fed <italic toggle="yes">ad libitum</italic> twice a day at 08:00 and 17:00, and had free access to exercise and water throughout the study.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>2.3</label><title>Dietary composition</title><p>Approximately 200&#8201;g of dietary sample from each block was collected daily and pooled at the end of the trial. The composited dietary sample was continuously dried in a blast oven at 65&#176;C for 48&#8201;h. After drying, the samples were ground and crushed using a 40-mesh screen. The gross energy of the sample was determined using an oxygen bomb calorimeter (6,400 CALORIMETER, Parr). The dry matter (method 934.01), crude protein (method 968.06), and ash (method 942.05) content were determined following AOAC methods (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). The neutral detergent fiber and acid detergent fiber were determined using the FIBRETHERM automatic system FT12 (Germany) according to the method of Van Soest et al. (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). The organic matter content was calculated using the following formula: organic matter (%)&#8201;=&#8201;100%&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;ash (%).</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><label>2.4</label><title>Growth performance and economic benefits</title><p>On the 1st and 36th days of the trial period, all sheep were weighed before the morning feeding. These weights were recorded as the initial body weight and the final weight, respectively. The provided feed and leftover were carefully documented throughout the experiment. From these data, the dry matter intake, average daily gain, average net gain, and the ratio of dry matter intake to average daily gain were calculated.</p><p>The cost of artificial and veterinary drugs was not considered in the analysis because the experimental sheep were large-scale farmed and received the same feeding management as that for ordinary Hu sheep, except for different diets. Therefore, the weight gain profit and cost were calculated using the following formula, which was based on the feed cost, feed intake, and weight gain data of the Hu sheep during the experiment.</p><p>Feed cost (CNY/sheep)&#8201;=&#8201;[dry matter intake (g/sheep/d)/1,000]&#8201;&#215;&#8201;test days(d)&#8201;&#215;&#8201;feed price (CNY/kg).</p><p>Weight gain income (CNY/sheep)&#8201;=&#8201;(final weight&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;initial weight)&#8201;&#215;&#8201;live sheep price (CNY/kg).</p><p>Gross profit (CNY/sheep)&#8201;=&#8201;Weight gain income &#8722; Feed cost.</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><label>2.5</label><title>Plasma biochemical metabolites</title><p>In each replicate, four sheep (the selecting criteria in one block is 3 sheep for the biggest body weight, 6 sheep for the medium body weight, and 3 sheep for the least body weight) were selected for blood sample Research Topic at the end of the experiment. Ten mL of blood was drawn from the jugular vein using a disposable heparin sodium anticoagulant vacuum. The blood samples were then centrifuged at 805&#8201;&#215;&#8201;g for 15&#8201;min and divided into 3-mL centrifuge tubes. Plasma metabolites, including total protein, albumin, alkaline phosphatase, alanine transaminase, aspartate transaminase, creatinine, high-density lipoprotein, total cholesterol, triglyceride, and urea, were measured using a fully automated biochemical analyzer (BS-360VET, Mindray).</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><label>2.6</label><title>Rumen fermentation</title><p>On day 36 after blood sampling, two sheep were randomly selected from each pen (totally 6 sheep per block) to obtain rumen fluid before morning feeding. A gastric tube ruminal fluid sampler was orally inserted into the rumen to collect the fluid. The pH was immediately measured using a portable pH meter (PHS-3C). The remaining ruminal fluid was filtered using four layers of gauze and then centrifuged at 1425&#8201;&#215;&#8201;g for 10&#8201;min. The supernatant was collected for N-NH<sub>3</sub> and volatile fatty acids analysis. VFA concentration was analyzed using a gas chromatograph (GC-2010-plus, Shimadzu, Japan) equipped with an SH-Rtx-WAX column (30.00&#8201;m&#8201;&#215;&#8201;0.25&#8201;mm&#8201;&#215;&#8201;0.25&#8201;&#956;m). The flame hydrogen ion detector (FID) and gasification chamber were set at temperatures of 220&#176;C and 200&#176;C, respectively. The initial column temperature was set at 100&#176;C and increased to 150&#176;C at a rate of 5&#176;C per minute. Crotonic acid was used as the internal standard (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><label>2.7</label><title>Slaughter performance</title><p>Six sheep closest to the average body weight in each block were slaughtered to collect longissimus dorsi for later analysis. The sheep were fasted for 24&#8201;h and water for 12&#8201;h before being weighed, and this weight was recorded as their pre-slaughter live weight. After evisceration, the carcass weight was measured. The carcass percentage was calculated using the formula: carcass weight divided by pre-slaughter live weight. The pH<sub>45 min</sub> and pH<sub>24 h</sub>, water holding capacity, shear force, and meat color of red chromaticity (a*), yellowness index (b*), and luminance (L*) were measured following the procedures described by Shackelford et al. (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec10"><label>2.8</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The experimental data were analyzed using MIXED models by SAS 9.4 (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC, United States). A randomized complete block design with repeated measures was employed for data analysis. The <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue levels (0, 10, 20, and 30%) were designated as fixed effects, with sheep as the random effect. Tukey&#8217;s method was adopted to determine differences among mean values, with statistical significance defined as <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05. Three sheep data in control, treatment 2, and treatment 3 were excluded from the analysis due to foot injuries, leading to decreased final body weight relative to initial body weight.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec11"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec12"><label>3.1</label><title>Growth performance and economic benefits</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, no significant differences were observed in the growth performance indicators (dry matter intake, average daily gain) among the four blocks of Hu sheep. The inclusion of three <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue-containing diets for treatment 1, treatment 2, and treatment 3 reduced the feed price relative to control, leading to decreased feed costs as the proportion of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue in the diet increased for treatment 1, treatment 2, and treatment 3. Sheep fed treatment 1 and treatment 2 showed reduced gross profit compared with control and treatment 3. The highest gross profit was observed in treatment 3, surpassing that of control.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effects of varying levels of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue on growth performance and economic benefits of Hu sheep.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment 1</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment 2</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment 3</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEM</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Growth performance</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial weight, kg</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.23</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.49</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.40</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.63</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dry matter intake, g/d</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2086.31</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2072.86</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2114.67</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2160.34</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">101.04</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Final weight, kg</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.38</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.01</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.64</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.47</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANG, kg</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.15</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.52</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.16</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.71</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average daily gain, g/d</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">232.87</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">214.81</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">204.49</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">220.39</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.67</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F/G</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.01</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.71</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.36</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.51</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" char="." colspan="7" rowspan="1">Economic benefit <sup>a</sup> (CNY/sheep)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feed price, CNY/Kg</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.25</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feed cost</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">248.27</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">235.79</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">229.44</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">223.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight gain income</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">260.80</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">240.64</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">231.68</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">250.88</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gross profit</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.53</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.85</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.24</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>The price of live Hu sheep is 32 CNY/kg during the trial. Control: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;0% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue; Treatment 1: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;10% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue; Treatment 2: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;20% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue; Treatment 3: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;30% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec13"><label>3.2</label><title>Plasma metabolites</title><p><xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> presents the effects of varying levels of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue on plasma metabolites of Hu sheep. Compared to control, the plasma albumin content was lower in treatment 1, treatment 2, and treatment 3 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Treatment 3 resulted in decreased plasma Crea compared to control and treatment 1 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Plasma high-density lipoprotein content was higher in treatment 2 and treatment 3 relative to control and treatment 1 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The plasma total cholesterol content of treatment 2 and treatment 3 was significantly higher than that of control (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). No significant differences were observed in other plasma metabolites among these four groups.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Effects of varying levels of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue on plasma metabolites of Hu sheep.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Item</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment 1</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment 2</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment 3</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEM</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TP, g/L</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.76</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.71</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.69</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.82</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALB, g/L</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.27<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.32<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.25<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.83<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALP, U/L</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">257.79</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">336.38</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">284.56</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">287.72</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.87</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT, U/L</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.43</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.26</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.91</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.68</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST, U/L</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">106.99</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">115.35</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.59</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.85</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.85</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST/ALT</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.84</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.48</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.44</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.96</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crea, &#956;mol/L</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.51<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.67<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.59<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.73<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.24</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HDL, mmol/L</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TC, mmol/L</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.92<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.12<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG, mmol/L</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea, mmol/L</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.32</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.41</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.43</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.56</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a,b</sup>Means in the superscript differs in the same row (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Control: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;0% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue; Treatment 1: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;10% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue; Treatment 2: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;20% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue; Treatment 3: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;30% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec14"><label>3.3</label><title>Rumen fermentation parameters</title><p>Feeding varying levels of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue did not exert a difference in levels of rumen pH and N-NH<sub>3</sub>. The rumen total volatile fatty acids, acetic acid, propionic acid, butyric acid, and methane were also unaffected for Hu sheep consuming the four diets (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Effects of varying levels of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue on rumen fermentation paramenters of Hu sheep.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment 1</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment 2</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment 3</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEM</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.72</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.75</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.77</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.73</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NH<sub>3</sub>-N, mmol/L</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.88</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.44</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.77</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.87</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total VFA, mmol/L</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">146.64</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">152.30</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">155.11</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">159.57</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.47</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetic, %</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.29</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.72</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.38</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.32</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propionic, %</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.24</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.58</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.81</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.74</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Butyric, %</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.06</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.32</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.45</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetic/Propionic</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.36</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.37</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CH<sub>4</sub>, mmol/L</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.99</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.74</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.34</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.38</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a,b</sup>Means in the superscript differs in the same row (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). CH<sub>4</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;0.45&#8201;&#215;&#8201;Acetic acid-0.275&#8201;&#215;&#8201;Propionic acid&#8201;+&#8201;0.4&#8201;&#215;&#8201;Butyric acid. Control: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;0% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue; Treatment 1: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;10% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue; Treatment 2: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;20% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue; Treatment 3: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;30% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec15"><label>3.4</label><title>Slaughter performance and organ index</title><p>No significant differences were observed for the slaughter performance and organ index of Hu sheep fed varying levels of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue (<xref rid="tab5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Effects of varying levels of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue on slaughter performance of Hu sheep.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment 1</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment 2</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment 3</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEM</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-slaughter live weight, kg</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.32</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.47</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.38</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dressed weight, kg</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.75</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.87</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.15</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.40</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carcass weight, kg</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.19</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.64</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.72</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.70</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carcass percentage, %</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.47</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.20</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.90</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart weight, g</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">141.85</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">144.78</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">147.85</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">146.98</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.03</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver-gallbladder weight, g</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">598.37</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">609.22</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">572.33</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">582.82</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.77</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kidney weight, g</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.10</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.82</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.77</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.02</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung weight, g</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">884.10</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">782.15</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">776.75</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">768.43</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.61</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intestines weight, kg</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.53</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stomach weight, kg</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a,b</sup>Means in the superscript differs in the same row (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Control: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;0% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue; Treatment 1: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;10% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue; Treatment 2: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;20% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue; Treatment 3: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;30% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec16"><label>3.5</label><title>Meat quality</title><p>As listed in <xref rid="tab6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>, compared with control and treatment 1, sheep in treatment 2 and treatment 3 showed decreased water holding capacity (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Correspondingly, the shear force of treatment 2 and treatment 3 was increased compared to that of control and treatment 1 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). There were no significant differences in pH, red chromaticity (a*), yellowness index (b*), and luminance (L*).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Effects of varying levels of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue on meat quality of Hu sheep.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment 1</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment 2</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment 3</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SEM</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH<sub>45 min</sub></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.80</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.03</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.81</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.85</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH<sub>24 h</sub></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.63</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.64</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.57</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.62</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water holding capacity (%)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.01<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.68<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.93<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.60<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shear force (N)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.59<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.84<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.79<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.49<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Red chromaticity (a*)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.77</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.65</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.07</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.39</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yellowness index (b*)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.13</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.35</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.11</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.06</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Luminance (L*)</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.08</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.54</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.79</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.61</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a,b</sup>Means in the superscript differs in the same row (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Control: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;0% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue; Treatment 1: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;10% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue; Treatment 2: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;20% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue; Treatment 3: basal diet&#8201;+&#8201;30% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec17"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>The livestock industry faces challenges such as rising roughage prices, insufficient supply, and high transportation costs (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Leveraging fruit residues as alternative feed sources could offer a promising solution. Fruit residues are rich in nutrients, including vitamins, minerals, polyphenols, and dietary fiber (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Previous studies (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) have shown that they can reduce feed costs. However, while many fruit residues have been explored as substitutes in ruminant production, limited information exists regarding the utilization of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue, a locally unique fruit residue primarily produced in Guizhou province, China. Therefore, this study seeks to assess the feasibility of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue as an alternative roughage for Hu sheep.</p><sec id="sec18"><label>4.1</label><title>Effects of varying levels of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue on growth performance and economic benefits of Hu sheep</title><p>The present study revealed that feeding <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue had no statistically adverse effects on growth parameters, including dry matter intake, average daily gain, and feed-to-gain ratio. This suggests that <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue can serve as a viable roughage option for Hu sheep. However, these findings contradict those of Oduguwa (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>), who reported improved feed intake and growth performance in West African dwarf sheep fed pineapple residue. The disparity may stem from differences in fruit residue types. In another study by Hsu et al. (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>), it was observed that 15% citrus residue had no effect on average daily gain, but whole citrus residue silage significantly improved feed conversion efficiency compared to dried citrus residue.</p><p>Regarding economic benefits, the net gross profit increased gradually with higher levels of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue, peaking at a 30% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue inclusion level. This suggests that <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue utilization can reduce feed costs and enhance economic returns. However, it was unexpected to find lower gross profits at 10 and 20% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue levels, possibly due to decreased average daily gain and increased feed-to-gain ratio. We observed that the lowest gross profit for the treatment 2 diet compared to control would remain relatively stable only if the live sheep price decreased by 20.69 CNY/kg, representing a 35.34% reduction. However, such a significant price drop is unlikely to take place. Therefore, in practice, there may be an animal threshold price for substituting low-price fruit residues while considering economic returns. The economic viability of low-price fruit residues will be significantly enhanced with increased live animal prices.</p></sec><sec id="sec19"><label>4.2</label><title>Effects of varying levels of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue on plasma metabolites of Hu sheep</title><p>Plasma metabolites are vital indicators of animal health and metabolic activity <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). The study results revealed that, in comparison to the control group, <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue treatment significantly reduced plasma albumin levels in treatment 1, treatment 2, and treatment 3 with increasing dosage. Nonetheless, it&#8217;s worth noting that all four groups remained within the normal range, indicating minimal detrimental effects on protein metabolism. Plasma Crea, a by-product of protein metabolism, serves as a marker of protein efficiency (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Typically, a higher blood Crea level correlates with lower protein utilization. Interestingly, in this study, plasma Crea concentration was lower in treatment 3 compared to the control and treatment 1 groups, suggesting that incorporating a high level of R<italic toggle="yes">osa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue may enhance plasma protein utilization efficiency in Hu sheep (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). The authors assume that tannin might be the specific compound within the <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> extract which reduces the protein utilization, because the phenolic hydroxyl groups in tannins could form the insoluble complexes with proteins which cannot be used by animals (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). In the review of Wang et al. Who determined the tannin level is 1.6&#8201;g (calculated per 100&#8201;g edible part) (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Triglyceride, a measure of lipid metabolism, primarily consists of low-density lipoprotein and high-density lipoprotein. High-density lipoprotein has the capacity to transport cholesterol out of cells, thereby reducing blood cholesterol levels (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Zeweil et al. (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>) reported that rabbits showed increased blood high-density lipoprotein content when pomegranate was added to their diet. The heightened plasma high-density lipoprotein levels in treatment 2 and treatment 3 groups in our study may imply that <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue is beneficial for lipid metabolism. According to the study (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), the dry matter (DM) of pomegranate pomace was 33.02%, which is higher than <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue (31.50%); the crude protein (CP) of pomegranate pomace was 9.2%, which is lower than <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue (11.99%); the neutral detergent fiber (NDF) and acid detergent fiber (ADF) respectively were 35.35 and 30.61%, which is lower than <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue (53.71 and 47.22%). No significant differences were observed for other plasma metabolites.</p><p>Effects of varying levels of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue on rumen fermentation parameters of Hu sheep.</p><p>In this study, no significant differences were found for rumen fermentation parameters among the four groups of sheep. These results indicate that <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue inclusion had no adverse impact on rumen fermentation in Hu sheep. Considering the significance of rumen fermentation parameters, it can be concluded that <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue is safe for use in ruminant production. However, the limited microbial diversity in the rumen observed in this study warrants further investigation in future research.</p></sec><sec id="sec20"><label>4.3</label><title>Effects of varying levels of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue on slaughter performance and organ index of Hu sheep</title><p>Slaughter performance is a crucial measure of livestock productivity in animal feeding (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33&#8211;35</xref>), typically associated with economic benefits. In this study, the carcass percentage slightly decreased with the increased <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue level. This result may be attributed to the RRT seed, which constitutes 39.60% of the <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue, being too hard to be digested and absorbed by Hu sheep, thus restricting nutrient utilization. Therefore, finding effective methods to better utilize <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt seed in future research is necessary. The organ index remained unaffected by <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue treatment.</p></sec><sec id="sec21"><label>4.4</label><title>Effects of varying levels of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue on meat quality of Hu sheep</title><p>Meat quality is a general evaluation based on different kinds of meat quality traits, which greatly influence the choice of consumers (<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Meat sensory quality indicators, including pH, water holding capacity, shear force, and color, are critical factors influencing consumer preference (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Shear force is a crucial indicator of meat tenderness and is negatively correlated with the meat&#8217;s water holding capacity. Meat becomes tougher with increased shear force or decreased water holding capacity. In our study, the increased shear force and decreased water holding capacity in treatment 2 and treatment 3 compared to control and treatment 1 may suggest that <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue can influence meat tenderness. Further investigation is needed to determine the reasons for this. No other significant differences were observed in meat sensory quality.</p><p>Since <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue is a local and novel feed resource, according to the authors&#8217; knowledge, it has not been reported using as a feed resource till now, therefore, we take the proportion of other fruit residues added into ruminant feed as the reference adding level in the current study. Taasoli and Kafilzadeh (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>) respectively provided 30% ensiled apple residue and 20% dried apple residue, on dry matter basis, to Sanjabi male lambs; Gowda et al. (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>) fed a total mixed ration containing 62% silage pineapple fruit residue and 48% concentrate mixture (dry matter basis) to sheep; Tayengwa and Mapiye (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>) summarized the effect of dietary supplements citrus and winery wastes (grape pomace) for ruminant animal, the amount of citrus residue added is 25&#8201;~&#8201;400&#8201;g/kg for lambs, 90&#8201;~&#8201;180&#8201;g/kg for cows, 50&#8201;~&#8201;200&#8201;g/kg for calves, and the amount of grape pomace added is 762&#8201;g/kg for lambs, 300&#8201;g/kg for wethers, 100&#8201;g/kg for steers.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec22"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>Overall, the inclusion of up to 30% <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue in the diet had no effect on growth performance and could save feed costs for Hu sheep. <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue is beneficial for improving plasma protein efficiency and enhancing lipid metabolism. The use of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue does not affect rumen fermentation parameters. Feeding <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue has no effect on slaughter performance and organ index, and it resulted in a limited effect on meat quality. When considering a low-price diet, <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue is a good choice, but its seed requires further processing for better utilization, and there might be a threshold level in practice to ensure economic income. Therefore, based on the available results and taking into account the cost-effectiveness of supplemental <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue, we recommend an optimal inclusion level of 30% for <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt residue.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec23"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/supplementary material, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="sec24"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The animal study was approved by Animal Ethics Committee of Guizhou University. The study was conducted in accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="sec25"><title>Author contributions</title><p>HL: Conceptualization, Writing &#8211; original draft. XS: Writing &#8211; original draft, Investigation, Data curation. WW: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Supervision, Project administration. CZ: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Validation, Funding acquisition.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors thank the Animal Nutrition Laboratory of Guizhou University for providing the chemical analysis facilities for this research. We also thank the Charlesworth Group for English language editing.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec27"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec28"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerra-Rivas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubio</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;nez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallardo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mantec&#243;n</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of grape pomace in growing lamb diets compared with vitamin E and grape seed extract on meat shelf life</article-title>. <source>Meat Sci</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>116</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2016.02.022</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26908145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Massod</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ganai</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheikh</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farooq</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Afzal</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of feeding graded levels of apple pomace on growth performance, haemato-biochemical parameters and rumen metabolites in crossbred calves</article-title>. <source>Indian J Anim Res</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>1000</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18805/ijar.B-3229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharif</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mushtaq</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nawaz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mustafa</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of varying levels of dried citrus pulp on nutrient intake, growth performance and economic efficiency in lambs</article-title>. <source>J Appl Anim Res</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>264</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09712119.2017.1294540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Molosse</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deolindo</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>C&#233;cere</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Rosa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vedovatto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of dietary supplementation with grape residue flour on weight gain, metabolic profile, leukogram, proteinogram and antioxidant response in suckling lambs</article-title>. <source>Res Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>139</volume>:<fpage>112</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rvsc.2021.07.004</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34280655</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nutrient digestibility, rumen microbial protein synthesis, and growth performance in sheep consuming rations containing sea buckthorn pomace1</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>3412</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jas/sky201</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29762731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6095388</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Recent advances on main active ingredients, pharmacological activities of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxbughii</italic> and its development and utilization</article-title>. <source>Food Secur</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1051</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/foods12051051</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36900567</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10001392</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Botanical characteristics, phytochemistry and related biological activities of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt fruit, and its potential use in functional foods: a review</article-title>. <source>Food Funct.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1432</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/d0fo02603d</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33533385</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>QQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farha</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phytochemicals, essential oils, and bioactivities of an underutilized wild fruit Cili (<italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Ind Crop Prod</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>143</volume>:<fpage>111928</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2019.111928</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rout</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhanja</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maity</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Bioactive polysaccharides from natural sources: a review on the antitumor and immunomodulating activities</article-title>. <source>Biocatal Agric Biotechnol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>101425</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bcab.2019.101425</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Physicochemical, functional, and biological properties of water-soluble polysaccharides from <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt fruit</article-title>. <source>Food Chem</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>249</volume>:<fpage>127</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2018.01.011</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29407915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Polyphenol from <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> tratt fruit ameliorates the symptoms of diabetes by activating the P13K/AKT insulin pathway in db/db mice</article-title>. <source>Food Secur</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>636</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/foods11050636</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35267269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8909201</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of dietary energy on growth performance, carcass characteristics, serum biochemical index, and meat quality of female Hu lambs</article-title>. <source>Anim Nutr</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>499</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>506</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aninu.2020.05.008</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33364466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7750792</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Inhibition of metastasis and invasion of ovarian cancer cells by crude polysaccharides from <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt in vitro</article-title>. <source>Asian Pac J Cancer Prev</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>10351</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7314/APJCP.2014.15.23.10351</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25556474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessing the potential value of <italic toggle="yes">Rosa roxburghii</italic> Tratt in arsenic-induced liver damage based on elemental imbalance and oxidative damage</article-title>. <source>Environ Geochem Health</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>1165</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>75</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10653-020-00612-4</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32564172</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diao</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Nutritional requirements of meat-type sheep in China</source>. <publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>China Agriculture Press</publisher-name> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll1">Association of Official Analytical Chemists, Association of Official Agricultural Chemists (US)</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Official methods of analysis of the association of official analytical chemists</article-title>. <source>J Pharm Sci</source>. (<year>1971</year>) <volume>60</volume>:<fpage>334</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jps.2600600253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Soest</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Methods for dietary fiber, neutral detergent fiber, and nonstarch polysaccharides in relation to animal nutrition</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci</source>. (<year>1991</year>) <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>3583</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>97</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(91)78551-2</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1660498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Feeding a negative dietary cation-anion difference to female goats is feasible, as indicated by the non-deleterious effect on rumen fermentation and rumen microbial population and increased plasma calcium level</article-title>. <source>Animals</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>664</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani11030664</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33801486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7999398</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shackelford</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koohmaraie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of sampling, cookery, and shear force protocols for objective evaluation of lamb longissimus tenderness1</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>82</volume>:<fpage>802</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/2004.823802x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15032437</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Erinle</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adewole</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fruit pomaces their nutrient and bioactive components, effects on growth and health of poultry species, and possible optimization techniques</article-title>. <source>Anim Nutr</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>357</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>77</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aninu.2021.11.011</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35600557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9110891</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wargovich</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anticancer properties of fruits and vegetables</article-title>. <source>HortScience</source>. (<year>2000</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>573</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21273/hortsci.35.4.573</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alhotan</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Commercial poultry feed formulation: current status, challenges, and future expectations</article-title>. <source>Worlds Poult Sci J</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>279</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>99</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00439339.2021.1891400</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roll</surname><given-names>AAP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Medeiros Gon&#231;alves</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>DCN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Olive pomace for the feeding of commercial poultry: effects on performance, meat and eggs quality, haematological parameters, microbiota and immunity</article-title>. <source>Worlds Poult Sci J</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>363</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>76</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00439339.2021.1894409</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oduguwa</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanusi</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fasae</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oni</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arigbede</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nutritive value, growth performance and haematological parameters of west African dwarf sheep fed preserved pineapple fruit waste and cassava by-products</article-title>. <source>Niger J Anim Prod</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.51791/njap.v40i1.671</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Xylooligosaccharides and Fructooligosaccharides affect the intestinal microbiota and precancerous colonic lesion development in rats</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>134</volume>:<fpage>1523</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jn/134.6.1523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15173423</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Degen</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>QM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Growth performance and hormonal status during feed restriction and compensatory growth of small-tail Han sheep in China</article-title>. <source>Small Rumin Res</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>144</volume>:<fpage>191</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smallrumres.2016.09.018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yakubu</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bilbis</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akanji</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of selected parameters of rat liver and kidney function following repeated administration of yohimbine</article-title>. <source>BIOKEMISTRI</source>. (<year>2003</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mount</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The molecular physiology of uric acid homeostasis</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Physiol</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>323</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-physiol-021113-170343</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25422986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Makkar</surname><given-names>HPS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects and fate of tannins in ruminant animals, adaptation to tannins, and strategies to overcome detrimental effects of feeding tannin-rich feeds</article-title>. <source>Small Rumin Res</source>. (<year>2003</year>) <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>241</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>56</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0921-4488(03)00142-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haemmerle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schoiswohl</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Birner-Gruenberger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riederer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Fat mobilization in adipose tissue is promoted by adipose triglyceride lipase</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>306</volume>:<fpage>1383</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1100747</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15550674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeweil</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zahran</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Gindy</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdulgader</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of pomegranate peel addition to the diet enriched with linseed oil on performance, lipid traits in the meat, blood lipid profile and antioxidant property of rabbits under summer conditions</article-title>. <source>Egypt J Nutr Feeds</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>485</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21608/ejnf.2016.74990</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guclu</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baytok</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aktug</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oguz</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamalak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Investigation in terms of digestive values, silages quality and nutrient content of the using pomegranate pomace in the ensiling of apple pomace with high moisture contents</article-title>. <source>J Appl Anim Res</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>1233</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09712119.2018.1490300</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>LHP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Assis</surname><given-names>DEF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Estrada</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Assis</surname><given-names>GJF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zamudio</surname><given-names>GDR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Carcass and meat quality traits of Nellore young bulls and steers throughout fattening</article-title>. <source>Livest Sci</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>229</volume>:<fpage>28</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.livsci.2019.09.012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary &#946;-glucan supplementation improves growth performance, carcass traits and meat quality of finishing pigs</article-title>. <source>Anim Nutr</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>380</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aninu.2019.06.006</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31890915</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6920398</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of dietary inulin supplementation on growth performance, carcass traits, and meat quality in growing&#8211;finishing pigs</article-title>. <source>Animals (Basel)</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>840</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani9100840</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31640197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6826911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Biffin</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of whole carcase medium voltage electrical stimulation, tenderstretching and longissimus infusion with actinidin on alpaca meat quality</article-title>. <source>Meat Sci</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>164</volume>:<fpage>108107</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2020.108107</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32155532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prache</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schreurs</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guillier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Review: factors affecting sheep carcass and meat quality attributes</article-title>. <source>Animal</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>100330</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.animal.2021.100330</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34400114</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taasoli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kafilzadeh</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of dried and ensiled apple pomace from puree making on performance of finishing lambs</article-title>. <source>Pak J Biol Sci</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>294</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3923/pjbs.2008.294.297</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18817207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gowda</surname><given-names>NKS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vallesha</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Awachat</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anandan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pal</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasad</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Study on evaluation of silage from pineapple (<italic toggle="yes">Ananas comosus</italic>) fruit residue as livestock feed</article-title>. <source>Trop Anim Health Prod</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>557</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11250-015-0762-2</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25633915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tayengwa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mapiye</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Citrus and winery wastes: promising dietary supplements for sustainable ruminant animal nutrition, health, production, and meat quality</article-title>. <source>Sustain For</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>3718</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su10103718</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>