<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11772351</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11772351.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11772351</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11772351</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39877731</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2024.1539556</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial: Advancements in understanding zoonotic parasitic diseases</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morch&#243;n</surname><given-names initials="R">Rodrigo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/42300/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gabrielli</surname><given-names initials="S">Simona</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/769561/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciuca</surname><given-names initials="L">Lavinia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/795609/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Napoli</surname><given-names initials="E">Ettore</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carret&#243;n</surname><given-names initials="E">Elena</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/49724/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Zoonotic Disease and One Health Group, Faculty of Pharmacy, Biomedical Research Institute of Salamanca (IBSAL), Centre for Environmental Studies and Rural Dynamization (CEADIR), University of Salamanca</institution>, <addr-line>Salamanca</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Public Health and Infectious Diseases, Sapienza University of Rome</institution>, <addr-line>Rome</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Veterinary Medicine and Animal Production, University of Naples Federico II</institution>, <addr-line>Naples</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Department of Veterinary Sciences, University of Messina</institution>, <addr-line>Messina</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Internal Medicine, Veterinary Medicine and Therapeutic Research Group, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Research Institute of Biomedical and Health Sciences (IUIBS), Universidad de Las Palmas de Gran Canaria</institution>, <addr-line>Las Palmas de Gran Canaria</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited and reviewed by: Antoinette Marsh, The Ohio State University, United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Rodrigo Morch&#243;n <email>rmorgar@usal.es</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">454084</issue-id><elocation-id>1539556</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>04</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>28</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-01-31 11:25:15.980"><day>31</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2025 Morch&#243;n, Gabrielli, Ciuca, Napoli and Carret&#243;n.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Morch&#243;n, Gabrielli, Ciuca, Napoli and Carret&#243;n</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-11-1539556.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="commentary-article" xml:lang="en" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/60883/advancements-in-understanding-zoonotic-parasitic-diseases"/><kwd-group><kwd>zoonosis</kwd><kwd>One Health</kwd><kwd>humans</kwd><kwd>animals</kwd><kwd>wildlife</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="4"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="1675"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Parasitology</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>The field of zoonotic parasitic diseases, which encompasses infections transmissible between animals and humans, is currently undergoing significant advances, underscoring their growing importance in global public health. These diseases, caused by diverse range of pathogens including protozoa, helminths and ectoparasites, exhibit a broad spectrum of symptoms and severities, some of which result in severe acute illness or even death. Transmission of these parasites can occur through a variety of sources, including contaminated food and water, direct contact with domestic and wild animals, and vector-borne pathways involving insects or other arthropods. Despite the critical impact of zoonotic parasitic diseases, their detection, treatment, and control are often hindered by incomplete understanding and fragmented knowledge of their complex life cycles, host interactions, and environmental reservoirs (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>).</p><p>These challenges are further exacerbated by environmental and societal factors. Global warming is altering the habitats and distribution of both vectors and hosts, leading to the emergence and re-emergence of zoonotic diseases in previously unaffected regions (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Additionally, the globalization of trade and travel facilitates the rapid movement of animal and human reservoirs, introducing parasites and vectors into new geographic areas and increasing the risk of outbreaks. These factors call for a comprehensive and integrated approach to the management of zoonotic parasitic diseases (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p><p>The primary aim of this Research Topic is to enhance the understanding of zoonotic parasitic diseases, especially those that are emerging and that have recently come to widespread public attention. This includes deepening the knowledge of their biology, epidemiology, and the local, regional, national or global advances in their diagnosis, treatment and control. Additionally, the Research Topic aims to facilitate the exchange of updated information on these diseases, particularly in relation to their proteomics, immunology and molecular biology, as well as new vaccines and diagnostic tools.</p><p>This Research Topic has gathered 15 manuscripts&#8722;12 original research papers, one short research paper, one case report and one opinion paper&#8212;with contributions from 104 authors. These papers focus on zoonotic parasitic diseases and related areas, covering Research Topics such as the biology and epidemiology of these diseases; advances in their diagnosis, treatment and control; studies on parasite-host relationships; research in proteomics, immunology and molecular aspects; the development of new vaccines and diagnostic tools; and illustrative clinical cases of these conditions.</p><p>The team of <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2023.1270202" ext-link-type="uri">Rond&#243;n et al.</ext-link> has contributed to the detection of <italic toggle="yes">Iodamoeba b&#252;tschlii, Dientamoeba fragilis</italic>-like<italic toggle="yes">, Giardia</italic> sp., <italic toggle="yes">Balantidium/Buxtonella</italic> sp., <italic toggle="yes">Capillaria</italic> sp., <italic toggle="yes">Trichuris</italic> sp., strongyliform larvae, and <italic toggle="yes">Oesophagostomum</italic> sp. potentially zoonotic parasites, in primates from a zoo in Italy. The results provide important and necessary information that justifies the generation of adequate safety measures for both visitors and animal keepers. Another study, by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2023.1334832" ext-link-type="uri">Cancino-Faure et al.</ext-link>, searched for the presence of zoonotic filarial nematodes in mosquitoes [<italic toggle="yes">Aedes</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Ochlerotatus</italic>) <italic toggle="yes">albifasciatus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Culex pipiens</italic>] and dogs in a previously unstudied semi-rural area of Central Chile, finding <italic toggle="yes">Acanthocheilonema reconditum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Setaria equina</italic>; although the authors did not detect the presence of zoonotic parasites, they did stress the importance of continuous surveillance, especially in areas that are not regularly monitored.</p><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1360593" ext-link-type="uri">de Andrade Vieira et al.</ext-link> analyzed the presence of <italic toggle="yes">Dirofilaria immitis</italic> in an area of Rio de Janeiro (Brazil) showing the expansion of the disease and highlighting the importance of the use of prophylactic measures and awareness of both health personnel and dog owners to interrupt the spread and establishment of heartworm disease. On the other hand, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1368307" ext-link-type="uri">Esteban-Mendoza et al.</ext-link>, through the application of molecular and morphological characterization techniques, demonstrated the importance of their use in the detection of microfilaremic dogs infected by <italic toggle="yes">D. immitis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">A. reconditum</italic>, and their usefulness in making an accurate diagnosis to establish an appropriate treatment for each filarial species. Likewise, and in relation to the study of diagnostic techniques, the study carried out by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1392238" ext-link-type="uri">Albasyouni et al.</ext-link> underlines the need to use molecular techniques to describe intestinal coccidian parasites (<italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> spp.) together with morphological tools in birds (pigeons).</p><p>The research of <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1406564" ext-link-type="uri">Liu et al.</ext-link> presented a study in which molecular techniques were applied to detect several zoonotic species of <italic toggle="yes">Cryptosporidium</italic> spp. and others adapted to wild rodents in a province of China. Similarly, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1452237" ext-link-type="uri">Uakhit et al.</ext-link> identified <italic toggle="yes">Baylisascaris</italic> spp. by molecular and phylogenetic analyses in wild carnivores from different regions of Kazakhstan, highlighting their potential risk of infection to humans. These findings underscore the importance of a multidisciplinary &#8220;One Health&#8221; approach to prevent the spread of such pathogens.</p><p>Also, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1444614" ext-link-type="uri">Bandelj et al.</ext-link> presented, for the first time, a case report describing the presence of <italic toggle="yes">Gongylonema pulchrum</italic>, a potentially zoonotic parasite, in a Slovenian roe deer using morphological and molecular techniques. Moreover, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1434627" ext-link-type="uri">Elshahawy et al.</ext-link> conducted a study to molecularly characterize leukocytozoonosis in pigeons in Egypt, with the aim of developing more effective control and prevention strategies to limit the spread of infection to other birds.</p><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1399772" ext-link-type="uri">Rodr&#237;guez-Escolar, Balmori-de la Puente et al.</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1352236" ext-link-type="uri">Rodr&#237;guez-Escolar, Hern&#225;ndez-Lambra&#241;o et al.</ext-link> conducted two studies focused on controlling vector-borne zoonotic diseases, developing infection risk maps for <italic toggle="yes">Dirofilaria</italic> spp. in Serbia and canine leishmaniasis in Spain and Portugal. To this aim, they took into account the habitat suitability map for their main vectors, the weighting of these maps with the parasite behavior in these vectors and their validation with the geolocation of infected dogs. This approach offers high predictive accuracy, providing an excellent tool for the control and prevention of these diseases.</p><p>In addition, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1460452" ext-link-type="uri">Raw et al.</ext-link> highlight the relevance of conducting efficient and effective deworming programs in dogs for <italic toggle="yes">Ancylostoma caninum</italic> that can be administered regularly without the need for veterinary supervision in Australian Aboriginal communities where veterinary visits may be limited. In reference to leishmaniasis, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1477696" ext-link-type="uri">Cavalera et al.</ext-link> report that the seasonality of anti-<italic toggle="yes">L. infantum</italic> titres in dogs should be considered in the design of clinical trials to evaluate treatments and preventive measures for canine leishmaniasis, which would enhance the efficacy of control strategies.</p><p>In relation to parasite-host relationships and the resulting immune response, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1342169" ext-link-type="uri">Chai et al.</ext-link> presented data on the T cell-mediated immune response in the maintenance of intestinal immune homeostasis and the impact of <italic toggle="yes">Moniezia benedeni</italic> infections in sheep, particularly in altering immune cell densities. In addition, the role of a recombinant protein (rEg.P29) from <italic toggle="yes">Echinococcus granulosus</italic> as a potential epitope peptide vaccine is explored by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2024.1451538" ext-link-type="uri">Yang et al.</ext-link>, emphasizing its relevance given the zoonotic significance of this parasite.</p><p>We would like to express all our gratitude to all 104 researchers who have contributed to this Research Topic by sharing their valuable studies on zoonotic parasitoses from the &#8220;One Health&#8221; perspective. We also extend our thanks to the reviewers and staff of <italic toggle="yes">Frontiers in Veterinary Science</italic>, whose efforts have ensured the successful completion of this Research Topic.</p></body><back><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>RM: Writing &#8211; original draft, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. SG: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. LC: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. EN: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. EC: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s2"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Zoonotic parasitic diseases: emerging issues and problems</article-title>. <source>Int J Parasitol</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>1209</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpara.2008.05.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18603251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2547118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Noman</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tasnim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masud</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anika</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>AMMT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A systematic review on reverse-zoonosis: global impact and changes in transmission patterns</article-title>. <source>J Adv Vet Anim Res</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>601</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/javar.2024.k810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39605779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11590586</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tazerji</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nardini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Safdar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shehata</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An overview of anthropogenic actions as drivers for emerging and re-emerging zoonotic diseases</article-title>. <source>Pathogens</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1376</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/pathogens11111376</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36422627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9692567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anisuzzaman</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Labony</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwofie</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Food- and vector-borne parasitic zoonoses: global burden and impacts</article-title>. <source>Adv Parasitol</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>120</volume>:<fpage>87</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>136</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/bs.apar.2023.02.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36948728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>