<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="brief-report" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10899473</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10899473.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10899473</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10899473</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38420212</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2024.1335939</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Brief Research Report</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Risk factors for the development of stifle injuries in canine agility athletes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kieves</surname><given-names initials="NR">Nina R.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/942892/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoben</surname><given-names initials="A">Abigail</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1479960/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Markley</surname><given-names initials="AP">Arielle Pechette</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/834835/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Veterinary Clinical Sciences, College of Veterinary Medicine, The Ohio State University</institution>, <addr-line>Columbus, OH</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Division of Biostatistics, College of Public Health, The Ohio State University</institution>, <addr-line>Columbus, OH</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0001"><p>Edited by: David Levine, University of Tennessee at Chattanooga, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0002"><p>Reviewed by: Barbara Bockstahler, University of Veterinary Medicine Vienna, Austria</p><p>James Edward Miles, University of Copenhagen, Denmark</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Nina R. Kieves, <email>kieves.1@osu.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">454084</issue-id><elocation-id>1335939</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>09</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>02</day><month>2</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>28</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-02-29 17:25:10.590"><day>29</day><month>02</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2024 Kieves, Shoben and Markley.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kieves, Shoben and Markley</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-11-1335939.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="sec1"><title>Objectives</title><p>Our aim was to determine risk factors for developing stifle injuries in canine agility athletes. We hypothesized that increased weight, increased frequency of competing, and greater number of runs/day would increase risk.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Study design</title><p>Internet based survey, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;4,197.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Methods</title><p>Individuals with at least one dog who had competed in agility in the past 3&#8201;years were eligible. Injury history was defined as an injury to the stifle that kept the dog from participating in agility for &gt;1&#8201;week. Logistic regression models were used to estimate associations between variables of interest and injury history.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Results</title><p>Handlers of 216 dogs reported a history of injury. The majority were cranial cruciate ligament (CCL) injury (101/216), and patella luxation (40/216). In the final model, five variables were independently associated with odds of stifle injury (in addition to age). Heavier dogs (adjusted for height), Border Collies, male dogs neutered &lt;10&#8201;months, female dogs spayed before their first heat cycle, handlers aged 18&#8211;24, and teeter contact behavior were associated with increased risk.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Heavier dogs were more likely to report injury, but there was no association with injury and increased number of competition days, or runs/day. The Border Collie breed was at the highest risk of injury. There was substantial risk for stifle injury with early spay/neuter. Additionally, a significant increase in risk of injury was reported for younger (18&#8211;24) vs. older handlers (65+). Athlete fitness level, conformation, and genetic predisposition to injury may play the most significant role in the development of injury.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>agility</kwd><kwd>canine</kwd><kwd>stifle injury</kwd><kwd>risk factor</kwd><kwd>canine athlete</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that no financial support was received for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="27"/><page-count count="6"/><word-count count="4917"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Veterinary Surgery</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec6"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Canine agility is a highly physical sport with frequent abrupt turns taken at high speed, coupled with running and jumping, and the need to navigate obstacles that change in elevation. Courses include numerous obstacles that dogs must complete, with the goal of completing the course in the shortest time with no errors. The physical demands of these activities place significant stress on the dog&#8217;s musculoskeletal system, particularly on the joints. Injury rates of up to 42% have been reported in the literature for dogs competing in agility (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1&#8211;5</xref>). Thoracic limb injury is most commonly reported including injury to the shoulder and paws (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1&#8211;3</xref>). However, one study reported pelvic limb injuries to be more common than thoracic limb injuries (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p><p>One of the most common debilitating orthopedic injuries an athlete can suffer is a knee injury. In humans, injury is often suffered during athletic events that require similar lateral cutting motions such as dogs undergo while competing in agility. Stifle injury in dogs competing in agility has been reported as high as 13% of injuries in one study (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), and 10% in another, with over 75% of these being classified as severe (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>).</p><p>Stifle disease is a significant health concern for agility dogs, particularly if the injury is to the cranial cruciate ligament (CCL), as it is documented that these dogs have a low chance of returning to sport (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Treatment of CCL disease is also costly financially to the handler/owner and carries with it a significant loss of competition time. Given the impact that injury to the stifle can have on a dog&#8217;s agility career, our aim was to evaluate risk factors associated with developing stifle injury while participating in canine agility competitions. We hypothesized that increased weight, along with increased frequency of competing and increased number of runs per day of competition would increase risk of stifle injury.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec7"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec8"><label>2.1</label><title>Study design</title><p>An internet-based survey, in English, was distributed via the internet with approval by the institutional review board at The Ohio State University using Qualtrics survey software (Qualtrics; Provo, UT). Specifics of this survey and results were previously published (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Briefly, individuals with at least one dog who had competed in agility in the past 3&#8201;years were eligible to complete the survey.</p><p>Stifle injury history was defined as an injury to the stifle that kept the dog from participating in agility for over a week. All participating owners were asked several questions about demographic variables (for handler and dog), training variables (e.g., age starting training each obstacle, method used for training contact and weave obstacles, trained contact obstacle behavior), and competition history (frequency of competing, runs per competition day, frequency of national and international competition, and frequency of competing on various surfaces). Owners reporting a stifle injury were asked additional follow up questions regarding the injury.</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><label>2.2</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Statistical analysis was performed with commercially available software (Stata version 15.1, StataCorp, College Station, TX). Logistic regression models were used to estimate possible associations between variables of interest and stifle injury history. All models were adjusted for dog age to account for differences in exposure time for injury history. For the three pre-specified variables of interest (height and weight together, number of competition weekends per year, and typical number of runs per day), we tested each for an association in models that only adjusted for dog age. Given the lack of information on risk factors for stifle injury in the literature, we also considered a broader set of candidate variables via a stepwise model building process. All candidate variables were first assessed for univariate association with injury; variables significant at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.20 were kept for future model building. Then three models were built via backward selection using blocks of variables (demographic, training, and competition factors). Variables that were significant in the stepwise model building at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.20 were kept for consideration in the final model. The final model was built via backward selection until all included variables were associated with injury at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec10"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><p>Complete demographic data related to this study population has been previously published (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). The most common breeds represented were Border Collie (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1,052), mixed breed (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;616), and Australian Shepherd (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;312). Mean age of the dogs at the time of survey was 6.3&#8201;&#177;&#8201;2.6&#8201;years.</p><p>Of the 4,197 dogs in the sample, 216 (5.2%) had a history of stifle injury. Nearly half (46.8%) of dogs reporting a stifle injury reported a cranial cruciate ligament (CCL) rupture (101/216). Other stifle injuries reported by more than 5 dogs were: medial luxating patella (26, 12.0%), arthritis (16, 7.4%), lateral luxating patella (14, 6.5%), medial collateral ligament sprain (13, 6.0%), lateral collateral ligament sprain (12, 5.6%), and caudal cruciate rupture (6, 2.8%). The exact diagnosis was reported to be unknown for 37 dogs (17%). Owners reported that they knew or suspected the injury occurred in competition or practice for 30% of dogs (65/214), while 45% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;97) said it did not and 24% (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;52) were unsure. These percentages were nearly identical for the 101 CCL rupture injuries reported: 32% (32/101) in competition or practice; 46% (46/101) not in competition or practice, and 23% (23/101) were unsure.</p><p>In models adjusting only for dog age, body characteristics (height and weight) were associated with stifle injury risk, with heavier dogs (of the same height) having a higher odds of stifle injury (OR: 1.27 per 10 pounds (4.5 kilograms) heavier; 95% CI: 1.12 to 1.44) and taller dogs (of the same weight) having lower odds of stifle injury (OR: 0.73 per 4 inches (10.2 centimeters) shorter; 95% CI: 0.59 to 0.91). Number of trial weekends per year was not associated with odds of stifle injury (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.99) with all groups (&lt;5&#8201;weeks per year up to 26+ weekends per year) having similar odds of injury. Similarly, number of runs per trial day was not associated with odds of stifle injury (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.46).</p><p>In the final model built via stepwise selection (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>; <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>), five variables were independently associated with odds of stifle injury (in addition to age). Body characteristics (height and weight) were associated with stifle injury, with taller dogs having lower odds of developing a stifle injury and heavier dogs (adjusted for height) having increased odds of injury. The other four variables in the final model were breed, spay/neuter status, handler age, and teeter contact behavior. Among breeds, Border Collies were at higher risk and there were minimal differences noted among other breed groups. Male dogs neutered before 10&#8201;months and female dogs spayed before their first heat cycle had markedly higher reported rates of stifle injury compared to all other sex/neuter groups that had generally similar odds of stifle injury. There was a notable decrease in odds as handler age increased, with the highest odds of injury observed among dogs of the youngest handlers (18&#8211;24) and the lowest among dogs of handlers aged 65&#8201;years and older (OR: 0.35). For the teeter contact, dogs that were either not trained to perform a specific behavior at the end of the teeter or dogs performing a different behavior than the most common training options, had lower risk of reporting a history of stifle injury.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Odds ratios from final model built using stepwise selection.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjusted OR final model</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dog Age (per 1&#8201;year older)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 (1.13, 1.25)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height &amp; Weight</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height (per 4 in (10.2&#8201;cm) taller)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 (0.47, 0.80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight (per 10 lbs. (4.5&#8201;kg) heavier)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39 (1.20, 1.60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breed</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Border Collie</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63 (1.10, 2.40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed Breed</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 (0.46, 1.24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shetland Sheepdog</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.46, 1.86)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australian Shephard</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 (0.36, 1.43)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REFERENCE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male, Intact</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REFERENCE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female, Intact</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26 (0.63, 2.50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male, Neutered &lt;10&#8201;months</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.32 (1.27, 4.26)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male, Neutered 10&#8211;18&#8201;months</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 (0.57, 2.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male, Neutered &gt;24&#8201;months</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 (0.45, 1.78)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female, Spayed &lt;1&#8201;cycle</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.81 (1.62, 4.88)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female, Spayed 1&#8201;cycle</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27 (0.64, 2.53)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female, Spayed &gt;1&#8201;cycle</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 (0.60, 2.05)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Handler current age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#8211;24</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REFERENCE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#8211;34</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 (0.43, 1.96)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35&#8211;44</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 (0.42, 1.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#8211;54</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (0.37, 1.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55&#8211;64</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (0.35, 1.46)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65+</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35 (0.15, 0.80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Teeter contact</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 on 2 off</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">REFERENCE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 on (down)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.51, 1.75)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 on (standing)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 (0.59, 1.25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No specific behavior</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 (0.13, 0.86)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 (0.11, 0.83)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Graphical display of the odds ratios for history of stifle injury from the final model built using stepwise selection.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-11-1335939-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec11"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>While we found the expected association between heavier dogs and stifle injury history, there was no association with report of injury and an increased number of competition days, or runs per day. Therefore, our hypothesis was partially accepted. The lack of association of increased injury risk with increased number of competition days and/or runs may indicate that there truly is no association with increased agility-specific activity and stifle injury. It could also be a reflection of overall training load. If a dog trains substantially but does not compete often, their overall time under load could be similar to a dog that trains little but competes frequently. Prospective training data would need to be collected over the duration of a dog&#8217;s competitive lifespan to elucidate such information. Our group has previously evaluated the effect of training load on injury risk and found that dogs who train very little, or for &gt;120&#8201;h per week had a higher risk of developing injury than dogs who trained an intermediate amount (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). However, this study evaluated overall risk of injury while competing in agility, not specific types of injury. The lack of association observed between increased injury risk and number of competition days may also reflect a scenario in which dogs who are not as fit, or have had a stifle injury, are not entered into as many competitions or runs during competition by their handler as compared to those dogs who are healthy. Without training data, and prospective evaluation of fitness levels, we cannot assess these factors.</p><p>In the adjusted model, the Border Collie breed was at the highest risk of reporting stifle injury as compared to other breeds, with no other common agility breed (Australian Shepherd, Shetland Sheepdog, or mixed breed) showing an increased risk of injury. Border Collies competing in agility have been previously reported as having a higher risk factor of injury overall (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). In a previous report evaluating CCL injury risk in the general population, Border Collies were the 29th most common breed to report CCL injury (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). There is likely geographic variability in injury given that Engdahl found Boerboel&#8217;s and Dogo Canario to have the highest rate of development of CCL injury in Sweden (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). We were unable to specifically evaluate risk for breeds known to be considered high risk for CCL injury (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) as they were not highly represented in this survey. Therefore, it is possible, due to the sample size for some of these breeds (i.e., Labrador Retriever), that we were unable to capture a significant increase in risk in these populations. Furthermore, we evaluated overall stifle risk injury, not only CCL injury.</p><p>Further study is needed into why Border Collies competing in agility may be at a higher risk of developing stifle injury including CCL injury than the general population of Border Collies. It may be related to genetics of the breed, breed conformation, or their speed and high drive during competitions, which have become even more complex and challenging over time. Contrary to our finding here that the Border Collie is at higher risk for developing stifle disease, a recent publication evaluating risk factors associated with CCL injury in agility dogs did not find the Border Collie to be at a higher risk for injury than other breeds (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Our finding of increased risk for Border Collies developing stifle injury was especially high after adjusting for dog height and weight when compared to other breeds evaluated. This adjustment was not done in the Sellon et al. study (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), which could also explain the differences seen between these two studies. Again, our study assessed risk for all types of stifle injury, of which CCL injury was the highest reported injury, but this difference could also account for the increased risk found here.</p><p>The majority of stifle injuries reported here were CCL injuries, which pose a substantial potential loss of career for these athletes, as only 65% of agility dogs return to sport following tibial plateau leveling osteotomy (TPLO) surgery for treatment of CCL injury (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). In human medicine a higher percentage of patients are reported to return to sport at 80% following anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) reconstruction surgery. However, only 65% of them return to their pre-injury level of performance and only 55% return to a competitive level of sport (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). This is despite studies showing that dogs undergoing TPLO have a return to near normal ground reaction forces as soon as 150&#8201;days after surgery (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Therefore, it is unknown why dogs may not return to competition despite returning to &#8220;normal&#8221; function as evaluated by force plate. Given these data, clients should be warned that when CCL injury is sustained, return to sport, particularly return to highly competitive levels of sport, may not be possible. Setting appropriate expectations early in the process of recovery should improve clinician-client relationships. It is currently unknown why such a low percentage of dogs return to sport. This could indicate that competitive agility dogs do not have the standard expected outcome with the stabilization technique elected, or it may be the handler&#8217;s choice to no longer compete with that dog following injury and treatment, as opposed to the dog&#8217;s lack of physical ability to perform agility activities. Furthermore, we do not know what degree of osteoarthritis these dogs had, nor what their meniscal status was, both of which likely play a role in ability to return to full competitive level of agility. We also cannot determine based on the survey data collected what the nature of the CCL injury in terms of a possible traumatic tear vs. the more commonly sustained degenerative injury to which dogs are prone. Histopathology of the CCL would be required to determine the ultimate cause of injury, and this is not commonly performed.</p><p>It may be that conformation and genetic predisposition to CCL injury play the most significant role in the development of this injury (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). In human ACL injury, the most common mechanism of injury is sudden pivoting or cutting maneuver which often occur during sports such as soccer, basketball, and football. Non-contact injury is also reported, with risk factors associated with tearing of the ACL including sex (female &gt; male), and numerous bone morphologic characteristics such as lateral femoral condylar ratio, notch width index, and lateral posterior tibial slope (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). In dogs, one study found an association between tibial anatomical-mechanical axis angle and CCL injury (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Due to the nature of this survey, conformational and genetic factors were not able to be assessed. The survey did ask whether the injury was thought to have occurred during competition or training, with approximately 30% of owners reporting that the injury (either CCL or other) occurred during agility training or competition. However, the complex etiology of CCL disease specifically makes it challenging to determine whether stifle injuries reported during training and competition were truly acute, traumatic injuries, or progression of previous chronic partial tears that were a result of other underlying risk factors. A study evaluating the cause of CCL injury in field trial dogs found owners to be inaccurate in their understanding of and assessment of how the injury occurs (i.e., traumatic vs. degenerative) (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Therefore, we cannot say if any of the injuries reported were truly traumatic while actively participating during agility, or in fact whether they might have occurred regardless of the dog&#8217;s participation in agility activities. For instance, dogs that sustained a CCL injury may have done so even without participation in agility at all during their lifetimes.</p><p>An increased risk of stifle injury with increased body weight was identified. Sellon and Marcellin-Little, also reported an association between increasing dog weight and CCL injury in a population of agility dogs (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Obesity has been found to be associated with CCL injury (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20&#8211;22</xref>), and obesity is more common in neutered dogs (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Heavier weight, as adjusted for height, was found to be a risk factor for injury in this survey, which may support those previous findings (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Athlete fitness level may also play a substantial role in the development of CCL injury. Sellon and Marcellin-Little reported that agility dogs performing routine core strength and balance exercises had lower risk of reported CCL injury (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Muscle activation has been proposed as a contributing factor to the development of CCL injury in dogs (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>), as well as humans (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>).</p><p>Early spay/neuter was associated with a substantial increase in risk for stifle injury. Previous reports have suggested that early spay/neuter may increase risk of CCL injury (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>), and the majority of stifle injuries reported here were CCL injury, which may have helped drive this result. Previous reports have also shown an overall increased risk in the development of orthopedic disease in larger dogs with early spay/neuter (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Given the small number of other injuries reported, we were unable to statistically evaluate CCL injury as compared to other stifle injuries to better assess which risk factors are most associated with which specific stifle injuries. This should be prospectively studied in the future to determine if the risk factors reported here influence specific stifle injuries (CCL vs. patella vs. other). Ultimately, additional prospective work is needed to best assess what factors may decrease risk of developing CCL injury in agility dogs including whether targeted strengthening programs may help prevent CCL and stifle injury in general in dogs.</p><p>Similar to previous studies (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>), we found a significant increase in risk of injury history in dogs with younger handlers (18&#8211;24) as compared to older handlers (particularly 65+). Younger handlers are likely to be less experienced and may not be as precise with their handling, which could result in more reactionary movements from the dog, such as more sudden changes in speed and turning. It is also possible that they may have started agility as a hobby with their pet dog, who may not be the fittest or conformationally sound and thus be more prone to injury. Additionally younger handlers may not pick up on subtle signs of injury as well as older, more experienced handlers, therefore allowing their dog to continue competing and ultimately leading to progression of injury. The finding that dogs either not trained to perform a specific behavior at the end of the teeter, or dogs performing a different behavior than the most common options, have a lower risk for reporting a history of stifle injury may be related to handler experience, particular training techniques, or specific biomechanical forces incurred during teeter performance.</p><p>Inherit limitations of a survey include potential inaccuracies due to participant recall and handler-reported data without confirmation by a veterinarian. Self-selection bias may also result in the sample selection not being representative of the total agility dog population. Furthermore, we were unable to assess risk factors for specific stifle injuries due to small numbers reported here. Lastly, while injuries are reported in dogs performing agility, we could not elucidate whether the injuries occurred specifically due to agility training or competition or occurred secondary to performing agility. The injuries might have occurred in these dogs regardless of whether they actively participated in agility or not.</p><p>This survey provides insight into potential risk factors associated with all stifle injuries in agility athletes. The potential risk for stifle injury with early spay/neuter should be further explored. While we have begun to have a better understanding of musculoskeletal injuries due to increased availability of advanced imaging, there remains a lack of understanding of the kinetics and kinematics of dogs participating in sport, and how it relates to injury risk. Such studies are needed to enable us to make appropriate recommendations for prevention of injury. This particularly true regarding CCL injury given its significant impact on athletic capabilities following injury.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec12"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be made available by the authors, without undue reservation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="sec13"><title>Author contributions</title><p>NK: Conceptualization, Investigation, Methodology, Project administration, Supervision, Writing &#8211; original draft, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. AS: Data curation, Formal analysis, Methodology, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. AM: Data curation, Formal analysis, Methodology, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Investigation, Project administration.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec15"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec100"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pechette Markley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoben</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kieves</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Internet-based survey of the frequency and types of orthopedic conditions and injuries experienced by dogs competing in agility</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>259</volume>:<fpage>1001</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/javma.259.9.1001</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34647477</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trentacosta</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Percival</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A preliminary retrospective survey of injuries occurring in dogs participating in canine agility</article-title>. <source>Vet Comp Orthop Traumatol</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>321</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3415/VCOT-08-09-0089</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19597633</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fields</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Comstock</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology of injury among handlers and dogs competing in the sport of agility</article-title>. <source>J Phys Act Health</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1032</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/jpah.2012-0236</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23799256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evanow</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Deventer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinallo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Internet survey of participant Demogrpahics and risk factors for injury in competitive agility dogs</article-title>. <source>VCOT Open</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e92</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0041-1735843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inkil&#228;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyyti&#228;inen</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hielm-Bj&#246;rkman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Junnila</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bostr&#246;m</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Part II of Finnish agility dog survey: agility-related injuries and risk factors for injury in competition-level agility dogs</article-title>. <source>Animals</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>227</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani12030227</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35158551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8833498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cullen</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickey</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bent</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomason</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mo&#235;ns</surname><given-names>NMM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Internet-based survey of the nature and perceive causes of injury to dogs participating in agility trianing and competion events</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>243</volume>:<fpage>1010</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/javma.243.7.1010</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24050568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heidorn</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Canapp</surname><given-names>SO</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zink</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rate of return to agility competition for dogs with cranial cruciate ligament tears asscoiated with tibial plateau leveling osteotomy</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>253</volume>:<fpage>1439</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/javma.253.11.1439</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30451626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pechette Markley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoben</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kieves</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Internet survey of risk factors associated with training and competition in dogs competing in agility competitions</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>791617</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.791617</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35059455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8764449</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pechette Markley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoben</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kieves</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Training load and relationship to injury risk in dogs competing in agility competitions</article-title>. <source>VCOT Open</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>A1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>A11</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0043-1768902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Witsberger</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villamil</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevelance of and risk factors for hip dysplasia and cranial cruciate ligmaent deficiency in dogs</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>232</volume>:<fpage>1818</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/javma.232.12.1818</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18598150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Engdahl</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emanuelson</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#246;glund</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergstr&#246;m</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The epidemiology of cruciate ligament rupture in an insured Swedish dog population</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>9546</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-88876-3</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33953264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8100293</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sellon</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marcellin-Little</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for cranial cruciate ligament rupture in dogs participating in canine agility</article-title>. <source>BMC Vet Res</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12917-022-03146-2</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35033070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8760802</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ardern</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feller</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fifty-five per cent return to competitive sport following anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction surgery: an updated systematic review and meta-analysis including aspects of physical functioning and contextual factors</article-title>. <source>Br J Sports Med</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>1543</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjsports-2013-093398</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25157180</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koreeda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of recovery of limb function by use of force plate gait analysis after tibial plateau leveling osteotomy for management of dogs with unilateral cranial cruciate ligament rupture</article-title>. <source>Am J Vet Res</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>80</volume>:<fpage>461</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/ajvr.80.5.461</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31034268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krotscheck</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Todhunter</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Long term functional outcome of Tibial tuberosity advancement vs. Tibial plateau leveling osteotomy and extracapsular repair in a heterogeneous population of dogs</article-title>. <source>Vet Surg</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>261</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vsu.12445</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26768085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baird</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Innes</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ollier</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Short</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic basis of cranial cruciate ligament rupture (CCLR) in dogs</article-title>. <source>Connect Tissue Res</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>275</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/03008207.2014.910199</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24684544</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Victoroff</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bone morphological characteristics as risk factors for anterior cruciate ligament injury: comparison between contact and noncontact injury</article-title>. <source>Orthop J Sports Med</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>23259671231179757</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/23259671231179757</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37384238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10293527</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu&#233;n&#233;go</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Payot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charru</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verwaerde</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of tibial anatomical-mechanical axis angle between predisposed dogs and dogs at low risk for cranial cruciate ligament rupture</article-title>. <source>Vet J</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>225</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tvjl.2017.04.011</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28720297</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hynes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manfredi</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shull</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cranial cruciate ligament disease is perceived to be prevalent and is misunderstood in field trial sport</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source>. (<year>2023</year>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/javma.23.01.0004</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37451677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duval</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Budsberg</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flo</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sammarco</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Breed, sex, and body weight as risk factors for rupture of the cranial cruciate ligament in young dogs</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source>. (<year>1999</year>) <volume>215</volume>:<fpage>811</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/javma.1999.215.06.811</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10496133</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spinella</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arcamone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valentini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cranial cruciate ligament rupture in dogs: review on biomechanics, Etiopathogenetic factors and rehabilitation</article-title>. <source>Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>186</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vetsci8090186</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34564580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8472898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santarossa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TWG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monteith</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Durzi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gowland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Body composition of medium to giant breed dogs with or without cranial cruciate ligament disease</article-title>. <source>Vet Surg</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>1144</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vsu.13434</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32357267</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adrian</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haussler</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawcak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reiser</surname><given-names>RF</given-names><suffix>2nd</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riegger-Krugh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The role of muscle activation in cruciate disease</article-title>. <source>Vet Surg</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>765</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-950X.2013.12045.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23980704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bencke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aagaard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zebis</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Muscle activation during ACL injury risk movements in young female athletes: a narrative review</article-title>. <source>Front Physiol</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>445</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2018.00445</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29867521</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5962681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thigpen</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willits</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Assisting decision-making on age of neutering for mixed breed dogs of five weight categories: associated joint disorders and cancers</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>472</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2020.00472</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32851043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7412743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cullen</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickey</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bent</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomason</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mo&#235;ns</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Survey-based analysis of risk factors for injury among dogs participating in agility training and competition events</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>243</volume>:<fpage>1019</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/javma.243.7.1019</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24050569</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sundby</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pechette Markley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoben</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kieves</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Internet survey evaluation of demographic risk factors for injury in canine agility athletes</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>869702</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.869702</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35464366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9024059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>