<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12292019</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12292019.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12292019</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12292019</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40717918</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2025.1595147</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evaluation of clopidogrel responsiveness using the Platelet Function Analyzer-200 (PFA-200) in dogs</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names initials="JH">Joon-Ho</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2877590/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names initials="HJ">Hyun-Jung</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1035955/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Veterinary Emergency and Critical Care Medicine, College of Veterinary Medicine, Konkuk University</institution>, <addr-line>Seoul</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>KU Center for Animal Blood Medical Science, Konkuk University</institution>, <addr-line>Seoul</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0001"><p>Edited by: Valeria Pasciu, University of Sassari, Italy</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0002"><p>Reviewed by: Corrin John Boyd, Murdoch University, Australia</p><p>Dale Adam Lauver, Michigan State University, United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Hyun-Jung Han, <email>ab1234@konkuk.ac.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">480746</issue-id><elocation-id>1595147</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>11</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>27</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-07-29 09:25:24.283"><day>29</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2025 Shin and Han.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Shin and Han</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-12-1595147.pdf"/><abstract><p>We aimed to evaluate the prevalence of clopidogrel resistance in hypercoagulable dogs using the Platelet Function Analyzer-200 (PFA-200) P2Y cartridge; further, we aimed to assess the utility of hematocrit (HCT), platelet count (PLT), prothrombin time (PT), activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT), thromboelastography (TEG) parameters, and D-dimer level as indicators of clopidogrel efficacy. Forty healthy dogs underwent single measurements of P2Y closure time (CT), HCT, PLT, PT, aPTT, TEG parameters, and D-dimer levels, while thirty hypercoagulable dogs underwent two measurements of these parameters before and after clopidogrel treatment. The reference interval for P2Y CT in healthy dogs was 40.0&#8211;141.5&#8239;s, with a mean of 63.9&#8239;&#177;&#8239;26.82&#8239;s. Hypercoagulable dogs showed a mean baseline P2Y CT of 77.4&#8239;&#177;&#8239;37.6&#8239;s. Moreover, 23 (76.67%) and 7 (23.33%) showed responsiveness and resistance to the initial clopidogrel dose, respectively. The mean P2Y CT of the clopidogrel-resistant group after clopidogrel administration was 182.71&#8239;&#177;&#8239;78.43&#8239;s. Increasing the maintenance dose successfully overcame clopidogrel resistance in these seven dogs. Among the assessed parameters, only D-dimer levels showed a significant decrease in the clopidogrel-responder group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05), suggesting its potential utility in evaluating responsiveness. In conclusion, the PFA-200 P2Y cartridge effectively detects clopidogrel resistance in dogs and can guide therapeutic adjustments such as dose escalation.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Platelet Function Analyzer</kwd><kwd>PFA</kwd><kwd>P2Y cartridge</kwd><kwd>clopidogrel resistance</kwd><kwd>dogs</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that financial support was received for the research and/or publication of this article. This study was conducted as a contracted research project without a specific grant number, with financial support from Siemens Healthineers Ltd. The sponsor had no involvement in the study design, data collection, analysis, interpretation, or in the preparation and writing of this manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="1"/><ref-count count="56"/><page-count count="9"/><word-count count="6944"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Veterinary Clinical, Anatomical, and Comparative Pathology</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Clopidogrel is a common antiplatelet agent in small animal practice and a second-generation thienopyridine ADP (adenosine diphosphate) receptor (P2Y12) antagonist that requires hepatic activation via cytochrome P450-dependent oxidation (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). In humans, clopidogrel response variability has been widely investigated (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Additionally, clopidogrel response variability has been demonstrated in dogs and cats (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4&#8211;7</xref>). Accordingly, intended therapeutic outcomes may not be consistently achieved, and thus it is important to monitor treatment efficacy. In humans, platelet function tests identify failure to achieve the expected antiplatelet effect of clopidogrel (clopidogrel resistance) (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). In humans, clopidogrel resistance is common, with prevalence rates of 4&#8211;30% (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Although there is limited veterinary research on clopidogrel resistance, studies have identified clopidogrel resistance in dogs using thromboelastography (TEG) with platelet mapping and multiplate, as well as in cats using light transmission aggregometry (LTA), Platelet Function Analyzer (PFA)-100, and multiplate (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4&#8211;7</xref>).</p><p>The PFA-100/200 system (Siemens Healthcare, Germany) is a cartridge-based point-of-care assay that evaluates platelet function in high-shear-stress conditions by measuring the closure time (CT) of a membrane aperture (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). The PFA P2Y cartridge can assess the antiplatelet effects of clopidogrel. Although the current gold standard for platelet function testing is LTA, the PFA is simpler and faster, and thus more suitable for in-hospital testing (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Additionally, compared to TEG with platelet mapping, the PFA is more cost-effective and offers quicker assessment.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The Platelet Function Analyzer &#8722;200 device used to assess the antiplatelet effects of clopidogrel. Citrate-treated blood is dispensed into the P2Y cartridge.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1595147-g001.jpg"><alt-text content-type="machine-generated">A laboratory setup showing a Siemens INNOVANCE PFA-200 machine. A gloved hand is using a pipette to place a red liquid into a cartridge. The machine's screen displays test settings and status.</alt-text></graphic></fig><p>We aimed to establish a reference interval (RI) for P2Y CT in healthy dogs and observe changes in P2Y CT following clopidogrel administration in order to assess clopidogrel responsiveness in dogs. Additionally, we evaluated the utility of conventional coagulation-related markers, including hematocrit (HCT), platelet count (PLT), prothrombin time (PT), activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT), TEG parameters, and D-dimer level, as indicators of clopidogrel efficacy.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec3"><label>2.1</label><title>Animals</title><p>This prospective study included hypercoagulable dogs diagnosed via TEG at Konkuk Veterinary Medical Teaching Hospital and healthy donor dogs from the KU I&#8217;M DOgNOR Blood Donation Center. Ethical approval was granted by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at Konkuk University, under approval number [KU23191, KU24249]. Dogs exhibiting hypercoagulability, defined by TEG parameters with a maximum amplitude (MA)&#8239;&gt;&#8239;69 (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) and a coagulation index (CI)&#8239;&gt;&#8239;4 (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), were included. Exclusion criteria included the use of drugs that could potentially interfere with P2Y CT, including antiplatelet agents such as clopidogrel, aspirin, cilostazol, and tirofiban; anticoagulants such as heparin, rivaroxaban, and warfarin; and thrombolytic agents such as streptokinase, as well as a history of bleeding disorders or a platelet count of &lt;100&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup>/L. The healthy group comprised dogs without underlying diseases and normal findings in complete blood count, electrolytes (sodium, chloride, potassium), serum chemistry (albumin, alkaline phosphatase, alanine aminotransferase, blood urea nitrogen, creatinine, glucose, total protein), and coagulation tests (PT, aPTT).</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>2.2</label><title>Study design</title><p>Healthy dogs underwent TEG, PFA P2Y, and D-dimer tests. Hypercoagulable dogs underwent tests for P2Y CT, complete blood count, PT, aPTT, and D-dimer levels at diagnosis. Subsequently, they received 10&#8239;mg/kg clopidogrel (loading dose), followed by 2&#8239;mg/kg once daily for &#8805;4&#8239;days. Blood samples were obtained 5&#8211;7&#8239;days after initiation and 12&#8211;14&#8239;h following the last dose for re-assessments of the aforementioned parameters.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>2.3</label><title>Blood collection</title><p>To minimize mechanical stress on platelets during sample collection, blood was drawn from the jugular vein using needles no smaller than 21 gauge. After collection, the needle was removed from the syringe before gently transferring the blood into ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid and citrate tubes. We collected 0.3&#8239;mL of blood into tubes containing ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid for complete blood count analysis, and 2.7&#8239;mL of blood into 3.2% sodium citrate tubes using an exact 1:9 ratio of anticoagulant to blood for TEG, PFA P2Y, PT, aPTT, and D-dimer testing.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><label>2.4</label><title>TEG test procedure</title><p>Whole blood collected in 3.2% sodium citrate was gently mixed and then rested at room temperature (20&#8211;25&#176;C) for 15&#8239;min in accordance with the manufacturer&#8217;s instructions. One milliliter of citrated whole blood was transferred into a proprietary kaolin tube (Haemonetics<sup>&#174;</sup>, Braintree, MA, USA) containing kaolin, phospholipids, and stabilizers. From this, 340&#8239;&#956;L was placed into a TEG cup and recalcified with 20&#8239;&#956;L of 200&#8239;mM calcium chloride. Standard TEG parameters (reaction time [R], alpha angle [<italic toggle="yes">&#945;</italic>], coagulation time [K], and MA) were recorded. The CI was calculated as follows (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>):<disp-formula id="E1"><mml:math id="M1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>CI</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.1227</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0092</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">K</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.1655</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>MA</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#8211;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0241</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#945;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#8211;</mml:mo><mml:mn>5.0220</mml:mn></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="sec7"><label>2.5</label><title>PFA P2Y test procedure</title><p>As with the TEG assay, whole blood collected in 3.2% sodium citrate was gently mixed and then rested without agitation at room temperature (20&#8211;25&#176;C) for 15&#8239;min, in accordance with the manufacturer&#8217;s instructions. Using the PFA-200, 800&#8211;900&#8239;&#956;L of citrated whole blood was pipetted into a prewarmed P2Y test cartridge. P2Y CT was measured with a maximum threshold of 300&#8239;s; with values exceeding 300&#8239;s being reported as non-closure and recorded as 300&#8239;s. Dogs exhibiting non-closure in P2Y CT after clopidogrel administration were classified as the clopidogrel-responder group, whereas those with a P2Y CT of less than 300&#8239;s were classified as the clopidogrel-resistant group. Samples were tested within 1&#8239;h after venipuncture.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><label>2.6</label><title>Other blood test procedures</title><p>HCT and PLT were measured using an automated hematology analyzer (IDEXX ProCyte Dx, IDEXX Laboratories, Inc., Westbrook, ME, USA). PT and aPTT were measured with a coagulation analyzer (IDEXX Coag Dx, IDEXX Laboratories, Inc., Westbrook, ME, USA). D-dimer levels were determined by a fluorescent immunoassay (Vet Chroma&#8482;, ANIVET Diagnostic Inc., Chuncheon, Kangwon, South Korea), with a detection range of 50&#8211;10,000 ng/mL. Values &lt;50&#8239;ng/mL and &gt;10,000 ng/mL were recorded as 50&#8239;ng/mL and 10,000 ng/mL, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><label>2.7</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All statistical analyses were performed using SPSS software (version 29.0, IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA). Statistical significance was defined as <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05. Normality was assessed by the Shapiro&#8211;Wilk test. For normally distributed data, independent samples <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-tests were used for between-group comparisons and paired t-tests for pre- and post-treatment comparisons. For non-normally distributed data, the Mann&#8211;Whitney U and Wilcoxon signed-rank tests were used. Reference Value Advisor v2.1 was used to calculate the RI for P2Y CT (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Although robust methods are recommended by the American Society for Veterinary Clinical Pathology (ASVCP) guidelines (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), their application in this data set yielded unreliable estimates, likely due to a limited sample size. Therefore, a nonparametric percentile method was used as a more reliable alternative. Outliers were evaluated using Tukey&#8217;s method, which defines outliers as values falling below the first quartile minus 1.5 times the interquartile range (IQR) or above the third quartile plus 1.5 times the IQR. All identified outliers were assessed for potential analytical or clinical exclusion in accordance with ASVCP guidelines.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec10"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec11"><label>3.1</label><title>Animals</title><p>A total of 70 dogs were included in this study, consisting of 40 healthy dogs and 30 dogs diagnosed with hypercoagulability. The characteristics of the dogs in both the healthy control and hypercoagulable groups, including sex, breed, weight, and age are presented in an electronic spreadsheet database (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). The hypercoagulable dogs had a variety of underlying conditions, such as immune-mediated diseases, inflammation, and hemodynamic compromise. The medical information, including the diagnoses, was organized in the <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec12"><label>3.2</label><title>PFA P2Y test results</title><p>The mean P2Y CT in the healthy group was 63.9&#8239;&#177;&#8239;26.82&#8239;s (minimum, 40&#8239;s; maximum, 142&#8239;s), which was shorter than in the hypercoagulable group (77.37&#8239;&#177;&#8239;37.61&#8239;s; minimum, 41&#8239;s; maximum, 244&#8239;s; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05; <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). The RI for P2Y CT in the healthy group was determined to be 40.0&#8211;141.5&#8239;s using a nonparametric percentile method. The 90% confidence intervals for the lower and upper RI limits, calculated by bootstrap resampling, were 40.0&#8211;41.0&#8239;s and 119.6&#8211;142.0&#8239;s, respectively. Outlier analysis using Tukey&#8217;s method identified one value exceeding the upper fence, but this value was retained in the final RI as no clinical or analytical justification for exclusion was identified.</p><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Box-and-Whisker plots of P2Y closure time (CT) in the healthy and hypercoagulable groups. The boxes indicate the interquartile ranges (25<sup>th</sup>&#8211;75<sup>th</sup> percentile) and lines within the boxes indicate the median values. Whiskers indicate either 1.5 times the interquartile range or the range limit for the data, whichever is less. Circles represent mild outliers, which are values exceeding 1.5 times the interquartile range below the 25th percentile or above the 75th percentile. Asterisks represent extreme outliers, which are values exceeding three times the interquartile range beyond these percentiles. The hypercoagulable group shows prolonged P2Y CT compared to the healthy group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05, Mann&#8211;Whitney U test).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1595147-g002.jpg"><alt-text content-type="machine-generated">Box plot comparing P2Y CT times in seconds between a healthy control group and a hypercoagulable group. The healthy control group shows higher variability and outliers, while the hypercoagulable group has lower values and less dispersion.</alt-text></graphic></fig><p>In the hypercoagulable group, 23 (76.67%) and 7 (23.33%) dogs were classified as the clopidogrel-responder and clopidogrel-resistant groups, respectively (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In the clopidogrel-responder group, the mean P2Y CT significantly increased from 77.48&#8239;&#177;&#8239;41.67&#8239;s (41.00&#8211;244.00) to &gt;300&#8239;s (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05); similarly, it increased from 77.00&#8239;&#177;&#8239;21.63&#8239;s (55.00&#8211;118.00) s to 182.71&#8239;&#177;&#8239;78.43&#8239;s (70.00&#8211;273.00) in the clopidogrel-resistant group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of P2Y closure times before and after treatment with clopidogrel in clopidogrel-responder and clopidogrel-resistance groups.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Clopidogrel responder (n&#8239;=&#8239;23)</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Clopidogrel-resistance (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> =&#8239;7)</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p-</italic>value</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P2Y CT (s)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.48&#8239;&#177;&#8239;41.67 (41.00&#8211;244.00)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300.00&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.00 (300.00&#8211;300)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>*</sup> &lt;&#8239;0.001</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.00&#8239;&#177;&#8239;21.63 (55.00&#8211;118.00)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182.71&#8239;&#177;&#8239;78.43 (70.00&#8211;273.00)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>*</sup>0.018</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Mean &#177; SD (range), CT; closure time. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value&lt;0.05 indicates significance.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In the clopidogrel-resistant group, the maintenance dose was initially increased from 2&#8239;mg/kg to 4&#8239;mg/kg, which was administered for 5&#8239;days, followed by P2Y CT remeasurement. If the P2Y CT remained &lt;300&#8239;s, the dose was further increased to 6&#8239;mg/kg, followed by to 8&#8239;mg/kg, until the P2Y CT exceeded 300&#8239;s. In this group, five, one, and one dog achieved a P2Y CT&#8239;&gt;&#8239;300&#8239;s at 4&#8239;mg/kg, 6&#8239;mg/kg, and 8&#8239;mg/kg once daily, respectively. In the hypercoagulable group, 76.67, 16.67, 3.33, 3.33% of the dogs showed clopidogrel responsiveness at 2&#8239;mg/kg, 4&#8239;mg/kg, 6&#8239;mg/kg, and 8&#8239;mg/kg once daily, respectively (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Pie chart of proportion of dogs by responsive dosage. Among the 30 dogs in the hypercoagulable group, 76.67, 16.67, 3.33, 3.33% of the dogs showed clopidogrel responsiveness at 2&#8239;mg/kg, 4&#8239;mg/kg, 6&#8239;mg/kg, and 8&#8239;mg/kg once daily, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1595147-g003.jpg"><alt-text content-type="machine-generated">Pie chart titled "Proportion of dogs by responsive dosage" shows four segments: 76.67% for 2 mg/kg, 16.67% for 4 mg/kg, 3.33% for 6 mg/kg, and 3.33% for 8 mg/kg.</alt-text></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="sec13"><label>3.3</label><title>Hematological (HCT, PLT) and coagulation (PT, aPTT, D-dimer, R, K, <italic toggle="yes">&#945;</italic>, MA, CI) test results</title><p>In the healthy group, the mean HCT, PLT count, PT, and aPTT were 48.63&#8239;&#177;&#8239;4.55% (40.20&#8211;60.80), 207.95&#8239;&#177;&#8239;42.61&#8239;K/&#956;L (150.00&#8211;300.00), 14.58&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.71&#8239;s (12.00&#8211;17.00), and 82.68&#8239;&#177;&#8239;7.12&#8239;s (72.00&#8211;101.00), respectively. The mean D-dimer levels was 474.26&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1110.54&#8239;ng/mL (50.00&#8211;6634.98). For TEG parameters, the mean R, K, <italic toggle="yes">&#945;</italic>, MA, and CI were 2.38&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.99&#8239;min (0.70&#8211;4.90), 4.64&#8239;&#177;&#8239;2.78&#8239;min (0.80&#8211;13.50), 53.54&#8239;&#177;&#8239;14.29 (22.80&#8211;81.70), 51.88&#8239;&#177;&#8239;6.72&#8239;mm (35.80&#8211;62.50), and 2.60&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.86 (0.94&#8211;4.00), respectively.</p><p><xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents the hematological and coagulation test results. In the clopidogrel-responder group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;23), mean HCT did not significantly differ, changing from 35.06&#8239;&#177;&#8239;8.28% (22.60&#8211;57.70) to 36.01&#8239;&#177;&#8239;6.04% (25.90&#8211;45.80) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.456) (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The mean PLT significantly increased from 356.30&#8239;&#177;&#8239;142.73&#8239;K/&#956;L (100.00&#8211;591.00) to 450.17&#8239;&#177;&#8239;184.52&#8239;K/&#956;L (227.00&#8211;792.00) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05). PT remained stable, with values of 13.48&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.12&#8239;s (11.00&#8211;16.00) before and 13.09&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.50&#8239;s (11.00&#8211;16.00) after treatment (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.441). Mean aPTT significantly decreased from 96.17&#8239;&#177;&#8239;10.28&#8239;s (78.00&#8211;119.00) to 88.09&#8239;&#177;&#8239;6.98&#8239;s (76.00&#8211;100.00) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05). D-dimer levels showed a significant reduction from 2476.95&#8239;&#177;&#8239;3185.40&#8239;ng/mL (50.00&#8211;10000.00) to 775.29&#8239;&#177;&#8239;880.31&#8239;ng/mL (50.00&#8211;3786.00) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05). For TEG parameters, the mean R did not significantly differ, changing from 3.14&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.19&#8239;min (1.60&#8211;6.40) to 3.27&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.29&#8239;min (1.50&#8211;5.80) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.681), K showed no meaningful difference, changing from 1.14&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.48&#8239;min (0.80&#8211;2.70) to 1.43&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.94&#8239;min (0.80&#8211;3.70) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.38), <italic toggle="yes">&#945;</italic> did not significantly differ, changing from 73.30&#8239;&#177;&#8239;8.02 (43.60&#8211;82.70) to 70.7&#8239;&#177;&#8239;9.85&#176; (48.20&#8211;81.40) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.336), MA did not change significantly, changing from 77.59&#8239;&#177;&#8239;3.87&#8239;mm (70.10&#8211;84.20) to 74.52&#8239;&#177;&#8239;7.24&#8239;mm (55.30&#8211;83.70) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.176), and CI did not differ significantly, changing from 6.37&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.78 (4.2&#8211;7.33) to 6.02&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.02 (3.38&#8211;7.35) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.069).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Hematological and coagulation test results before and after clopidogrel administration in the clopidogrel-responder and clopidogrel-resistance groups.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Variables</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Reference interval</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Clopidogrel responder</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Clopidogrel-resistance</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p-</italic>value</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Before</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">After</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p-</italic>value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hematocrit (%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.3&#8211;61.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.06&#8239;&#177;&#8239;8.28 (22.60&#8211;57.70)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.01&#8239;&#177;&#8239;6.04 (25.90&#8211;45.80)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.456</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.89&#8239;&#177;&#8239;8.79 (17.60&#8211;41.80)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.43&#8239;&#177;&#8239;11.37 (21.40&#8211;50.80)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platelet (K/&#956;L)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148&#8211;484</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">356.30&#8239;&#177;&#8239;142.73 (100.00&#8211;591.00)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">450.17&#8239;&#177;&#8239;184.52 (227.00&#8211;792.00)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>*</sup>0.01</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">443.57&#8239;&#177;&#8239;151.22 (308.00&#8211;720.00)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">429.86&#8239;&#177;&#8239;148.43 (259.00&#8211;683.00)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.612</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PT (s)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#8211;17</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.48&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.12 (11.00&#8211;16.00)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.09&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.50 (11.00&#8211;16.00)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.441</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.57&#8239;&#177;&#8239;2.07 (11.00&#8211;16.00)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.86&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.86 (13.00&#8211;18.00)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aPTT (s)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72&#8211;102</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.17&#8239;&#177;&#8239;10.28 (78.00&#8211;119.00)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.09&#8239;&#177;&#8239;6.98 (76.00&#8211;100.00)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>*</sup>0.011</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.00&#8239;&#177;&#8239;12.60 (77.00&#8211;112.00)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.86&#8239;&#177;&#8239;16.04 (72.00&#8211;113.00)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.499</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D-dimer (ng/mL)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 250</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2476.95&#8239;&#177;&#8239;3185.40 (50.00&#8211;10000.00)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">775.29&#8239;&#177;&#8239;880.31 (50.00&#8211;3786.00)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><sup>*</sup>0.01</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">681.56&#8239;&#177;&#8239;523.00 (127.70&#8211;1780.21)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">782.23&#8239;&#177;&#8239;810.40 (62.60&#8211;1925.10)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.735</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R (minute)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8&#8211;8.6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.14&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.19 (1.60&#8211;6.40)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.27&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.29 (1.50&#8211;5.80)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.681</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.69&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.96 (2.80&#8211;5.20)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.89&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.21 (1.40&#8211;4.70)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.116</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K (minute)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3&#8211;5.7</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.48 (0.80&#8211;2.70)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.94 (0.80&#8211;3.70)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.47 (0.80&#8211;2.10)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.71 (0.80&#8211;2.70)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#945; (&#176;)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.9&#8211;74.6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.30&#8239;&#177;&#8239;8.02 (43.60&#8211;82.70)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.70&#8239;&#177;&#8239;9.85 (48.20&#8211;81.40)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.336</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.13&#8239;&#177;&#8239;6.90 (59.70&#8211;78.80)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.70&#8239;&#177;&#8239;8.00 (58.00&#8211;79.90)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.735</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MA (mm)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.9&#8211;67.9</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.59&#8239;&#177;&#8239;3.87 (70.10&#8211;84.20)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.52&#8239;&#177;&#8239;7.24 (55.30&#8211;83.70)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.176</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.49&#8239;&#177;&#8239;6.07 (70.40&#8211;85.10)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.36&#8239;&#177;&#8239;8.75 (62.40&#8211;84.60)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.352</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CI</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-4&#8211;4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.37&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.78 (4.20&#8211;7.33)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.02&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.02 (3.38&#8211;7.35)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.19&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.19 (4.24&#8211;7.58)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.30&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.13 (4.24&#8211;7.64)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.109</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Mean &#177; SD (range). HCT; hematocrit, PLT; platelet count, PT; prothrombin time, aPTT; activated partial thromboplastin time, R; reaction time, K; coagulation time, &#945;; alpha angle, MA; maximum amplitude, CI; coagulation index. *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value&lt;0.05 indicates significance.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In the clopidogrel-resistant group (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;7), the mean HCT showed no meaningful difference, changing from 33.89&#8239;&#177;&#8239;8.79% (17.60&#8211;41.80) to 33.43&#8239;&#177;&#8239;11.37% (21.40&#8211;50.80) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;1.00) (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The mean PLT did not significantly differ, changing from 443.57&#8239;&#177;&#8239;151.22&#8239;K/&#956;L (308.00&#8211;720.00) to 429.86&#8239;&#177;&#8239;148.43&#8239;K/&#956;L (259.00&#8211;683.00) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.612). PT did not change significantly, changing from 13.57&#8239;&#177;&#8239;2.07&#8239;s (11.00&#8211;16.00) to 13.86&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.86&#8239;s (13.00&#8211;18.00) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;1.00). Mean aPTT did not differ significantly, changing from 95.00&#8239;&#177;&#8239;12.60&#8239;s (77.00&#8211;112.00) to 91.86&#8239;&#177;&#8239;16.04&#8239;s (72.00&#8211;113.00) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.499). D-dimer levels did not significantly differ, changing from 681.56&#8239;&#177;&#8239;523.00&#8239;ng/mL (127.70&#8211;1780.21) to 782.23&#8239;&#177;&#8239;810.40&#8239;ng/mL (62.60&#8211;1925.10) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.735). For TEG parameters, mean R showed no meaningful difference, changing from 3.69&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.96&#8239;min (2.80&#8211;5.20) to 22.89&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.21&#8239;min (1.40&#8211;4.70) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.116), K did not significantly differ, changing from 1.21&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.47&#8239;min (0.80&#8211;2.10) to 1.34&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.71&#8239;min (0.80&#8211;2.70) after (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;1.00), &#945; did not change significantly, changing from 72.13&#8239;&#177;&#8239;6.9 (59.70&#8211;78.80) to 72.70&#8239;&#177;&#8239;8.00 (58.00&#8211;79.90) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.735), MA did not differ significantly, changing from 78.49&#8239;&#177;&#8239;6.07&#8239;mm (70.40&#8211;85.10) to 75.36&#8239;&#177;&#8239;8.75&#8239;mm (62.40&#8211;84.60) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.352), and CI did not significantly differ, changing from 6.19&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.19 (4.24&#8211;7.58) to 6.30&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.13 (4.24&#8211;7.64) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.109).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec14"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>Antiplatelets have been traditionally used to prevent arterial thrombosis, with emerging evidence suggesting platelets also contribute to venous thrombosis (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15&#8211;18</xref>). In humans, antiplatelet agents have demonstrated efficacy in preventing venous thrombosis (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19&#8211;21</xref>), suggesting that the application of clopidogrel in veterinary medicine can be expanded. Additionally, advancements in coagulation tests to facilitate hypercoagulability diagnosis (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>), as well as advances in interventional cardiology and open-heart surgery in veterinary medicine, have led to an increase in clopidogrel prescriptions (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>).</p><p>Clopidogrel resistance is defined as insufficient platelet inhibition <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> following drug administration (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). In humans, the CYP2C19 gene, which is essential for clopidogrel metabolism, exhibits various polymorphisms that lead to significant variability in enzyme activity, which is the primary cause of clopidogrel resistance (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26&#8211;28</xref>). Other known mechanisms of clopidogrel resistance in humans include differences in intestinal absorption, genetic polymorphisms of ABC1 as well as GpIIb-IIIa, GPIa-IIa and P2Y12 receptors, and clinical factors such as diabetes and overweightness (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). In cats, mutations in the P2RY1 gene, one of the platelet ADP receptor genes, excessively activates the P2Y1 receptor in response to ADP, contributing to clopidogrel resistance (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). The mechanisms underlying clopidogrel resistance in dogs remains unclear. Nonetheless, clopidogrel resistance in dogs is considered to involve genetic polymorphisms in either platelet ADP receptor genes (P2RY1, P2RY12) or the cytochrome P450 enzyme gene.</p><p>In humans, clopidogrel resistance is clinically associated with an increased risk of thrombosis (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Although therapeutic strategies for clopidogrel resistance remain inconclusive in humans, increasing the loading dose, using a higher maintenance dose, or switching to alternative thienopyridines such as ticlopidine or prasugrel, may enhance platelet inhibition in clopidogrel-resistant patients (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). In veterinary medicine, there remains scarce research on treatment strategies related to clopidogrel resistance. Therefore, it is important to identify patients with inadequate responses to clopidogrel and implement alternative therapeutic strategies in order to improve prognosis and survival in veterinary patients.</p><p>There remain no established standards for evaluating the efficacy of antiplatelet therapy in dogs, which is further complicated by inconsistencies across platelet function tests and the lack of an established RI for treatment monitoring. Platelet function tests measure the inhibition of ADP-induced platelet aggregation to evaluate the efficacy and resistance of clopidogrel; however, the methods differ across devices (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). LTA and turbidimetric-based optical detection systems both assess platelet aggregation by detecting changes in light transmission, using platelet-rich plasma and whole blood, respectively. Another method, electrical aggregometry, assesses platelet aggregation by measuring changes in electrical impedance as platelets adhere to electrodes in whole blood. TEG with platelet mapping measures platelet aggregation and thrombus formation in real-time, indirectly confirming clopidogrel inhibition by observing a decrease in clot strength. Flow cytometry evaluates the expression and activation status of platelet surface receptors to assess the effectiveness of clopidogrel-mediated P2Y12 receptor inhibition. Furthermore, the PFA P2Y test is a useful tool for assessing the antiplatelet effects of clopidogrel. This cartridge-based point-of-care assay involves aspirating whole blood through a small aperture (150-&#956;m diameter) in a membrane coated with 20&#8239;&#956;g of ADP, 5&#8239;ng of prostaglandin E1, and 459&#8239;&#956;g of calcium chloride. Under high shear conditions, these platelet activators induce platelet plug formation, eventually occluding the aperture, with the time until full occlusion being measured.</p><p>LTA is considered the gold standard for evaluating the antiplatelet effect of clopidogrel. However, ADP-induced LTA may be slightly inappropriate for evaluating clopidogrel&#8217;s effect since ADP can induce platelet aggregation through both the P2Y12 and P2Y1 receptors, meaning that using ADP alone may lack the specificity required to accurately assess clopidogrel&#8217;s effect (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). LTA requires larger sample volumes and a high level of technical expertise, which impedes its practicability in routine clinical settings, especially in veterinary medicine. Additionally, electrical aggregometry and flow cytometry also require a high level of technical expertise, while TEG with platelet mapping is relatively expensive and time-consuming.</p><p>Contrastingly, the PFA is simpler and only requires small blood volumes; therefore, it is widely used in clinical practice. The PFA has three cartridge types, including the collagen/epinephrine cartridge (C/Epi), which uses collagen and epinephrine as platelet activators; the collagen/adenosine diphosphate cartridge (C/ADP), which uses collagen and adenosine diphosphate; and the P2Y cartridge, which is coated with prostaglandin E1. In humans, both C/Epi and C/ADP cartridges are used to evaluate platelet function, showing particular sensitivity to von Willebrand disease, and the C/Epi cartridge is especially sensitive to aspirin therapy (<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Both cartridges are useful for evaluating primary hemostasis disorders in dogs (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>); however, the role of epinephrine remains unclear in canine platelet aggregation, which differs from humans (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). Accordingly, the use of the C/Epi cartridge in assessing canine platelet function remains controversial. Contrastingly, ADP is highly sensitive to platelet aggregation in dogs, making the C/ADP cartridge useful for evaluating platelet function (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40&#8211;42</xref>). Specifically, P2Y cartridge is considered more suitable for evaluating clopidogrel efficacy since it inhibits P2Y1-mediated aggregation using prostaglandin E1 in the cartridge, facilitating more specific evaluation of P2Y12-mediated aggregation, which is directly influenced by clopidogrel. In cats, the P2Y cartridge is more sensitive and effective than the C/ADP cartridge in evaluating clopidogrel efficacy, expanding the potential applications of the PFA in veterinary medicine (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). We performed the PFA P2Y test using a relatively small volume of whole blood (approximately 800&#8239;&#956;L), making the testing procedure simple and quick (5&#8211;10&#8239;min). These factors contribute to the practicality and ease of applying this method in veterinary clinical settings. Consequently, via this clinical utility, we established the RI for P2Y CT using P2Y cartridge and observed that some P2Y CT parameters were significantly longer in the hypercoagulable group than in the healthy group. Further, 76.67% of the clopidogrel-administered dogs showed clopidogrel responsiveness, with a P2Y CT&#8239;&gt;&#8239;300&#8239;s.</p><p>Notably, the PFA P2Y test has several limitations, including a capped measurement limit of 300&#8239;s for CT, beyond which values are not recorded, and the influence by various hematologic factors. If a patient&#8217;s P2Y CT prior to clopidogrel administration already exceeds 300&#8239;s, it may be impossible to use the PFA P2Y test to monitor treatment responsiveness. Additionally, human studies on C/Epi and C/ADP cartridges have showed that significant reductions in PLT or HCT, lower von Willebrand factor levels, and the use of higher-concentration sodium citrate tubes all led to prolonged CT (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44&#8211;46</xref>). Furthermore, these factors may similarly affect the P2Y cartridge, making it unsuitable for dogs with low PLT, HCT, or von Willebrand factor levels. In our study, all blood samples for the PFA P2Y test were uniformly treated with 3.2% sodium citrate, which eliminated the effects of variations in sodium citrate concentration. Therefore, the relatively low HCT in the hypercoagulable group may have contributed to the prolonged P2Y CT. Furthermore, one hypercoagulable dog, with a P2Y CT of 244&#8239;s outside the normal reference range, presented with thrombocytopenia (100&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup>/L). This suggests that the low platelet count may have contributed to the prolonged CT.</p><p>In dogs, a P2Y CT&#8239;&lt;&#8239;300&#8239;s after clopidogrel administration is considered indicative of clopidogrel resistance (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). The rate of clopidogrel resistance in our study was 23.33%, which is consistent with a previously reported value of 25% (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) and comparable to that in humans (4&#8211;30%) (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), although its clinical implications may differ. Unlike in humans, where clopidogrel is administered at a fixed dose of 300&#8239;mg on the first day, followed by 75&#8239;mg/day, dogs are typically dosed based on body weight. Additionally, the broader dosing range for clopidogrel in dogs (1&#8211;4&#8239;mg/kg) (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48&#8211;52</xref>) and the variability in the use of a loading dose impedes determination of an optimal personalized dose without inducing resistance or causing adverse effects. These challenges in dogs emphasize the need for monitoring clopidogrel efficacy.</p><p>Our findings showed that the effective clopidogrel dosage varies across dogs, highlighting the importance of confirming clopidogrel efficacy. Furthermore, increasing the maintenance dose helped overcome resistance. In this study, we implemented a personalized antiplatelet therapy inspired by therapeutic strategies from human medicine for managing clopidogrel resistance (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). To date, the highest maintenance dose of clopidogrel reported in the veterinary literature is 4&#8239;mg/kg (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Therefore, we established 8&#8239;mg/kg, which is twice that amount, as the maximum maintenance dose in our protocol. To minimize the risk of adverse effects associated with high-dose escalation, an intermediate step of 6&#8239;mg/kg was incorporated. For dogs receiving doses exceeding the standard maintenance regimen, consent was obtained from the owners after providing a comprehensive explanation of the rationale, potential benefits, and possible adverse effects of the proposed treatment. Safety monitoring consisted of complete blood count assessments and thorough clinical evaluations for signs of bleeding, including petechiae, ecchymosis, epistaxis, melena, and hematochezia. These evaluations were conducted on days 2 and 5 following clopidogrel administration. No adverse events were observed in any dog throughout the study period. All dogs exhibiting resistance responded when the dose was increased to a maximum of 8&#8239;mg/kg once daily. However, for dogs that continue to exhibit resistance despite this dose adjustment, other thienopyridine therapies, similar to those used in humans, could be an alternative. Nonetheless, further studies are warranted to validate these approaches in veterinary medicine.</p><p>Among the conventional coagulation markers, only PLT, aPTT, and D-dimer levels showed significant pre-post differences in the clopidogrel-responder group. Following clopidogrel administration, the increase in PLT and shortening of aPTT is suggestive of enhanced coagulation. However, no significant changes were observed in TEG parameters, and P2Y CT was prolonged after clopidogrel administration. Therefore, the increase in PLT and shortening of aPTT were not considered significant risk factors for hypercoagulability or increased thrombus formation following clopidogrel administration. Although D-dimer levels cannot be considered a specific indicator of thrombus formation, a decrease in D-dimer level reflects reduced thrombin generation and fibrin turnover, which is associated with a decreased risk of thrombus-related cardiovascular events in humans (<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Consequently, D-dimer levels only significantly decreased in the clopidogrel-responder group, suggesting that clopidogrel may have contributed to reducing blood clot formation. Among the conventional markers, D-dimer could be useful in evaluating clopidogrel responsiveness.</p><p>This study has several limitations. First, the relatively small sample size, particularly in the clopidogrel-resistant group, may have impeded the statistical robustness and the generalizability of the findings. Anemia, characterized by low HCT, may influence the accuracy of CT measurements. A previous study in human medicine has reported that HCT levels below 25% can result in CT prolongation (<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). In the present study, 18 of the 30 dogs in the hypercoagulable group were anemic (HCT&#8239;&lt;&#8239;36%), yet 17 of these had P2Y CT values within the established reference interval (40.0&#8211;141.5&#8239;s). Given that the primary objective of this study was to evaluate within-individual pre- and post-treatment changes, these cases were retained in the analysis. Furthermore, a prior canine study has shown that the extent of CT prolongation associated with low HCT is relatively modest (<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). Nonetheless, in dogs with moderate to severe anemia (HCT&#8239;&lt;&#8239;30%), the potential impact of HCT on P2Y CT values should be recognized as a limitation of this study, warranting cautious interpretation and further investigation. The healthy group mainly comprised large-breed dogs, while the hypercoagulable group was composed primarily of small-breed dogs, introducing potential breed-related variability. Additionally, the underlying causes of hypercoagulability and their treatment strategies differed across the dogs, which may have influenced the results. However, in the hypercoagulable group, no dogs were receiving any antiplatelet or anticoagulant therapy except for clopidogrel.</p><p>Another consideration is that the mean D-dimer concentration in the healthy group was unexpectedly high. The median D-dimer concentration in this group was 152.29&#8239;ng/mL, indicating that most healthy dogs had physiologically normal levels. However, three dogs exhibited markedly elevated values of 2199.84, 2287.67, and 6634.98&#8239;ng/mL, which significantly influenced the group mean. Vigorous physical activity prior to blood sampling, such as playing fetch, may have contributed to this finding, as reported in human studies demonstrating exercise-induced increases in D-dimer levels (<xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). While this variability may influence interpretation, the PFA P2Y cartridge is less likely to be affected by such factors, as it specifically evaluates the P2Y12 receptor pathway and minimizes the impact of non-specific physiological changes. Importantly, our analysis focused on within-individual changes, and a significant reduction in D-dimer levels was still observed in responders. Nevertheless, as D-dimer is a non-specific marker, reliance on absolute values should be avoided, and this should be acknowledged as a potential limitation in interpreting the study findings. Finally, although we identified clopidogrel resistance in some dogs, we did not evaluate long-term clinical outcomes such as thromboembolic events or bleeding complications. Given the role of genetic factors, such as CYP2C19 and P2Y12 receptor polymorphisms, in clopidogrel resistance in humans, future studies investigating genetic variability in dogs are warranted to improve our understanding of the underlying mechanisms of clopidogrel resistance and to optimize antiplatelet therapy in this species.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec15"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our findings confirmed individual variability in response to clopidogrel, emphasizing the importance of monitoring clopidogrel efficacy in dogs. The PFA P2Y test effectively assessed clopidogrel efficacy, and thus is a highly useful tool for veterinarians to objectively monitor clopidogrel responsiveness in dogs and inform therapeutic strategies.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><title>Abbreviations</title><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>ADP, adenosine diphosphate; ASVCP, American Society for Veterinary Clinical Pathology; aPTT, activated partial thromboplastin time; CI, coagulation index; CT, closure time; HCT, hematocrit; K, coagulation time; LTA, light transmission aggregometry; MA, maximum amplitude; PFA, Platelet Function Analyzer; PLT, platelet count; PT, prothrombin time; R, reaction time; RI, reference interval; TEG, thromboelastography; &#945;, alpha angle.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec16"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref>, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="sec17"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The animal studies were approved by Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at Konkuk University. The studies were conducted in accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements. Written informed consent was obtained from the owners for the participation of their animals in this study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="sec18"><title>Author contributions</title><p>J-HS: Writing &#8211; original draft, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. H-JH: Writing &#8211; original draft, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec20"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ai-statement" id="sec21"><title>Generative AI statement</title><p>The authors declare that no Gen AI was used in the creation of this manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec22"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec23"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2025.1595147/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2025.1595147/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Abcha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Radwan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blais</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazzaferri</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boudoulas</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Essa</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genotype-guided use of P2Y12 inhibitors: a review of current state of the art</article-title>. <source>Front Cardiovasc Med</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>850028</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcvm.2022.850028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35402528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8983962</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weissler</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pack</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Latz</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A systematic review of clopidogrel resistance in vascular surgery: current perspectives and future directions</article-title>. <source>Ann Vasc Surg</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>91</volume>:<fpage>257</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.avsg.2022.12.071</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36539113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diodati</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pharand</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Resistance to clopidogrel: a review of the evidence</article-title>. <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1157</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2005.01.034</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15837243</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Griebsch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrs</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness of aspirin vs. clopidogrel in dogs with immune mediated haemolytic anaemia evaluated by serial thromboelastography and platelet mapping</article-title>. <source>Vet J</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>287</volume>:<fpage>105882</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tvjl.2022.105882</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35963596</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosati</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jandrey</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>RHL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of clopidogrel response in healthy cats using a novel viscoelastic test and thromboelastography</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1371781</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2024.1371781</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38957799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11217344</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shropshire</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olver</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Platelet aggregometry testing during aspirin or clopidogrel treatment and measurement of clopidogrel metabolite concentrations in dogs with protein-losing nephropathy</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>710</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.15694</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31981378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7096639</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teuber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mischke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of a low dosage of clopidogrel on platelet function in cats as measured by the platelet function analyser PFA-100 and the multiplate analyser</article-title>. <source>Res Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>109</volume>:<fpage>149</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>56</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rvsc.2016.09.011</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27892864</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sambu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curzen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Monitoring the effectiveness of antiplatelet therapy: opportunities and limitations</article-title>. <source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>72</volume>:<fpage>683</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>96</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2125.2011.03955.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21366666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3195743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterisation of changes in the haemostasis system in dogs with thrombosis</article-title>. <source>J Small Anim Pract</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsap.12037</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23458642</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jandrey</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Use of thromboelastography in clinical practice</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin North Am Small Anim Pract</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>1397</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>409</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cvsm.2020.08.001</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32981595</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Correlation between D-dimer concentrations and thromboelastography in dogs with critical illness: a retrospective, cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>844022</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.844022</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35498739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9047750</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Donahue</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Thromboelastography: a tool for measuring hypercoagulability, hypocoagulability, and fibrinolysis</article-title>. <source>J Vet Emerg Crit Care</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1476-4431.2005.04025.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Geffr&#233;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Concordet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trumel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Reference value advisor: a new freeware set of macroinstructions to calculate reference intervals with Microsoft excel</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin Pathol</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>107</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-165X.2011.00287.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21366659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedrichs</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harr</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szladovits</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnhart</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>ASVCP reference interval guidelines: determination of de novo reference intervals in veterinary species and other related topics</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin Pathol</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>441</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vcp.12006</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23240820</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agnelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becattini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Venous thromboembolism and atherosclerosis: common denominators or different diseases?</article-title><source>J Thromb Haemost</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>1886</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1538-7836.2006.02138.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16961596</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Arterial disease and venous thrombosis: are they related, and if so, what should we do about it?</article-title><source>J Thromb Haemost</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>1882</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1538-7836.2006.02130.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16848865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>GDO</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Common risk factors for both arterial and venous thrombosis</article-title>. <source>Br J Haematol</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>140</volume>:<fpage>488</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2141.2007.06973.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18275426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mackman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>New insights into the mechanisms of venous thrombosis</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>122</volume>:<fpage>2331</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI60229</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22751108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3386811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castellucci</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Gal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodger</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coyle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy and safety outcomes of oral anticoagulants and antiplatelet drugs in the secondary prevention of venous thromboembolism: systematic review and network meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>347</volume>:<fpage>f5133</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.f5133</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23996149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3758108</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flumignan</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baptista-Silva</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flumignan</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antiplatelet agents for the treatment of deep venous thrombosis</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>CD012369</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD012369.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35876829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9311262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Anticoagulation plus antiplatelet therapy versus anticoagulation alone following iliac vein stent implantation in acute and subacute deep vein thrombosis: a multicenter study with propensity score matching</article-title>. <source>Thromb Res</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>244</volume>:<fpage>109197</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.thromres.2024.109197</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39471544</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borjesson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Application of thrombelastography/thromboelastometry to veterinary medicine</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin Pathol</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>405</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-165X.2010.00263.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20969608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitsui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yaxley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lapsley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tremolada</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selmic</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hypercoagulability based on thromboelastography is common in dogs undergoing adrenalectomy</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>262</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/javma.23.08.0456</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38608654</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukamachi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niimi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jingya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wakao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Combination of the modified loop technique and de Vega annuloplasty in dogs with mitral regurgitation</article-title>. <source>Animals</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1653</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani12131653</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35804552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9264785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petchdee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pongkan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaturanratsamee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bootcha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meepoo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Transcatheter edge-to-edge repair of the mitral valve in four dogs: preliminary results regarding efficacy and safety</article-title>. <source>Animals</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>3068</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani14213068</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39518790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11545755</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hulot</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azizi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Remones</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goyenvalle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cytochrome P450 2C19 loss-of-function polymorphism is a major determinant of clopidogrel responsiveness in healthy subjects</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>108</volume>:<fpage>2244</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2006-04-013052</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16772608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical impact of CYP2C19 genotype on clopidogrel-based antiplatelet therapy after percutaneous coronary intervention</article-title>. <source>JACC Cardiovasc Interv</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>829</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcin.2023.01.363</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37045504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaban</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sosa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Role of genetic polymorphisms in clopidogrel response variability: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Open Heart</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e002436</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/openhrt-2023-002436</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37963685</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10649851</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Clopidogrel resistance: the way forward</article-title>. <source>Indian Heart J</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>530</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ihj.2014.08.012</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25443607</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4223168</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>RHL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ontiveros</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oldach</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A genetic polymorphism in P2RY1 impacts response to clopidogrel in cats with hypertrophic cardiomyopathy</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>12522</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-91372-3</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34131167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8206363</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matetzky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shenkman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guetta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shechter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beinart</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldenberg</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clopidogrel resistance is associated with increased risk of recurrent atherothrombotic events in patients with acute myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Circulation</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>109</volume>:<fpage>3171</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.0000130846.46168.03</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15184279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sofi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marcucci</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gori</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giusti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbate</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gensini</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Clopidogrel non-responsiveness and risk of cardiovascular morbidity. An updated meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Thromb Haemost</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>103</volume>:<fpage>841</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1160/TH09-06-0418</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20135063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neubauer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>AFC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Endres</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kr&#252;ger</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Engelhardt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lask</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Tailored antiplatelet therapy can overcome clopidogrel and aspirin resistance--the Bochum clopidogrel and aspirin plan (BOCLA-plan) to improve antiplatelet therapy</article-title>. <source>BMC Med</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1741-7015-9-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21226927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3033359</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunapuli</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorsam</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quinton</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Platelet purinergic receptors</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Pharmacol</source>. (<year>2003</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>175</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1471-4892(03)00007-9</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12681240</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsantes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikonomidis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Papadakis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kottaridi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsante</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalamara</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of the role of the new innovance PFA P2Y test cartridge in detection of clopidogrel resistance</article-title>. <source>Platelets</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>481</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/09537104.2012.689037</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22646492</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Favaloro</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pasalic</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lippi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Towards 50 years of platelet function analyser (PFA) testing</article-title>. <source>Clin Chem Lab Med</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>851</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/cclm-2022-0666</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35859143</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Callan</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giger</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of a point-of-care instrument for identification of primary hemostatic disorders in dogs</article-title>. <source>Am J Vet Res</source>. (<year>2001</year>) <volume>62</volume>:<fpage>652</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/ajvr.2001.62.652</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11341380</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Favaloro</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical utility of the PFA-100</article-title>. <source>Semin Thromb Hemost</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>709</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0029-1145254</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19214910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mischke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Studies on platelet aggregation using the born method in normal and uraemic dogs</article-title>. <source>Vet J</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>168</volume>:<fpage>270</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tvjl.2004.02.009</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15501144</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrams-Ogg</surname><given-names>ACG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of laboratory methods to improve characterization of dogs with von Willebrand disease</article-title>. <source>Can J Vet Res</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>73</volume>:<fpage>252</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20046626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2757705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keidel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mischke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Untersuchungen zur klinischen Anwendung des Pl&#228;ttchenfunktionsanalysenger&#228;tes PFA-100 beim Hund [clinical evaluation of platelet function analyzer PFA-100 in dogs]</article-title>. <source>Berl Munch Tierarztl Wochenschr</source>. (<year>1998</year>) <volume>111</volume>:<fpage>452</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9880941</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mischke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keidel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of platelet count, acetylsalicylic acid, von Willebrand&#8217;s disease, coagulopathies, and haematocrit on results obtained using a platelet function analyser in dogs</article-title>. <source>Vet J</source>. (<year>2003</year>) <volume>165</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1090-0233(02)00169-7</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12618069</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kornya</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrams-Ogg</surname><given-names>ACG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blois</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Investigation of platelet function analyzer 200 platelet function measurements in healthy cats and cats receiving clopidogrel</article-title>. <source>J Vet Diagn Invest</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>664</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/10406387231197440</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37646490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10621536</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Favaloro</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical application of the PFA-100</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Hematol</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>407</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00062752-200209000-00004</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12172459</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of PFA-100 testing in the investigation and management of haemostatic defects in children and adults</article-title>. <source>Br J Haematol</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>130</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2141.2005.05511.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15982339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jilma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Platelet function analyzer (PFA-100): a tool to quantify congenital or acquired platelet dysfunction</article-title>. <source>J Lab Clin Med</source>. (<year>2001</year>) <volume>138</volume>:<fpage>152</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mlc.2001.117406</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11528368</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrams-Ogg</surname><given-names>ACG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blois</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of multiplate, platelet function Analyzer-200, and Plateletworks in healthy dogs treated with aspirin and clopidogrel</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.14886</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29194772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5787169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borgarelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavlisko</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menciotti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aherne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mitral valve repair in dogs using an ePTFE chordal implantation device: a pilot study</article-title>. <source>J Vet Cardiol</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>256</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>67</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jvc.2017.03.002</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28576476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brainard</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleine</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Papich</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Budsberg</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacodynamic and pharmacokinetic evaluation of clopidogrel and the carboxylic acid metabolite SR 26334 in healthy dogs</article-title>. <source>Am J Vet Res</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>71</volume>:<fpage>822</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/ajvr.71.7.822</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20594086</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Green</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The pharmacodynamics of clopidogrel in the dog</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>135</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mellett</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bianco</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A prospective study of clopidogrel therapy in dogs with primary immune-mediated hemolytic anemia</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-1676.2010.0656.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21155892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morassi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bianco</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of the safety and tolerability of rivaroxaban in dogs with presumed primary immune-mediated hemolytic anemia</article-title>. <source>J Vet Emerg Crit Care (San Antonio)</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>488</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vec.12480</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27074368</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Christersson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oldgren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bylock</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siegbahn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallentin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Early decrease in coagulation activity after myocardial infarction is associated with lower risk of new ischaemic events: observations from the ESTEEM trial</article-title>. <source>Eur Heart J</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>692</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehl564</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17314111</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Belkacemi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merad</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Variables that influence platelet function Analyzer-100&#8482; closure times in healthy Algerian adults</article-title>. <source>Int J Appl Basic Med Res</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>154</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijabmr.IJABMR_532_20</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34458117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8360221</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clancey</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horney</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mackenzie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicastro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>C&#244;t&#233;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of in vitro hemodilution of canine blood on platelet function analysis using the PFA-100</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin Pathol</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>467</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-165X.2009.00162.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19548968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zadow</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitic</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>SSX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fell</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Time of day and short-duration high-intensity exercise influences on coagulation and fibrinolysis</article-title>. <source>Eur J Sport Sci</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>367</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>75</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17461391.2017.1420237</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29320303</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>