<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11956828</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11956828.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11956828</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11956828</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40166705</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2025.1587332</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial: Exploring anesthetic risk: challenges and solutions in veterinary medicine</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Portier</surname><given-names initials="K">Karine</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/84508/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Senior</surname><given-names initials="M">Mark</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2175399/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>VetAgro Sup, CREFAC, Universit&#233; de Lyon</institution>, <addr-line>Marcy l'Etoile</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Centre de Recherche en Neurosciences de Lyon, INSERM, CRNL U1028 UMR5292, Trajectoire, Universit&#233; Claude Bernard Lyon 1</institution>, <addr-line>Bron</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>School of Veterinary Science, University of Liverpool,Leahurst Campus</institution>, <addr-line>Neston</addr-line>, <country>United Kingdom</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited and reviewed by: Andres M. Perez, University of Minnesota Twin Cities, United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Karine Portier <email>karine.portier@vetagro-sup.fr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">480746</issue-id><elocation-id>1587332</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>04</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>05</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>31</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-04-01 10:25:39.437"><day>01</day><month>04</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2025 Portier and Senior.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Portier and Senior</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-12-1587332.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="commentary-article" xml:lang="en" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/60344/exploring-anesthetic-risk-challenges-and-solutions-in-veterinary-medicine"/><kwd-group><kwd>anesthesia</kwd><kwd>anesthetic risks</kwd><kwd>veterinary medicine</kwd><kwd>drug interactions</kwd><kwd>analgesic</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="0"/><page-count count="2"/><word-count count="1078"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Anesthesiology and Animal Pain Management</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>The field of veterinary anesthesia is continuing to evolve: however, anesthetic risk remains a critical concern for veterinarians and pet owners alike. As the need for surgical procedures continues to grow, so does the necessity to refine anesthetic protocols, minimize complications, and improve patient safety. No surgical anesthetic intervention is completely benign, and so to improve patient safety we need to evaluate the potential benefit of an intervention against its risk. Understanding anesthetic risk, in simple terms, means understanding the possibility of something bad happening in relation to anesthesia, and that something bad normally means a morbidity or a fatality. Assessing anesthetic risk involves multiple factors, such as species-specific responses, drug interactions, and pre-existing conditions. The studies presented in this Research Topic explore anesthetic risk through a breadth of topics that include providing information on the efficacy and safety of drugs in anesthetized exotic species, uncommon complications in commonly anesthetized species using commonly administered drugs, structured risk assessment methods, and novel strategies to mitigate adverse effects.</p><p>One of the significant challenges in veterinary anesthesia is the assessment of pain and analgesic efficacy across diverse species. The study on hydromorphone administration in American alligators (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2025.1520172" ext-link-type="uri">Henke et al.</ext-link>) sheds light on pain management in reptiles, a field where research remains limited. By demonstrating the efficacy of hydromorphone with minimal adverse effects, this research expands our knowledge of species-specific analgesia and highlights the importance of tailored pain management strategies in non-mammalian patients.</p><p>In wildlife and conservation medicine, anesthesia is essential for capture and for both medical and research purposes. A study on snow leopard immobilization with ketamine-xylazine (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2025.1492640" ext-link-type="uri">Talukdar et al.</ext-link>) provides valuable insight into the physiological responses of free-ranging animals under emergency conditions. The documented safety and efficacy of this anesthetic combination reinforce its viability in field settings, offering a benchmark for future anesthetic protocols in large wild felids.</p><p>Anesthetic-induced complications remain a significant concern, as evidenced by a case report on hyperkalemia in a domestic cat under general anesthesia (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1398128" ext-link-type="uri">Irizarry and Graidlla</ext-link>). The suspected link to propofol infusion syndrome (PRIS) highlights the importance of vigilance in recognizing and managing intraoperative metabolic disturbances. This case serves as a reminder of the unpredictable nature of anesthetic reactions and the need for continuous monitoring and preparedness for rapid intervention.</p><p>Risk assessment tools play a vital role in pre-anesthetic evaluation. The introduction of the CHARIOT scoring system for equine anesthesia (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1384525" ext-link-type="uri">Brumund et al.</ext-link>) provides a structured approach to predicting peri-anesthetic morbidity and mortality. While the study included in this Research Topic indicates that CHARIOT has moderate predictive accuracy, refining and validating risk assessment tools remains an ongoing priority to improve anesthetic safety in horses.</p><p>Pharmacologic formulations significantly impact anesthetic safety, as illustrated by a study on etomidate in propylene glycol in minipigs (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1376604" ext-link-type="uri">Petrucci et al.</ext-link>). The observed adverse effects, such as hemolysis and laryngeal edema, raise concerns about the suitability of the formulation. This study underscores the necessity of evaluating drug formulations across different species to mitigate unforeseen complications.</p><p>Long-term analgesic management also warrants careful consideration. A study on enflicoxib, a COX-2 selective NSAID, explores its efficacy and safety in managing osteoarthritis in dogs (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1349901" ext-link-type="uri">Homedes et al.</ext-link>). The sustained analgesic benefits and lack of significant adverse effects over an extended period suggest that enflicoxib may offer a viable long-term pain management solution for canine patients with osteoarthritis.</p><p>Finally, a comparative study of propofol and alfaxalone on canine electrocardiographic parameters highlights the potential cardiac effects of anesthetic agents (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2023.1330111" ext-link-type="uri">Casoria et al.</ext-link>). The findings suggest that both drugs prolong the QTc interval, raising concerns about their proarrhythmic potential. This research underscores the importance of selecting anesthetic agents based on individual patient risk profiles, particularly in animals with pre-existing cardiac conditions.</p><p>Taken together, these studies contribute to a more comprehensive understanding of anesthetic risk across a range of species and clinical scenarios. By addressing key challenges in anesthetic management, from species-specific analgesia to risk assessment tools and pharmacologic considerations, this Research Topic fosters advances in veterinary anesthesia. Moving forward, continued research and interdisciplinary collaboration will be essential to refine anesthetic protocols, minimize risk, and improve patient outcomes in veterinary medicine.</p></body><back><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>KP: Writing &#8211; original draft. MS: Writing &#8211; original draft.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. The author(s) declared that they were an editorial board member of Frontiers, at the time of submission. This had no impact on the peer review process and the final decision.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s2"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></back></article></pmc-articleset>