<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10090457</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10090457.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10090457</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10090457</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37065257</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1157878</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Analysis of cell-free DNA concentration, fragmentation patterns and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> gene expression in mammary tumor-bearing dogs: A pilot study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guil-Luna</surname><given-names initials="S">Silvia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn003" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8225;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/942621/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#225;nchez-C&#233;spedes</surname><given-names initials="R">Raquel</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivas Crespo</surname><given-names initials="A">Aurora</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolores Fern&#225;ndez</surname><given-names initials="M">Mar&#237;a</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#225;ndez Sarmiento</surname><given-names initials="JA">Jos&#233; Andr&#233;s</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodr&#237;guez-Ariza</surname><given-names initials="A">Antonio</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/670360/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mill&#225;n</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yolanda</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2236257/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Grupo Nuevas Terapias en c&#225;ncer, Instituto Maim&#243;nides de Investigaci&#243;n Biom&#233;dica de C&#243;rdoba</institution>, <addr-line>C&#243;rdoba</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Centro de Investigaci&#243;n Biom&#233;dica en Red de C&#225;ncer (CIBERONC)</institution>, <addr-line>Madrid</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Departamento de Anatom&#237;a y Anatom&#237;a Patol&#243;gica Comparadas, Facultad de Veterinaria de C&#243;rdoba, Universidad de C&#243;rdoba</institution>, <addr-line>C&#243;rdoba</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Departamento de Medicina y Cirug&#237;a Animal, Facultad de Veterinaria, Universidad de C&#243;rdoba</institution>, <addr-line>C&#243;rdoba</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Ricardo Marcos, University of Porto, Portugal</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Gilda Alves Brown, Rio de Janeiro State University, Brazil; Raquel Chaves, University of Tr&#225;s-os-Montes and Alto Douro, Portugal; Ana Canadas Sousa, University of Porto, Portugal</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Silvia Guil-Luna <email>v22gulus@uco.es</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Oncology in Veterinary Medicine, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn002"><p>&#8224;These authors have contributed equally to this work and share first authorship</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn003"><p>&#8225;ORCID: Silvia Guil-Luna <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7542-3903" ext-link-type="uri">orcid.org/0000-0001-7542-3903</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">427755</issue-id><elocation-id>1157878</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>13</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-17 18:25:13.113"><day>17</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 Guil-Luna, S&#225;nchez-C&#233;spedes, Rivas Crespo, Dolores Fern&#225;ndez, Fern&#225;ndez Sarmiento, Rodr&#237;guez-Ariza and Mill&#225;n.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Guil-Luna, S&#225;nchez-C&#233;spedes, Rivas Crespo, Dolores Fern&#225;ndez, Fern&#225;ndez Sarmiento, Rodr&#237;guez-Ariza and Mill&#225;n</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-10-1157878.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Liquid biopsy based on the analysis of circulating cell-free DNA (cfDNA), as well as on detection of point mutations by digital droplet PCR (ddPCR), has revolutionized the research in oncology. In recent years, this technique has been pioneering in veterinary medicine since it is a minimally invasive approach with very promising results for characterization of tumors.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>The aim of this study was, firstly, to analyze the concentration and the fragmentation pattern of cfDNA of dogs with mammary tumors (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 36) and healthy dogs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5) and its correlation with clinicopathological data. Secondly, analysis of <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> gene expression and the point mutation in the codon 245 were performed in cfDNA and in tumor tissues to assess their potential as plasma biomarkers.</p></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><p>Our results highlighted that those dogs with worse clinicopathological characteristics (simple or undifferentiated carcinomas, higher histological grade and presence of peritumoral inflammation) shown higher cfDNA concentration and higher concentrations of short-fragments (&lt;190 bp) than healthy dogs. In addition, although no detection of the point mutation in codon 245 of <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> gene could be detected neither in plasma nor tumor tissue, an increased <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> expression was detected in animals with tumors bearing malignant characteristics. Finally, a high concordance with <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> gene expression in plasma and tumor tissue and cfDNA concentration was also found. The results derived from this work confirm the valuable potential of cfDNA and its fragments, as well as the analysis of <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> expression in plasma as useful liquid biomarkers for clinical application in veterinary oncology.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>canine mammary tumors</kwd><kwd>liquid biopsy</kwd><kwd>p53 mutation detection</kwd><kwd>cell-free DNA</kwd><kwd>tumor biomarkers</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by BIO287 of the Plan Andaluz de Investigaci&#243;n (PAIDI), Consejer&#237;a de la Educaci&#243;n y Ciencia, Junta de Andaluc&#237;a, and by grant number AGL2017-84189-R of the Ministerio de Econom&#237;a, Industria y Competitividad, Spain.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="8"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="49"/><page-count count="14"/><word-count count="8155"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>In the era of precision cancer medicine, circulating cell-free DNA (cfDNA) liquid biopsy has received enormous attention due to its huge potential in human oncology (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). In contrast to tissue sampling, liquid biopsy is emerging as a minimally invasive tool which is not limited by sampling frequency or tumor accessibility (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Thus, it offers the potential for providing rapid results for the diagnosis, prognosis and progression of cancer patients. cfDNA is an extracellular short double-stranded DNA released into the bloodstream or any body fluid, as a result of release mechanisms including apoptosis, necrosis, senescence, NETosis and active secretion (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). In cancer patients, circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) is the principal component of cfDNA since it is shed by tumor cells and contains the same genetic and epigenetic alterations (mutations, copy number alterations, chromosomal rearrangements, hyper and hypomethylation) present in the primary tumor (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Several studies have confirmed that high levels of cfDNA in the peripheral blood are associated with tumor progression and poor prognosis in cancer patients (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). In addition, not only tumor progression and prognosis, but also its proliferation rate, have been positively correlated to the amount of cfDNA (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Thus, the analysis of cfDNA have drastically revolutionized the field of oncology in the last years offering ease in tumor sampling, early diagnosis, disease staging and for the monitoring of disease progression (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p><p>In veterinary medicine, cfDNA analysis in canine tumors are still very limited with a huge need for more fundamental research on its origin and kinetics. As in humans, higher plasma cfDNA concentrations have been positively correlated with the severity of several canine malignancies including canine mammary tumors (CMTs) (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Additionally, the presence of genomic alterations in cfDNA in several canine tumors has opened new opportunities for characterizing tumor mutational landscapes with many applications in comparative oncology (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p><p>Recent studies has revealed that cfDNA from tumor cells is generally more fragmented [160&#8211;190 pair of basis (bp)] than non-tumoral cfDNA (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Thus, the analysis of cfDNA fragmentation patterns is currently a tumor biomarker for the prediction of tumor prognosis and malignancy in human oncology (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). In veterinary medicine, until now, just one study has analyzed cfDNA fragments in CMTs by qPCR of two amplicons to assess its potential to differentiate benign and malignant lesions (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p><p>At present, there is an increased focus on the analysis in cfDNA of cancer-related genomic alterations, such as mutations in <italic toggle="yes">KRAS, TP53, PIK3CA</italic>, or <italic toggle="yes">p16</italic> genes, by using new highly sensitive technologies such as digital droplet PCR (ddPCR), BEAMing (beads, emulsion, amplification and magnetics) or next-generation sequencing (NGS) approaches (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). In this sense, <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> overexpression and point mutations are one of the most common genetic abnormalities detected in up to 20% of CMTs comparable to that of human breast carcinoma (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). As well as tumor mutational analysis of ctDNA shows numerous clinical applications in human medicine, the detection of point mutations in cfDNA in veterinary oncology is currently receiving increasing interest but with limited studies so far. Thus, overexpression of the protein p53 and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> genetic alterations observed in human and CMTs, has been associated with cancer cell proliferation, invasion, metastasis and drug resistance (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). The high frequency of TP53 mutations found in tumor cells makes it a highly promising target for veterinary oncology so its detection by liquid biopsy can be used as a tumor biomarker with great potential in veterinary oncology.</p><p>Based on the above, in this study, firstly, we determined the cfDNA concentration and the fragmentation pattern in plasma of dogs with CMTs and healthy dogs were analyzed and, secondly, this information was correlated it with clinicopathological data and the molecular classification of the tumors. Moreover, we analyzed the <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> gene expression and the point mutation in the codon 245 of <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> gene in cfDNA and its respective tumor tissue to assess its correlation and possible potential as a liquid biomarker in CMTs.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>2. Materials and methods</title><sec><title>2.1. Case selection and clinicopathological data</title><p>A cohort of 36 female dogs undergoing resection of mammary tumors (malignant and benign tumors) by radical or partial mastectomy at the Veterinary Hospital of the University of C&#243;rdoba was included in the study. In addition, five healthy female dogs without any signs of pathological disease were selected as control group. Clinicopathological data of each dog, as well as the informed consent from each owner, was also prospectively collected for the study. The study was approved by the Ethical Committee of University of C&#243;rdoba in accordance with the Code of Ethics of the World Medical Association (Declaration of Helsinki).</p></sec><sec><title>2.2. Blood and tumor sample collection</title><p>Blood and fresh tissue tumor samples from bitches were collected during the surgery. Additionally, around 6&#8211;10 ml of blood was taken from each dog in ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA) tubes. Immediately after blood collection, plasma was separate by centrifugation at 1,600 &#215; g during 10 min at room temperature (RT) followed by centrifugation at 6,000 &#215; g during 10 min at RT to remove any possible cell debris. Plasma samples were then aliquoted, transferred to cryotubes and stored at &#8722;80&#176;C before DNA isolation. Fresh tumor samples were sliced and fixed in 10% buffered formaldehyde for 24 hours and processed for paraffin embedding for histological and immunohistochemical (IHC) analyses.</p></sec><sec><title>2.3. Histological and IHC analysis of tumor samples</title><p>The histological diagnosis was confirmed on hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E)-stained full-sections by two independent pathologists (YMR and RSC) according to Zapulli et al. (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). In addition, assessment of tumor inflammatory cell infiltration and presence of necrosis within the tumor (yes/no) was performed on H&amp;E-stained full sections (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p><p>For IHC analysis, four-&#956;m-thick sections were obtained and placed on Vectabond-coated slides (Sigma Diagnosis, St Louis, Missouri) and immunostaining was performed using mouse/rabbit anti-human monoclonal antibodies previously standardized in canine samples and listed in <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>. The slides were deparaffined, rehydrated in a graded series of ethanol and incubated with 3% hydrogen peroxide in methanol for 30 min. Heat-induced antigen retrieval was performed in a water bath at 96&#176;C with 0.01 M citrate buffer (pH 6) for 15 min. Then, sections were covered with 10% normal goat serum in phosphate buffer saline for 30 min before incubation with the primary antibody for 18 h at 4&#176;C. Afterwards, the avidin-biotin-peroxidase complex method was applied as recommended by the manufacturer (Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, California) followed by 3,3&#8242;diaminiobenzidine (DAB) staining (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA). Sections were then counterstained with hematoxylin, dehydrated and mounted. As positive control tissues, human breast carcinoma tissue was used for HER2, canine uterus tissue was used for progesterone receptor (PR) and estrogen receptor (ER) antibodies, canine epithelial mammary tissue was used for CK5 and CK14 and canine duodenum tissue was used for Ki67. The normal mammary gland found in the tissue sections under study was used as an internal positive control in every assay. As negative controls, the primary antibodies were replaced immunoglobulin fraction of serum from non-immunized rabbits (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA) for anti-HER2 and anti-ER, mouse IgG2 (Agilent, Burlingame, CA, USA) for anti-PR, and mouse IgG1 (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA) for anti-CK5, anti-CK14 and Ki67 antibodies.</p></sec><sec><title>2.4. Molecular classification of canine mammary carcinomas</title><p>For molecular classification of canine mammary carcinomas (CMC), the classification previously described by S&#225;nchez-C&#233;spedes et al. (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) was used. Immunostaining of anti-HER2, -PR, -ER, -CK5, -CK14, and Ki67 were semi-quantitatively analyzed based on the intensity and percentage of positive tumor cells. To evaluate HER2 expression, the 2018 ASCO/CAP guidelines were followed; 10 selected fields with the strongest protein expression were evaluated, and those cases with 3<sup>+</sup> [complete membrane staining &gt;10 % of positive luminal epithelial (LE) tumor cells] were considered HER2 positive (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>).</p><p>PR and ER labeling were assessed using the Allred score in 10 randomly selected fields (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>), following a semi-quantitative system that accounts for the staining intensity (scored on a scale of 0&#8211;3: 0 = none; 1 = weak; 2 = intermediate, and 3 = strong) and the proportion of positive cells (scored on a scale of 0&#8211;5: 0 = none; 1 = &lt; 1%; 2 = 1%&#8722;10%; 3 = 10%&#8722;33%; 4 = 33%&#8722;66 %, and 5 = 66%&#8722;100%), regardless of their myoepithelial (ME) or epithelial nature. The intensity and proportion of the immunolabelling against each antibody, ER and PR, were evaluated together yielding a total score of 0 to 8. A score of &#8805;3 was considered positive (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>).</p><p>For the IHC evaluation of CK5 and CK14 expression, both epithelial and myoepithelial cells (when presented in complex and mixed tumors), 10 randomly selected fields were evaluated. Cases with &#8805;10 % of positive tumor cells, without considering the residual/pre-existing myoepithelial cells, and with strong cytoplasmic staining were considered to be positive (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Ki67 expression was used to determine the proliferation index (PI). To do so, images were captured from four fields at high power field magnification (40 &#215; microscope objective) with high number of Ki67-positive cells. The number of Ki67-positive and Ki67-negative epithelial cells was assessed by image analysis using ImageJ software (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://imagej.net/Fiji" ext-link-type="uri">https://imagej.net/Fiji</ext-link>). The PI was expressed as the percentage of positively-labeled cells. A minimum of 1,000 tumor cells were counted per case (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p><p>The 26 CMCs were grouped into molecular subtypes as follows: luminal A (ER<sup>+</sup> and/or PR<sup>+</sup>, Ki67<sup>low</sup>, and CK5 <sup>&#177;</sup> or CK14 <sup>&#177;</sup>); luminal B (ER<sup>+</sup> and/or PR<sup>+</sup>, Ki67<sup>high</sup>, and CK5 <sup>&#177;</sup> or CK14 <sup>&#177;</sup>); HER2-overexpression (HER2<sup>+</sup>, ER&#8211;, PR&#8211;, and CK5 <sup>&#177;</sup> or CK14 <sup>&#177;</sup>); triple negative subtype (TN; HER2<sup>&#8722;</sup>, ER<sup>&#8722;</sup>, and PR<sup>&#8722;</sup>, HER2<sup>&#8722;</sup>; <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Immunohistochemical expression pattern of the different markers used for the molecular classification of canine mammary tumors. Representative immunohistochemical staining for HER-2 <bold>(A)</bold>, PR <bold>(B)</bold>, ER <bold>(C)</bold>, CK5 <bold>(D)</bold>, CK14 <bold>(E)</bold>, and Ki67 <bold>(F)</bold> antibodies.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1157878-g0001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>2.5. cfDNA isolation from plasma samples</title><p>Cell-free DNA isolation was performed from each plasma sample. Briefly, cfDNA was extracted from &#177; 3 ml of plasma with the QIAamp Circulating Nucleic Acid Kit and the vacuum system QIAvac 24 Plus (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany). The Quantus fluorometer (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) and the Agilent 2200 TapeStation system (Agilent, Santa Clara, CA, USA) with the High Sensitivity D1000 ScreenTape assay were used for assessment of sample purity, cfDNA concentration and fragment size distribution according to the manufacturer's instructions. The average fragment size was determined with the Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer Expert software, and calculated across the first three peaks 75&#8211;675 bp.</p></sec><sec><title>2.6. Design of primers and digital droplet PCR analysis for wildtype <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> gene and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> point mutation in codon 245 in plasma samples</title><p>For the assessment of the wildtype <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> gene and its mutation at codon 245 in plasma samples, ddPCR assays were designed using the Bio-Rad Droplet Digital PCR Assays. Two different probes, one targeting the wildtype sequence and the other one targeting the mutation region were labeled with FAM and SUN probes to detect the wildtype (<italic toggle="yes">wt</italic>) and mutant (<italic toggle="yes">mut</italic>) <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> allele, respectively. These customized primers and fluorescent probes were ordered from Integrate DNA Technologies (IDT; <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). In addition, synthetic positive controls with the <italic toggle="yes">wt-</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">mut-TP53</italic> sequence were designed.</p><p>One microgram (&#956;g) of genomic DNA from plasma was digested with five units of ApoI restriction endonuclease in a total volume of 25 &#956;l. ddPCR was performed using a QX100 Droplet Digital PCR System (Bio-rad). A reaction mixture (20 &#956;l) containing a final concentration of 500 nM of forward and reverse primers, 2 &#215; ddPCR Master Mix (Bio-Rad), 250 nM of FAM- and SUN-labeled probes and 80 ng DNA from each isolated plasma sample was used. Primers and probe sequences are reflected in <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S2</xref>. Next, reaction mixtures were partitioned into an emulsion of ~20,000 droplets using QX100 Droplet Generator (Bio-Rad). Based on clearest separation of negative and positive droplet cluster with a previous standardization, thermal cycling conditions were established at 95&#176;C for 10 min followed by 40 cycles of 95&#176;C for 30 s and 62&#176;C for 60 s. After thermal cycling the PCR plates were transferred to the QX100 Droplet Reader (Bio-Rad). Wild-type and mutant synthetic positive control DNA and the non-template control reactions were included in each experiment. To ensure experiment quality, wells with total droplet counts &lt; 8,000 were considered invalid, and the experiment was repeated to obtain a sufficient number of droplets. Additionally, positive control samples carrying <italic toggle="yes">wt-</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">mut-TP53</italic> sequences were used. For each bitch, plasma was analyzed in triplicate. QuantaSoft v1.7.4.0917 (Bio-Rad Laboratories) software was used for data analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>2.7. RT-qPCR analysis from tumor tissue samples</title><p>RNA from tumor samples was isolated and quantified using a High Pure FFPET RNA isolation kit (Roche, Germany) and NanoDrop 2000 spectrophotometer (NanoDrop) respectively, following the manufacturer's instructions. An iScript&#8482; gDNA clear cDNA synthesis kit (BioRad, H&#233;rcules, CA, USA) was used to obtain cDNA. The same probes and primers than ddPCR were used for RT-qPCR in triplicate by using the PrimeTime Gene Expression Master Mix (IDT) with a CFX96&#8482; Real-Time PCR Detection System (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA; <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). The samples were normalized to &#946;<italic toggle="yes">-actin</italic> and relative expression was calculated by the 2<sup>&#8722;&#916;&#916;Ct</sup> method to obtain the fold-change value (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>2.8. Statistical analysis</title><p>In order to assess normality distribution of the data, D'Agostino and Pearson Normality test was performed. &#967;<sup>2</sup> test or Fisher's exact test was used to examine the association between the different clinicopathological, IHC data and cfDNA parameters. When the data were not normally distributed, non-parametric tests were performed. Mann&#8211;Whitney <italic toggle="yes">U</italic>-test was used to compare differences between two groups. Data in graphs are represented as mean &#177; standard deviation. All <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> values &#8804; 0.05 were considered statistically significant. The data were analyzed using GraphPad Prism 8 (version 3.5.0).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>3. Results</title><sec><title>3.1. Clinicopathological features of tumors</title><p>Dogs included in the study presented a single mammary tumor (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 17) or multiple mammary tumors (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 19). In those cases with multiple tumors, the most malignant tumor was the one considered for the data analysis. From the total, 26 tumors were diagnosed as carcinomas while 10 tumors were benign tumors. Histological subtypes of carcinomas determined that simple carcinoma was the most frequent subtype (10/26 cases, 39%) followed by mixed carcinoma (7/26 cases, 27%) and complex subtype (5/26 cases, 19%). Other special types of carcinomas such as carcinosarcomas, adenosquamous carcinomas or undifferentiated sarcomas were encompassed as &#8220;other carcinomas&#8221; representing 15% of total (4/26). According to the histological malignant grade, 12 carcinomas were classified as histological grade I (46%), five as grade II (19%) and nine as grade III (35%). On the other hand, lymphatic invasion was present in six out of 26 carcinomas (23%), tumor necrosis was present in 17 cases (65%) and 21 carcinomas (80%) showed notable tumor-associated inflammation.</p><p>Considering molecular subtypes of carcinomas, TN subtypes were the most frequent between carcinomas (9/26, 35%). Next, luminal A subtype was the second most frequent with six cases (26%), luminal B with five cases (22%) and only three cases were considered HER2<sup>+</sup> subtype (13%).</p></sec><sec><title>3.2. Analysis of cfDNA concentration and correlation with clinicopathological data</title><p>Isolation of plasma cfDNA from mammary tumor-bearing dogs and from healthy dogs was successfully assessed with an average of concentration of 0.91 &#177; 2.74 ng/&#956;l (range 0.03&#8211;17 ng/&#956;l). The relationship between cfDNA concentration and clinicopathological characteristics of dogs are presented in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The cfDNA concentration in tumor-bearing dogs (malignant/benign tumors) was higher (1 ng/&#956;l) than in healthy dogs (0.25 ng/&#956;l). Additionally, carcinomas showed higher cfDNA concentrations than benign tumors but without statistical significance (0.60 vs. 0.37 ng/&#956;l, respectively). While no differences were observed between histological subtypes in benign tumors (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) &#8220;other carcinomas&#8221; (carcinosarcomas, adenosquamous carcinomas/undifferentiated sarcomas) and simple carcinomas displayed higher cfDNA concentrations than complex carcinomas (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.03 and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.05, respectively) and mixed carcinomas (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.08; <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). Interestingly, &#8220;other carcinomas&#8221; showed the highest cfDNA concentration values in comparison to non-simple carcinomas (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.02), and cfDNA values were higher in simple carcinomas than non-simple carcinomas (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.06; <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>). On the other hand, histological grade III of carcinomas showed a significant higher cfDNA concentrations compared to grade I carcinomas (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.03). In addition, carcinomas with tumor-associated inflammation also shown higher cfDNA concentrations than those carcinomas without inflammation (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.08; <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3A</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">B</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Association between cfDNA concentration (ng/&#956;l) and clinicopathological features of female dogs included in the study.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Clinical characteristics</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Number (%)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>cfDNA (ng/&#956;l)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>P-value</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Age</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 9 years old</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (45%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41 &#177; 0.37</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">0.31</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 9 years old</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (55%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 &#177; 0.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Breed</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pure</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (55%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 &#177; 0.48</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">0.89</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (45%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 &#177; 0.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Tumor characteristics</bold>
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Number of tumors</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unique</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (47%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.58 &#177; 44.43</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">0.28</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (53%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.56 &#177; 27.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Tumor type</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benign</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (27.8%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37 &#177; 0.41</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.45</italic> (benign vs. malignant)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malignant</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (72.2%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 &#177; 1.14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.42</italic> (malignant vs. no tumors)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No tumor</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (12.2%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25 &#177; 0.08</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.48</italic> (benign vs. no tumors)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Histological subtype in benign tumors</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simple adenoma</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (10%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complex adenoma</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (40%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26 &#177; 0.08</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.36</italic> (complex vs. mixed)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed adenoma</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (30%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 &#177; 0.70</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.20</italic> (mixed vs. others)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other benign lesions</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (20%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18 &#177; 0.05</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.20</italic> (complex vs. others)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Histological subtype in malignant tumors</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simple carcinoma</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (39%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38 &#177; 0.36</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.05</italic> (simple vs. complex)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complex carcinoma</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (19%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19 &#177; 0.37</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.39</italic> (complex vs. mixed)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed carcinoma</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (27%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37 &#177; 0.40</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.19</italic> (simple vs. mixed)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other carcinomas</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (15%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 &#177; 0.51</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.18</italic> (simple vs. others)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.03</italic> (complex vs. others)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.08</italic> (mixed vs. others)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Histological subtype in malignant tumors</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simple carcinomas</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (39%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38 &#177; 0.36</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.06</italic> (simple vs. non-simples)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-simple carcinomas</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (46%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 &#177; 0.30</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.23</italic> (others vs. simples)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other malignant tumors</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (15%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 &#177; 0.53</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.05</italic> (others vs. non-simples)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Histological grade</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (46%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 &#177; 0.29</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.03</italic> (I vs. III)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (19%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24 &#177; 0.07</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.12</italic> (II vs. III)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (35%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58 &#177; 0.49</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.33</italic> (I vs. II)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Lymphatic invasion</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (23%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 &#177; 1.26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">0.44</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (77%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26 &#177; 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Peritumoral inflammation in malignant tumors</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (80%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64 &#177; 1.23</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">0.08</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (20%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35 &#177; 0.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Necrosis in malignant tumors</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (65%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 &#177; 0.40</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">0.30</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (35%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 &#177; 1.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Molecular subtype of carcinomas</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Luminal A</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (26%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 &#177; 0.35</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.16</italic> (Lum. A vs. Lum. B)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Luminal B</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (22%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 &#177; 0.39</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.12</italic> (Lum. B vs. HER2<sup>+</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TN-basal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (35%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 &#177; 1.88</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.26</italic> (TN-basal vs. Lum. A)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.20</italic> (TN-basal vs. Lum. B)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HER2<sup>+</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (13%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18 &#177; 0.01</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.47</italic> (HER2<sup>+</sup> vs. Lum. A)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.22</italic> (HER2<sup>+</sup> vs. TN-basal)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No determined</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 &#177; 0.56</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.13</italic> (no det vs. Lum. A)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.39</italic> (no det vs. Lum. B)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.15</italic> (no det vs. HER2<sup>+</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.28</italic> (no det vs. TN-basal)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Italic numbers are the <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Circulating cell-free (cf) DNA concentrations in dogs with mammary carcinomas. <bold>(A)</bold> Scatterplot of cfDNA concentration (ng/&#956;l) in the different histological subtypes of carcinomas <bold>(A)</bold> and between simple, non-simple and undifferentiated carcinomas <bold>(B)</bold>. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1157878-g0002.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Circulating cell-free (cf) DNA concentrations in dogs with mammary carcinomas. <bold>(A)</bold> Scatterplot of cfDNA concentration (ng/&#956;l) in the different malignant histological grade of carcinomas <bold>(A)</bold> and between carcinomas with inflammation and non-inflammation <bold>(B)</bold>. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1157878-g0003.jpg"/></fig><p>Regarding molecular subtypes of carcinomas, TN subtype shown the highest cfDNA concentrations in plasma (0.98 ng/&#956;l) but no significant differences were observed with respect to the other molecular subtypes (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Finally, gender, age, breed, the lymphatic invasion, number of tumors or presence of necrosis were not linked to plasma cfDNA concentration (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>3.3. Analysis of cfDNA fragmentation and correlation to clinicopathological data</title><p>In addition to concentration, cfDNA fragment size was also analyzed in order to evaluate its association with the rest of the clinicopathological parameters. Firstly, we decided to focus on cfDNA fragmentation less than 190 bp (short cfDNA fragments) which is known to be specifically enriched for DNA fragments derived from tumors (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Thus, in our study it was noted that tumor-bearing dogs had significantly higher concentration of short-fragments than healthy control dogs (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.02; <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>). Likewise, malignant and benign-bearing dogs showed a higher concentration of cfDNA short-fragments than healthy dogs (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.05 and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.02, respectively, <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B</xref>). Moreover, grade II and III carcinomas also trended to show higher rates of short-fragments than grade I carcinomas (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.06; <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5A</xref>). In addition, when cfDNA fragmentation was analyzed and correlated with the histological subtype, simple carcinomas displayed significantly higher cfDNA concentrations of short-fragments than non-simple carcinomas (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5B</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Circulating cell-free (cf) DNA fragmentation size (&lt;190 bp, pg/&#956;l) in dogs with mammary carcinomas. Scatterplot of cfDNA fragmentation size &lt;190 bp (pg/&#956;l) in dogs with tumors and healthy dogs <bold>(A)</bold> and between malignant and benign tumors and controls dogs <bold>(B)</bold>. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1157878-g0004.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Circulating cell-free (cf) DNA fragmentation size (&lt;190 bp, pg/&#956;l) in dogs with mammary carcinomas. Scatterplot of cfDNA fragmentation size &lt;190 bp (pg/&#956;l) between different histological grade <bold>(A)</bold> and between simple, non-simple carcinomas and undifferentiated carcinomas <bold>(B)</bold>. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1157878-g0005.jpg"/></fig><p>Regarding the rest of parameters and the ranges of fragments analyzed (&lt; 400 bp, 450&#8211;650 bp, 650&#8211;850, and 1.000&#8211;1,200 bp), no statistically significant differences were observed between them.</p></sec><sec><title>3.4. Quantitative detection of wt-<italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> expression and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic>-point mutation detection in cfDNA</title><p>We were successful to amplified <italic toggle="yes">wt-TP53</italic> gene in plasma cfDNA in all cases but no positive samples for <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic>-point mutation at codon 245 (<italic toggle="yes">mut-TP53 gene</italic>) could be confirmed. Interestingly, the <italic toggle="yes">wt-TP53</italic> expression analysis by ddPCR showed significant association with some of the clinicopathological data of the dogs (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Thus, the percentage of positive <italic toggle="yes">wt-TP53 (wt-TP53</italic><sup>+</sup>) droplets by ddPCR was higher in older dogs (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.02), with multiple tumors (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.06) and with histological grade III (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0005) than in their countersparts (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figures 6A</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">C</xref>). In addition, dogs with &#8220;other carcinomas&#8221; had an even greater <italic toggle="yes">wt-TP53</italic> expression than those that had simple (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.03) complex (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.03) or mixed (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.09) carcinomas (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6D</xref>). Regarding molecular subtype of carcinomas, we also appreciated that bitches with TN subtype were the one with highest concentration of <italic toggle="yes">wt-TP53</italic><sup>+</sup> droplets than the rest of molecular subtypes but without statistically significance (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Association between percentage of droplet <italic toggle="yes">wt-TP53</italic> expression analysis determined by ddPCR and clinicopathological features of female dogs included in the study.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Clinical characteristics</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Number (%)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>% droplet <italic toggle="yes">p53</italic>wt</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>P-value</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Age</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 9 years old</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (45%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05 &#177; 3.90</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">0.02</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 9 years old</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (55%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.02 &#177; 2.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Breed</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pure</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (55%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.93 &#177; 18.42</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">0.65</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (45%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48 &#177; 4.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Tumor characteristics</bold>
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Number of tumors</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unique</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (47%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.56 &#177; 4.09</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">0.06</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (53%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.36 &#177; 21.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Tumor type</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benign</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (27.8%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.32 &#177; 5.03</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.23</italic> (benign vs. malignant)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malignant</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (72.2%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.25 &#177; 10.37</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.17</italic> (malignant vs. no tumors)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No tumor</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (12.2%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 &#177; 0.58</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.33</italic> (benign vs. no tumors)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Histological subtype in benign tumors</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simple adenoma</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (10%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complex adenoma</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (40%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78 &#177; 0.91</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.40</italic> (complex vs. mixed)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed adenoma</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (30%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.96 &#177; 8.34</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.11</italic> (mixed vs. others)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other benign lesions</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (20%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18 &#177; 0.05</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.11</italic> (complex vs. others)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Histological subtype in malignant tumors</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simple carcinomas</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (39%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47 &#177; 3.46</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 (simple vs. non-simples)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-simple carcinomas</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (46%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48 &#177; 13.12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 (others vs. simples)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other carcinomas</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (15%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.67 &#177; 6.63</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 (others vs. non-simples)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Histological subtype in malignant tumors</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Simple carcinoma</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (39%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48 &#177; 3.50</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.11</italic> (simple vs. complex)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Complex carcinoma</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (19%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39 &#177; 0.82</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.11</italic> (complex vs. mixed)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed carcinoma</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (27%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.26 &#177; 4.47</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.16</italic> (simple vs. mixed)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other carcinomas</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (15%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.81 &#177; 5.20</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.03</italic> (simple vs. others)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.03</italic> (complex vs. others)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.09</italic> (mixed vs. others)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Histological grade</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (46%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.44 &#177; 3.14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.0005</italic> (I vs. III)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (19%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.62 &#177; 22.51</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.11</italic> (II vs. III)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (35%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.78 &#177; 4.41</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.19</italic> (I vs. II)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Lymphatic invasion</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (23%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.67 &#177; 11.67</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (77%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.84 &#177; 4.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Peritumoral inflammation in malignant tumors</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (80%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.08 &#177; 4.17</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">0.44</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (20%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.90 &#177; 11.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Necrosis in malignant tumors</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (65%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.28 &#177; 4.47</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">0.19</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (35%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.34 &#177; 12.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr style="background-color:#e0e1e3"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Molecular subtype of carcinomas</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Luminal A</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (26%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97 &#177; 4.35</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.12</italic> (Lum. A vs. Lum. B)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Luminal B</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (22%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.19 &#177; 4.47</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.99</italic> (Lum. B vs. HER2<sup>+</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TN-basal</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (35%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.48 &#177; 16.60</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.07</italic> (TN-basal vs. Lum. A)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.30</italic> (TN-basal vs. Lum. B)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HER2<sup>+</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (13%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.96 &#177; 1.32</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.13</italic> (HER2<sup>+</sup> vs. Lum. A)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.43</italic> (HER2<sup>+</sup> vs. TN-basal)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No determined</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 &#177; 0.56</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.13</italic> (no det vs. Lum. A)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.39</italic> (no det vs. Lum. B)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.15</italic> (no det vs. HER2<sup>+</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">0.28</italic> (no det vs. TN-basal)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Italic numbers are the <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F6" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Percentage of positive <italic toggle="yes">wt-p53</italic> droplets detected in cfDNA in dogs with mammary carcinomas. Scatterplot of percentage of positive <italic toggle="yes">wt-p53</italic> droplets in dogs with &lt;9 years old and &gt;9 years old <bold>(A)</bold>, between dogs with single and multiple tumors <bold>(B)</bold>, between different malignant histological grades <bold>(C)</bold> and the different histological subtypes of carcinomas <bold>(D)</bold>. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 and <sup>***</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1157878-g0006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.5. Quantitative detection of <italic toggle="yes">wt-TP53</italic> expression and <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic>-point mutation detection in tumor tissue</title><p>In parallel to the analysis in plasma, in 26 dogs (four with benign and 22 with mammary carcinomas), the expression of the <italic toggle="yes">wt-TP53</italic> gene and <italic toggle="yes">mut-TP53</italic> gene was carried out by RT-qPCR from tumor tissue. The mean concentration of RNA extracted from the tumor tissue samples was 261.84 ng/&#956;l (range 32.96 ng/&#956;l&#8722;621.15 ng/&#956;l). As observed in plasma, the mutation under study was not detected in any of the tumor tissues analyzed, but there was differential expression regarding to <italic toggle="yes">wt-TP53</italic> gene expression. The fold-change analysis with respect to the analyzed benign tumors, determined that the carcinomas showed an average of 18 times more (18 fold-changes) expression of the <italic toggle="yes">wt-TP53</italic> gene than the <italic toggle="yes">wt-TP53</italic> gene in benign tumors (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.04, <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7A</xref>). As observed in plasma, complex carcinomas were the tumors with a lower fold-change compared to benign tumors and compared to simple and mixed carcinomas (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.06, <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7B</xref>). Regarding molecular subtypes, no significant differences were observed.</p><fig position="float" id="F7" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Quantitative PCR fold-change <italic toggle="yes">p53</italic> expression differences in tumor tissues of dogs with mammary carcinomas. Scatterplot of PCR fold-change expression between benign and malignant tumors <bold>(A)</bold> and between simple, complex, and mixed carcinomas <bold>(B)</bold>. <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1157878-g0007.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.6. Correlation of <italic toggle="yes">wt-TP53</italic> gene expression in plasma and tumor tissue</title><p>The comparative analysis of <italic toggle="yes">wt-TP53</italic> gene expression at the plasma and tissue level tumor determined a high correlation between both (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.83<italic toggle="yes">, p</italic> &lt; 0.0001; <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8A</xref>), so that those animals that presented higher values of expression of the gene <italic toggle="yes">wt-TP53</italic> (% <italic toggle="yes">TP53-wt</italic> droplets<sup>+</sup>) at the plasma level showed lower Ct values in tissue by RT-qPCR. In the same way, the expression of <italic toggle="yes">wt-TP53</italic> in tissue and plasma also showed a significant correlation with the total concentration of cfDNA in plasma (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.61, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.03 and <italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.72 <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001, respectively), observing higher levels of <italic toggle="yes">wt-TP53</italic> in those cases with higher concentrations of cfDNA (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figures 8B</xref>, <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">C</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F8" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Correlation analysis between <italic toggle="yes">p53</italic>-expression in plasma and tumor tissue <bold>(A)</bold> and between cfDNA concentration and <italic toggle="yes">p53</italic>-expression in tumor tissue <bold>(B)</bold> and plasma <bold>(C)</bold> of dogs with mammary carcinomas.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1157878-g0008.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>4. Discussion</title><p>The detection of cfDNA by liquid biopsy is considered one of the most advanced and minimally invasive tools that have emerged in the recent years in the field of human oncology and, more recently, in veterinary medicine (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). In the last years, an increasing number of studies demonstrate the relevance of cfDNA as an attractive tumor biomarker with great potential for the amount of information it provides about the tumor progression and prognosis as well as genetic alterations of certain cancer-related genes (<italic toggle="yes">BRAF, EGFR, TP53, KRAS, PIK3CA&#8230;</italic>), in a non-invasive way (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p><p>One of the outstanding results from this study is the analysis of cfDNA concentration and fragmentation as well as the <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> gene expression in the plasma of dogs with mammary tumors and its association with clinicopathological data. Thus, as early studies in human medicine, we found that plasma cfDNA concentrations were elevated in tumor-bearing dogs compared with healthy dogs and with poor prognosis characteristics: simple or undifferentiated carcinomas, higher histological grade of tumors and presence of peritumoral inflammation (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). While several studies in human medicine have observed the usefulness of cfDNA concentration as an early predictor of prognosis, aggressiveness or metastasis, there has been a lack of studies in veterinary oncology (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). In the present study, the concentration of cfDNA in dogs with benign tumors was higher than that in healthy dogs, but lower than that in carcinoma-bearing dogs as previously has been reported for humans (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). As we have observed here, some studies in CMTs and lymphomas, have found a correlation between ctDNA concentration and worse prognosis and severity of the tumor (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). In another study, the number of repetitive DNA sequences (CAN SINE sequences) was evaluated in cfDNA of dogs with mammary tumors and observed a direct association with a worse prognosis (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). However, it should be noted in this study, that cfDNA concentration in carcinomas does not vary significantly depending on molecular subtype, lymphatic invasion or presence of necrosis.</p><p>Another interesting finding was the elevated percentage of short-fragments in the ctDNA of animals with malignant and benign tumors compared to healthy dogs. Interestingly, grade II and III carcinomas showed higher concentration of cfDNA short-fragments than grade I and simple carcinomas displayed higher cfDNA short-fragments than non-simple carcinomas. According to our results, Beffagna et al. (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), quantified the amount of short and long cfDNA fragments by qPCR, and demonstrated higher cfDNA short-fragments than healthy dogs or non-neoplastic diseased dogs. Coinciding with previous publications in human medicine (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) we have been able to quantify and analyse cfDNA fragments by using a more specific fragment analyzer system for cancer patients. The fragment length of cfDNA tends to be shorter (&lt; 190 bp) in more malignant tumors (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). It has also been suggested that higher ctDNA fragmentation (and therefore a greater number of short-fragments) may be present in cancer cell apoptosis compared to non-cancer cell apoptosis. This would imply that the degree of fragmentation during apoptosis may be different between tumor-bearing and healthy individuals (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Likewise, the canine cfDNA fragmentome is poorly understood at this time, requiring future studies, with higher number of dogs, to this regards to fully understand its potential as a biomarker for clinical use.</p><p>Accordingly, the determination of ctDNA levels in plasma, as well as the analysis of the size of the ctDNA fragments, can be detected using a non-invasive technique, providing significant clinical relevance in veterinary oncology and contribute to the better definition and detection of tumors.</p><p>Finally, it is worth highlighting the findings regarding the basal expression of the <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> gene in plasma of dogs with mammary tumors. In both human and animal patients, <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> overexpression, primarily assessed by IHC techniques in tumor tissues, is linked to poor prognosis and tumor progression confirming the usefulness of this oncogene as a tumor biomarker (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). In our study, a differential expression of the <italic toggle="yes">TP53-wt</italic> gene has been observed in plasma and in tumor tissue in dogs.</p><p>From our knowledge, this is the first study that analyzes the expression of this tumor suppressor gene using the ddPCR technique in CMTs. Thus, we observed that the percentage of expression of <italic toggle="yes">TP53-wt</italic> is higher in dogs with tumors than in healthy dogs and in the case of &#8220;other carcinomas&#8221; the expression is increased with respect to simple or complex carcinomas. As in human breast cancer, <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> gene is one of the most frequently mutated gene in CMTs (15%&#8722;20%) (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). In addition, in breast carcinoma, overexpression of <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> is associated with point mutations within highly conserved regions of in exon 5&#8211;8. To date, the most frequent <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> mutations that has been describe in dogs are located in exon 7 at codons 236, 245 and 249 (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>) but no data from canine plasma samples have been previously described. The most likely reason why the point mutation at codon 245 has not been detected in our study could be: that the analyzed samples do not carry said mutation, or that it was at a lower frequency than ddPCR detection limit. Therefore, in order to confirm these results, it is essential that other studies are carried out including a larger number of animals as well as the analysis of other potential key point mutations for this cancer related-gene. Taking into account that human and canine <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> gene shows 86.3% homology, makes the dog a good model for comparative studies of this oncogene in human oncology.</p><p>Interestingly, it was also observed that the expression of the <italic toggle="yes">TP53-wt</italic> gene in plasma showed a high concordance with the levels of expression of the gene found in tumor tissue. Moreover, a correlation was also observed between a higher expression of the <italic toggle="yes">TP53-wt</italic> gene and the presence of a higher amount of cfDNA in plasma, which would also determine a poor prognosis indicator. These findings are quite novel since this is the first study that analyses this oncogene at the plasma and tissue level at the same time and determine that the <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> expression in plasma faithfully reflects what is observed in the tumor.</p><p>In summary, the results obtained from this work indicate, as occurs in humans, that higher cfDNA concentration, short-fragments and higher <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> expression (in plasma and tissue) in CMTs correlates with worse prognosis clinicopathological parameters. The validation and standardization of this methodology in CMTs will offer a unique, safe and easy opportunity for the diagnosis, prognosis and treatment of animals with mammary tumors. Future research in the field will confirm the prognostic and predictive value of ctDNA and its fragments, as well as the analysis of target mutations in veterinary oncology and make this methodology available to clinical veterinary centers.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s5"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/<xref rid="s10" ref-type="sec">Supplementary material</xref>, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="s6"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by Comit&#233; de Bio&#233;tica y Seguridad and Universidad de C&#243;rdoba. Written informed consent was obtained from the owners for the participation of their animals in this study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s7"><title>Author contributions</title><p>SG-L, RS-C, and YM designed this study and critically revised the manuscript. MDF performed IHQ analysis and interpretation of data. AR performed the gene analysis of plasma and tissue samples. JAF and AR-A contributed to the collection, clinical characterization of clinical samples, and elaboration of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to thank all the veterinarians who participated in this research study as well as the technical help from the Genomics Units at the IMIBIC.</p></ack><fn-group><title>Abbreviations</title><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>cfDNA, circulating cell-free DNA; ddPCR, digital PCR; EDTA, ethylenediaminetetraacetic; IHC, immunohistochemistry; H&amp;E, hematoxylin and eosin; DAB, 3'3 diaminiobenzidine; PR, progesterone receptor; ER, estrogen receptor; CMC, canine mammary carcinoma; PI, proliferation index; TN, triple negative.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s9"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s10"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2023.1157878/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2023.1157878/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM2" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_2.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cescon</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bratman</surname><given-names>S V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siu</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Circulating tumor DNA and liquid biopsy in oncology</article-title>. <source>Nat Cancer.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>276</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s43018-020-0043-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35122035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jahr</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hentze</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Englisch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hardt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fackelmayer</surname><given-names>FO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hesch</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>fragments in the blood plasma of cancer patients: quantitations and evidence for their origin from apoptotic and necrotic cells</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>1659</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11245480</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heitzer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>CES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Speicher</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Current and future perspectives of liquid biopsies in genomics-driven oncology</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>88</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41576-018-0071-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30410101</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Circulating cell-free DNA for cancer early detection</article-title>. <source>Innovation.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>100259</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.xinn.2022.100259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35647572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9133648</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>QR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cell-free DNA: hope and potential application in cancer</article-title>. <source>Front Cell Dev Biol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>192</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcell.2021.639233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33693004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7938321</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Garcia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hills</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hastings</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toghill</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goddard</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Plasma cell-free DNA (cfDNA) as a predictive and prognostic marker in patients with metastatic breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Breast Cancer Res.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13058-019-1235-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31856868</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6924016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbosh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Birkbak</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jamal-Hanjani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Constantin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phylogenetic ctDNA analysis depicts early stage lung cancer evolution</article-title>. <source>Nature.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>545</volume>:<fpage>446</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature22364</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28445469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5812436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raleigh</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callahan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vergara</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ftouni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatzimihalis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Circulating tumor DNA analysis and functional imaging provide complementary approaches for comprehensive disease monitoring in metastatic melanoma</article-title>. <source>JCO Precis Oncol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>2017</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/PO.16.00009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35172485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mair</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mouliere</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandrananda</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marass</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Measurement of plasma cell-free mitochondrial tumor DNA improves detection of glioblastoma in patient-derived orthotopic xenograft models</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>79</volume>:<fpage>220</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-18-0074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30389699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6753020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>DMW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kisseberth</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lehman</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelbick</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Quantification of plasma DNA as a prognostic indicator in canine lymphoid neoplasia</article-title>. <source>Vet Comp Oncol.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>145</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1476-5829.2007.00122.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19754786</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vernau</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Modiano</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olver</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avery</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Diagnosis of canine lymphoid neoplasia using clonal rearrangements of antigen receptor genes</article-title>. <source>Vet Pathol.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>32</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1354/vp.40-1-32</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12627711</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beffagna</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sammarco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romualdi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mainenti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mollo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Circulating cell-free DNA in dogs with mammary tumors: short and long fragments and integrity index</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0169454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28081183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5231265</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guil-Luna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#225;nchez-C&#233;spedes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mill&#225;n</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Andr&#233;s</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roll&#243;n</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Domingo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Aglepristone decreases proliferation in progesterone receptor-positive canine mammary carcinomas</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>518</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-1676.2011.0723.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21488964</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elvers</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner-Maier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swofford</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koltookian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Exome sequencing of lymphomas from three dog breeds reveals somatic mutation patterns reflecting genetic background</article-title>. <source>Genome Res.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1634</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.194449.115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26377837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4617960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Durrant</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Motsinger-Reif</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Genome-wide DNA copy number analysis and targeted transcriptional analysis of canine histiocytic malignancies identifies diagnostic signatures and highlights disruption of spindle assembly complex</article-title>. <source>Chromosome Res.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>179</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>202</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10577-019-09606-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31011867</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tagawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tambo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maezawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomihari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inokuma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Quantitative analysis of the BRAF V595E mutation in plasma cell-free DNA from dogs with urothelial carcinoma</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>e0232365</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0232365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32330187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7182225</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hennecke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bornemann-Kolatzki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urnovitz</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neumann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Str&#246;bel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genome aberrations in canine mammary carcinomas and their detection in cell-free plasma DNA</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e0075485</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0075485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24098698</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3787092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prouteau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Denis</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Fornel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cadieu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Derrien</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kergal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Circulating tumor DNA is detectable in canine histiocytic sarcoma, oral malignant melanoma, and multicentric lymphoma</article-title>. <source>Sci Repo.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-80332-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33441840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7806858</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bardelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Liquid biopsies: genotyping circulating tumor DNA</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>579</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>86</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2012.45.2011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24449238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4820760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mouliere</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandrananda</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piskorz</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahlborn</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Enhanced detection of circulating tumor DNA by fragment size analysis</article-title>. <source>Sci Transl Med</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>10</volume>:eaat4921 <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.aat4921</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30404863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6483061</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarzenbach</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Circulating nucleic acids as biomarkers in breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Breast Cancer Res.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/bcr3446</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24090167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3978696</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wakui</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maekawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masaoka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ushigome</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>p53 gene mutations occurring in spontaneous benign and malignant mammary tumors of the dog</article-title>. <source>Vet Pathol.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>248</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1354/vp.37-3-248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10810989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alsaihati</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobbin</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Canine tumor mutational burden is correlated with TP53 mutation across tumor types and breeds</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>4670</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-24836-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34344882</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8333103</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumaraguruparan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prathiba</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Of humans and canines: immunohistochemical analysis of PCNA, Bcl-2, p53, cytokeratin and ER in mammary tumours</article-title>. <source>Res Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>81</volume>:<fpage>218</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rvsc.2005.08.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16740286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kweon</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mutation and overexpression of p53 as a prognostic factor in canine mammary tumors</article-title>. <source>J Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4142/jvs.2004.5.1.63</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15028887</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mau&#233;s</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramundo</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Figueiredo</surname><given-names>AMS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Mello</surname><given-names>MFV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Jaick</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>TP53 gene expression levels and tumor aggressiveness in canine mammary carcinomas</article-title>. <source>J Vet Diagn Inv</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1040638717721730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28754073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zapulli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pe&#241;a</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rassoto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldschmidt</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scruggs</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Volume 2: Mammary Tumour. Surgical Pathology of Tumors Domestic Animals</source> (<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiupel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, editor). <publisher-loc>Gurnee, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Davis-Thompson Foundation</publisher-name> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#225;nchez-C&#233;spedes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#225;ndez-Mart&#237;nez</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raya</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pineda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#243;pez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mill&#225;n</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Vitamin D receptor (VDR) expression in different molecular subtypes of canine mammary carcinoma</article-title>. <source>BMC Vet Res.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12917-021-02901-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34034728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8152340</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elizabeth Hale Hammond</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mangu</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>JMS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 testing in breast cancer: american society of clinical oncology/college of American pathologists clinical practice guideline focused update</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>2105</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2018.77.8738</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29846122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allred</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berardo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prognosis and predictive factors in breast cancer by immunohistochemical analysis</article-title>. <source>Mod Patho</source>. (<year>1998</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>155</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>68</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9504686</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2 C T method</article-title>. <source>Methods.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>402</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burchell</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Worth</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gedye</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Kinetics of plasma cell-free DNA and creatine kinase in a canine model of tissue injury</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.14901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29230875</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5787206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cave</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gedye</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bridges</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Investigation of cell-free DNA in canine plasma and its relation to disease</article-title>. <source>Vet Q.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>122</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01652176.2016.1182230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27103480</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang ZH Li</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Quantitative analysis of plasma circulating DNA at diagnosis and during follow-up of breast cancer patients</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>243</volume>:<fpage>64</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.canlet.2005.11.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16412565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarzenbach</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#252;ller</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milde-Langosch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinbach</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pantel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of cell-free tumour DNA and RNA in patients with breast cancer and benign breast disease</article-title>. <source>Mol Biosyst.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>2848</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>54</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c1mb05197k</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21785770</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cherepanova</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamkovich</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryzgunova</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vlassov</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laktionov</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Deoxyribonuclease activity and circulating DNA concentration in blood plasma of patients with prostate tumors</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>1137</volume>:<fpage>218</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1196/annals.1448.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18837950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Casadio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calistri</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tebaldi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bravaccini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martorana</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Urine cell-free DNA integrity as a marker for early bladder cancer diagnosis: preliminary data</article-title>. <source>Urol Oncol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>1744</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.urolonc.2012.07.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23141783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Radpour</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barekati</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asadollahi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bitzer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wight</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Levels of plasma circulating cell free nuclear and mitochondrial DNA as potential biomarkers for breast tumors</article-title>. <source>Mol Cancer.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-4598-8-105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19922604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2780981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gelaleti</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Granzotto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leonel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jardim B</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moschetta</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carareto</surname><given-names>CMA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Short interspersed CAN SINE elements as prognostic markers in canine mammary neoplasia</article-title>. <source>Oncol Rep.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>435</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/or.2013.2827</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24173085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vishnubhatla</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raina</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gogia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deo</surname><given-names>SSV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Circulating cell-free DNA and its integrity as a prognostic marker for breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Springerplus.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40064-015-1071-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26090312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4469592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Umetani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hiramatsu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reber</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hines</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bilchik</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Increased integrity of free circulating DNA in sera of patients with colorectal or periampullary cancer: direct quantitative PCR for ALU repeats</article-title>. <source>Clin Chem.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>1062</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1373/clinchem.2006.068577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16723681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madhavan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallwiener</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bents</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zucknick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nees</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schott</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Plasma DNA integrity as a biomarker for primary and metastatic breast cancer and potential marker for early diagnosis</article-title>. <source>Breast Cancer Res Treat.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>146</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10549-014-2946-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24838941</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kweon</surname><given-names>OK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mutations of p53 tumor suppressor gene in spontaneous canine mammary tumors</article-title>. <source>J Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>321</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4142/jvs.2002.3.4.321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12819382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Melling</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norrenbrock</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kluth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hube-Magg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steurer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>p53 overexpression is a prognosticator of poor outcome in esophageal cancer</article-title>. <source>Oncol Lett.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>3826</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/ol.2019.10020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30881503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6403495</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seung</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sur</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Overexpression and mutation of p53 exons 4&#8211;8 in canine intestinal adenocarcinoma</article-title>. <source>J Comp Pathol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>175</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcpa.2019.12.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32138847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klopfleisch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Differential expression of cell cycle regulators p21, p27 and p53 in metastasizing canine mammary adenocarcinomas versus normal mammary glands</article-title>. <source>Res Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>87</volume>:<fpage>91</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rvsc.2008.12.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19185891</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leeuwen I</surname><given-names>Van</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hellmen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van den</surname><given-names>Burgh</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>G R</surname><given-names>Rutteman</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>P53 mutations in mammary tumor cell lines and corresponding tumor tissues in the dog</article-title>. <source>Anticancer Res</source>. (<year>1996</year>) <volume>16</volume>(<issue>6B</issue>):<fpage>3737</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9042250</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayr</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dressler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reifinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feil</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cytogenetic alterations in eight mammary tumors and tumor-suppressor gene p53 mutation in one mammary tumor from dogs</article-title>. <source>Am J Vet Res.</source> (<year>1998</year>) <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>78</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9442248</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Setoguchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minehata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yazawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishizaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Aberrations of the p53 tumor suppressor gene in various tumors in dogs</article-title>. <source>Am J Vet Res.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>62</volume>:<fpage>433</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/ajvr.2001.62.433</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11277210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>