<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12380827</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12380827.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12380827</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12380827</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40881628</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2025.1672786</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial: Vetinformatics: an insight for decoding livestock systems through <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> biology, volume II</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="JM">Jun-Mo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/749802/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names initials="RK">Rajesh Kumar</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/388702/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Animal Science and Technology, Chung-Ang University</institution>, <addr-line>Anseong-si</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Pere Virgili Institute for Health Research (IISPV)</institution>, <addr-line>Tarragona</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited and reviewed by: Johann S&#246;lkner, University of Natural Resources and Life Sciences Vienna, Austria</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Jun-Mo Kim <email>junmokim@cau.ac.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">480746</issue-id><elocation-id>1672786</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>01</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>13</day><month>08</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>28</day><month>08</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-08-31 12:25:40.890"><day>31</day><month>08</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2025 Kim and Pathak.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kim and Pathak</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-12-1672786.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="commentary-article" xml:lang="en" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/60467/vetinformatics-an-insight-for-decoding-livestock-systems-through-in-silico-biology-volume-ii"/><kwd-group><kwd>vetinformatics</kwd><kwd>veterinary science</kwd><kwd>animal health</kwd><kwd>machine learning</kwd><kwd>One Health</kwd><kwd>multi-omics</kwd><kwd>molecular docking and molecular dynamics (MD) simulation</kwd><kwd>vaccine design</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="7"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="1608"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Livestock Genomics</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Global demand for food is increasing alongside the rapidly growing human population, which is projected to reach nearly 10 billion by 2050 (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Livestock systems face unprecedented pressures as emerging pathogens increase because of climate change, antimicrobial resistance, and the urgent need for sustainable intensification (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Traditional veterinary science approaches have struggled to address these multidimensional challenges. Vetinformatics is an emerging interdisciplinary field poised to revolutionize animal health and production by decoding the complex molecular mechanisms governing livestock biology (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Vetinformatics integrates computational biology, data science, and multiomics technologies into core veterinary disciplines, such as pharmacology, genetics, and epidemiology (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). This represents a new bioinformatic research concept that employs an interdisciplinary approach to understand the complex molecular mechanisms of animal systems. This synergy accelerates research, ensures food security, optimizes animal welfare, and support One Health (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p><p>The catalyst for vetinformatics is the deluge of data from next-generation sequencing and functional genomics (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Genome assemblies for cattle, pigs, poultry, and other livestock provide blueprints for identifying disease resistance genes, markers, and metabolic pathways. For example, transcriptomics reveals how genes regulate reproductive efficiency, whereas metagenomics reveals how rumen microbiomes influence feed efficiency in livestock (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). However, the raw data alone are inert. Vetinformatics transforms them into actionable knowledge through tools, such as SPAdes, for genome assembly, edgeR for RNA-Seq data analysis, and GATK for variant detection, enabling species-specific insights (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Additionally, predictive modeling, such as molecular dynamics simulations, assesses how mutations affect protein stability, whereas systems biology integrates genomics, proteomics, and metabolomics to model host-pathogen interactions. Furthermore, molecular docking and virtual screening of compound libraries against target receptors have accelerated veterinary medicine research (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>).</p><p>These implications extend beyond productivity alone. Vetinformatics underpins vaccine design and offers alternatives to antibiotics (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Machine learning algorithms classify livestock behavior from video data (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), thereby enabling early disease detection. However, challenges remain, such as non-integrated data, scarce species-specific databases, and training gaps between veterinarians and computational biologists (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). As we stand at these crossroads, vetinformatics is not merely an adjunct to veterinary science; it is its evolving backbone. Bridging genotype to phenotype equips us to foster resilient livestock systems, mitigate zoonotic risks, and ethically meet global food needs. The future will demand nothing less than a computationally empowered revolution in animal health (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>).</p><p>&#8220;<italic toggle="yes">Vetinformatics: an insight for decoding livestock systems through in silico biology, volume II</italic>&#8221; attracted eight submissions, with six high-quality contributions accepted for this Research Topic.</p><p>The first article in this Research Topic, titled &#8220;<italic toggle="yes">Machine learning-based risk prediction model for canine myxomatous mitral valve disease using electronic health record data</italic>,&#8221; analyzed the records of 143 MMVD-affected dogs (2018&#8211;2022). Researchers tested four machine learning models to predict the risk of heart failure. The random forest model emerged as the most effective (88% accuracy), with heart imaging and radiograph measurements ranking as the top predictors. Packed cell volume, respiratory rate, and chloride levels also showed strong predictive values. This tool helps veterinarians make more informed prognostic decisions for dogs with this common heart condition (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2023.1189157" ext-link-type="uri">Kim et al.</ext-link>). The second article, titled &#8220;<italic toggle="yes">Aflatoxin contamination of animal feeds and its predictors among dairy farms in Northwest Ethiopia: One Health approach implications</italic>,&#8221; highlights the widespread contamination of dairy feeds with aflatoxins in this region. This study identified poor storage practices, certain feed ingredients, and seasonal factors as major contributors. These findings point to a serious risk to milk safety and underline the need for better awareness and health-based interventions at the farm level (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2023.1123573" ext-link-type="uri">Tadele et al.</ext-link>). The third article, entitled &#8220;<italic toggle="yes">Structure-based virtual screening and molecular dynamics studies to explore potential natural inhibitors against 3C protease of foot-and-mouth disease virus</italic>,&#8221; used molecular modeling to search thousands of natural compounds targeting a key viral protein. Researchers identified promising candidates with strong binding affinities. These findings open the door for the development of new antiviral drugs for foot-and-mouth disease in livestock (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2023.1340126" ext-link-type="uri">Sahoo et al.</ext-link>). The fourth article, titled &#8220;<italic toggle="yes">RNA sequencing analysis of sexual dimorphism in Japanese quail</italic>,&#8221; shows that quails and chickens share similar sex-related gene expression patterns. Similar to chickens, quails lack global Z-chromosome dosage compensation. Some genes shift sex bias by tissue or stage, offering insights into avian sexual dimorphism and supporting future genetic research (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1441021" ext-link-type="uri">Park et al.</ext-link>). The fifth article, titled &#8220;<italic toggle="yes">Identifying feature genes of chickens with different feather pecking tendencies based on three machine learning algorithms and WGCNA</italic>,&#8221; analyzes gene expression in chickens with varying feather-pecking behaviors. By integrating network analysis and three machine learning approaches, this study identified five key genes&#8212;<italic toggle="yes">NUFIP2, ST14, OVM, GLULD1</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">LOC424943</italic>&#8212;which were validated using ROC analysis in an independent dataset. These findings provide a foundation for further research on the behavioral traits of poultry (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1508397" ext-link-type="uri">Wen et al.</ext-link>). Concluding this Research Topic is an article titled &#8220;<italic toggle="yes">Genome-wide association studies with prolapsed gland of the third eyelid in dogs</italic>.&#8221; This study conducted genome-wide association analyses of 653 brachycephalic dogs and 788 dogs with various head shapes, identifying significant SNPs on chromosomes CFA3 and CFA22. Notably, genes, such as <italic toggle="yes">NR2F1, DIO3</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">TTC8</italic>, are associated with eye development and disease. These findings offer new insights into the genetic underpinnings of cherry eye disease in dogs (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1520155" ext-link-type="uri">Zeng et al.</ext-link>).</p><p>To address the increasing need for computational resources in veterinary science, this Research Topic highlights the advances and potential of vetinformatics. It explores how these approaches can help unravel complex livestock biology and offer practical ways to enhance animal health and welfare.</p></body><back><ack><p>We thank all contributing authors for their valuable work and the reviewers for their thoughtful and constructive feedback. We are also grateful to Professor Kyu Sang Lim and Dr. Neetesh Pandey for serving as coordinators for this special Research Topic. Finally, we extend our appreciation to Ilaria Lopez, Senior Journal Specialist, and the entire editorial team at <italic toggle="yes">Frontiers in Veterinary Science</italic> for their continued support in editing and managing this Research Topic. The authors acknowledge support from the Basic Science Research Program through the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF), funded by the Ministry of Education (NRF-2018R1A6A1A03025159).</p></ack><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>J-MK: Writing &#8211; original draft, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. RP: Writing &#8211; original draft, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p><p>The author(s) declared that they were an editorial board member of Frontiers, at the time of submission. This had no impact on the peer review process and the final decision.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ai-statement" id="s2"><title>Generative AI statement</title><p>The author(s) declare that no Generative AI was used in the creation of this manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s3"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ranganathan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waite</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Searchinger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>How to Sustainably Feed 10 Billion People by 2050 in 21 Charts</source> (<year>2018</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.wri.org/insights/how-sustainably-feed-10-billion-people-2050-21-charts" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.wri.org/insights/how-sustainably-feed-10-billion-people-2050-21-charts</ext-link> (Accessed July 1, 2025).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Vetinformatics from functional genomics to drug discovery: insights into decoding complex molecular mechanisms of livestock systems in veterinary science</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1008728</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.1008728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36439342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9691653</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>editors</surname></name></person-group>. <source>Bioinformatics in Veterinary Science: Vetinformatics</source>. <publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer Nature</publisher-name> (<year>2025</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://link.springer.com/10.1007/978-981-97-7395-4" ext-link-type="uri">https://link.springer.com/10.1007/978-981-97-7395-4</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-981-97-7395-4</pub-id> (Accessed July 1, 2025).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Editorial: Vetinformatics: an insight for decoding livestock systems through in silico biology</article-title>. <source>Front. Vet. Sci.</source> (<year>2023</year>). 10:1292733. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1292733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38026650</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10643129</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bick</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Metcalf</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayo</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lichtenstein</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genomic data in the all of us research program</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>627</volume>:<fpage>340</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-023-06957-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38374255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10937371</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>C3D-ConvLSTM based cow behaviour classification using video data for precision livestock farming</article-title>. <source>Comput. Electr. Agric</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>193</volume>:<fpage>106650</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.compag.2021.106650</pub-id>38632328
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Veterinary systems biology for bridging the phenotype-genotype gap via computational modeling for disease epidemiology and animal welfare</article-title>. <source>Brief Bioinform</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>bbae025</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bib/bbae025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38343323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10859662</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>