<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11638244</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11638244.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11638244</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11638244</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39679173</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2024.1415753</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evaluation and spatiotemporal evolution of veterinary talent competitiveness: a new perspective of veterinary education</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names initials="X">Xianhang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2713025/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arshad</surname><given-names initials="MA">Mohd Anuar</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c002" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1403513/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jian</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yugang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c003" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names initials="A">Arshad</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1386914/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names initials="M">Mengdie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>School of Management, Chongqing Institute of Engineering</institution>, <addr-line>Chongqing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>School of Management, Universiti Sains Malaysia</institution>, <addr-line>Penang</addr-line>, <country>Malaysia</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>School of Business and Economics, University of Wuppertal</institution>, <addr-line>Wuppertal</addr-line>, <country>Germany</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Jose Antonio Tapia, University of Extremadura, Spain</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Juan Claudio Gutierrez, University of California, Davis, United States</p><p>A. L. Oropesa, University of Extremadura, Spain</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Xianhang Xu <email>xuxianhang@cqie.edu.cn</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Mohd Anuar Arshad <email>anuar_arshad@usm.my</email></corresp><corresp id="c003">Yugang Jian <email>00070@cqie.edu.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">454084</issue-id><elocation-id>1415753</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-12-17 16:25:16.470"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2024 Xu, Arshad, Jian, Mahmood and Dong.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Xu, Arshad, Jian, Mahmood and Dong</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-11-1415753.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Improving the quantity and quality of veterinary talent cultivation is an urgent issue to address in current veterinary education and is key to enhancing veterinary talent competitiveness. Starting from an industrial perspective, the introduction of scientific analytical methods for studying veterinary talent competitiveness offers a new view on veterinary education and helps to improve the quality of veterinary education and talent cultivation.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>This study develops a veterinary talent competitiveness evaluation index based on the characteristics of veterinary talent. It proposes a visual method to analyze the level and spatiotemporal evolution of veterinary talent competitiveness using the Entropy method and ArcGIS tools, with Western China as a case study. Data is collected from 12 regions in Western China, spanning 2015 to 2021.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The results show that the method not only evaluates the current state of veterinary talent competitiveness but also considers temporal and spatial evolution, achieving good evaluation effectiveness and high accuracy, thereby guiding the improvement of veterinary education and talent cultivation.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Based on the research findings, the study suggests improving the quality of veterinary education and talent cultivation through measures such as strengthening talent resource development, addressing regional imbalances, and promoting spatial integration to achieve a virtuous cycle between veterinary education and industrial development.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>veterinary</kwd><kwd>talent competitiveness</kwd><kwd>veterinary education</kwd><kwd>evaluation index</kwd><kwd>spatiotemporal evolution</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare financial support was received for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This work was supported by the Chongqing Education and Research Experimental Base (Grant No. JD2024G028) and the Chongqing University Student' Innovation and Entrepreneurship Training Program (Grant No. 202312608001S).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="4"/><equation-count count="12"/><ref-count count="119"/><page-count count="13"/><word-count count="9056"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Veterinary Humanities and Social Sciences</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>1 Introduction</title><p>Animal husbandry is vital to people's livelihood (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), serving as a strategic industry that ensures food security and the wellbeing of residents (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Veterinarians are an indispensable part of animal husbandry (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), playing a crucial role in ensuring animal health, improving production efficiency, securing food safety, and supporting public health (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). China is the largest animal husbandry producer in the world (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). With the rapid development of animal husbandry, the demand for veterinary professionals has significantly increased (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). However, issues such as the insufficient number of veterinarians and the uneven quality of veterinary talent have begun to hinder the sustainable development of this industry. Talent is the primary resource (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), and the progress of any industry is deeply linked to the strategic distribution of skilled talent (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), which cannot be separated from veterinary talent cultivation. Improving the quantity and quality of veterinary talent cultivation has become an urgent issue that needs to be addressed in current veterinary education (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Veterinary education forms the foundation for cultivating veterinary talent (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), and the quantity and quality of talent cultivation directly determine veterinary talent competitiveness. It requires veterinary educational institutions to provide high-quality education to cultivate talents that meet the demands of the modern industry, and it necessitates continuous evaluation and monitoring of veterinary talent competitiveness. Furthermore, with changing societal needs and advancements in veterinary science, veterinary education faces many new challenges and opportunities (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). It calls for a new perspective to review and adjust the strategies and content of veterinary education, to cultivate veterinary professionals who can adapt to future changes.</p><p>Veterinary talent competitiveness is essentially the research category of industrial talent competitiveness. This competitiveness is a complex concept, encompassing factors like the scale, structure, and efficiency of talent within an industry and the investment, policies, and environmental factors influencing talent development (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). This concept is manifested as the comprehensive competitiveness of a country or region's specific industry regarding the quantity, quality, structure, support, and environment of talent (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Scholars have utilized various methods such as Analytic Hierarchy Process (AHP), Principal Component Analysis (PCA), Entropy, Neural Network, Gray analysis, and Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) to develop talent competitiveness evaluation indexes (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), which are used to assess the talent competitiveness across different countries, regions, and industries.</p><p>Regarding national and regional talent competitiveness research, the Global Talent Competitiveness Index (GTCI) released by the European Institute of Business Administration (INSEAD) has gained widespread recognition. This index analyzes the talent competitiveness of various countries primarily from talent input and output (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Based on GTCI, many scholars have developed talent competitiveness evaluation indexes to study talent competitiveness in countries like Romania, Lithuania, India, the Republic of Moldova, China, Ukraine, and others (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Based on their understanding, scholars have studied national and regional talent competitiveness from the dimensions of talent resources, talent input, talent efficiency, talent environment, etc. (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>).</p><p>In exploring industrial talent competitiveness, scholars have delved into various sectors. These include Nigeria's banking industry, the green chemical technology industry in Eastern China, Greece's shipping industry, Shenzhen's chip industry, Chongqing's intelligent industry, and Liaoning's manufacturing industry (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). As a particular type of industrial talent competitiveness, some scholars have also studied scientific and technological talent competitiveness (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>).</p><p>Currently, interdisciplinary research has become a trend in various fields. GIS technology can perform spatial analysis and visualization display (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), scholars have increasingly conducted various competitiveness studies using GIS technology, mainly involving tourism competitiveness (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>), logistics competitiveness (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>), cultural competitiveness (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>), environmental competitiveness (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>), trade competitiveness (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>), regional competitiveness (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>), industrial competitiveness (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>), and corporate competitiveness (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>).</p><p>The literature shows that current research on talent competitiveness primarily focuses on national, regional, and scientific and technological talents, with limited results related to industries. Particularly, there is a significant gap in research concerning the veterinary talent competitiveness. Meanwhile, the research on the competitiveness of GIS technology has involved multiple aspects, but there is little research on talent competitiveness. Therefore, from the perspective of industry, constructing an evaluation index based on the characteristics of veterinary talent to measure the level of veterinary talent competitiveness, combining GIS technology to analyze its spatiotemporal evolution, and providing a new perspective for the formulation of veterinary education strategies, which has theoretical and practical implications. The powerful spatial data analysis of GIS technology provides a new perspective and method for the study. It provides effective support for understanding the spatial evolution of competitiveness and can promote the development of interdisciplinary research such as veterinary medicine, economics, and geography, which will be an interesting exploration.</p><p>According to the above analysis, the aims of this study are as follows: Firstly, to develop a veterinary talent competitiveness evaluation index based on the characteristics of veterinary talent; Secondly, to utilize the Entropy method and GIS technology to analyze the level and spatiotemporal evolution of veterinary talent competitiveness in Western China; Thirdly, to propose suggestions for veterinary education from the perspective of talent competitiveness.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>2 Methods</title><sec><title>2.1 Research area</title><p>The scope of this study covers Western China, including 12 provinces, municipalities, and autonomous regions (see <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Western China occupies 70.6% of China's land area and 84.2% of its grassland area. All four of China's major pastoral areas are in Western China, making it a focal point for developing animal husbandry. Western region has abundant animal husbandry resources and gathers most of the veterinary talent in China. Therefore, selecting Western China for research is representative and feasible.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The regions of China.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-11-1415753-g0001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>2.2 Data sources</title><p>This study evaluates the veterinary talent competitiveness in 12 regions in Western China, spanning 2015 to 2021. The data are sourced from the &#8220;China Statistical Yearbook&#8221; (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>), &#8220;China Animal Husbandry and Veterinary Yearbook&#8221; (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>), &#8220;China Rural Statistical Yearbook&#8221; (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>), &#8220;China Statistical Yearbook on Science and Technology&#8221; (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>), and &#8220;National Education Fund Implementation Statistics Announcement&#8221; (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>2.3 Evaluation method</title><p>This study develops a veterinary talent competitiveness evaluation index and applies the Entropy method for evaluation.</p><sec><title>2.3.1 Development of evaluation index</title><p>From the perspective of veterinary education and veterinary talent cultivation, this study draws on scholars' selection of dimensions and indicators for talent competitiveness evaluation. It explores a conceptual model from four dimensions: talent resources, talent investment, development support, and development environment.</p><p>The talent resources dimension reflects the number, structure, and contribution of talents in the industry within the region (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>), representing the effect of veterinary talent cultivation and the current level of talent competitiveness, which are the key to ensuring industry development (<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>). Given the inconsistency in the statistical caliber of veterinary talent in different regions, this study uses data from local township animal husbandry and veterinary stations. The talent investment dimension reflects the comprehensive investment in talent development within a certain period in the region (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>, <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>), including the investment in veterinary education, representing the importance that governments and residents attach to activities such as education, technology, and innovation, which is directly related to potential talent cultivation (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>). The development support dimension reflects the external support forces of the region in attracting, selecting, developing, and retaining talents, representing the support of education, technology, culture, and health affairs, and are directly related to the sustainable development of talents (<xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>), which will act on the process of veterinary education and veterinary talent cultivation. The development environment dimension reflects the economic development, industry development, and people's living standards of rural areas in the region (<xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>), representing the impact of the development environment on the work and life of talents. It has become an important factor and potential attraction for attracting veterinary talent.</p><p>According to the conceptual model above, this study learns from scholars' selection of talent competitiveness evaluation indicators and develops an evaluation index (see <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Evaluation index of veterinary talent competitiveness.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Dimension</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Indicator</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Unit</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Direction</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>References</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Talent resources</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of personnel of township animal husbandry and veterinary station</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">People</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of the number of senior technical titles of township animal husbandry and veterinary station</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of personnel with master's degree or above in township animal husbandry and veterinary station</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Per capita output value of township animal husbandry and veterinary station</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,000 CNY</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Talent investment</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of education expenses in general public budget expenditures</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intensity of local financial investment in science and technology</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Per capita education, culture, and entertainment expenditure of rural residents</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNY</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General public budget agricultural, forestry, and water input per hectare of agricultural land</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNY</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Development support</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of students in higher education per 100,000 people</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">People</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of R&amp;D employees per 10,000 people</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">People</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of cultural service institutions per 100,000 people</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unit</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of beds in medical and health institutions per 1,000 people</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bed</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Development environment</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total power for agricultural machinery per 10,000 rural people</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KWH</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Per capita electricity consumption of rural residents</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KWH</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Per capita disposable income of rural residents</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNY</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Personnel salary of township animal husbandry and veterinary station</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CNY</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>CNY, Chinese Yuan; KWH, Kilowatt-hour.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>2.3.2 Talent competitiveness evaluation</title><p>The weighting of evaluation indicators is the key to building a talent competitiveness evaluation index. Considering the subjective arbitrariness of the subjective weight method and the significant deviation it brings (<xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>), this study uses the Entropy method to weight the indicators and evaluate the veterinary talent competitiveness in different regions.</p><p>
<bold>(1) Data standardization processing</bold>
</p><p>Constructing the original data matrix of indicators:</p><disp-formula id="E1"><mml:math id="M1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#8943;</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#8942;</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#8945;</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#8942;</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#8943;</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Here, X<sub>ij</sub> is the original value, representing the j-th indicator of the i-th region, and i = 1, 2, &#8230;, 12, j = 1, 2, &#8230;, 16.</p><p>Using the extreme value method to process positive and negative indicators separately, and Y<sub>ij</sub> is the standardized value.</p><p>Positive indicator processing:</p><disp-formula id="E2"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M2" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mo class="qopname">min</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo class="qopname">max</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mo class="qopname">min</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Negative indicator processing:</p><disp-formula id="E3"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M3" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo class="qopname">max</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>To avoid zero values, perform translation processing on the processed data:</p><disp-formula id="E4"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M4" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#8242;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#945;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#945;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Here, to preserve the original data pattern, take &#945; = 0.001.</p><p>After processing, the standardized data matrix is finally obtained:</p><disp-formula id="E5"><mml:math id="M5" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#8242;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#8943;</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#8242;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#8942;</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#8945;</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#8942;</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#8242;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#8943;</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#8242;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p>
<bold>(2) Calculate the proportion of each measurement indicator</bold>
</p><disp-formula id="E6"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M6" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#8242;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#8721;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#8242;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p>
<bold>(3) Calculate the information entropy of each measurement index</bold>
</p><disp-formula id="E7"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M7" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover accentunder="false" accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#8721;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover></mml:mstyle><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo class="qopname">ln</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>
<bold>(4) Calculate the weight of each evaluation indicator</bold>
</p><disp-formula id="E8"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="M8" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="false"><mml:munderover accentunder="false" accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#8721;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover></mml:mstyle><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Among them, the range of W<sub>j</sub> is [0, 1], j=1, 2, &#8230;, m.</p><p>
<bold>(5) Calculate the comprehensive veterinary talent competitiveness</bold>
</p><disp-formula id="E9"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="M9" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#215;</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>&#8721;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#8242;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Among them, the V<sub>i</sub> value reflects the strength of veterinary talent competitiveness in the region. The larger the V<sub>i</sub> value, the higher the veterinary talent competitiveness in the region.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>2.4 Spatial analysis method</title><p>This study analyzes the spatiotemporal evolution of veterinary talent competitiveness using ArcGIS software. Based on the principle of quartile difference in statistics, this study grades the total scores of veterinary talent competitiveness in Western China from 2015 to 2021 according to four levels. Then, it employs ArcGIS software to visualize the spatial pattern of competitiveness and intuitively display the spatial distribution of veterinary talent competitiveness.</p><p>Spatial autocorrelation analysis is an essential method in geographical research (<xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>). By measuring the degree of aggregation of spatial unit attribute values, the spatial dependence between an object and its spatial position is explored, which is utilized to analyze the statistical distribution of spatial data (<xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>). A positive correlation indicates that a spatial unit's attribute values change has the same trend as its neighboring units, while a negative correlation indicates the opposite (<xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>). To better reveal the spatial changes in veterinary talent competitiveness, this study analyzes the spatial correlation of regions through Global Moran's I.</p><disp-formula id="E10"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="M10" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="false"><mml:munderover accentunder="false" accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#8721;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover></mml:mstyle><mml:mstyle displaystyle="false"><mml:munderover accentunder="false" accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#8721;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover></mml:mstyle><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mstyle displaystyle="false"><mml:munderover accentunder="false" accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#8721;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover></mml:mstyle><mml:mstyle displaystyle="false"><mml:munderover accentunder="false" accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#8721;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover></mml:mstyle><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Here, I is the value of Moran's I, with a range of [&#8722;1,1]. A value exceeding 0 signifies a positive correlation, a value below 0 denotes a negative correlation, and a value exactly at 0 indicates no correlation. X<sub>i</sub> and X<sub>j</sub> are the values of variables i and j in regions, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M11" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> is the mean value, n is the province number, s<sup>2</sup> is the variable's variance, and W<sub>ij</sub> is the spatial weight between regions i and j.</p><p>To ensure the accuracy of Moran's I, Z-Score is commonly utilized for significance testing (<xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>). The calculation formula is:</p><disp-formula id="E11"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="M12" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Here, Z(I) represents the level of significance, E(I) is the expectation of the I value, and VAR(I) is the variance of the I value. A 95% confidence interval is used for significance testing. When |Z| &gt; 1.96, it indicates a significant spatial autocorrelation. When |Z| &lt; 1.96, it indicates a random distribution of observed values. When Z &gt; 1.96, there is a positive correlation and a clustered distribution. When Z &lt; &#8722;1.96, there is a negative correlation and a discrete distribution.</p><p>Global Moran's I is difficult to reflect the degree of correlation between a region and its surrounding provinces and cities. Consequently, the study integrates the Local Indicators of Spatial Association (LISA) analysis technique. This method is employed to break down the overall spatial correlation coefficient into individual spatial autocorrelations for each specific region, facilitating a more localized and detailed spatial analysis (<xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>). Divide the LISA aggregation map into four types of regions, namely high value regions surrounded by adjacent high values (H-H), high value regions surrounded by adjacent low values (H-L), low value regions surrounded by adjacent high values (L-H), and low value regions surrounded by adjacent low values (L-L). H-H and L-L represent spatial aggregation, while H-L and L-H represent spatial dispersion or differentiation. The formula of LISA Moran's I is:</p><disp-formula id="E12"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="M13" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover accentunder="false" accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#8721;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover></mml:mstyle><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>3 Results</title><sec><title>3.1 Evaluation index weighting</title><p>According to <xref rid="E2" ref-type="disp-formula">Equations 1</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="E8" ref-type="disp-formula">6</xref> and the data of western region from 2015 to 2021, the evaluation dimensions and indicators selected in Section 2 were weighted (see <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Weights of veterinary talent competitiveness evaluation dimensions and indicators.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Dimension</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Weight</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Indicator</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Entropy value</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Weight</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Talent resources</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3285</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of personnel of township animal husbandry and veterinary station</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9382</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0669</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of the number of senior technical titles of township animal husbandry and veterinary station</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8763</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1338</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of personnel with master's degree or above in township animal husbandry and veterinary station</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9356</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0697</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Per capita output value of township animal husbandry and veterinary station</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9462</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0581</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Talent investment</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1838</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of education expenses in general public budget expenditures</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9586</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0448</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intensity of local financial investment in science and technology</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9503</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0537</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Per capita education, culture, and entertainment expenditure of rural residents</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9804</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0212</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">General public budget agricultural, forestry, and water input per hectare of agricultural land</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9408</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0640</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Development support</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2379</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of students in higher education per 100,000 people</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9599</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0434</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of R&amp;D employees per 10,000 people</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9376</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0675</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of cultural service institutions per 100,000 people</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9115</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0957</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of beds in medical and health institutions per 1000 people</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9710</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0313</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Development environment</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2499</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total power for agricultural machinery per 10,000 rural people</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9112</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0961</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Per capita electricity consumption of rural residents</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9545</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0492</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Per capita disposable income of rural residents</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9645</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0384</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Personnel salary of township animal husbandry and veterinary station</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9389</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0661</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>From the four dimensions of veterinary talent competitiveness in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, the weight of the talent resources dimension is 0.3285, and the average weight of a single indicator is 0.0821. The weight of the talent investment dimension is 0.1838, and the average weight of a single indicator is 0.0459. The weight of the development support dimension is 0.2379, and the average weight of a single indicator is 0.0595. The weight of the development environment dimension is 0.2499, and the average weight of a single indicator is 0.0625. From the weight of 16 indicators to evaluate the level of veterinary talent competitiveness, the proportion of the number of senior technical titles of township animal husbandry and veterinary station (0.1338), the total power for agricultural machinery per 10,000 rural people (0.0961), the number of cultural service institutions per 100,000 people (0.0957), the proportion of people with master's degree or above in township animal husbandry and veterinary station (0.0697), the number of R&amp;D practitioners per 10,000 people (0.0675), the number of personnel of township animal husbandry and veterinary station (0.0669), the personnel salary of township animal husbandry and veterinary station (0.0661), and the general public budget agricultural, forestry, and water input per hectare of agricultural land are greater than the average (0.0625). The talent resources dimension has the highest weight, and three indicators are above average (0.0625), indicating that it has a significant impact on veterinary talent competitiveness. The weight of development support and development environment dimensions takes second place, indicating their impact on veterinary talent competitiveness is moderate. The weight of the talent investment dimension is the lowest, indicating its impact on veterinary talent competitiveness is relatively small.</p></sec><sec><title>3.2 Measurement of veterinary talent competitiveness</title><p>According to <xref rid="E9" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation 7</xref>, this study calculates the comprehensive index of veterinary talent competitiveness of 12 regions in Western China. The results are ranked to quantitatively reflect the veterinary talent competitiveness in each region from 2015 to 2021 (see <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Evaluation of veterinary talent competitiveness (2015&#8211;2021).</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Region</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>2015</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>2016</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>2017</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>2018</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>2019</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>2020</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>2021</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>Average</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Value</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Rank</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Value</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Rank</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Value</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Rank</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Value</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Rank</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Value</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Rank</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Value</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Rank</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Value</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Rank</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Value</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Rank</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chongqing</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.78</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.93</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.81</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.61</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sichuan</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.92</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.35</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.68</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.93</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.86</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.68</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guizhou</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.59</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.64</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yunnan</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.67</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.63</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xizang</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.68</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shaanxi</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.98</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.61</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.61</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.93</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.98</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gansu</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.91</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.70</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.49</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.65</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Qinghai</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ningxia</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.52</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.92</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.72</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xinjiang</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.99</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.77</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.63</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.68</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.69</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inner Mongolia</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.34</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.55</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.81</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.94</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guangxi</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.74</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.35</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.83</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8212;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The score of veterinary talent competitiveness in Western China has continued to rise from 2.11 in 2015 to 4.14 in 2021, showing an upward trend year by year. The score of talent competitiveness in the veterinary industry in various regions is relatively low, and the overall level needs to be improved, with uneven regional development levels. Chongqing has always had the strongest veterinary talent competitiveness. It has risen from 3.23 in 2015 to 5.81 in 2021, ranking first for 7 consecutive years. Shaanxi has continued to rise from 2.98 in 2015 to 4.93 in 2021, ranking second on average. Ningxia has risen from 2.47 in 2015 to 5.03 in 2021, ranking third on average. Sichuan has risen from 2.73 in 2015 to 4.86 in 2021, ranking fourth on average. Yunnan has risen from 2.00 in 2015 to 4.96 in 2021, ranking fifth on average. The average score of these five regions is greater than the average level in the western region, indicating relatively strong talent competitiveness. The average score of Inner Mongolia, Guizhou, Xinjiang, Gansu, Guangxi, Qinghai, Xizang, and other regions ranks sixth to twelfth, respectively. The average score of these seven regions is lower than the average level of the western region, and the talent competitiveness is relatively weak.</p></sec><sec><title>3.3 Spatiotemporal evolution of veterinary talent competitiveness</title><sec><title>3.3.1 Spatial differentiation and evolution of veterinary talent competitiveness</title><p>According to the principle of quartile difference in statistics, the veterinary talent competitiveness in 12 regions from 2015 to 2021 is divided into four levels based on their scores: the first level (high level), the second level (relatively high level), the third level (relatively low level), and the fourth level (low level). Their respective score ranges are 3.717&#8211;5.811, 3.003&#8211;3.716, 2.225&#8211;3.002, 0.620&#8211;2.224. This study selected data from 2015, 2017, 2019, and 2021 for comparison, and use ArcGIS software to draw a spatial pattern level distribution of veterinary talent competitiveness (see <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Spatial pattern level distribution of veterinary talent competitiveness. First level, high level, score ranges 3.717&#8211;5.811; Second level, relatively high level, score ranges 3.003&#8211;3.716; Third level, relatively low level, score ranges 2.225&#8211;3.002; and Fourth level, low level, score ranges 0.620&#8211;2.224.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-11-1415753-g0002.jpg"/></fig><p>This study found that the overall pattern for veterinary talent competitiveness in Western China has undergone significant changes, with all regions maintaining an upward trend, extending from northeast to southwest. Chongqing's competitiveness has always been the strongest, while Xizang's has always been the weakest. Compared with 2015, the number of regions with the first and second levels of competitiveness in 2021 has significantly increased, from 0 and 1 to 6 and 5, respectively. Most regions have increased by 2 levels. The most significant change is in Yunnan, which has risen from the fourth level to the first level, with an increase of three levels. The competitiveness of Xizang has improved slowly, from the fourth level to the third level, with only one level of improvement.</p></sec><sec><title>3.3.2 Spatial autocorrelation analysis of veterinary talent competitiveness</title><p>Based on <xref rid="E10" ref-type="disp-formula">Equations 8</xref>, <xref rid="E11" ref-type="disp-formula">9</xref>, the global spatial autocorrelation analysis and significance test were conducted on the veterinary talent competitiveness using the ArcGIS software (see <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Global spatial autocorrelation of veterinary talent competitiveness.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2015</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2017</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2019</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2021</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I Value</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2791</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3276</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3024</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2286</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z-Score</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0127</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2912</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0956</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7021</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>From <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, the Global Moran's I value of veterinary talent competitiveness over the years are all &gt;0, showing a significant positive spatial correlation feature in the veterinary talent competitiveness. Each region presents a clustering phenomenon in space. That is, there are one or several regions with higher competitiveness around regions with higher competitiveness, and regions with lower competitiveness will also have one or several regions with lower competitiveness adjacent to them. Using Z-Score to test the significance of the index, it was found that the Z-Score in 2015, 2017, and 2019 were greater than the critical value of 1.96, indicating a significant spatial autocorrelation and a clustering distribution of veterinary talent competitiveness. The Z-Score in 2021 is all &lt; 1.96, indicating a random distribution of observed values. Although there were fluctuations, the I values remained above 0.2, maintaining a relatively stable spatial pattern overall.</p><p>Based on <xref rid="E12" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation 10</xref>, this study uses ArcGIS software to conduct LISA analysis on the veterinary talent competitiveness in 12 regions. The spatial agglomeration types were visualized to obtain the LISA analysis map of talent competitiveness (see <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>LISA analysis map of veterinary talent competitiveness.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-11-1415753-g0003.jpg"/></fig><p><xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref> show that the regions with &#8220;H-H&#8221; clustering characteristics in veterinary talent competitiveness are concentrated in regions such as Chongqing, Sichuan, and Shaanxi. The regions with &#8220;L-L&#8221; clustering characteristics are only Xizang, and the regions with &#8220;L-H&#8221; clustering characteristics are only Guizhou, without any regions with &#8220;H-L&#8221; clustering characteristics.</p><p>There is a spatial agglomeration of veterinary talent competitiveness in Western China with increasingly evident regionalization and a relatively stable spatial pattern. The competitiveness remains on the rise, extending from northeast to southwest. The spatial differentiation of talent competitiveness has shifted from dispersion to aggregation, and the regionalization of aggregation has become increasingly evident. A clear positive spatial correlation characteristic indicates a stable overall spatial pattern. Regarding evolutionary trends, the local spatial correlation characteristics of veterinary talent competitiveness have not changed much, with severe spatial differentiation and no spatial linkage pattern yet formed, indicating that the regional veterinary talent competitiveness has certain path dependence or spatial locking characteristics.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>4 Discussion</title><p>This study is based on veterinary education and the characteristics of veterinary talent. A veterinary talent competitiveness evaluation index was developed, incorporating the Entropy method and ArcGIS software. These methods were utilized to analyze the level and spatiotemporal evolution of veterinary talent competitiveness in Western China from 2015 to 2021. Based on the previous analysis, the main discussions of this study are as follows:</p><p>The weightings of dimensions and indicators for evaluating the veterinary talent competitiveness indicate that talent resources exert the greatest influence on this competitiveness. Specifically, the number of veterinary talents, particularly the proportion of those holding senior technical titles and master's degrees or above, exerts a notable impact. Talent resources constitute the most important part of veterinary talent competitiveness, which is consistent with the research results on agricultural technology talent competitiveness (<xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>). Talent resources refer to the group of people with higher levels of quality in human resources (<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>), reflecting the quantity, quality, and structure of talent (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>), it is the most fundamental factor affecting talent competitiveness (<xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>). A sufficient number of talent is the foundation of competitive advantage, ensuring initiative in industrial development (<xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>), and the quality of talent is crucial for high-performance human resources (<xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>, <xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>). Given the significant impact of high-quality talent on the competitiveness of veterinary professionals, it is important to focus on increasing the quantity and quality of veterinary professionals. Targeted education reform and talent development strategies can enhance the quantity and quality of senior talents in the veterinary industry (<xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>, <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>). Veterinary education should strengthen employment skills and practical experience, promote cooperation with employers, and improve the quality and retention rate of veterinary professionals (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>), contemporary practices and technologies should also be incorporated to align with the Industry 4.0 trend (<xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>). By providing advanced training and continuing education in the field of veterinary medicine, professionals can be informed of the latest developments (<xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>), enhance their professional knowledge, and promote innovation (<xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>). Attractive salary and clear career paths also help attract and retain top talents in the veterinary field (<xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>), achieving sustainable development of industry talent (<xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>). In addition, universities should provide graduate education that focuses on cultivating future abilities, consistent with regional talent development strategies (<xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>).</p><p>The veterinary talent competitiveness in western regions has been improving year by year, but there is still significant room for improvement. In recent years, China's economy and society have developed rapidly, and the strategies of western development and rural revitalization have been deeply implemented (<xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>). The continuous improvement of various indicators in four dimensions has enabled the veterinary talent competitiveness to be continuously enhanced. Talent competitiveness is a complex, multidimensional, and relative concept (<xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>), which comprehensively considers the level of human resource development (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). The government should develop talent development strategies that focus on attracting, developing, and retaining talent (<xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>), accelerate the transformation of the population into talent that meets the requirements of industry enterprises (<xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>), thereby enhance the talent competitiveness.</p><p>The uneven development of veterinary talent competitiveness in different regions is related to local education resource allocation, policy support, talent cultivation, and economic development level (<xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>). Targeted strategies are needed to improve the competitiveness of regions with lower competitiveness (<xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>). Implementing policies that focus on developing human capital potential can enhance the talent competitiveness of underdeveloped regions (<xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>). Education is a long-term investment (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>), and from an educational perspective, talent development requires high-quality education (<xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>). In the regional innovation ecosystem, higher education institutions play a crucial role in developing, attracting, and retaining talent (<xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>). To attract and retain talent, the government needs to invest more resources in higher education (<xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>), increase support for education in relatively underdeveloped areas (<xref rid="B108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>), and actively improve education infrastructure in underdeveloped regions (<xref rid="B109" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>). Universities can also rely on their majors to introduce veterinary industry enterprises to invest equipment and improve the practical training scenarios for veterinary students (<xref rid="B110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>).</p><p>The spatial agglomeration trend of veterinary talent competitiveness in western regions continues to strengthen, maintaining a relatively stable spatial pattern, but a spatial linkage pattern has not yet been formed. This result is similar to the agglomeration of talent competitiveness in China (<xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>). There is a spatial agglomeration effect in competitiveness (<xref rid="B112" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>), and regions with better economic development have a higher degree of agglomeration (<xref rid="B113" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>, <xref rid="B114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>). The spatial agglomeration effect of regions with stronger competitiveness should be leveraged to enhance their radiation and driving effect on regions with weaker competitiveness (<xref rid="B115" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>, <xref rid="B116" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>). The trend of spatial clustering suggests that in the future, efforts can be made to establish regional centers of excellence in veterinary science, promoting technical exchange and collaborative innovation in professional fields (<xref rid="B117" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>). In addition, cooperation among different regions should be encouraged, as best practices and resource aggregation can help alleviate spatial disparities (<xref rid="B118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>, <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>), and enhance the overall competitiveness of veterinary talents.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>5 Conclusion</title><p>Improving the quantity and quality of veterinary talent cultivation is an urgent issue to address in current veterinary education and is key to enhancing veterinary talent competitiveness. Introducing scientific analytical methods for studying veterinary talent competitiveness provides a new perspective for veterinary education. This study develops a veterinary talent competitiveness evaluation index based on the characteristics of veterinary talent. It proposes a visual method to analyze the level and spatiotemporal evolution of veterinary talent competitiveness using the Entropy method and ArcGIS tools, with Western China as a case study. The results show that this method not only evaluates the current state of veterinary talent competitiveness but also considers temporal and spatial evolution, achieving good evaluation effectiveness and high accuracy, thereby guiding the improvement of veterinary education and talent cultivation.</p><p>This study proposes a scientific method for evaluating the level and spatiotemporal evolution of talent competitiveness in the veterinary industry, providing new ideas and methods for quantitative research and visual display of the competitiveness, expanding the field of veterinary research, and promoting interdisciplinary research in veterinary science, economics, and geography. It has theoretical significance and methodological contributions. In addition, this study helps to accurately grasp the demand for veterinary talents, assist governments and educational institutions in adjusting veterinary education plans and strategies, ensure that education content and direction are synchronized with industry demand, cultivate talents that meet market demand, further optimize and improve education quality, and achieve a virtuous cycle between veterinary education and industry development, which has practical significance.</p><p>However, as various factors influence industrial talent competitiveness, we plan to incorporate more elements affecting veterinary talent competitiveness in the future to optimize the evaluation index continuously. Meanwhile, continuous monitoring of the spatial and temporal evolution of veterinary talent competitiveness is essential for understanding and responding to the constantly changing demands of the veterinary industry. In addition, we will introduce machine learning algorithms and more econometric models to evaluate and predict veterinary talent competitiveness, promoting the improvement of veterinary education and veterinary talent cultivation quality.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/supplementary material, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding authors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s7"><title>Author contributions</title><p>XX: Methodology, Writing &#8211; original draft, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. MA: Data curation, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. YJ: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. AM: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. MD: Data curation, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s9"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>General Office of the State Council</collab></person-group>. <source>Opinions on Promoting the High-quality Development of Animal Husbandry</source>. (<year>2020</year>). Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.gov.cn/zhengce/content/2020-09/27/content_5547612.htm" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.gov.cn/zhengce/content/2020-09/27/content_5547612.htm</ext-link> (accessed April 2, 2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Satpati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar Sharma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Livelihood options and livelihood security among tribal in South Western Plateau and Highland Region in West Bengal</article-title>. <source>J Land Rural Stud.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>119</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>39</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2321024920967844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonnaud</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fortan&#233;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Being a vet: the veterinary profession in social science research</article-title>. <source>Rev Agric Food Environ Stud.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>102</volume>:<fpage>125</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>49</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s41130-020-00103-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palacios-D&#237;az M D</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mendoza-Grim&#243;n</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Environment in veterinary education</article-title>. <source>Veter Sci</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>146</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vetsci10020146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36851450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9964437</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Irfan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of the impact of livestock structure on carbon emissions of animal husbandry: a sustainable way to improving public health and green environment</article-title>. <source>Front Public Health.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2022.835210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35223746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8873578</pub-id><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="retraction-forward" ext-link-type="pmc" xlink:href="PMC12367640"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Exploration of modern apprenticeship talent training model for animal husbandry and veterinary medicine based on the intensive production characteristics of modern animal husbandry</article-title>. <source>Heilongjiang Animal Husbandry Veter Med</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>141</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>155</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Embryonic role of human resource development in knowledge economy</article-title>. <source>ZENITH International J Multidisciplinary Research.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>190</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>203</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4135/9781473906891.n13</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karacay</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Talent Development for Industry 4.0. In Managing the Digital Transformation</source>. <publisher-loc>Switzerland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer International Publishing.</publisher-name> (<year>2018</year>). p. <fpage>123</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>136</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-57870-5_7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Byers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nigito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Werners-Butler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The changing face of veterinary professionalism&#8212;implications for veterinary education</article-title>. <source>Educ Sci.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>182</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/educsci13020182</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matthew</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bok</surname><given-names>HGJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaney</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Read</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hodgson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rush</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Collaborative development of a shared framework for competency-based veterinary education</article-title>. <source>J Vet Med Educ.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>579</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3138/jvme.2019-0082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32530802</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaper</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Haeften</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wandall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iivanainen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Penell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Press</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Development of a shared item repository for progress testing in veterinary education</article-title>. <source>Front Veter Sci</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1296514</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1296514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38026654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10652386</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cabolis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caballero</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>J</surname></name></person-group>. <source>Talent Competitiveness and Leadership Quality. In IMD World Talent Report</source>. IMD. (<year>2017</year>). Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.imd.org/research-knowledge/economics/articles/talent-competitiveness-and-leadership-quality" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.imd.org/research-knowledge/economics/articles/talent-competitiveness-and-leadership-quality</ext-link> (accessed April 3, 2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leikuma-Rimicane</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baloran</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ceballos</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>MND</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of higher education in shaping global talent competitiveness and talent growth</article-title>. <source>Int J Inf Educ Technol.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1211</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18178/ijiet.2022.12.11.1741</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessment and evaluation of national human resource development system competitiveness in emerging countries</article-title>. <source>Asia Pacific Educ Rev.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>477</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12564-015-9390-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Guangdong Province's scientific and technological talent competitiveness evaluation and improvement strategy</article-title>. <source>Res Sci Technol Manag.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>134</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Research on the evaluation of the competitiveness of scientific and technological talents in Hebei province</article-title>. <source>J Hebei Univ Econ Business.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>82</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Innovation ecosystems and national talent competitiveness: A country-based comparison using fsQCA</article-title>. <source>Technol Forecast Soc Change.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>194</volume>:<fpage>122733</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.techfore.2023.122733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanvin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The Global Talent Competitiveness Index 2022: The Tectonics of Talent: Is the World Drifting Towards Increased Talent Inequalities?</article-title> In: <source>The Routledge Companion to Talent Management INSEAD.</source> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Serban</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andanut</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Talent competitiveness and competitiveness through talent</article-title>. <source>Procedia Econ Finance.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>506</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2212-5671(14)00831-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buracas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Navickas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Criteria of global talent competitiveness: cases of Turkey &amp; Lithuania</article-title>. <source>J Knowl Econ Knowl Manag.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naqvi</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of India and China based on global talent competitiveness index</article-title>. In: <source>2nd International Conference on Latest Innovations in Science, Engineering, and Management.</source> (<year>2016</year>). p. <fpage>230</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>238</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunicica</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of moldova's talent competitiveness index based on the global talent competitiveness index model</article-title>. <source>Annals - Econ Series.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>238</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Talent competitiveness of countries along the &#8220;Belt and Road&#8221;: rankings, characteristics and enlightenments</article-title>. <source>J Higher Educ Manag.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative study on talent competitiveness between China and the US: based on global talent competitiveness index</article-title>. <source>Global Sci Technol Econ Outlook.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuznetsova</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Competitiveness of Ukrainian talents in world ratings</article-title>. <source>Socio-Econ Probl Modern Period Ukraine.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.36818/2071-4653-2022-1-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Study on evaluation of development level for innovation talents of science and technology in Hubei province based on AHP-GRA</article-title>. <source>Mathem Pract Theory.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>118</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Si</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Establishment and example calculation of Shandong Provincial talent competitiveness evaluation system</article-title>. <source>Stat Decis-Making.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>100</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation and research on talent competitiveness in Northern Jiangsu -Investigation based on the county and districts under the jurisdiction of Huai'an City</article-title>. <source>J Huaiyin Inst Technol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>78</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The time series' fluctuation and regional difference of the competitiveness of talents in China</article-title>. <source>J Henan Univ Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11431-020-1652-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibidunni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osibanjo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adeniji</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salau</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falola</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Talent retention and organizational performance: a competitive positioning in nigerian banking sector</article-title>. <source>Period Polytechn Soc Manag Sci</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3311/PPso.7958</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pantouvakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karakasnaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The human talent and its role in ISM Code effectiveness and competitiveness in the shipping industry</article-title>. <source>Maritime Policy Manag.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>649</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03088839.2018.1454989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Research on the conditions and countermeasures for enhancing the talent competitiveness of chip industry in Shenzhen</article-title>. <source>Special Zone Econ.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>365</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arshad</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Talent competitiveness evaluation of the chongqing intelligent industry based on using the entropy TOPSIS method</article-title>. <source>Information.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>288</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/info12080288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>T</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>J</surname></name></person-group>. <article-title>Enhancing the competitiveness of innovative technological talents in manufacturing industry: taking Liaoning province as an example</article-title>. <source>J Shenyang Univ</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>653</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>659</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>On urban competitiveness of talents in science and technology based on ahp - with Bejjing, Tianjin, Shanghai and Chongqing as examples</article-title>. <source>J Univ Sci Technol Beijing.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>109</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of regional scientific and technological talent competitiveness in China during 2016-2018</article-title>. <source>Sci Technol Manag Res.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of agricultural science and technology talents competitiveness based on analytic hierarchy process</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of the 2022 International Conference on Computer Science, Information Engineering and Digital Economy (CSIEDE 2022).</source> (<year>2022</year>). p. <fpage>204</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>212</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2991/978-94-6463-108-1_23</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farshidi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmadi</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadeghi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Modeling and prediction of land use land cover change dynamics based on spatio-temporal analysis of optical and radar time series of remotely sensed images</article-title>. <source>Earth Sci Inform</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>2781</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2793</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12145-023-01072-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaki</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Claramunt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahmad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Merging spatio-temporal objects and business processes: land reform process case study</article-title>. <source>Appl Sci.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>12372</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/app132212372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Costantino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cracolici</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piacentino</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A new spatial shift-share decomposition: an application to tourism competitiveness in Italian Regions</article-title>. <source>Geogr Anal.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/gean.12262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jurkus</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taminskas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Povilanskas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kontautiene</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baltranaite</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dailide</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Delivering tourism sustainability and competitiveness in seaside and marine resorts with gis</article-title>. <source>J Mar Sci Eng</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>312</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jmse9030312</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Claramunt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Knowledge-driven spatial competitive intelligence for tourism</article-title>. <source>Trans GIS.</source> (<year>2024</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>535</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tgis.13145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Somenahalli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scrafton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation and analysis of urban logistics competitiveness and spatial evolution</article-title>. <source>Int J Logist Res Applic.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>493</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>507</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13675567.2019.1703916</pub-id>34984807
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Encarnacion</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magnaye</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>AGM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Spatial analysis of local competitiveness: relationship of economic dynamism of cities and municipalities in major regional metropolitan areas in the Philippines</article-title>. <source>Sustainability.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>15020950</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su15020950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Komasi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zolfani</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of the social-cultural competitiveness of cities based on sustainable development approach</article-title>. <source>Dec Mak.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>583</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>602</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.31181/dmame06012023k</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Komasi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zolfani</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kahvand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antuchevi&#269;iene</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#352;aparauskas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessing the environmental competitiveness of cities based on a novel MCDM approach</article-title>. <source>J Competitiveness.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>29</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7441/joc.2023.02.07</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Constantin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sacala</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pi</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>stalu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patarlageanu</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munteanu</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Vegetable trade flows and chain competitiveness linkage analysis based on spatial panel econometric modelling and porter's diamond model</article-title>. <source>Agronomy.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>12020411</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/agronomy12020411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#246;bius</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Althammer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sustainable competitiveness : a spatial econometric analysis of European regions European regions</article-title>. <source>J Environ Plan Manag.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>453</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09640568.2019.1593005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Montoya</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Escobar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galindo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of road intervention based on geographical accessibility as a development tool in regional competitiveness</article-title>. <source>J Urban Reg Anal.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>359</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>75</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.37043/JURA.2021.13.2.9</pub-id>27409075
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Musikhin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karpik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Use of GIS technology and cellular automata for modeling multiple socio-economic scenarios of regional spatial development and inter-regional cooperation</article-title>. <source>Geo-Spatial Inform Sci.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10095020.2023.2182237</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tousi</surname><given-names>S N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Clustering policy for urban competitiveness: one-size-fits-all? Evidence from tehran regional</article-title>. <source>Sci Policy Pract.</source> (<year>2024</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/rsp3.12699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lubinga M</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ngqangweni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van der Walt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Potelwa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyhodo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phaleng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Geographical indications in the wine industry: does it matter for South Africa?</article-title><source>Int J Wine Business Res.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/IJWBR-06-2019-0041</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varga</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sustainable international competitiveness of regional construction industry: spatiotemporal evolution and influential factor analysis in China</article-title>. <source>J Clean Prod.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>337</volume>:<fpage>130592</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2022.130592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asrol</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warid</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Redi</surname><given-names>AANP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prasetyo</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>A</surname></name></person-group>. <article-title>framework for GIS-Based sustainability assessment for palm oil industry: an overview</article-title>. <source>AIP Conf Proc.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>2594</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/5.0109243</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Study on the competitiveness and regional layout of the tea industry in Sichuan Province</article-title>. In: <source>Economic Management and Big Data Application: Proceedings of the 3rd International Conference, World Scientific.</source> (<year>2024</year>). p. <fpage>98</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>104</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1142/9789811270277_0009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Algeri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forgione A</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mucciardi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Spatial dependence in small cooperative bank risk behavior and its effects on bank competitiveness and SMEs</article-title>. <source>Appl Stochastic Models Bus Ind.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>1080</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/asmb.2637</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grechnikov</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khaimovich</surname><given-names>IN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Simulation and data analysis of competitiveness of industrial enterprises</article-title>. In: <source>2024 X International Conference on Information Technology and Nanotechnology (ITNT).</source> (<year>2024</year>). p. <fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ITNT60778.2024.10582285</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National Bureau of Statistics</collab></person-group>. <source>China Statistical Yearbook</source>. (<year>2024</year>). Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.stats.gov.cn/sj/ndsj" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.stats.gov.cn/sj/ndsj</ext-link> (accessed October 24, 2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>China Animal Husbandry and Veterinary Yearbook Editorial Committee</collab></person-group>. <source>China Animal Husbandry and Veterinary Yearbook</source>. (<year>2024</year>). Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://navi.cnki.net/knavi/yearbooks/YZGXM/detail?uniplatform=NZKPT" ext-link-type="uri">https://navi.cnki.net/knavi/yearbooks/YZGXM/detail?uniplatform=NZKPT</ext-link> (accessed October 24, 2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Department Department of Rural Socio-economic Survey National National Bureau of Statistics</collab></person-group>. <source>China Rural Statistical Yearbook</source>. (<year>2024</year>). Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://navi.cnki.net/knavi/yearbooks/YMCTJ/detail?uniplatform=NZKPT" ext-link-type="uri">https://navi.cnki.net/knavi/yearbooks/YMCTJ/detail?uniplatform=NZKPT</ext-link> (accessed October 24, 2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Department Department of Social Science and Technology and Cultural Statistics National National Bureau of Statistics Department Department of Strategy and Planning Ministry Ministry of Science and Technology</collab></person-group>. <source>China Statistical Yearbook on Science and Technology</source>. (<year>2024</year>). Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://navi.cnki.net/knavi/yearbooks/YBVCX/detail?uniplatform=NZKPT" ext-link-type="uri">https://navi.cnki.net/knavi/yearbooks/YBVCX/detail?uniplatform=NZKPT</ext-link> (accessed October 24, 2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Ministry of Education of the People's Republic of China</collab></person-group>. <source>National Education Fund Implementation Statistics Announcement</source>. (<year>2023</year>). Available at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.moe.gov.cn/jyb_xxgk/xxgk/neirong/tongji/jytj_jftjgg" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.moe.gov.cn/jyb_xxgk/xxgk/neirong/tongji/jytj_jftjgg</ext-link> (accessed October 24, 2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henriksen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stambulova</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roessler K</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Successful talent development in track and field: Considering the role of environment</article-title>. <source>Scandinavian J Med Sci Sports.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>122</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0838.2010.01187.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20840570</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petroni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Venturini</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verbano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Open innovation and new issues in R&amp;D organization and personnel management</article-title>. <source>Int J Hum Resour Manag.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>147</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09585192.2011.561250</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elarabi</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of human resources management on healthcare quality</article-title>. <source>Asian J Manag Sci Educ.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kravariti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Talent management: a critical literature review and research agenda for public sector human resource management</article-title>. <source>Public Manag Rev.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14719037.2019.1638439</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kesenne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Revenue sharing and absolute league quality; talent investment and talent allocation</article-title>. <source>Scott J Polit Econ.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>62</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/sjpe.12062</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The construction and training path of China's enterprise science and technology innovation talent team</article-title>. <source>Fujian Forum.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>85</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ganaie</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Talent management and value creation: a conceptual framework</article-title>. <source>Acad Strat Manag J</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.35644590
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marconi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Education as a long-term investment: the decisive role of age in the education-growth relationship</article-title>. <source>Kyklos</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>71</volume>:<fpage>132</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>161</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/kykl.12165</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zagade</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Brain drain or brain circulation: A study of returnee professionals in India</article-title>. <source>J Commerce Manag Thought.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>422</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5958/0976-478X.2017.00025.8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tlaiss</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Exploring talent management in practice: an Arab country-specific empirical investigation</article-title>. <source>Employee Relat.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/ER-10-2019-0411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Markaryan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mezinova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Human capital competitiveness management as a resource for sustainable development</article-title>. <source>E3S Web Conf.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>371</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/e3sconf/202337105028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Latukha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soyiri</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Determinants of Talent Mobility in Africa: Talent Attraction and Retention Practices in Ghana</source>. St. Petersburg University. (<year>2018</year>). p. 5.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Useche</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Competitiveness, economic growth and human development in Latin American and Caribbean countries 2006-2015: a performance and correlation analysis</article-title>. <source>Competit Rev.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>139</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1108/CR-11-2017-0085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Djiraro</surname><given-names>MCL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonondo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Academic culture and talent cultivation: the Chinese experience</article-title>. <source>J Compar Int Higher Educ.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>133</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32674/jcihe.v13i1.3133</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><label>77.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kov&#225;cs</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Talent competitiveness of Hungary&#8212;Decline without &#8220;Fleurs du Mal</article-title>.&#8221; <italic toggle="yes">Soc Economy</italic>. (<year>2016</year>) 38: 537&#8211;558. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1556/204.2016.38.4.6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><label>78.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukhametzyanov</surname><given-names>IZ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Specific character of objective methods for determining weights of criteria in MCDM problems: entropy, CRITIC, SD</article-title>. <source>Decis Mak.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>105</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.31181/dmame210402076i</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><label>79.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alfaro-C&#243;rdoba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hidalgo</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alfaro</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Aridity trends in central america: a spatial correlation analysis</article-title>. <source>Atmosphere.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/atmos11040427</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><label>80.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Spatial autocorrelation analysis of &#8220;Internet + agriculture&#8221; public concern based on Baidu Index</article-title>. <source>Chinese J Agric Resour Reg Plan</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>325</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>330</lpage>.38721539
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><label>81.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Builes-Jaramillo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lotero</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Closeness matters. Spatial autocorrelation and relationship between socioeconomic indices and distance to departmental Colombian capitals</article-title>. <source>Soc Econ Plan Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>100662</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.seps.2018.10.013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><label>82.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evolution in the spatio-temporal pattern on animal husbandry green development competitiveness in China</article-title>. <source>J Agric Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><label>83.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The evolution of spatial-temporal pattern of the regional agriculture competitiveness in Gansu Province</article-title>. <source>Res Agric Modern.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>238</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><label>84.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of comprehensive competitiveness to high level agricultural science and technology talents in China</article-title>. <source>Anhui Agric Sci.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><label>85.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Research on the training model of high-skill talent under the background of industrial upgrading in China</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of the 2015 International Conference on Management Science and Management Innovation.</source> (<year>2015</year>). p. <fpage>376</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>381</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2991/msmi-15.2015.69</pub-id>32175718
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><label>86.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rozman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tominc</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strukelj</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Competitiveness through development of strategic talent management and agile management ecosystems</article-title>. <source>Global J Flexible Syst Manag.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>373</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40171-023-00344-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><label>87.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kofler</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Innerhofer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marcher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pechlaner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>The Future of High-Skilled Workers: Regional Problems and Global Challenges</source>. <publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer Nature.</publisher-name> (<year>2020</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-42871-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B88"><label>88.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arifin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Talent management-based training planning to produce high-performing human resources</article-title>. <source>J Ilmiah Ilmu Admin Publik.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>303</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26858/jiap.v13i1.47154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B89"><label>89.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolachina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sumanth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Godavarthi</surname><given-names>VRC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rayapudi</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajest</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jalil</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of talent management to accomplish its principal purpose in human resource management</article-title>. In: <source>Data-Driven Intelligent Business Sustainability</source>. IGI Global (<year>2024</year>). p. <fpage>274</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>292</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4018/979-8-3693-0049-7.ch019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B90"><label>90.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mykhaylichenko</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hridin</surname><given-names>OV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vitkovskyi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hryschenko</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reznik</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Improvement of the personnel management system in the process of employment as a factor of increasing the competitiveness of enterprises</article-title>. In: <source>AlP Conference Proceedings.</source> (<year>2022</year>). p. 040004. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/5.0091674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B91"><label>91.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Recruiting and retaining a diverse veterinary team</article-title>. <source>Veter Clin North Am Small Animal Pract.</source> (<year>2024</year>) <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>785</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cvsm.2024.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39003172</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B92"><label>92.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quigley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenna</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Best practices for recruitment in veterinary clinical trials</article-title>. <source>Front Veter Sci.</source> (<year>2024</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1418747</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2024.1418747</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39086763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11288851</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B93"><label>93.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zapsha</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sedov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Training of highly qualified personnel for the agricultural sector of the economy in the conditions of modern transformations</article-title>. <source>Ukrainian J Appl Econ Technol.</source> (<year>2024</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>382</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.36887/2415-8453-2024-1-65</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B94"><label>94.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vardarlier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Gamification in human resources management: an agenda suggestion for gamification in HRM</article-title>. <source>Res J Bus Manag.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>39</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17261/Pressacademia.2021.1402</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B95"><label>95.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grecic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>How to create a much more attractive living environment for talent retaining and attracting? The Case of Serbia</article-title>. <source>Ekonomske Ideje i Praksa.</source> (<year>2024</year>) <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>29</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.54318/eip.2024.vg.372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B96"><label>96.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Piwowar-Sulej</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Human resources development as an element of sustainable HRM - with the focus on production engineers</article-title>. <source>J Clean Prod.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>278</volume>:<fpage>124008</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2020.124008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32901179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7470767</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B97"><label>97.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sustainable development levels and influence factors in rural China based on rural revitalization strategy</article-title>. <source>Sustainability.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>8908</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su14148908</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B98"><label>98.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flanagan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jewell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Competitiveness in construction: a critical review of research</article-title>. <source>Constr Manag Econ.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>989</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1000</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01446190701258039</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B99"><label>99.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koumpan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mcowen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Revolutionizing talent: the path in 21st century workforce transformation</article-title>. <source>Human Factors, Bus Manag Soc.</source> (<year>2024</year>) <volume>135</volume>:<fpage>74</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>83</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.54941/ahfe1004932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B100"><label>100.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of regional socio-economic development on spatial and temporal differences in the distribution pattern of top-tier education in China</article-title>. <source>Sustainability.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>15277</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su152115277</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B101"><label>101.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Supply and demand of higher vocational education in China: Comprehensive evaluation and geographical representation from the perspective of educational equality</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>e0293132</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0293132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37856520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10586648</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B102"><label>102.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huggins</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Uneven development, competitiveness and behavioural economic geography: addressing &#8216;levelling up'policies from a human perspective</article-title>. <source>Reg Sci Policy Pract.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>2274</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/rsp3.12714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B103"><label>103.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaliannan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darmalinggam</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorasamy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Inclusive talent development as a key talent management approach: a systematic literature review</article-title>. <source>Hum Resour Manag Rev.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>100926</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.hrmr.2022.100926</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B104"><label>104.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tijanic</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Obadic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Can we boost the competitiveness of the European union through reducing regional inequalities in human capital</article-title>. <source>Eng Econ.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>295</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>305</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5755/j01.ee.26.3.8029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B105"><label>105.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Komazec</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vuksan</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>New technologies generate need for a new organizational practice</article-title>. <source>Acta Technica Corvininesis - Bull Eng.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>59</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>67</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B106"><label>106.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira-Oliveira A</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paiva</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rauch M</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Talent engagement and attraction: strategic involvement of Heis in regional innovation ecosystems</article-title>. In: <source>9th International Conference on Future of Education CL-Florence, Italy</source>. (<year>2019</year>). p. <fpage>751</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>755</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B107"><label>107.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Phuong T</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Talent development for faculty: the case of Vietnam</article-title>. <source>Adv Dev Hum Resour.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>428</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1523422318803086</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B108"><label>108.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>ZL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The problems, needs and strategies of rural teacher development at deep poverty areas in China: Rural schooling stakeholder perspectives</article-title>. <source>Int J Educ Res.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>101496</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijer.2019.101496</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B109"><label>109.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nurhayati</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Policy Effectiveness Program for Improving Education Equality through the Development of Education Facilities and Infrastructure</article-title>. <source>J Educ Rev Provision.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.55885/jerp.v1i1.31</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B110"><label>110.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The cultivation of veterinary professionals in the context of pet economy</article-title>. <source>Chinese J Veter Med</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>134</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>136</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B111"><label>111.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Understanding regional talent attraction and its influencing factors in China: From the perspective of spatiotemporal pattern evolution</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>e0234856</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0234856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32555616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7302713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B112"><label>112.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation and spatial agglomeration analysis of the green competitiveness of China's manufacturing industry at the provincial level</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>e0246351</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0246351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33784316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8009360</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B113"><label>113.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Population agglomeration in Chinese cities: is it benefit or damage for the quality of economic development?</article-title><source>Environ Sci Pollut Res.</source> (<year>2024</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>10106</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-023-25220-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36680716</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B114"><label>114.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Towards sustainability: the impact of industrial synergistic agglomeration on the efficiency of regional green development</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollution Res</source>. (<year>2023</year>). <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>85415</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>85427</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-023-28449-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37391560</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B115"><label>115.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elahi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of high-tech manufacturing co-agglomeration and producer service industry on regional innovation efficiency</article-title>. <source>Front Environ Sci.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>942057</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fenvs.2022.942057</pub-id>37507566
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B116"><label>116.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The spatial spillover impact and transmission mechanisms of logistics agglomeration on eco-efficiency: a case study in China</article-title>. <source>Energy.</source> (<year>2024</year>) <volume>308</volume>:<fpage>132826</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.energy.2024.132826</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B117"><label>117.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leckel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Veilleux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dana</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Local Open Innovation: a means for public policy to increase collaboration for innovation in SMEs</article-title>. <source>Technol Forecast Soc Change.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>153</volume>:<fpage>119891</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.techfore.2019.119891</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B118"><label>118.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Todes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turok</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Spatial inequalities and policies in South Africa: place-based or people-centred?</article-title><source>Progr Planning.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>123</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.progress.2017.03.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B119"><label>119.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Collaborative innovation efficiency: from within cities to between cities - Empirical analysis based on innovative cities in China</article-title>. <source>Growth Change.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>1330</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/grow.12504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>