<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11039921</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11039921.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11039921</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11039921</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38659454</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2024.1367843</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">Salvia sclarea</italic> L. extract on growth performance, antioxidant capacity, and immune function in lambs</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaoling</given-names></name><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2348628/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yujie</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nan</surname><given-names initials="S">Shanshan</given-names></name><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1883387/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="W">Wenju</given-names></name><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2025265/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff><institution>College of Animal Science and Technology, Shihezi University</institution>, <addr-line>Shihezi</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0001"><p>Edited by: Xianwen Dong, Chongqing Academy of Animal Science, China</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0002"><p>Reviewed by: Adham Al-Sagheer, Zagazig University, Egypt</p><p>Maria Giovanna Ciliberti, University of Foggia, Italy</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Wenju Zhang, <email>zhangwj1022@sina.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">454084</issue-id><elocation-id>1367843</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>01</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>24</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-04-25 17:25:12.770"><day>25</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2024 Ma, Niu, Nan and Zhang.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Ma, Niu, Nan and Zhang</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-11-1367843.pdf"/><abstract><p>The aim of this experiment is to explore the effects of <italic toggle="yes">salvia sclarea</italic> extract on the growth performance, apparent nutrient digestibility, antioxidant capacity, and immune function of lambs. Sixty female lambs (Chinese Merino sheep) aged 2&#8201;months and weighing 20&#8201;&#177;&#8201;2&#8201;kg were selected and randomly divided into five groups of twelve lambs in each. While the control group (CK) received only basal feed, the experimental group was supplemented with different concentrations of <italic toggle="yes">salvia sclarea</italic> extract in the basal feed at 0.04&#8201;mL/kg (group CL1), 0.08&#8201;mL/kg (group CL2), 0.12&#8201;mL/kg (group CL3), and 0.16&#8201;mL/kg (group CL4). The feeding period was 85&#8201;days, including 15&#8201;days of pre-feeding and 70&#8201;days of regular feeding. Body weight and feed intake were recorded during the test period, and blood was collected at the end of the test for the determination of immune and antioxidant indices. The results showed that the average daily gain and average daily feed intake of lambs were significantly increased in CL3 group compared to CK group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Also, the apparent nutrient digestibility of crude protein and neutral detergent fiber was significantly increased (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The Dry matter, acid detergent fiber and Ether extract were not significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05). The serum levels of superoxide dismutase, catalase, glutathione peroxidase, and antioxidant capacity were significantly higher in the CL2, CL3, and CL4 groups compared to CK group, while malondialdehyde levels were significantly lower (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The serum levels of immune globulin A, immune globulin G, immune globulin M, interferon-&#947;, and interleukin-10 were significantly higher and the levels of tumor necrosis factor-&#945; and interleukin-1&#946; were significantly lower in the CL2, CL3, and CL4 groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). In conclusion, the addition of <italic toggle="yes">salvia sclarea</italic> extract to the ration promotes growth performance and nutrient digestion in lambs. Improvement of immune response by increasing immunoglobulin and cytokine concentrations. And it enhances the antioxidant status by increasing the antioxidant enzyme activity in lambs.</p><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>This study aimed to explore the effects of <italic toggle="yes">Salvia sclarea</italic> extract on the growth performance, apparent nutrient digestibility, antioxidant capacity, and immune function of the lambs.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Methods</title><p>Sixty female lambs (Chinese Merino sheep) aged 2&#8201;months and weighing 20&#8201;&#177;&#8201;2&#8201;kg were selected and randomly divided into five groups of 12 lambs each. The control group (CK) received only basal feed, whereas the experimental group was supplemented with different concentrations of <italic toggle="yes">salvia sclarea</italic> extract in the basal feed at 0.04, 0.08, 0.12, and 0.16&#8201;mL/kg (CL1, CL2, CL3, and CL4, respectively). The feeding period was 85&#8201;days, including 15&#8201;days of pre-feeding and 70&#8201;days of regular feeding. Body weight and feed intake were recorded during the test period, and blood was collected at the end of the test to determine immune and antioxidant indices.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Results</title><p>The results showed that the average daily weight gain and feed intake of the lambs were significantly higher in the CL3 group than in the CK group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). In addition, the apparent nutrient digestibility of crude protein and neutral detergent fiber increased significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The dry matter, acid detergent fiber, and ether extract were not significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05). Serum levels of superoxide dismutase, catalase, and glutathione peroxidase and antioxidant capacity were significantly higher in the CL2, CL3, and CL4 groups than in the CK group, whereas malondialdehyde levels were significantly lower (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The serum levels of immune globulin immune globulin A, immune globulin G, immune globulin M, interferon-&#947;, and interleukin-10 were significantly higher and the levels of tumor necrosis factor-&#945; and interleukin-1&#946; were significantly lower in the CL2, CL3, and CL4 groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05).</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p>In conclusion, the addition of the <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract to the diet promoted growth performance and nutrient digestion in lambs. Immune response was improved by increasing Ig and cytokine concentrations. It enhances antioxidant status by increasing antioxidant enzyme activity in lambs.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Salvia sclarea</italic> L. extract</kwd><kwd>lambs</kwd><kwd>growth performance</kwd><kwd>immune function</kwd><kwd>antioxidant capacity</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare financial support was received for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This study was funded by the Xinjiang Uygur Autonomous Region Key Research and Development Program, &#8220;Research on Nutritional Control and Intelligent Technology for Precision Feeding of Meat Sheep in Northern Xinjiang Pastoral Areas&#8221;, Project No. 2022B02029-2.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="41"/><page-count count="8"/><word-count count="5901"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Animal Nutrition and Metabolism</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec5"><title>Introduction</title><p>Early postweaning stressors in lambs release glucocorticoids and coincide with a decrease in growth hormones, which suppress the immune system and reduce growth performance (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). A dietary change from milk to solid feed is considered a major stressor after weaning. The lack of a fully functional rumen in recently weaned ruminants reduces nutrient digestibility (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Nutritional strategies have recently emerged. It has been proposed as a key factor in improving animal health and welfare as well as increasing livestock productivity (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Dietary composition has long been recognized as an important factor in animal health, with significant effects on the acquired and innate immune systems, especially on inflammation (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). A number of compounds and products derived from plant-derived byproducts have been reported to show proinflammatory or anti-inflammatory effects and therapeutic responses and can trigger the expected response of the animal body to production parameters (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>).</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Salvia sclarea</italic> L. is a native Asian plant that is widely used in various fields including food, medicine, oils, and landscaping (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). It originated in Europe and is now primarily cultivated in France, Russia, and other countries. This plant was introduced into China in the early 1970s and cultivated in the Shaanxi and Henan provinces. In 2011, it was introduced into the Zhaosu area of Xinjiang, which has a cultivated area of approximately 1,000&#8201;ha per year. The plant produces 30&#8201;t of raw material and 60&#8201;kg of essential oil per ha (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Previous phytochemical studies have identified and isolated various bioactive compounds, including flavonoids, volatile oils, fatty acids, triterpenes, and phenolic compounds, from <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> frutescens (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Owing to these biological components, pharmacological effects have been shown, including anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, and antibacterial effects (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Previous studies have shown that dietary supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> improves meat quality without adversely affecting growth performance or carcass characteristics (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). However, few studies have investigated the effects of <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract on lambs. Based on this, this study aimed to provide valuable scientific insights and powerful references for the rational application of <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract in lamb production by adding different levels of <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract to the growth performance, apparent nutrient digestibility, serum immunity, and antioxidant indices of lambs.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec6"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>All experimental procedures were performed in strict accordance with guidelines and were reviewed and approved by the Institutional Animal Bioethics Committee of Shihezi University (Xinjiang, China).</p><sec id="sec7"><title>Experiment material</title><p>The <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract (essential oil) used in the experiment appeared to be a light-yellow liquid. It was prepared by hydrodistillation of the flowers, leaves, and stems of <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic>. The active ingredients were linalyl acetate (54.79%) and linalool (30.22%), as detected using LC&#8211;MS. The purity of the <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract was 85%. It was produced in the East Industrial Park of Zhaosu County, Xinjiang, China.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><title>Experimental design, animals, and management</title><p>Sixty female lambs (Chinese Merino sheep) aged 2&#8201;months and weighing 20&#8201;&#177;&#8201;2&#8201;kg were selected and randomly divided into five groups of 12 lambs each. The control group (CK) received basal feed alone, whereas the experimental group was supplemented with different gradients of <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract in the basal feed at 0.04, 0.08, 0.12, and 0.16&#8201;mL/kg (CL1, CL2, CL3, and CL4, respectively). The feeding period was 85&#8201;days, including 15&#8201;days of pre-feeding and 70&#8201;days of normal feeding, and the sheep were fed daily at 06:00&#8201;h and 18:00&#8201;h. <italic toggle="yes">Salvia sclarea</italic> extract was precisely and uniformly mixed with the ration in strict accordance with the experimental design additive ratios. The sheep were housed in single-cage enclosures (1.5&#8201;&#215;&#8201;1&#8201;&#215;&#8201;1&#8201;m) with free access to water, and the sheds, water troughs, and troughs were cleaned and sterilized regularly to record daily feed intake and body weight. The composition and nutritional levels of the basal rations are listed in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Composition and nutrient levels of the basal diet (DM basis, %).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ingredient</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Content</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nutrition level<xref rid="tfn2" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Content</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corn</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.2</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">ME/(MJ/Kg)</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.74</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean meal</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.9</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NaCl</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">DM</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alfalfa Hay</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.5</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDF</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Silage Corn</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.5</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADF</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Premix<xref rid="tfn1" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn1"><label>a</label><p>Premix is provided per kilogram of feed. Each kilogram of trace element premix contains 5&#8201;mg of CuSO<sub>4</sub>&#183;5H<sub>2</sub>O, 30&#8201;mg of FeSO<sub>4</sub>&#183;7H<sub>2</sub>O, 20&#8201;mg of MnSO<sub>4</sub>&#183;5H<sub>2</sub>O, 20&#8201;mg of ZnSO<sub>4</sub>&#183;7H<sub>2</sub>O, 20&#8201;mg of KI, 40&#8201;mg of Na<sub>2</sub>SeO<sub>3</sub>, and 50&#8201;mg of CoCl&#183;6H<sub>2</sub>O. VA 3000&#8201;IU, VD 400&#8201;IU, VE 90&#8201;IU.</p></fn><fn id="tfn2"><label>b</label><p>Metabolic energy is the calculated according to NRC (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), while other indicators are measured values.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec9"><title>Sample collection and measurement methods</title><sec id="sec10"><title>Growth performance</title><p>The lambs were weighed on the 1st and lower 70th days of the positive trial period and recorded as the initial body weight (IBW) and final body weight (FBW) of the test lambs, respectively, both on an empty stomach before the morning feeding. During the trial period, the amount of feed and leftovers were recorded in detail for each bureau pen per day, which was used as the basis for calculating the average daily feed intake (ADFI, ADFI&#8201;=&#8201;total feed intake/experimental days), average daily gain (ADG, ADFI&#8201;=&#8201;total feed intake/experimental days), and feed to weight ratio (F/G, F/G&#8201;=&#8201;ADFI/ADG) of the lambs.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec11"><title>Nutrient apparent digestibility</title><p>Ration and fecal samples were collected during the last 3&#8201;days of the positive trial period. Samples were collected using the partial collection method, in which the ewes in each group were placed in homemade collection bags at 09:00&#8201;h and feces were recovered at 17:00&#8201;h each day. A sample of 200&#8201;g of feces was added to 10&#8201;mL of 10% sulfuric acid for nitrogen fixation and stored at &#8722;20&#176;C for measurement. The collected grain and manure samples were placed in an oven at 65&#176;C for 48&#8201;h, weighed after 24&#8201;h of moisture return, and prepared as analytical samples by crushing through an 80 mesh sieve. The dry matter (DM), crude protein (CP), crude ash (Ash), ether extract (EE), Ca, and P contents were determined using the methods of AOAC (2010) (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). The content of neutral and acid detergent fibers (NDF and ADF, respectively) was determined according to the method described by Van Soest et al. (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). The apparent digestibility of nutrients in lambs was determined using the acid-insoluble ash (AIA) endogenous indicator method (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec12"><title>Serum biochemical and antioxidant indices</title><p>At the end of the experiment, 10&#8201;mL of blood was collected from the jugular vein of the sheep using a disposable syringe, and the serum was separated statically and stored frozen (&#8722;20&#176;C) for subsequent experiments.</p><p>Serum immunity indicators, including antibodies: immunoglobulin G (IgG), immunoglobulin A (IgA) and immunoglobulin M (IgM), cytokines: tumor necrosis factor-&#945; (TNF-&#945;), interleukin-1&#946; (IL-1&#946;), interleukin-2 (IL-2), were measured using enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) method according to the instructions of the kit, Interleukin-4 (IL-4), Interleukin-6 (IL-6), Interleukin-8 (IL-8) and Interleukin-10 (IL-10) and antioxidant indexes: total antioxidant capacity (T-AOC), superoxide dismutase (SOD), glutathione peroxidase (GSH-Px), catalase (CAT), and malondialdehyde (MDA). The kits were purchased from Nanjing Jianjian Bioengineering Institute. Each sample was tested using an enzyme-labeling analyzer to detect the corresponding absorbance and a standard curve was established according to the manufacturer&#8217;s instructions to determine the concentration of the target factor.</p></sec><sec id="sec13"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All data were analyzed using one-way ANOVA, linear analysis, and quadratic correlation using the SPSS software (version 22.0; SPSS, Inc., Chicago, IL, United States). Duncan&#8217;s method was used for multiple comparisons, and the experimental data were expressed as the mean and standard error of the mean (SEM). <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05 indicated a significant difference, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01 indicated highly significant difference, and 0.05&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.10 indicated a trend.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec14"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec15"><title>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">salvia sclarea</italic> extract on the growth performance of lambs</title><p>No significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05) was observed in the initial weight of lambs in each group. The final weight of lambs in the CL4 group was significantly higher than that in the CK group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05), and there was no significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05) among the CL2, CL3, and CL4 groups. Compared to the CK group, the ADG and ADFI of lambs in the CL3 and CL4 groups supplemented with <italic toggle="yes">Salvia sclarea</italic> extract were significantly higher, and the F/G was significantly lower (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The ADG of CL1, CL2, CL3, and CL4 increased by 7.97, 16.56, 23.31, and 34.35%, respectively, compared to that of the CK group (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">salvia sclarea</italic> extract on the growth performance of lambs.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Items</th><th align="center" valign="middle" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Treatment</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">SEM</th><th align="center" valign="middle" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK Group</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CL1 Group</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CL2 Group</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CL3 Group</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CL4 Group</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treat</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linear</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quadratic</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial weight/kg</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.80</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.70</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.90</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.80</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.40</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.938</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.661</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.819</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Final weight/kg</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.20<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.05<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.29<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.94<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.78<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.471</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADG/(g/d)</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">163.00<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">176.00<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">190.00<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">201.00<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">219.00<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.71</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADFI/(kg/d)</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.068</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F/G</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.79<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.44<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.10<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.96<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.58<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The same superscript letters in peer data indicate no significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05), while different letters indicate significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). CK, control group; CL1: 0.04&#8201;mL/kg; CL2: 0.08&#8201;mL/kg; CL3: 0.12&#8201;mL/kg; CL4: 0.16&#8201;mL/kg.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec16"><title>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">salvia sclarea</italic> extract on the apparent digestibility of lambs</title><p>The apparent digestibility of DM, ADF, and EE in the four experimental groups CL1, CL2, CL3 and CL4 with the addition of <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract was higher than that in the CK group, but the difference was not significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05). The apparent digestibility of NDF in the CL2 group was significantly higher than that in the CK group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05); however, there was no significant difference among the CL1, CL3, and CL4 groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05). The apparent digestibility of CP and NDF in the CL3 group was significantly higher than that in the CK group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05); however, there was no significant difference between the CL1 and CL3 groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05) (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">salvia sclarea</italic> extract on apparent digestibility of lambs (%).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Items</th><th align="center" valign="middle" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Treatment</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">SEM</th><th align="center" valign="middle" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK Group</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CL1 Group</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CL2 Group</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CL3 Group</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CL4 Group</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treat</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linear</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quadratic</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DM</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.80</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.72</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.23</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.80</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.39</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.610</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.814</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.423</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.20<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.05<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.29<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.94<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.78<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.048</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.313</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDF</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.34<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.83<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.97<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.84<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.81<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.102</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.241</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADF</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.27</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.42</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.13</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.49</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.67</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.647</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.428</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.460</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EE</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.79</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.36</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.63</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.96</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.58</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.717</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.836</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.517</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>DM, dry matter; CP, crude protein; NDF, neutral detergent fibre; ADF, acid detergent fibre; EE, ether extract; CK, control group; CL1: 0.04&#8201;mL/kg; CL2: 0.08&#8201;mL/kg; CL3: 0.12&#8201;mL/kg; CL4: 0.16&#8201;mL/kg.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec17"><title>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">salvia sclarea</italic> extract on serum antioxidant indices in lambs</title><p>Compared with the CK group, the levels of SOD, CAT, GSH-Px, and T-AOC in the serum of lambs in the CL2, CL3, and CL4 groups treated with <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract were significantly higher, whereas the MDA content was significantly lower (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Moreover, with an increase in the amount of <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract, the content of SOD, CAT, GSH-Px, and T-AOC in the four experimental groups first increased and then decreased, whereas the MDA content showed the opposite trend. The CL1 group with 0.04&#8201;mL/kg <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract had significantly higher CAT and GSH-Px content than the CK group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05), whereas the content of MDA, SOD, and T-AOC was not significantly affected (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05). The SOD content was significantly higher (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) in the CL3 group with the addition of 0.12&#8201;mL/kg <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract than in the other four groups (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">salvia sclarea</italic> extract on serum antioxidant indexes in lambs. <bold>(A)</bold> SOD; <bold>(B)</bold> CAT; <bold>(C)</bold> GSH-Px; <bold>(D)</bold> MDA; <bold>(E)</bold> T-AOC, CK, control group; CL1: 0.04&#8201;mL/kg; CL2: 0.08&#8201;mL/kg; CL3: 0.12&#8201;mL/kg; CL4: 0.16&#8201;mL/kg. Lower case letters in each bar chart indicate significant difference, the same letter indicates no significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05), and different lower case letters indicate significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-11-1367843-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec18"><title>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">salvia sclarea</italic> extract on serum immunity indices in lambs</title><p>Compared with the CK group, the content of IgA, IgG, IgM, IFN-&#947;, and IL-10 in the serum of lambs in the CL2, CL3, and CL4 groups was significantly higher (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05); that of TNF-&#945;, and IL-1&#946; was significantly lower (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05); and that of IL-2 and IL-6 showed no significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05). The IL-4 content decreased in the test groups CL1, CL2, CL3, and CL4 with the addition of <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract; however, the difference between the CL2 and CK groups was significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05), whereas the rest were not significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05). The content of IgA, IgG, IgM, IFN-&#947;, and IL-10 in the serum of lambs in the CL3 group was higher than that in the other three test groups (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">salvia sclarea</italic> extract on serum immunity indexes in lambs. <bold>(A)</bold> IgA; <bold>(B)</bold> IgG; <bold>(C)</bold> IgM; <bold>(D)</bold> TNF-&#945;; <bold>(E)</bold> IFN-&#947;; <bold>(F)</bold> IL-1&#946;; <bold>(G)</bold> IL-2; <bold>(H)</bold> IL-4; <bold>(I)</bold> IL-6; <bold>(J)</bold> IL-10, CK, control group; CL1: 0.04&#8201;mL/kg; CL2: 0.08&#8201;mL/kg; CL3: 0.12&#8201;mL/kg; CL4: 0.16&#8201;mL/kg. Lower case letters in each bar chart indicate significant difference, the same letter indicates no significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05), and different lower case letters indicate significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-11-1367843-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec19"><title>Discussion</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Salvia sclarea</italic> has long been grown in China as a medicinal and food plant, and has attracted attention for its unique active substances (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Studies have shown that the aromatic <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> is rich in phenolic acids (caffeic and rosemarinic acids), flavonoids, and volatiles (monoterpenes and sesquiterpenes) (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), among other active ingredients that enhance the immunity and antioxidant capacity of the animal and promote its growth and development (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). In this study, we found that the addition of <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> frutescens extract to lamb rations had a positive effect on the growth performance of lambs by improving feed conversion efficiency and optimizing the nutrient utilization. Moreover, the feed intake of lambs increased with an increase in <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract addition, and the feed intake significantly increased by 10.24% when the addition reached 0.12&#8201;mL/kg. This indicates that the unique aromatic odor due to the richness of terpenes, alkenes, and aromatic compounds improved the palatability of the feed and induced appetite in the lambs (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Feed palatability can effectively increase the feed intake of lambs, increase their dietary intake, and improve their daily weight gain and feed utilization. Another study showed that phenolics in <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extracts could increase the activity of digestive enzymes by entering the intestinal tract (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). This reduces the number of harmful bacteria in the intestinal tract including <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Beneficial bacteria colonize the intestine, consume free oxygen, create a low-oxygen environment, and inhibit the growth of harmful aerobic bacteria and spoilage microorganisms. The joint action of the two reduces harmful bacteria on the consumption of nutrients to promote growth (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p><p>The maintenance of good production performance in animals is closely related to the digestion and metabolism of various nutrients in the body. Increasing nutrient digestibility can promote the absorption of nutrients such as DM and CP, thus promoting growth performance to a certain extent. The test group of lambs fed the <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract had a higher apparent digestibility of CP and NDF than the CK group. No differences in the apparent digestibility of DM, EE, or NDF were found between the diets. In the present study, the concentrations of ingredients in the experimental TMR diet were similar. Therefore, these differences were attributed to the incorporation of the <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract. There were some differences in the chemical compositions and bioactivities of the diets. The variable response of apparent digestibility in the diet treatment groups may be partly due to the higher CP of these lambs, as these factors positively influenced the degree of digestibility of the rations (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>).</p><p>A positive correlation between oxidative stress and disease has been widely documented in animals. Antioxidant capacity reflects the body&#8217;s ability to scavenge free radicals accumulated in cells and tissues and protect the structure and function of cell membranes from damage by peroxides (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). MDA is a product of the lipid peroxidation reaction, and its content reflects the degree of lipid peroxidation in the body, which in turn reflects the degree of cellular attack by free radicals. The results of our study showed that the addition of <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract to the ration increased serum CAT, SOD, GSH-Px activity, and T-AOC and decreased serum MDA content in lambs, with the best effect in the 0.12&#8201;mL/kg addition group. This indicated that the <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract improved the performance and health of lambs by effectively reducing oxidative stress. Similar to the results of Deng et al. (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), the addition of <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> to the diet of lambs significantly increased T-AOC activity and MDA content in the liver and improved the oxidative status of muscle and meat quality.</p><p>Li et al. (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) found that the dietary addition of <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract increased serum SOD activity and decreased MDA content in the liver, spleen, and jejunal mucosa of piglets. The <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract used in this study is rich in phenolic acids, flavonoids, and other bioactive components. Phenolic acids can combine with peroxyl radicals to reduce or eliminate free radicals. Phenolic hydroxyl groups can chelate transition metal ions to block biological oxidation (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Terpenoids can increase the activity of antioxidant enzymes in animals and thus exert their antioxidant capacity (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Flavonoids such as lignans, rosmarinic acid, and apigenin have powerful antioxidant properties (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Based on this, we hypothesized that <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract enhances serum CAT, SOD, and GSH-Px activities in lambs by competitively scavenging reactive oxygen species. Therefore, it has great potential as an antioxidant to prevent oxidative damage during livestock production.</p><p>Immunoglobulins are humoral immune effector molecules that play an important role in the immune system of young animals, and serum immunoglobulin levels can be used to evaluate the health status of an organism (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). IgA, IgM, and IgG, play a major role in the immune response. As a class of immunologically active molecules, they specifically bind to antigens and remove them via sedimentation and phagocytosis (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). They mediate immune and inflammatory responses when an animal is infested with bacteria and viruses and play an important role in the body&#8217;s immune response and immunoregulation (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). In this study, the <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract affected the immune response in lambs by inducing IgG and IgM production. These responses protect lambs from pathogenic and nonpathogenic immune attacks. Linoleic and linolenic acids are &#8220;essential fatty acids&#8221; converted into eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) and docosahexaenoic acid (DHA). Most studies have shown that EPA and DHA can clinically attenuate T cell immune-mediated inflammatory diseases. And &#945;-linolenic acid enhances the immunity of the body (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Previous studies demonstrated that essential fatty acids exert anti-inflammatory effects. When the animal body suffers from acute or chronic inflammation, as well as infection, it inhibits the production of prostaglandin 2 by secreting inflammatory factors and plays a role in regulating immune function (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Liu et al. injected different doses of linolenic acid into the duodenum of dairy cows through a fistula and found that serum IgG levels increased significantly and prostaglandin 2 levels decreased in the 200&#8201;g/day dose group (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Moreover, <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract contains phenolics that increase leukocyte phagocytosis and can increase the release of IgA, IgM, and IgG. Regulating the expression of cytokines and increasing the expression of antibodies in the serum enhances the ability of the body to clear pathogens, thus strengthening its immune function (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>).</p><p>As important components of cellular immunity, cytokines are critical for lymphocyte development and the subsequent functional activity of the peripheral immune system (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Cytokines are produced by immune and non-immune cells and can be categorized into proinflammatory cytokines produced by a variety of immune cells (such as IL-1&#946;, IL-6, and TNF-&#945;) and anti-inflammatory cytokines (such as IL-4, IL-10) (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Among them, IL-1&#946; can induce cells to secrete inflammatory factors and inflammatory transmitters, triggering the body&#8217;s inflammatory response (<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). IL-6 promotes immune cell differentiation and enhances their functional activity. IL-1&#946; secretes IL-2 via T cells, whereas IL-6 induces IL-2 production by activating the NF-&#954;B signaling pathway through signal transduction. IL-2 is a core substance in the immunoregulatory network of the body, reflecting the initiation of the immune response and playing an important regulatory role in both cellular and humoral immunity (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). IL-10 is an important anti-inflammatory factor secreted by Tregs and is regulated by the immunomodulatory factor IL-4, which can be used to determine the level of immunity in lambs (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). In this study, the addition of <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract to the ration decreased the levels of proinflammatory cytokines IL-1&#946; and TNF-&#945; and increased the serum anti-inflammatory cytokine IL-10, thereby modulating the immune response. Lignans, a constituent of <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract, inhibited the production of TNF-&#945; in mouse serum (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). Moreover, linolenic acid, an anti-inflammatory agent in a mouse model of colonic inflammation, had a protective effect against TNBS-induced colitis through the Th1/Th2/Th17 pathway with inflammation-reducing efficacy (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). In addition, a previous study demonstrated that dietary supplementation with phenolic compounds inhibited LPS-induced expression of proinflammatory cytokines IL-1&#946; and IFN-&#947; through NF-&#954;B and MAPK signaling pathways (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). These results demonstrate the potential of <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extracts to reduce the infection load and inflammatory responses <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec20"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, the addition of 0.12&#8201;mL/kg <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract to the diet improves the growth performance of lambs by increasing feed intake and nutrient digestibility. It also improves the health status of lambs by increasing their serum antioxidant capacity and immune function. <italic toggle="yes">S. sclarea</italic> extract has great potential as a feed additive in livestock production. It is also worth exploring its potential use in various animal production environments.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec21"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/supplementary material, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="sec22"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The animal studies were approved by the Institutional Animal Bioethics Committee of Shihezi University. The studies were conducted in accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements. Written informed consent was obtained from the owners for the participation of their animals in this study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="sec23"><title>Author contributions</title><p>XM: Writing &#8211; original draft. YN: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. SN: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. WZ: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec25"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec100"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guilloteau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zabielski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammon</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Metges</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Adverse effects of nutritional programming during prenatal and early postnatal life, some aspects of regulation and potential prevention and treatments</article-title>. <source>J Physiol Pharmacol</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>60</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jso.2930140314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19996479</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of dietary Astragalus polysaccharide and Astragalus membranaceus root supplementation on growth performance, rumen fermentation, immune responses, and antioxidant status of lambs</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>174</volume>:<fpage>60</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2012.02.013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahimi-Tari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadeghi</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Motamedi-Sedeh</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aminafshar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chamani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hematological parameters, antioxidant status, and gene expression of &#947;-INF and IL-1&#946; in vaccinated lambs fed different type of lipids</article-title>. <source>Trop Anim Health Prod</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>168</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11250-023-03585-5</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37084030</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>High-concentrate feeding upregulates the expression of inflammation-related genes in the ruminal epithelium of dairy cattle</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci Biotechnol</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>42</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40104-016-0100-1</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27478614</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4966727</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vinuesa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pomilio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gregosa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bentivegna</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Presa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellotto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Inflammation and insulin resistance as risk factors and potential therapeutic targets for Alzheimer&#8217;s disease</article-title>. <source>Front Neurosci</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>653651</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnins.2021.653651</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33967682</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8102834</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sargi</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>HMC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montanher</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boeing</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos J&#250;nior</surname><given-names>OO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Antioxidant capacity and chemical composition in seeds rich in omega-3: chia, flax, and perilla</article-title>. <source>Food Sci Technol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>541</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0101-20612013005000057</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cultivation technology of high yielding aromatic perilla in Zhaosu alpine dry farming area of Xinjiang with spot sowing on membrane</article-title>. <source>Agric Eng Technol</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.16815/j.cnki.11-5436/s.2016.20.047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chemical compositions and bioactivities of essential oil from perilla leaf (Perillae folium) obtained by ultrasonic-assisted hydro-distillation with natural deep eutectic solvents</article-title>. <source>Food Chem</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>375</volume>:<fpage>131834</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2021.131834</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34920308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>J-F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>J-B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Phytochemical and phytopharmacological review of <italic toggle="yes">Perilla frutescens</italic> L. (Labiatae), a traditional edible-medicinal herb in China</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>108</volume>:<fpage>375</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2016.11.023</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27890564</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>TanTai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of perilla frutescens seed supplemented to diet on fatty acid composition and lipogenic gene expression in muscle and liver of Hu lambs</article-title>. <source>Livest Sci</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>211</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.livsci.2018.03.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mordenti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corino</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crovetto</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casa</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franci</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nutrient requirements of sheep</article-title>. <source>Natl Acad Sci</source>. (<year>1975</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>73</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>87</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4081/ijas.2003.73</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aoac</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Official methods of analysis of AOAC international, 18^ed</article-title>. <source>AOAC Int</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>382</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0924-2244(95)90022-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Soest</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Methods for dietary fiber, neutral detergent fiber, and nonstarch polysaccharides in relation to animal nutrition</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci</source>. (<year>1991</year>) <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>3583</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>97</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(91)78551-2</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1660498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Merchen</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Digestion, absorption and excretion in ruminants</article-title>. <source>Ruminant Animal Digestive Physiology &amp; Nutrition</source> (<year>1988</year>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Multi-omics analysis of the bioactive constituents biosynthesis of glandular trichome in <italic toggle="yes">Perilla frutescens</italic></article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>277</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-021-03069-4</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34144672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8214284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tavaszi-Sarosi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification and quantification of essential oil content and composition, total polyphenols and antioxidant capacity of <italic toggle="yes">Perilla frutescens</italic> (L.) Britt</article-title>. <source>Food Chem</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>275</volume>:<fpage>730</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2018.09.155</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30724256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loo</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Modulation of the human gut microbiota by phenolics and phenolic fiber-rich foods</article-title>. <source>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Saf</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1268</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>98</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12563</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33337077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Extraction, preparative monomer separation and antibacterial activity of total polyphenols from <italic toggle="yes">Perilla frutescens</italic></article-title>. <source>Food Funct</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>880</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/d1fo02282b</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34994359</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdallah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Application of traditional Chinese herbal medicine by-products as dietary feed supplements and antibiotic replacements in animal production</article-title>. <source>Curr Drug Metab</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1389200219666180523102920</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29788885</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soest</surname><given-names>PJV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nutritional ecology of the ruminant</article-title>, <source>Nutritional ecology of the ruminant</source>. <publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name> (<year>2018</year>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lauridsen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>From oxidative stress to inflammation: redox balance and immune system</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>4240</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pey407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30371893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>TanTai</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Carcass traits, meat quality, antioxidant status and antioxidant gene expression in muscle and liver of Hu lambs fed perilla seed</article-title>. <source>J Anim Physiol Anim Nutr</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>102</volume>:<fpage>e828</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>37</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jpn.12841</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29119654</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Che</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of multi-strain probiotics and <italic toggle="yes">Perilla frutescens</italic> seed extract supplementation alone or combined on growth performance, antioxidant indices, and intestinal health of weaned piglets</article-title>. <source>Animals</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>2246</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani12172246</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36077966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9454523</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hrom&#225;dkov&#225;</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polovka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko&#353;&#357;&#225;lov&#225;</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebringerov&#225;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Structural features of two heteroxylan polysaccharide fractions from wheat bran with anti-complementary and antioxidant activities</article-title>. <source>Carbohydr Polym</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>93</volume>:<fpage>22</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2012.05.021</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23465897</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Antioxidant activities of the polysaccharides of Chuanminshen violaceum</article-title>. <source>Carbohydr Polym</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>157</volume>:<fpage>629</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2016.10.040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27987971</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>AWL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>K d C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Figueiredo</surname><given-names>DDR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>David</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>In vitro antioxidant properties of the biflavonoid agathisflavone</article-title>. <source>Chem Cent J</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13065-018-0443-0</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29959550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6026112</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khol-Parisini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schafft</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lahrssen-Wiederholt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hulan</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinse</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The role of dietary selenium in bovine mammary gland health and immune function</article-title>. <source>Anim Health Res Rev</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1466252308001588</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19195425</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rumen fluid transplantation affects growth performance of weaned lambs by altering gastrointestinal microbiota, immune function and feed digestibility</article-title>. <source>Animal</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>100076</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.animal.2020.100076</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33516015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosoi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>ER stress upregulated PGE&#8322;/IFN&#947;-induced IL-6 expression and down-regulated iNOS expression in glial cells</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>3388</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep03388</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24291824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3844943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effects of a low linoleic acid/&#945;-linolenic acid ratio on lipid metabolism and endogenous fatty acid distribution in obese mice</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>12117</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms241512117</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37569494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10419107</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinsella</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lokesh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Broughton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary polyunsaturated fatty acids and eicosanoids: potential effects on the modulation of inflammatory and immune cells: an overview</article-title>. <source>Nutrition</source>. (<year>1990</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>24</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2135755</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khas-Erdene</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bu</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drackley</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>QS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Short communication: responses to increasing amounts of free alpha-linolenic acid infused into the duodenum of lactating dairy cows</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>93</volume>:<fpage>1677</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2009-2681</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20338445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brenes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roura</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Essential oils in poultry nutrition: main effects and modes of action</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>158</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>14</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2010.03.007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Growth performance, nutrient digestibility, immune responses and antioxidant status of lambs supplemented with humic acids and fermented wheat bran polysaccharides</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>269</volume>:<fpage>114644</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2020.114644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schroder</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hertzog</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ravasi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hume</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Interferon-gamma: an overview of signals, mechanisms and functions</article-title>. <source>J Leukoc Biol</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>75</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>89</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1189/jlb.0603252</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14525967</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jimenez-Del-Rio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Velez-Pardo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The bad, the good, and the ugly about oxidative stress</article-title>. <source>Oxidative Med Cell Longev</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>2012</volume>:<fpage>163913</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2012/163913</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22619696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3350994</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The functions of antioxidants and heat shock proteins are altered in the immune organs of selenium-deficient broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Biol Trace Elem Res</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>169</volume>:<fpage>341</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12011-015-0407-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26123162</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Sadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boivin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanism of cytokine modulation of epithelial tight junction barrier</article-title>. <source>Front Biosci</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>2765</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>78</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2741/3413</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19273235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3724223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X-F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q-Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Anti-inflammatory constituents from <italic toggle="yes">Perilla frutescens</italic> on lipopolysaccharide-stimulated RAW264.7 cells</article-title>. <source>Fitoterapia</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>130</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fitote.2018.08.006</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30121232</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Alpha-linolenic acid given as an anti-inflammatory agent in a mouse model of colonic inflammation</article-title>. <source>Food Sci Nutr</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>3873</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/fsn3.1225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31890165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6924294</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Degen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Protective effect of resveratrol improves systemic inflammation responses in LPS-injected lambs</article-title>. <source>Animals</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>872</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani9110872</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31661768</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6912468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>