<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vet Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Vet Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2350</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jvms</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JVMS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Veterinary Medical Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0916-7250</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1347-7439</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10372259</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10372259.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10372259</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10372259</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37258126</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.23-0167</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">23-0167</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Surgery</subject><subj-group><subject>Note</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Repair of a calcaneal fracture with a combination of internal and external fixation in a calf</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>INOUE</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yoshiyuki</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>MOGI</surname><given-names initials="W">Wataru</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>NAIK</surname><given-names initials="MV">Mrunmayi Vishwanath</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>KIM</surname><given-names initials="S">Sueun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>KIRINO</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yumi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>HIDAKA</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuichi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>SATO</surname><given-names initials="R">Reiichiro</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1)</label>Faculty of Agriculture, University of Miyazaki, Miyazaki, Japan</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2)</label>Miyazaki Agricultural Mutual Aid Association, Miyazaki, Japan</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3)</label>Graduate School of Medicine and Veterinary Medicine, University of Miyazaki, Miyazaki, Japan</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4)</label>Japan International Cooperation Agency, Tokyo, Japan</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Sato R: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="r-sato@cc.miyazaki-u.ac.jp">r-sato@cc.miyazaki-u.ac.jp</email>, Graduate School of Medicine and Veterinary Medicine, University of Miyazaki, 1-1 Gakuen Kibanadai-nishi, Miyazaki 889-2192, Japan</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>85</volume><issue>7</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">441657</issue-id><fpage>739</fpage><lpage>742</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>4</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>28</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-07-28 00:25:09.307"><day>28</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169;2023
The Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License. (CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>)</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jvms-85-739.pdf"/><abstract><p>A 6-day-old male Japanese Black calf presented with a transverse fracture of the left calcaneus. In calcaneal fractures, traction of the gastrocnemius muscle causes substantial displacement of the proximal fracture fragment; therefore, external fixation alone is prone to failure of fusion or deformed fusion. Furthermore, internal fixation alone may result in refracture due to the high load on the implant. Therefore, internal and external fixation were used to treat the fracture. Bone fusion was observed on postoperative day 50; the wire was removed on postoperative day 90. Radiographic examination at 4 months postoperatively revealed that the bone had fused in normal alignment. Therefore, a good prognosis can be expected for calcaneal fractures treated with combined internal and external fixation.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>calcaneal fracture</kwd><kwd>calf</kwd><kwd>external fixation</kwd><kwd>internal fixation</kwd><kwd>tarsal joint</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Appendicular fractures (including those of the front and hind limb bones) are common in cattle. The most commonly fractured bones in cattle are the metacarpus and metatarsus, followed by the tibia, radius and ulna, humerus, and femur [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><p>Tarsal fractures are very rare in cattle. Instead, they are often observed in small animals such as racing dogs, and often involve the calcaneus, the central tarsal bone or numerous tarsal bones, and the talus. However, little peer-reviewed veterinary literature is available on calcaneal fractures in non-racing dogs and cats [<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Calcaneal fractures in small animal are thought to be caused by fatigue and stress [<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In contrast, calcaneal fractures in cattle are thought to be caused by trauma due to tumbling or trampling and kicking but are extremely under-reported [<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p><p>The proximal end of the calcaneus of a cow is attached to a composite tendon consisting of the gastrocnemius and biceps femoris tarsal tendons, superficial digital flexor tendon (SDFT), and semitendinosus tarsal tendon. This composite tendon generates a traction force in the proximal direction with each landing. Additionally, even when the foot is elevated, the contractile force of the gastrocnemius muscle always exerts a traction force in the proximal direction.</p><p>Therefore, external fixation as a treatment for calcaneal fractures cannot be expected to result in adequate bone fusion. The optimal strategy depends on the fracture classification and presence of concurrent tarsal injuries; however, in dogs, internal fixation with pins and tension band wires is commonly used [<xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. In horses, cases of repair using internal fixation with plates and lag screws have been reported [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>In the present case, the use of a lag screw would risk an insufficient length of screw for insertion into the distal bone fragments. Furthermore, we were concerned that internal fixation with plates would not allow adequate fixation of the calcaneus bone, that the implant would rupture and impede proper bone remodeling and healing, and that fixation across the talus bone would result in a loss of functionality of the joint. Moreover, residual lameness has been reported for bovine calcaneal fractures treated by internal fixation with plates [<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><p>A male Japanese Black calf was discovered to have left hind limb lameness the day after birth (the first sick day). On the same day, radiographic imaging by the referring veterinarian confirmed a transverse fracture of the calcaneus of the left hind limb. At 7 days of age with a body weight of 28 kg, the calf was admitted to the Veterinary Teaching Hospital, University of Miyazaki for diagnosis and treatment. During initial examination, the calf&#8217;s heart rate, respiratory rate, and rectal temperature were 84 bpm, 36 breaths/min, and 39.2&#176;C, respectively. He was able to stand up on his own but was unable to bear weight on his left hind limb, resting the limb only lightly on the hoof tips. Swelling of the tarsal joint was noted around the calcaneus; however, no open wounds were observed.</p><p>The complete blood counts were in the normal range (white blood cell count, 5,900 cells/&#956;L; red blood cell count, 522 &#215; 10<sup>4</sup> cells/&#956;L; and thrombocytes, 191 &#215; 10<sup>4</sup> cells/&#956;L). The serum examination revealed no abnormalities: aspartate aminotransferase activity, 32 U/L; gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase (GGT) activity; 128 U/L, and glucose concetration, 83 mg/dL. The high GGT activity indicated colostrum intake. None of the other parameters were outside the specific reference values.</p><p>Radiographic examination at presentation revealed a transverse fracture of the calcaneus and severe medial and plantar displacement of the proximal bony fragment (<xref rid="fig_001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A, 1B</xref><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig_001" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Preoperative radiographic view of the left tarsus on day 7. (<bold>A</bold>) Lateromedial view showing a transverse fracture of the calcaneus. (<bold>B</bold>) Dorsoplantar view showing a plantar displacement. There is severe proximal and medial displacement of the fragment.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jvms-85-739-g001.jpg"/></fig>). A 6 days had passed since the injury, we deemed prompt repositioning of the calf&#8217;s calcaneus necessary. Hence, we performed repositioning surgery with internal fixation on the same day on which the calf arrived (day 7).</p><p>The calf was administered an intravenous injection of cefazolin sodium (2 mg/kg, Cefazolin-Chu; Fujita Pharmaceutical, Tokyo, Japan) to prevent perioperative infections. Subsequently, the calf was sedated with intravenous xylazine hydrochloride (0.2 mg/kg) and placed in right lateral recumbency. General anesthesia was administered using a 47-Fr tracheal tube (JORVET; Jorgensen Laboratories, LLC, Loveland, CO, USA) and inhalation anesthesia apparatus (COMPACT 15; Kimura Medical Instrument Co., Ltd., Tokyo, Japan). We did not use a ventilator. General anesthesia was performed via continuous administration of 2% isoflurane (Isoflu; Zoetis Japan, Tokyo, Japan) in oxygen.</p><p>The fracture site was approached via a semicircular skin incision made on the lateral tarsal joint. A large hematoma had formed around the fracture site, with a callus at the fracture edge. After the hematoma was removed, the callus was removed with a rongeur to expose the fracture edge. The fracture fragment was held in the normal position, and a Steinmann pin (3.5 mm, Kirikan, Ltd., Tokyo, Japan) was inserted from the proximal fragment towards the talus (<xref rid="fig_002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2A</xref><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig_002" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>The Steinmann pin through the calcaneus and the tension band-wiring technique using a stainless-steel wire. (<bold>A</bold>) Intraoperative photograph. (<bold>B</bold>) Lateromedial radiographic view. (<bold>C</bold>) Dorsoplantar radiographic view.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jvms-85-739-g002.jpg"/></fig>). The pin was supposed to penetrate only the calcaneus, but radiographs showed that the pin had penetrated deeper than expected and reached the talus. Next, Kirschner wires (1.4 mm; DePuy Synthes Japan, Tokyo, Japan) were used to create guide hole in the proximal and distal bone fragments from the outside to the inside. A stainless-steel wire (18 G; Kirikan Ltd.) was threaded through the guide hole, and both sides were fastened with tension-band wires (<xref rid="fig_002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2B, 2C</xref>). After cutting the excess portions of the pin and wires, the ends of the wires were bent along the bone, and the ends of the pins were covered with rubber from PRN adapter (Nippon Becton Dickinson Co., Ltd., Tokyo, Japan). The surgical site was rinsed thoroughly with saline solution, and 2 mL of bupivacaine hydrochloride hydrate (0.5% Marcaine; Sandoz K.K., Tokyo, Japan) was drop to the surgical wound. Muscle and subcutaneous tissues were closed with Polyglactin 910, a synthetic, absorbable, multifilament suture material (USP 0; Vicryl Plus, Ethicon Inc., Raritan, NJ, USA), and the skin was closed with a single interrupted suture by using nylon thread (USP 1, Nesco suture; Alfressa Pharma Co., Ltd., Tokyo, Japan). The time from skin incision to skin suture was 177 min. A casting bandage (Oltex; ALCARE Co., Ltd., Tokyo, Japan) was applied from the distal knee joint to the apex, and a casting tape (7.6 cm; Scotchcast Plus, 3M Japan Ltd., Tokyo, Japan) was applied over the bandage from the distal knee joint to the tip of the limb. For wound management, a window was made in the cast in the operative field by using a cast cutter. After the povidone-iodine gel (ISODINE GEL, Mundipharma K.K., Tokyo, Japan) was applied to the surgical wound, it was covered with sterile gauze and an adhesive elastic bandage.</p><p>The calf was able to walk the day after surgery. An intramuscular penicillin-streptomycin fixed-dose combination (0.05 mL/kg, Mycillin Injection NZ; Nippon Zenyaku Kogyo Co., Ltd., Fukushima, Japan) was administered from the day after surgery until postoperative day 12. Sufficient negative weight bearing of the affected limb was observed when the cast was removed on postoperative day 17. On postoperative day 31, radiographs showed slight fracture lines but no pin or wire displacement or changes in bone alignment. At the 50-day postoperative radiographic examination, we discovered that the Steinmann pin had been lost (<xref rid="fig_003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3A</xref><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig_003" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Lateromedial radiographic view of the left tarsus. (<bold>A</bold>) Fifty days after surgery. (<bold>B</bold>) Four months after surgery.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jvms-85-739-g003.jpg"/></fig>), but the calcaneal fracture area had fused without complications, such as infection; therefore, the calf was left untreated for follow-up. Upon examination on postoperative day 90, the calf was walking well, and fusion of the calcaneus was radiographically confirmed; therefore, the stainless-steel wire was removed, with the calf under general anesthesia. At the 4-month postoperative examination, the calf demonstrated a good general condition, posture, and gait, and complete bony fusion of the calcaneus was observed (<xref rid="fig_003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3B</xref>). The calf grew up healthy without any complications and was slaughtered at a regular age for beef cattle, at 30 months of age.</p><p>The calcaneus is the largest bone in the bovine tarsal joint. The proximal end forms the calcaneal tuberosity, which serves as the attachment site of the gastrocnemius tendon to the distal third of the femur. The bony end of the calcaneus is attached to a composite tendon comprising the gastrocnemius, biceps femoris tarsal tendon, SDFT, and semitendinosus tarsal tendon.</p><p>Calcaneal fractures are uncommon in cattle [<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] and only two cases treated with internal fixation have been reported [<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. For calcaneal fractures, anatomically accurate reconstruction is important to avoid secondary osteoarthritis. The bone fragments are typically highly displaced and must be surgically repaired because external fixation alone is likely to result in inadequate or deformed fusion.</p><p>Transverse fractures, as encountered in the present case [<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], are common in small animals, and they are normally repaired using Kirschner wires and pins [<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In horses, combined internal and external fixation has been reported, such as internal fixation with plates [<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] and treatment with screws and Robert Jones bandages [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Repair with Robert Jones bandages alone has also been reported [<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In cattle, the tension side of the calcaneum is on the plantar surface, enabling a combination of plates, screws, and tension wires [<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. To the best of our knowledge, no reports of such a repair method have been made.</p><p>In cattle, the load on the implant is expected to be greater than that in small animals; internal fixation alone may risk implant rupture, whereas external fixation alone may risk gastrocnemius rupture or tibial fracture [<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. We previously encountered a case of calcaneal fracture similar to the present case, in which failure of fusion or deformed fusion occurred after only external fixation, which was repaired by corrective osteotomy. However, complete alignment was not restored in those cases, and the fetlock joint of the healthy limb was depressed, resulting in a poor prognosis. One equine calcaneal fracture was reportedly repaired with a plate, yielding good results; however, when a bovine fracture was similarly repaired with internal fixation using a plate, although fusion of the fracture was achieved, deformation of the implant reportedly caused deformed fusion in the fracture site, resulting in residual lameness [<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><p>As a proximal traction force is exerted on the calcaneus during each landing, the tension band-wiring technique is dynamically preferable for internal fixation because the traction force inversely brings the bone closer together. Furthermore, the addition of external fixation reduces the effect of negative weight bearing on the implant. Additionally, external fixation in combination with internal fixation likely reduces the strain on the implant in the early post-fixation period, reducing the risk of failure.</p><p>The intraoperative radiographic examination in this case revealed that the pin had been inserted deeper than planned, through the calcaneus into the talus. Re-pinning was considered; however, because a calf has a very soft bone cortex soon after birth, we were concerned about bone damage and loss of fixation strength due to re-pinning, we decided to rather remove the pin as soon as possible after confirming bone fusion. In the end, the Steinmann pin had been lost by postoperative day 50. We hypothesize that the pin had loosened owing to the movement of the calcaneus and talus after the cast was removed on postoperative day 17.</p><p>In conclusion, internal fixation with pins and wires may be an effective treatment for calcaneal fractures in calves, preserving tarsal joint function. In addition, its combination with external fixation can reduce the load on the implant. The combination of pin-and-wire internal fixation with external fixation is expected to yield a good prognosis in calcaneal fractures, as in our case.</p><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s1"><title>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST</title><p>The authors declare that this study was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as potential conflicts of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors thank the staff and student assistants for caring for the calf during hospitalization.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fessler</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1983</year>. <article-title>Treatment of radial-ulnar and tibial fractures in cattle, using a modified Thomas splint-cast combination</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Vet Med Assoc</italic></source><volume>183</volume>: <fpage>430</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>433</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6618968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>St. Jean</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2004</year>. External fixation. pp. 316&#8211;332. In: Farm Animal Surgery (Fubini S, Ducharme N eds.), WB Saunders, Philadelphia.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>St Jean</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vestweber</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desrochers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manhattan</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1994</year>. <article-title>Use of a Thomas splint-cast combination for stabilization of tibial fractures in cattle: 21 cases (1973&#8211;1993)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Agri Pract</italic></source><volume>15</volume>: <fpage>16</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonilla</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2012</year>. <article-title>Minimally invasive repair of a calcaneus fracture in a Standardbred foal</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Am Vet Med Assoc</italic></source><volume>241</volume>: <fpage>1209</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1213</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/javma.241.9.1209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23078569</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Boado</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clutton</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2007</year>. <article-title>Repair of a Salter-Harris type II fracture of the calcaneus of a foal</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet Rec</italic></source><volume>161</volume>: <fpage>350</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>352</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/vr.161.10.350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17827477</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cantatore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clements</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2015</year>. <article-title>Bilateral calcaneal stress fractures in two cats</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Small Anim Pract</italic></source><volume>56</volume>: <fpage>417</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>421</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsap.12358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25929309</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Devas</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1961</year>. <article-title>Compression stress fractures in man and the greyhound</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Bone Joint Surg Br</italic></source><volume>43-B</volume>: <fpage>540</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>551</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1302/0301-620X.43B3.540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13722338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Presnell</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1976</year>. <article-title>Tension band plating of a fractured equine fibular tarsal bone</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Can Vet J</italic></source><volume>17</volume>: <fpage>314</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>317</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1000462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1697414</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fessler</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1996</year>. <article-title>Decision making in ruminant orthopedics</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet Clin North Am Food Anim Pract</italic></source><volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0749-0720(15)30434-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8705796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fossum</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1997</year>. Carpal and tarsal fractures. pp. 826&#8211;829. In: Small Animal Surgery, 2nd ed. (Fossum TW, Hedlund CS, Hulse DA, Johnson AL, Seim HB, Willard MD, Carroll GL eds.), Mosby, St. Louis.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gannon</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1972</year>. <article-title>Stress fractures in the greyhound</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Aust Vet J</italic></source><volume>48</volume>: <fpage>244</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>250</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1751-0813.1972.tb05146.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5068807</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fennell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1951</year>. <article-title>Treatment of fracture of os calcis of a bull by plating</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet Rec</italic></source><volume>63</volume>: <fpage>363</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>364</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/vr.63.21.363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14836343</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ladefoged</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grulke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Busoni</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Serteyn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salciccia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verwilghen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Modified Thomas splint-cast combination for the management of limb fractures in small equids</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet Surg</italic></source><volume>46</volume>: <fpage>381</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>388</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vsu.12612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28145569</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kofler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bago</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2003</year>. <article-title>[Bilateral avulsion fracture (apophyseolysis) of the calcaneal tuber in a heifer]</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Berl Munch Tierarztl Wochenschr</italic></source><volume>116</volume>: <fpage>328</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>332</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12894689</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeBowes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1996</year>. Casting techniques. pp. 104&#8211;113. In: Equine Fracture Repair (Nixon AJ ed.), WB Saunders Co., Philadelphia.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lard&#233;</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2014</year>. <article-title>Noninfectious joint disease in cattle</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet Clin North Am Food Anim Pract</italic></source><volume>30</volume>: <fpage>205</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>223, vii</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cvfa.2013.11.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24534666</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Nuss</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2014</year>. <article-title>Plates, pins, and interlocking nails</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet Clin North Am Food Anim Pract</italic></source><volume>30</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>126, vi</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cvfa.2013.11.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24534661</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ost</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dee</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dee</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hohn</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1987</year>. <article-title>Fractures of the calcaneus in racing greyhounds</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet Surg</italic></source><volume>16</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>59</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-950X.1987.tb00913.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3507125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Calcaneal fractures in non-racing dogs and cats: complications, outcome, and associated risk factors</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet Surg</italic></source><volume>46</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vsu.12575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27731518</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Piermattei</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2006</year>. Handbook of Small Animal Orthopedics and Fracture Repair, 4th ed., Elsevier, Amsterdam.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tulleners</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1986</year>. <article-title>Management of bovine orthopedic problems. Part I. Fractures</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Compend Contin Educ Vet</italic></source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>79</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>