<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="brief-report" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12303825</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12303825.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12303825</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12303825</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40735280</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2025.1639712</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Brief Research Report</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Microbial contamination levels in water derived from dental units used in small animal dentistry</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>&#352;para&#353;</surname><given-names initials="L">Luka</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/3087539/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemec</surname><given-names initials="A">Ana</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/184924/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Biasizzo</surname><given-names initials="M">Majda</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/3110907/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Small Animal Clinic, Veterinary Faculty, University of Ljubljana</institution>, <addr-line>Ljubljana</addr-line>, <country>Slovenia</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Institute of Food Safety, Feed and Environment, Veterinary Faculty, University of Ljubljana</institution>, <addr-line>Ljubljana</addr-line>, <country>Slovenia</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0001"><p>Edited by: Boaz Arzi, University of California, Davis, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0002"><p>Reviewed by: Ching Ching Shirley Kot, CityU Veterinary Medical Centre, Hong Kong SAR, China</p><p>Kimi Kan-Rohrer, University of California, Davis, United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Luka &#352;para&#353;, <email>luka.sparas@vf.uni-lj.si</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">480746</issue-id><elocation-id>1639712</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>02</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>15</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>29</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-07-30 09:26:21.730"><day>30</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2025 &#352;para&#353;, Nemec and Biasizzo.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>&#352;para&#353;, Nemec and Biasizzo</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-12-1639712.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="sec1"><title>Objective</title><p>This prospective study aimed to assess microbial contamination levels in water from dental units used in small animal dentistry.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>Water from 24 dental units across various clinics in Slovenia was sampled between July 2022 and September 2024. Samples were tested for <italic toggle="yes">Legionella</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>, coliform bacteria, intestinal enterococci, and heterotrophic plate counts (HPC) at 36&#176;C. Statistical analysis assessed associations between the water source, implemented disinfection protocols, and microbial contamination levels of water.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 91.3% of the dental units were microbiologically non-compliant when considering potable drinking water standards. When criteria requiring the absence of <italic toggle="yes">Legionella</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, coliform bacteria, intestinal enterococci, and HPC&#8239;&lt;&#8239;200 colony-forming units (CFU)/ml were applied, 87.0% of the units were non-compliant. When threshold of HPC&#8239;&lt;&#8239;500&#8239;CFU/ml was applied, 79.2% of the units remained microbiologically non-compliant. Distilled water supplied 83.3% of units; the remaining 16.7% used municipal water. Disinfection protocols of dental unit waterlines were implemented in 16.7% of the dental units. None of these parameters were statistically significantly associated with microbial contamination levels of the water derived from dental units.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Conclusions and clinical relevance</title><p>The high microbial contamination and limited disinfection use in dental units raise concerns about potential health risks to animals and practitioners. This study highlights the need to establish clear guidelines for microbial levels in water derived from dental units used in small animal dentistry, and to assess disinfection protocols in future research.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>small animal dentistry</kwd><kwd>dental unit water</kwd><kwd>microbial contamination</kwd><kwd>cleaning protocols</kwd><kwd>biofilm</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that financial support was received for the research and/or publication of this article. This research was funded by P4-0092 grant of the Slovenian Research and Innovation Agency (ARIS).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="76"/><page-count count="9"/><word-count count="7268"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Veterinary Dentistry and Oromaxillofacial Surgery</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec5"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Dental procedures are frequently performed in small animal veterinary practice, as oral and dental diseases are among the most prevalent health issues in dogs and cats (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1&#8211;3</xref>).</p><p>Proper diagnostic procedures and treatments in veterinary dentistry require certain basic equipment, such as a dental unit, radiography and general anaesthesia equipment (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Dental units in small animal dentistry typically include a compressor, rheostat, and associated instruments such as scalers, a three-way syringe, and high-speed handpieces (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Dental unit waterlines (DUWLs) consist of a complex network of narrow plastic tubing, serving as the delivery system for water from its source to the dental unit&#8217;s associated instruments (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Microbial contamination of DUWLs is a well-known general problem in dental medicine. Many studies over the past decades have identified high microbial contamination levels [ranging from 10<sup>2</sup> to 10<sup>8</sup> colony-forming units (CFU)/ml] in water derived from DUWLs used in human dental practices and the potential health risks for patients and staff (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9&#8211;11</xref>). Microbial contamination of DUWLs can originate from the water source; either from municipal water system or from a water reservoir within the DUWLs. Several structural and operational factors of DUWLs contribute to the rapid formation of biofilm consisting of bacteria, fungi, and protozoa that adhere to DUWLs&#8217; inner surfaces. Structurally, the high surface-to-volume ratio, the use of hydrophobic polymeric plastic tubing with a small diameter, and the laminar flow of water through the system create an ideal environment for biofilm growth. Additionally, operational factors such as prolonged water stagnation further exacerbate these conditions, promoting accelerated biofilm development. The detachment and fragmentation of active biofilm are the primary reservoir for continued microbial contamination within the water supply (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). However, contamination can also result from the absence or malfunction of valves in rotating handpieces, which are designed to prevent the backflow of the patient&#8217;s biological fluids caused by negative pressure during the handpiece&#8217;s slowdown phase or inappropriate care of the handpieces (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).</p><p>According to the recommendation of the US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), water from DUWLs used in non-surgical procedures should not contain more than 500&#8239;CFU/ml of heterotrophic plate counts (HPCs), consistent with the national drinking water standard (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). In 1996, the American Dental Association (ADA) proposed an even stricter goal of a maximum of 200&#8239;CFU/ml of HPCs in such water for the following years (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). However, their current recommendation aligns with that of the CDC (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). In certain countries, there is currently no established maximum limit for CFU/ml of heterotrophic bacteria in water from DUWLs used in human dentistry and there are no standards worldwide for veterinary medicine/dentistry. Existing drinking water legislation in Slovenia states that heterotrophic bacteria levels at 36&#176;C must not exceed 100&#8239;CFU/ml. Additionally, these guidelines require that potable water be completely free of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, intestinal enterococci and coliform bacteria (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Sterile saline or sterile water should be used as a coolant/irrigant when performing surgical procedures as per CDC recommendations (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).</p><p>To our knowledge, no published studies have examined microbial contamination of water from dental units, or in particular DUWLs, in small animal veterinary practice. Furthermore, no maximum CFU/ml threshold has been established for HPCs in DUWLs water used for veterinary dentistry procedures. The aim of our cross-sectional study is to assess microbial contamination in water from dental units used in small animal veterinary dentistry and to examine its association with the disinfection protocols currently in use.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec6"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec7"><label>2.1</label><title>Sampling of the water from dental units</title><p>Sampling was conducted from dental units in small animal clinics in Slovenia, where dental procedures are routinely performed and the clinic owners voluntarily participated in the study. Water samples were collected in the morning, prior to the first dental procedure and in accordance with ISO 19458:2006 (the standard for water sampling intended for microbial analysis and water quality assessment) (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). For each dental unit, water samples were collected by the same person (L&#352;) from the scaler, high-speed handpiece, and three-way syringe outlets, always in this order and with the dental attachments in place. No flushing of the waterlines was performed prior to sampling. This approach mirrors the methodology used for sampling drinking water directly from a tap, ensuring an accurate evaluation of the water quality as it is consumed&#8212;straight from the potentially contaminated source. During sampling, protective measures (i.e., non-sterile nitrile gloves, cap and a face mask) were used to minimize the risks of microbial contamination from the sampler.</p><p>A 350&#8239;ml sample was taken from each outlet for the determination of HPCs at 22 and 36&#176;C, coliform bacteria, intestinal enterococci, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>. Additionally, a composite 1,000&#8239;ml sample was taken by combining equal parts of water from each outlet for the detection of <italic toggle="yes">Legionella</italic> spp.</p><p>Samples were collected in sterile plastic bottles (with sodium thiosulphate solution to neutralize free chlorine; <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>) and promptly transported to the laboratory in portable coolers maintained at 4&#176;C. All samples were processed within 24&#8239;h for microbiological evaluation.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Sterile plastic bottles with sodium thiosulphate solution, used to neutralize free chlorine, were used for water sample collection for microbiological analysis.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1639712-g001.jpg"><alt-text content-type="machine-generated">Two plastic bottles are shown. The left bottle is tall, rectangular, and blue with a red cap. The right bottle is white, smaller, has a red cap, and a label with text.</alt-text></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="sec8"><label>2.2</label><title>Microbiological testing</title><p>Detection of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, coliform bacteria and intestinal enterococci was performed by filtering 100&#8239;ml of the sample through 0.45&#8239;&#956;m cellulose filters (Millipore, Molsheim, France). The membranes were laid on Cromogenic Coliform Agar (Biokar, Beauvais, France) according to ISO 9308-1:2014 for <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>/coliform growth and on Compass&#174; Enterococcus Agar (Biokar, Beauvais, France) for Enterococcus growth (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). The same procedure was used for detection of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> using CN Pseudomonas Gelose/Agar (Biokar, Beauvais, France) according to ISO 16266:2006 (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). The results were expressed as CFU/100&#8239;ml.</p><p>Heterotrophic plate counts (HPCs) at 36&#176;C and 22&#176;C were determined by the pour plate method in accordance with the ISO 6222:1999 by using Yeast agar (Biolife, Milano, Italy) (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). The results were reported as CFU/ml.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Legionella</italic> spp. detection was performed in accordance with ISO 11731:2017 (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Specifically, 0.1&#8239;ml of the water sample was directly inoculated onto GVPC agar (Biokar, Beauvais, France). Additionally, 100&#8239;ml of the sample was filtered through a cellulose-nitrate membrane (diameter 47&#8239;mm, pore size 0.45&#8239;&#956;m) (Millipore, Molsheim, France), and the membrane was then placed directly onto GVPC agar. For another 100&#8239;ml sample, the filter was overlaid with 20&#8239;ml of 0.2&#8239;M HCl&#8211;KCl buffer (pH 2.2) for 5&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.5&#8239;min. After discarding the buffer, the filter was rinsed with 10&#8239;ml of sterile water and placed on a third GVPC agar plate. All cultures were incubated at (36&#8239;&#177;&#8239;2) &#176;C for 7&#8211;10&#8239;days, and results were expressed as CFU/L.</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><label>2.3</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>A chi-square test of independence was used to evaluate potential associations between the presence of bacteria/microbiological suitability and selected factors, including the type of water source, the presence of an implemented cleaning protocol, and the specific output tested (scaler, high-speed handpiece, or three-way syringe outlet). Expected frequencies were computed under the assumption of independence between the variables. The analysis was conducted using SPSS software, which provided the chi-square statistics and the corresponding <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value. If the p-value was less than the predetermined significance level (&#945;&#8239;=&#8239;0.05), the null hypothesis was rejected in favour of the alternative hypothesis, suggesting the presence of a statistically significant association between the presence of bacteria/microbiological suitability and the measured factors. In cases where more than 20% of the expected cell frequencies were below 5, Fisher&#8217;s exact test (for 2&#8239;&#215;&#8239;2 contingency tables) or the likelihood ratio test was applied instead of the chi-square test, as these methods were more appropriate for datasets with low expected frequencies. Pairwise deletion was used to handle missing data, allowing for the inclusion of all available cases for each analysis by considering only those variable pairs with non-missing values.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec10"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec11"><label>3.1</label><title>Dental units</title><p>A total of 24 dental units used in small animal dentistry were sampled. The units were supplied with either distilled water from an integrated reservoir (20/24; 83.3%) or municipal water (4/24; 16.7%). Only 16.7% (4/24) of the dental units had implemented any disinfection protocols for their DUWLs (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In three cases, a disposable cartridge (iM3 Straw, iM3 Inc., Vancouver, WA, USA) containing silver as the active ingredient was used in the unit&#8217;s integrated reservoir. The cartridge functioned as a water treatment system, incorporating a weak acid gelular cation exchange resin in its hydrogen form. In one case, a weekly disinfection protocol was implemented for the dental unit using municipal water. As per manufacturer instructions, 6% hydrogen peroxide solution (KaVo OXYGENAL&#8482; 6, KaVo Dental GmbH, Biberach, Germany) was introduced into the DUWLs over the weekend and flushed out before the dental unit was used again. High-speed handpieces were sterilized prior to sampling in five out of 23 cases where they were present on the dental unit. The scaler was sterilized in three out of 24 cases, while the three-way syringe was not sterilized in any case.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Results of microbiological testing, water source and DUWL cleaning protocol.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unit</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="13" rowspan="1">Scaler</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;150</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold overgrowth</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold overgrowth</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coliform bacteria</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold overgrowth</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intestinal enterococci</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold overgrowth</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HPCs (22&#176;C)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">270</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,600</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold overgrowth</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">760</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HPCs (36&#176;C)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,300</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">190</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,600</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold overgrowth</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">270</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Three-way syringe</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold overgrowth</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold overgrowth</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coliform bacteria</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold overgrowth</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intestinal enterococci</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold overgrowth</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HPCs (22&#176;C)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">820</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">490</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold overgrowth</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1900</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HPCs (36&#176;C)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,800</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">410</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">560</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold overgrowth</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High-speed handpiece</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold overgrowth</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold overgrowth</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coliform bacteria</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold overgrowth</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intestinal enterococci</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold overgrowth</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HPCs (22&#176;C)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,000</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">450</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold overgrowth</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3,000</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3,000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HPCs (36&#176;C)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,600</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">280</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">420</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">550</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mold overgrowth</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3,000</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3,000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Legionella</italic> spp.</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water source</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Municipal</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DUWLs cleaning protocol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unit</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="13" rowspan="1">Scaler</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;150</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;150</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coliform bacteria</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intestinal enterococci</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HPCs (22&#176;C)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">460</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;30,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;30,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,500</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HPCs (36&#176;C)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,200</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;30,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">920</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,100</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;30,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,800</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Three-way syringe</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not present</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;150</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coliform bacteria</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;150</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intestinal enterococci /</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HPCs (22&#176;C)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,100</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;30,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">730</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HPCs (36&#176;C)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;30,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,100</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">420</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;30,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">310</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="13" rowspan="1">High-speed handpiece</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coliform bacteria</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intestinal enterococci</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HPCs (22&#176;C)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,500</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;30,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,500</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">750</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">520</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">650</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1700</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HPCs (36&#176;C)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,100</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;3,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;30,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,000</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">260</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">760</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;30,000</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,300</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,600</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Legionella</italic> spp.</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">~0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water source</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Municipal</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Municipal</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distilled</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Municipal</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DUWLs cleaning protocol</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>~0 &#8211; under method detection limit.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec12"><label>3.2</label><title>Microbiological testing results</title><p>Detailed results of the microbiological testing are available in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><p>Water from one unit was microbiologically unsuitable because of mold growth, what also prevented the assessment of HPCs and other bacteria. This unit was deemed microbiologically non-compliant but could not be classified within the predefined categories and was therefore excluded from statistical analysis.</p><p>In the overall assessment of the microbial quality of water from the dental units, we considered the presence of <italic toggle="yes">Legionella</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa, E. coli</italic>, coliform bacteria, intestinal enteroccoci, and different thresholds of HPCs at 36&#176;C: HPC&#8239;&lt;&#8239;100&#8239;CFU/ml, HPC&#8239;&lt;&#8239;200&#8239;CFU/ml, and HPC&#8239;&lt;&#8239;500&#8239;CFU/ml. Under the most stringent criterion used for potable drinking water in Slovenia (absence of bacteria and HPC at 36&#176;C&#8239;&lt;&#8239;100&#8239;CFU/ml) 91.3% of the dental units were microbiologically non-compliant. When applying the former ADA criterion of absence of bacteria and HPC&#8239;&lt;&#8239;200&#8239;CFU/ml, 87.0% of sampled dental units were microbiologically non-compliant. Under the least restrictive CDC criterion, with absence of bacteria and HPC&#8239;&lt;&#8239;500&#8239;CFU/ml, 79.2% of the dental units were found to be microbiologically non-compliant. HPC values at 36&#176;C ranged from approximately 0 (below the detection limit) to over 30,000 CFU/ml (above the quantification limit). Two of the dental units had been in use for less than 6&#8239;months; one met the microbiological standard under the criterion of absence of bacteria and HPC&#8239;&lt;&#8239;200&#8239;CFU/ml, while the other failed to comply with any of the applied criteria.</p><p>At the level of the individual tested outlets, and applying the most stringent standards for potable water, 73.9% of samples from the scaler, 71.4% from the three-way syringe, and 81.8% from the high-speed handpiece were microbiologically non-compliant. When considering the least restrictive CDC criterion, 56.6% of samples from the scaler, 38.1% from the three-way syringe, and 59.1% from the high-speed handpiece were microbiologically non-compliant. HPCs values at 36&#176;C ranged from approximately 0 (below the detection limit) to over 30.000&#8239;CFU/ml (above the quantification limit) across all three sampled outlets.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> was detected in five dental units. At the level of the individual tested outlets, it was found in 13% of samples from the scaler, 4.8% from the three-way syringe, and 9.1% from the high-speed handpiece. <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> was present in three dental units, occurring in 13% of samples from the scaler, 4.8% from the three-way syringe, and 4.5% from the high-speed handpiece. Coliform bacteria were detected in three dental units, found in 8.7% of samples from the scaler, 9.5% from the three-way syringe, and none from the high-speed handpiece. Intestinal enteroccoci were also detected in three dental units, found in 8.7% of samples from the scaler, 4.8% from the three-way syringe, and none from the high-speed handpiece.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Legionella</italic> spp. was not detected in any of the samples.</p><p>Statistical analysis revealed no significant association between the type of water source used in dental units and the microbial suitability of tested water samples across the evaluated criterion: HPC&#8239;&lt;&#8239;100&#8239;CFU/ml at 36&#176;C (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;1.00), HPC&#8239;&lt;&#8239;200&#8239;CFU/ml at 36&#176;C (p&#8239;=&#8239;1.00), and HPC&#8239;&lt;&#8239;500&#8239;CFU/ml at 36&#176;C (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.539).</p><p>Similarly, the association between the implemented cleaning and disinfection protocol for dental unit waterlines and microbiological suitability of the water from the dental units was not statistically significant: HPC&#8239;&lt;&#8239;100&#8239;CFU/ml at 36&#176;C (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.324), HPC&#8239;&lt;&#8239;200&#8239;CFU/ml at 36&#176;C (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.067), and HPC&#8239;&lt;&#8239;500&#8239;CFU/ml at 36&#176;C (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.194).</p><p>No statistically significant association was found between the different tested water outlets (scaler, high-speed handpiece, and three-way syringe) and the microbiological suitability of the water, for both thresholds HPC&#8239;&lt;&#8239;100&#8239;CFU/ml at 36&#176;C (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.706) and HPC&#8239;&lt;&#8239;500&#8239;CFU/ml at 36&#176;C (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.325).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec13"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>The high levels of microbial contamination found in water derived from dental units used in small animal dentistry in this study align with previous research in human dentistry, which identified contamination levels as high as 10<sup>8</sup>&#8239;CFU/ml (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24&#8211;27</xref>). Only 8.7% of the dental units in this study met the national criterion for drinking water quality. Additionally, 13% of the dental units met ADA&#8217;s former recommendation for maximal levels of HPCs (&lt; 200&#8239;CFU/ml), while 20.8% met the recommendation from the CDC (&lt; 500&#8239;CFU/ml). These recommendations are intended for non-surgical dental treatments in humans, whereas in veterinary dentistry, dental units are often used in procedures requiring surgical tooth extractions. In one of the 24 dental units in this study, mold growth was observed, preventing assessment of bacterial presence and contamination levels.</p><p>Water plays a crucial role in dental treatment, serving both as a coolant for instruments (thereby preventing iatrogenic damage to oral and dental tissues) and as an irrigant for surgical field. In addition to direct contact with water, both dental staff and patients are exposed to aerosols generated by high-speed rotating instruments or ultrasonic and sonic scalers (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27&#8211;30</xref>). Aerosols can contain microorganisms and can remain airborne for extended periods, allowing them to spread throughout the dental room (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31&#8211;33</xref>). Substantial microbial contamination linked to the use of high-speed rotating instruments was recorded more than 1.5 meters from the patient and may be associated with occupational health risks including high risks for asthma (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34&#8211;37</xref>). In human dentistry, various strategies are employed to mitigate aerosol exposure in dental settings and one of the most effective ways to minimize aerosol exposure during dental procedures is to capture aerosols directly at the source&#8212;the patient&#8217;s mouth. This can be achieved using source control methods, such as high-volume evacuation and alternative dental evacuation systems (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38&#8211;40</xref>). To the authors&#8217; knowledge, veterinarians performing dentistry procedures in small animals generally rely on basic water/saliva ejectors, which are also not consistently used.</p><p>The selection of specific microbes (HPC, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, coliform bacteria and intestinal enterococci) for testing was based on the national standard for potable water in Slovenia (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Presence of other microbes (<italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa, Legionella</italic> spp.) was additionaly tested due to the known potential of these bacteria to contaminate medical equipment and their (opportunistic) pathogenicity (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7&#8211;10</xref>, <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Legionella</italic> spp. testing was initially conducted using a composite sample collected from individual outlets of the dental unit, with the aim of determining the presence of the bacteria within particular parts equipment only if the whole sample was found contaminated.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Legionella</italic> spp. was not detected in any of the samples obtained in this study. Although this Gram-negative bacterium has frequently been reported in previous studies of microbial contamination in DUWLs, the reported prevalence varies widely (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41&#8211;43</xref>). The inhalation of aerosols contaminated with <italic toggle="yes">Legionella</italic> spp. can pose serious health risks to humans, as it can result in Legionnaires&#8217; disease, a severe form of pneumonia (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44&#8211;46</xref>). Dental units provide an ideal environment for the multiplication and potential transmission of <italic toggle="yes">Legionella</italic> spp., with documented cases of legionellosis in a patient acquired through contaminated dental units (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). The occupational risk of <italic toggle="yes">Legionella</italic> spp. infection among dental health workers has also been widely discussed (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49&#8211;52</xref>). The absence of <italic toggle="yes">Legionella</italic> spp. in dental units in our study may be attributed to the fact that only four out of 24 sampled dental units used municipal water as their source, while the others relied on distilled water from small reservoir bottles integrated into the dental units. Previous studies have shown that large institutions are more susceptible to <italic toggle="yes">Legionella</italic> spp. colonization due to the use of large water storage tanks (<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). The prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Legionella</italic> spp. may also vary depending on the geographical location (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>).</p><p>In our study, <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> was detected in five out of 23 dental units. The presence of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> in DUWLs has often been the subject of research due to its pathogenic role in susceptible human hosts. Some of the previous studies have reported the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> in water from DUWLs used in human dental practices to range from 5 to 24% (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">54&#8211;56</xref>). To our knowledge no prior published studies have identified the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> in DUWLs used in small animal dentistry. Although <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> is considered one of the most important human pathogens in hospital-acquired infections, there are not many reports linking <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas</italic> spp. infections directly to patient exposure to contaminated DUWLs (<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, as in humans, is recognized as an opportunistic pathogen in dogs and cats associated with ulcerative keratitis, otitis, pyoderma, urinary tract infections, wound and respiratory tract infections in both species (<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">57&#8211;61</xref>). There is currently no information regarding dental units as a potential source of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> infection in small animals. <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> warrants significant attention due to its high levels of antimicrobial resistance. Notably, in the WHO Bacterial Priority Pathogen List 2024, it has been reclassified from the critical to the high-priority group. Organisms in this group are significantly difficult to treat, cause a substantial disease burden, show increasing trends in resistance, are uniquely challenging to prevent, are highly transmissible, and have few potential treatments under development (<xref rid="ref62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>).</p><p><italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> was detected in three of the dental units in this study. This bacterium is commonly used as an indicator of water quality because its presence signals fecal contamination of the water (<xref rid="ref63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). Consequently, this contamination raises the likelihood that enteric pathogens may also be present. In two of the units where <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> was detected, coliform bacteria and enterococci were also identified.</p><p>Cross-transmission of microorganisms is a common occurrence in dental treatment, primarily due to direct or indirect contact with patients, dental staff, and contaminated aerosols. While the overall risk of infection remains low, it is a greater concern when treating immunocompromised patients and the results of this study warrant further research to assess the risk to animals, as its potential pathological impact cannot be overlooked (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>).</p><p>Rapid biofilm formation on devices used in medical and dental procedures is a well-documented public health problem that is difficult to address as complex biofilm becomes very resistant (<xref rid="ref64" ref-type="bibr">64&#8211;70</xref>). Once mature, biofilm can act as a reservoir for microorganisms that are continuously released into the water from DUWLs during biofilm detachment and fragmentation (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>). As the aim of this study was to evaluate the overall microbial burden from water derived from the entire dental unit system, water quality of the source (input water) was not tested separately and the water samples were obtained with the dental attachments in place (where most of these were not sterilized). Therefore, it is not possible to ascribe the poor water quality derived from dental units in this study solely to DUWLs biofilm formation. However, as substantial variations in water quality were observed between different outlets of the same dental unit, biofilm formation within parts of DUWLs likely contributed to the microbial contamination.</p><p>Moreover, only four out of 24 dental units had a protocol in place for cleaning and disinfecting DUWLs. Notably, only two of these four&#8239;units met the CDC and ADA recommendations for HPCs, and just one met national potable water standards. As this study only recorded whether a cleaning and disinfection protocol was present or absent, without evaluating its&#8217; specific procedures, the reasons why microbial contaminations levels were high in the other two dental units remain unclear. Also, there was no statistically significant difference in microbial water quality between dental units with and without a cleaning and disinfection protocol. This may be due to the small sample size, as several prior studies in human dentistry have demonstrated that the use of chemical disinfectants significantly reduces microbial contamination in DUWLs. Protocols using peracetic acid, ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA) tetrasodium salt, sodium hypochlorite, chlorhexidine gluconate, iodine povidone, hydrogen peroxide and chlorine dioxide have been studied. Various dental chair manufacturers specify products that are compatible with their equipment to prevent damage (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="ref71" ref-type="bibr">71&#8211;76</xref>). Additional measures, such as cleaning, oiling and autoclaving handpieces (which was rarely observed during our study and likely contributed to the observed contamination of the water sampled), regularly replacing them, and flushing the waterlines between patients for 20 to 30&#8239;s, also play a crucial role in controlling water contamination levels (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="ref76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec14"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>The poor microbial quality of the water derived from dental units in this study, combined with the general absence of cleaning and disinfection protocols for DUWLs and lack of sterilization of handpieces, highlights a significant concern. Given that distilled water was used in 83.3% of the sampled cases (minimizing the likelihood of contamination at the water source) there is a clear need to implement effective disinfection measures for DUWLs and dental instruments in veterinary dentistry. Additionally, guidelines should be established to define the maximum recommended levels of microbial contamination in DUWL water, similar to those in human dentistry, along with regular monitoring to ensure compliance. Further studies with larger sample sizes, sampling of the input water, expanding microbiological testing to include other microorganisms such as mycobacteria and free-living protozoa, and an evaluation of the effectiveness of different DUWLs disinfection protocols in small animal dentistry are warranted.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec15"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be made available by the authors, without undue reservation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="sec16"><title>Author contributions</title><p>L&#352;: Conceptualization, Investigation, Methodology, Writing &#8211; original draft. AN: Writing &#8211; original draft, Supervision, Methodology, Conceptualization. MB: Conceptualization, Investigation, Methodology, Writing &#8211; original draft.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec18"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ai-statement" id="sec19"><title>Generative AI statement</title><p>The author(s) declare that no Gen AI was used in the creation of this manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec20"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stella</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Croney</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A cross-sectional study to estimate prevalence of periodontal disease in a population of dogs (<italic toggle="yes">Canis familiaris</italic>) in commercial breeding facilities in Indiana and Illinois</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>e0191395</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0191395</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29346448</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5773197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Summers</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Neill</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Church</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sargan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brodbelt</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Health-related welfare prioritisation of canine disorders using electronic health records in primary care practice in the UK</article-title>. <source>BMC Vet Res</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12917-019-1902-0</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31118035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6532203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holcombe</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A review of the frequency and impact of periodontal disease in dogs</article-title>. <source>J Small Anim Pract</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>529</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsap.13218</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32955734</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niemiec</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gawor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemec</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tutt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>World small animal veterinary association global dental guidelines</article-title>. <source>J Small Anim Pract</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>E36</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>E161</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsap.13132</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32715504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eubanks</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Equipping the dental operatory</article-title>. <source>J Vet Dent</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/089875641303000110</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23757825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pegg</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lothamer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rawlinson</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The air-driven dental unit: form and function at a mechanical level</article-title>. <source>J Vet Dent</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>202</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0898756419892635</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31928396</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spagnolo</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sartini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cristina</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Microbial contamination of dental unit waterlines and potential risk of infection: a narrative review</article-title>. <source>Pathogens</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>651</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/pathogens9080651</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32823641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7460066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain Akbar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Behbehani</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karched</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Biofilm growth and microbial contamination of dental unit waterlines at Kuwait University dental center</article-title>. <source>Front Oral Health</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>1071018</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/froh.2022.1071018</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36698450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9868918</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradshaw</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finney</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fulford</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frandsen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#216;stergaard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Microbiological evaluation of dental unit water systems in general dental practice in Europe</article-title>. <source>Eur J Oral Sci</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>112</volume>:<fpage>412</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0722.2004.00151.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15458499</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szyma&#324;ska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sitkowska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dutkiewicz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Microbial contamination of dental unit waterlines</article-title>. <source>Ann Agric Environ Med</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>173</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19061251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mashima</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakazawa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Monitoring the decontamination efficacy of the novel Poseidon-S disinfectant system in dental unit water lines</article-title>. <source>J Microbiol Immunol Infect</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>270</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmii.2015.05.006</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26066542</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbot</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodier</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imbert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Update on infectious risks associated with dental unit waterlines</article-title>. <source>FEMS Immunol Med Microbiol</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>196</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>204</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-695X.2012.00971.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22469485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Distinct microbial community of accumulated biofilm in dental unit waterlines of different specialties</article-title>. <source>Front Cell Infect Microbiol</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>670211</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2021.670211</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34222041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8248794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Volgenant</surname><given-names>CMC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Soet</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cross-transmission in the dental office: does this make you ill?</article-title><source>Curr Oral Health Rep</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40496-018-0201-3</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30524929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6244620</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohn</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cleveland</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harte</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eklund</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malvitz</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Guidelines for infection control in dental health-care settings&#8212;2003</article-title>. <source>MMWR Recomm Rep</source>. (<year>2003</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>. PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14685139</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll1">American Dental Association</collab></person-group>. <article-title>ADA statement on dental unit waterlines</article-title>. <source>Northwest Dent</source>. (<year>1996</year>) <volume>75</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9487889</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll2">American Dental Association</collab></person-group>. (<year>2024</year>). Dental unit waterlines [Internet]. Chicago: American Dental Association. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ada.org/resources/ada-library/oral-health-topics/dental-unit-waterlines/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ada.org/resources/ada-library/oral-health-topics/dental-unit-waterlines/</ext-link> [Accessed May 17, 2025].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll3">Uredba o pitni vodi</collab></person-group> (<year>2023</year>). Uradni List RS33(61):5235&#8211;5245. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.uradni-list.si/glasilo-uradni-list-rs/vsebina/2023-01-1848" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.uradni-list.si/glasilo-uradni-list-rs/vsebina/2023-01-1848</ext-link> [Accessed May 13, 2025].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll4">International Organization for Standardization</collab></person-group>. (<year>2006</year>). ISO 19458:2006. Water quality &#8212; Sampling for microbiological analysis. Geneva: ISO.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll5">European Committee for Standardization</collab></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). EN ISO 9308-1. Water quality &#8211; Enumeration of Escherichia coli and coliform bacteria &#8211; Part 1: Membrane filtration method for waters with low bacterial background flora. Brussels: CEN.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll6">European Committee for Standardization</collab></person-group>. (<year>2006</year>). EN ISO 16266:2006. Water quality &#8212; Detection and enumeration of Pseudomonas aeruginosa &#8212; Method by membrane filtration. Brussels: CEN.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll7">European Committee for Standardization</collab></person-group>. (<year>1999</year>). EN ISO 6222:1999. Water quality &#8211; Enumeration of culturable micro-organisms &#8211; Colony count by inoculation in a nutrient agar culture medium. Brussels: CEN.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll8">European Committee for Standardization</collab></person-group>. (<year>2017</year>). EN ISO 11731:2017. Water quality &#8211; Enumeration of Legionella. Brussels: CEN.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uzel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cogulu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oncag</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Microbiological evaluation and antibiotic susceptibility of dental unit water systems in general dental practice</article-title>. <source>Int J Dent Hyg</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1601-5037.2007.00269.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18205653</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barben</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuehni</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Water quality in dental chair units: a random sample in the canton of St. Gallen</article-title>. <source>Schweiz Monatsschr Zahnmed</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>119</volume>:<fpage>976</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>85</lpage>. PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19954129</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dahl&#233;n</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alen&#228;s-Jarl</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hjort</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Water quality in water lines of dental units in the public dental health service in G&#246;teborg, Sweden</article-title>. <source>Swed Dent J</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>72</lpage>. PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20162927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szyma&#324;ska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sitkowska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bacterial contamination of dental unit waterlines</article-title>. <source>Environ Monit Assess</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>185</volume>:<fpage>3603</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10661-012-2812-9</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22899458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3613572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Donnell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shore</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Biofilm problems in dental unit water systems and its practical control</article-title>. <source>J Appl Microbiol</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>106</volume>:<fpage>1424</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>37</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2008.04100.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19187140</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ather</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruparel</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diogenes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hargreaves</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Coronavirus disease 19 (COVID-19): implications for clinical dental care</article-title>. <source>J Endodont</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>584</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joen.2020.03.008</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32273156</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7270628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choudhary</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Durkin</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoeckel</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinkamp</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thornhill</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lockhart</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of aerosol mitigation strategies and aerosol persistence in dental environments</article-title>. <source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>1779</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/ice.2022.26</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35440351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10822722</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characteristics of blood-containing aerosols generated by common powered dental instruments</article-title>. <source>Am Ind Hyg Assoc J</source>. (<year>1995</year>) <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>670</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15428119591016683</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7618605</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perdelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spagnolo</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cristina</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sartini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malcontenti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dallera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of contamination by blood aerosols produced during various healthcare procedures</article-title>. <source>J Hosp Infect</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>174</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2008.06.012</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18725172</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holliday</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Currie</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pickering</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluating contaminated dental aerosol and splatter in an open plan clinic environment: implications for the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source>J Dent</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>105</volume>:<fpage>103565</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jdent.2020.103565</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33359041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7787509</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rautemaa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wuolijoki-Saaristo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meurman</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bacterial aerosols in dental practice - a potential hospital infection problem?</article-title><source>J Hosp Infect</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2006.04.011</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16820249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7114873</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bj&#246;rnsson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norb&#228;ck</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Widstr&#246;m</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmgren</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Str&#246;m</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Asthmatic symptoms and indoor levels of micro-organisms and house dust mites</article-title>. <source>Clin Exp Allergy</source>. (<year>1995</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>423</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2222.1995.tb01073.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7553245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheff</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hryhorczuk</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wadden</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association of asthma symptoms and severity with indoor bioaerosols</article-title>. <source>Allergy</source>. (<year>2000</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>705</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1398-9995.2000.00551.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10955695</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pankhurst</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coulter</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Philpott-Howard</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Surman-Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warburton</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Challacombe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of the potential risk of occupational asthma in dentists exposed to contaminated dental unit waterlines</article-title>. <source>Prim Dent Care</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>53</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1308/1355761053695176</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15901433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nulty</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lefkaditis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zachrisson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Tonder</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A clinical study measuring dental aerosols with and without a high-volume extraction device</article-title>. <source>Br Dent J</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>229</volume>:<fpage>657</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41415-020-2274-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7658616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33184481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Comisi</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ravenel</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teich</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Renne</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Aerosol and spatter mitigation in dentistry: analysis of the effectiveness of 13 setups</article-title>. <source>J Esthet Restor Dent</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>466</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>79</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jerd.12717</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33522677</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8014276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackley</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panagakos</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chipps</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Virji</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of dental evacuation systems for aerosol exposure mitigation in dental clinic settings</article-title>. <source>J Occup Environ Hyg</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>281</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15459624.2022.2053140</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35289720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9365099</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradshaw</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fulford</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Microbial biofilm formation and contamination of dental-unit water systems in general dental practice</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. (<year>2000</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>3363</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.66.8.3363-3367.2000</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10919792</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC92156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spagnolo</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sartini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cave</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casini</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuvo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cristina</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of microbiological and free-living protozoa contamination in dental unit waterlines</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>2648</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph16152648</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31344972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6696308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pankhurst</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coulter</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Philpott-Howard</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warburton</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of legionella waterline contamination and <italic toggle="yes">Legionella pneumophila</italic> antibodies in general dental practitioners in London and rural Northern Ireland</article-title>. <source>Br Dent J</source>. (<year>2003</year>) <volume>195</volume>:<fpage>591</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>; <comment>discussion 581.</comment> doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bdj.4810735</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14631437</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez-Valero</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rusniok</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchrieser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Legionella pneumophila</italic>: population genetics, phylogeny and genomics</article-title>. <source>Infect Genet Evol</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>727</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>39</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2009.05.004</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19450709</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ang</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Driel</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartland</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular pathogenesis of infections caused by <italic toggle="yes">Legionella pneumophila</italic></article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>274</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>98</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00052-09</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20375353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2863363</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laheij</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kistler</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belibasakis</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>V&#228;limaa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Soet</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>European oral microbiology workshop (EOMW) 2011. Healthcare-associated viral and bacterial infections in dentistry</article-title>. <source>J Oral Microbiol</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>17659</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/jom.v4i0.17659</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22701774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3375115</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fontana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiumana</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedna</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farolfi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pneumonia associated with a dental unit waterline</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>379</volume>:<fpage>684</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(12)60074-9</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22340301</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sch&#246;nning</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jernberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klingenberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>P&#228;&#228;j&#228;rvi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alm</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Legionellosis acquired through a dental unit: a case study</article-title>. <source>J Hosp Infect</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>89</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhin.2017.01.009</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28228245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fotos</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Westfall</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mutchler</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of Legionella-specific IgG and IgM antibody in a dental clinic population</article-title>. <source>J Dent Res</source>. (<year>1985</year>) <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>1382</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/00220345850640121101</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3865949</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reinthaler</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mascher</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>St&#252;nzner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Serological examinations for antibodies against Legionella species in dental personnel</article-title>. <source>J Dent Res</source>. (<year>1988</year>) <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>942</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/00220345880670061001</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3170906</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oppenheim</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sefton</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>ON</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tyler</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Mahony</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Widespread <italic toggle="yes">Legionella pneumophila</italic> contamination of dental stations in a dental school without apparent human infection</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Infect</source>. (<year>1987</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>159</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S095026880006698X</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3609170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2249186</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vitali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Occupational risk for Legionella infection among dental healthcare workers: meta-analysis in occupational epidemiology</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e015374</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2016-015374</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28710211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5734417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pankhurst</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Philpott-Howard</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casewell</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The efficacy of chlorination and filtration in the control and eradication of Legionella from dental chair water systems</article-title>. <source>J Hosp Infect</source>. (<year>1990</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0195-6701(90)90044-O</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1974912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbeau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanguay</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faucher</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avezard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trudel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>C&#244;t&#233;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Multiparametric analysis of waterline contamination in dental units</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. (<year>1996</year>) <volume>62</volume>:<fpage>3954</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aem.62.11.3954-3959.1996</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8899982</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC168213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giwercman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ojeniyi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bangsborg</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> in cystic fibrosis and the possible role of contamination by dental equipment</article-title>. <source>J Hosp Infect</source>. (<year>1997</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0195-6701(97)90117-1</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9211158</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tesauro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Consonni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grappasonni</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lodi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattina</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dental unit water content and antibiotic resistance of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas</italic> species: a case study</article-title>. <source>J Oral Microbiol</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>2107316</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/20002297.2022.2107316</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36034883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9415447</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alcorn</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kowalski</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pyoderma caused by <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> infection in dogs: 20 cases</article-title>. <source>Vet Dermatol</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>432</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3164.2006.00550.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17083575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen-Jones</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antibiotic susceptibility of bacteria isolated from cats with ulcerative keratitis in Taiwan</article-title>. <source>J Small Anim Pract</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>80</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1748-5827.2007.00437.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17850276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allbaugh</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenne</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sebbag</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and antibiotic susceptibility of bacterial isolates from dogs with ulcerative keratitis in Midwestern United States</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>583965</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2020.583965</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33330707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7714721</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Youala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Garch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrissey</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial susceptibility monitoring of canine and feline skin and ear pathogens isolated from European veterinary clinics: results of the ComPath surveillance programme</article-title>. <source>Vet Dermatol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>431</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>e114</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vde.12886</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32924232</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hattab</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mosca</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Francesco</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aste</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marruchella</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guardiani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Occurrence, antimicrobial susceptibility, and pathogenic factors of <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> in canine clinical samples</article-title>. <source>Vet World</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>978</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>85</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14202/vetworld.2021.978-985</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34083949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8167523</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sati</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrara</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Savoldi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garlasco</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campagnaro</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>WHO Bacterial priority pathogens list advisory group. The WHO bacterial priority pathogens list 2024: a prioritisation study to guide research, development, and public health strategies against antimicrobial resistance</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>. (<year>2025</year>):<fpage>S1473-3099(25)00118-5</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(25)00118-5</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40245910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadowsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Byappanahalli</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Environmental <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>: ecology and public health implications-a review</article-title>. <source>J Appl Microbiol</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>123</volume>:<fpage>570</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.13468</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28383815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>R&#246;mling</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balsalobre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Biofilm infections, their resilience to therapy and innovative treatment strategies</article-title>. <source>J Intern Med</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>272</volume>:<fpage>541</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/joim.12004</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23025745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jamal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andleeb</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jalil</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nawaz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Bacterial biofilm and associated infections</article-title>. <source>J Chin Med Assoc</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>81</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcma.2017.07.012</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29042186</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Donlan</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costerton</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Biofilms: survival mechanisms of clinically relevant microorganisms</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.15.2.167-193.2002</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11932229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC118068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szymanska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Biofilm and dental unit waterlines</article-title>. <source>Ann Agric Environ Med</source>. (<year>2003</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14677905</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#248;iby</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciofu</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>P&#216;</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The clinical impact of bacterial biofilms</article-title>. <source>Int J Oral Sci</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4248/IJOS11026</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21485309</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3469878</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Magana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sereti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magiorkinis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Options and limitations in clinical investigation of bacterial biofilms</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>e00084</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00084-16</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29618576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6056845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#225;ndez-Bill&#243;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Llamb&#237;as-Cabot</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jordana-Lluch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maci&#224;</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanisms of antibiotic resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> biofilms</article-title>. <source>Biofilms</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>100129</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bioflm.2023.100129</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37205903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10189392</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karpay</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plamondon</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dove</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Combining periodic and continuous sodium hypochlorite treatment to control biofilms in dental unit water systems</article-title>. <source>J Am Dent Assoc</source>. (<year>1999</year>) <volume>130</volume>:<fpage>957</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14219/jada.archive.1999.0336</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10422399</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Montebugnoli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A new chemical formulation for control of dental unit water line contamination: an 'in vitro' and clinical 'study'</article-title>. <source>BMC Oral Health</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6831-2-1</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11872153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC65694</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kite</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eastwood</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugden</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Percival</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Use of in vivo-generated biofilms from hemodialysis catheters to test the efficacy of a novel antimicrobial catheter lock for biofilm eradication in vitro</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>3073</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.42.7.3073-3076.2004</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15243062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC446317</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Svoboda</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giletto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seibert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puttaiah</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of hydrogen peroxide on dental unit biofilms and treatment water contamination</article-title>. <source>Eur J Dent</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>59</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0039-1698858</pub-id> PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21228956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3019751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mungara</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dilna</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of microbial profile in dental unit waterlines and assessment of antimicrobial efficacy of two treating agents</article-title>. <source>J Clin Pediatr Dent</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>367</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17796/jcpd.37.4.l6851n9g01223450</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24046983</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ditommaso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giacomuzzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ricciardi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zotti</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of a low dose of hydrogen peroxide (Peroxy ag&#8314;) for continuous treatment of dental unit water lines: challenge test with <italic toggle="yes">Legionella pneumophila</italic> serogroup 1 in a simulated dental unit waterline</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>745</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph13070745</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27455299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4962286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>