<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12090930</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12090930.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12090930</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12090930</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40395804</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2025.1545696</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Heat-stable enterotoxin induced apoptosis in small intestine epithelial cells via mitochondrial oxidative phosphorylation pathway</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names initials="M">Meijia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn0003" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names initials="W">Wei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn0003" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="N">Nian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2607878/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names initials="S">Simeng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qizheng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names initials="B">Bo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="J">Jiali</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiumei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Veterinary Medicine College, Northeast Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Harbin</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Heilongjiang Key Laboratory for Animal Disease Control and Pharmaceutical Development, College of Veterinary Medicine, Northeast Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Harbin</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0004"><p>Edited by: Elena Franco Robles, University of Guanajuato, Mexico</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0005"><p>Reviewed by: Osmar Antonio Jaramillo-Morales, University of Guanajuato, Mexico</p><p>Marco Antonio Hern&#225;ndez-Luna, University of Guanajuato, Mexico</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Xiumei Dong, <email>neaudxm@163.com</email></corresp><fn id="fn0003" fn-type="equal"><p><sup>&#8224;</sup>These authors share first authorship</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">480746</issue-id><elocation-id>1545696</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>20</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-05-21 10:25:14.437"><day>21</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2025 Hou, Yang, Liu, Sun, Feng, Shi, Liu and Dong.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Hou, Yang, Liu, Sun, Feng, Shi, Liu and Dong</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-12-1545696.pdf"/><abstract><p>Newborn piglet diarrhea caused by enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> (ETEC) causes serious economic losses in the swine industry worldwide. Heat-stable enterotoxins (STa) secreted by ETEC can damage the intestine, resulting in villus atrophy and shedding, which is the main cause of diarrhea in newborn piglets; however, the mechanism is not clear. This experiment was conducted <italic toggle="yes">in&#8239;vivo</italic> (three-day-old suckling mice) and <italic toggle="yes">in&#8239;vitro</italic> (IPEC-J2 cells) to explore the effect of STa on the intestinal epithelium by comparing the differences after infection with STa toxin-secreting <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 or STa-knockout <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;estA. The results showed that STa caused diarrhea, small intestinal edema, atrophy and rupture of small intestinal villi, and death in a dose-dependent manner in mice, and downregulated oxidative phosphorylation (OXPHOS) in IPEC-J2 cells. Activation of the mitochondria-mediated cell apoptosis pathway through excessive reactive oxygen species (ROS) production induces injury of the small intestinal villi, leading to diarrhea in piglets.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>STa</kwd><kwd>intestinal epithelium</kwd><kwd>mitochondria</kwd><kwd>apoptosis</kwd><kwd>enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> (ETEC)</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn1"><institution-wrap><institution>Natural Science Foundation of Heilongjiang Province</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100005046</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id award-type="contract" rid="cn1">LH2022C037</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn2">Science and Technology Planning Project of Heilongjiang Province</funding-source><award-id award-type="contract" rid="cn2">GC12B303</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that financial support was received for the research and/or publication of this article. This research was funded by Natural Science Foundation of Heilongjiang Province (LH2022C037) and the Science and Technology Planning Project of Heilongjiang Province (GC12B303).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="8"/><table-count count="4"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="34"/><page-count count="14"/><word-count count="9127"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Veterinary Infectious Diseases</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> (ETEC) is one of the main causes of diarrhea in neonatal and weaned piglets (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), resulting in great economic losses to the swine industry due to reduced growth performance of piglets and increased morbidity and mortality (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). ETEC-induced diarrhea depends on adhesion to the epithelial villi of the small intestine and enterotoxin secretion (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Enterotoxins belong to two major classes, heat-labile enterotoxins (LT) and heat-stable enterotoxins (ST). Heat-resistant enterotoxins can be divided into STa and STb according to their solubility in methanol (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), both of which are composed of a single peptide chain (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). STa is synthesized as a precursor molecule of 72 amino acids, referred to as pre-pro-STa, which is cleaved in the periplasmic space to yield a mature peptide of 18 or 19 amino acids, with a molecular weight of approximately 2&#8239;kDa (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). When acting on intestinal mucosal epithelial cells, ST acts on the membrane surface or in the membrane and does not enter the cytoplasm. STa-mediated diarrhea begins with the binding of STa to its receptor, guanylate cyclase C (GC-C). The binding of STa to the extracellular domain of GC-C and the activation of the intracellular catalytic domain of GC-C results in the hydrolysis of GTP and cellular accumulation of cGMP (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>).</p><p>Diarrhea mediated by STa has been shown to be accompanied by histological damage to the intestine, characterized by shortening and atrophy of the villi, a reduced ratio of small intestinal villi height to crypt depth, and a reduced villi surface (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). This damage leads to impaired absorption in the small intestine. Damage to villous epithelial cells of the small intestine, which absorb amino acids, glucose, and inorganic salts from the digestive tract into the bloodstream, affects the absorption of these nutrients (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). However, there are few reports on the specific molecular mechanisms by which STa leads to small intestinal epithelial cell injury and intestinal villus shedding.</p><p>Apoptosis is a type of programmed cell death that involves two classical pathways: the exogenous death receptor pathway and the endogenous mitochondrial pathway, of which the mitochondrial pathway is dominant. The ability of enterotoxins to induce apoptosis is well documented (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). STp inhibits cell proliferation and induces apoptosis of mice intestinal stem cells by down-regulating the Wnt/&#946;-catenin signal transduction pathway (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). LT induces intestinal epithelial cell apoptosis through the endoplasmic reticulum pathway by causing upregulation of ROS. The ROS inhibitor, NAC, alleviates apoptosis caused by LT (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Heat-labile enterotoxin IIc (LT-IIc) induces apoptosis in breast cancer cells MDA-MB-231 by increasing caspase-3/7 activity (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic> enterotoxin (CPE) causes caspase-3-dependent apoptosis in the human intestinal epithelial cell line, Caco-2 (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). The cytotoxic enterotoxin of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> (Act) may induce apoptosis in the human intestinal epithelial cell line, HT-29, by binding to protein-binding partners, including galectin-3 and the SNARE complex scaffolding protein synaptosomal-associated protein 23 (SNAP23) (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). We found that STa inhibits the OXPHOS pathway in IPEC-J2 cells. OXPHOS is the process by which mitochondria transfer electrons through the respiratory chain to generate adenosine triphosphate (ATP). Therefore, STa leads to apoptosis and small intestinal villus damage through this pathway, causing diarrhea. Although STa is the main toxin associated with diarrhea in neonatal pigs (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), the molecular mechanism underlying STa interactions with epithelial cells remains relatively unknown. In this study, IPEC-J2 cells and three-day-old suckling mice were infected with STa-bearing wild-type and STa knockout recombinant bacteria to explore the molecular mechanism by which the STa toxin induces apoptosis and causes cell damage.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec3"><label>2.1</label><title>Experimental design</title><p>To investigate the mechanistic effects of STa enterotoxin on small intestinal epithelial cells, we adopted a dual experimental strategy encompassing <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> models.</p><p>For the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> studies, cytotoxicity assessment of STa-treated epithelial cells was first performed. RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) was subsequently employed to identify differentially expressed genes (DEGs) and conduct pathway enrichment analysis. The transcriptomic findings were further validated through complementary biochemical assays.</p><p>In the <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> experiments, 3-day-old neonatal mice were orally administered bacterial suspensions containing either wild-type <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 (STa-producing) or its isogenic mutant <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;estA (STa-deficient) at graded concentrations. The optimal bacterial inoculum for inducing enterotoxicity was determined by monitoring clinical manifestations and histopathological alterations in intestinal tissues via hematoxylin&#8211;eosin (H&amp;E) staining. Crucially, the molecular mechanisms identified <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> were functionally corroborated in the <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> infection model.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>2.2</label><title>Bacterial strains and growth conditions</title><p>The ETEC strain of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 (serotype O142; ST<sup>+</sup>) was collected and an <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 mutant lacking STa expression (<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;estA) was constructed in a previous study (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Both strains were used to infect IPEC-J2 cells. The frozen bacteria were resuspended in LB broth and inoculated onto Luria-Bertani (LB) plates. Single colonies were then selected and placed in 100&#8239;mL LB medium at 37&#176;C and 170&#8239;rpm. Bacteria were collected in the logarithmic growth phase and resuspended in Dulbecco&#8217;s modified Eagle&#8217;s medium (DMEM) without serum and antibiotics. The concentration of the bacteria was adjusted, and the cells were infected in the next step. The colony-forming units (CFU) of the bacteria were determined by plotting growth curves through live bacterial counting.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>2.3</label><title>Culture of epithelial cells and animals</title><p>The porcine jejunal intestinal cell line, IPEC-J2, is a non-transformed epithelial cell line that originates from a neonatal unsuckled piglet. It was isolated in 1989 by Helen Berschneider (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). IPEC-J2 cells were cultured in DMEM (Hyclone, United States) supplemented with 10% Sijiqing fetal bovine serum (Zhejiang Tianhang Biotechnology Co., Ltd., Zhejiang, China) and 1% Penicillin&#8211;Streptomycin Solution (100&#8239;U/mL, 0.1&#8239;&#956;g/mL, respectively) (Beyotime Biotechnology, China). The cells were maintained in 25&#8239;cm<sup>2</sup> cell culture flasks or 6/24/96-well cell plates (5% CO<sub>2</sub>, 37&#176;C) (Corning, NY) in a humidified atmosphere and cultured for 24&#8239;h before receiving various treatments.</p><p>All procedures used in this study were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) of Northeast Agricultural University (NEAUEC2021 03 42). Twenty male and female mice were randomly grouped and placed in cages for mating. The three-day-old offspring were randomly selected for oral gavage of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 or O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic>. The negative control cells were treated with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS). All mice were housed in an environmentally controlled room. Food and water were freely provided using traditional feeding methods. No parent mice died during feeding and no suckling mice died during gavage. Eight hours after intragastric administration, the suckling mice were euthanized and the small intestinal tissue was harvested for subsequent experiments.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><label>2.4</label><title>Determination of lactate dehydrogenase activity</title><p>The lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) cytotoxicity assay kit (Beyotime Biotechnology, China) was used to evaluate the cytotoxicity induced by STa. When the cells in the 96-well plates had grown to 80&#8211;90%, they were washed three times with sterile PBS and bacteria resuspended in serum-free and antibiotic-free DMEM were added. The negative control contained only DMEM. <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 and O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> with different multiplicity of infection (MOI) were used to infect IPEC-J2 cells, and the LDH released from the cells at different times was measured. We infected IPEC-J2 cells with ETEC at an MOI of 25, 50, 75, 100, 150, and 200. The CFU quantities were measured and normalized according to minor differences in the bacterial inoculations. After incubation for various times (1, 2, 4, and 6&#8239;h), the operations and result calculations were strictly performed according to the manufacturer&#8217;s protocol to detect LDH secreted by cells.</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><label>2.5</label><title>Cell apoptosis detection using Annexin V-FITC and propidium iodine staining assays</title><p>IPEC-J2 cells were grown in 6-well tissue culture plates and infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> at an MOI of 100. The negative control cells were infected with the same volume of DMEM. Cells were harvested and washed with cold PBS. Apoptosis was determined using an Annexin V-FITC/PI cell apoptosis detection kit (Wanleibio Co., Ltd., Shengyang, Liaoning, China), according to the manufacturer&#8217;s instructions. The cells were suspended in 500&#8239;&#956;L binding buffer, and then incubated with Annexin V-FITC and propidium iodine (PI) at room temperature for 15&#8239;min in the dark, followed by analysis using a flow cytometer.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><label>2.6</label><title>Transmission electron microscopy</title><p>For electron microscopy analysis, IPEC-J2 cells were infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> at an MOI of 100. The negative control cells were incubated with the same volume of DMEM. After infection, at least 5&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>6</sup> cells were collected from each group of samples and fixed with 2.5% glutaraldehyde at 4&#176;C overnight, followed by washing with 0.1&#8239;M PBS three times and 1% osmic acid fixation at 4&#176;C for 2&#8239;h. Thereafter, cells were washed with PBS and underwent acetone gradient dehydration, resin embedding, sectioning, and negative staining. The cells were observed using an H-7650 transmission electron microscope (Hitachi, Tokyo, Japan).</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><label>2.7</label><title>Hematoxylin-eosin staining</title><p>Three-day-old suckling mice were orally given 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>7</sup>, 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>8</sup>, 7.5&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>8</sup>, 1.5&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup>, 2.25&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup>, and 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 bacterial suspension, and 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> bacterial suspension, separately. Negative control suckling mice were treated with the same volume of PBS. Nine hours later, the small intestinal tissue was fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde for 48&#8239;h and embedded in paraffin blocks to prepare sections. The sections were stained using an hematoxylin-eosin (HE) Staining Kit (Beijing Leagene Biotechnology Co., Ltd., Beijing, China) and visualized using Lionheart LX Automated Microscope (BioTek, Vermont, United States), the images were obtained by Gene5 3.05 Imager.</p></sec><sec id="sec10"><label>2.8</label><title>RNA-seq transcriptomic assay</title><p>IPEC-J2 cells were grown in 25&#8239;cm<sup>2</sup> cell culture flasks, infected with ETEC strains at an MOI of 100, and cultured in cell incubators for 2&#8239;h. Negative control cells were treated with the same dose of DMEM. Three replicates were used for each group. After incubation, the cells were washed three times with cold PBS and lysed with TRIzol (Invitrogen). Total RNA from IPEC-J2 cells (1&#8239;&#956;g) was used as starting material for deep sequencing using NEBNext<sup>&#174;</sup> UltraTM RNA Library Prep Kit for Illumina<sup>&#174;</sup> (NEB, United States). Briefly, mRNA was purified using oligo-dT beads, fragmented with divalent cations, subjected to heat-catalyzed hydrolysis, and used as a template for first- and second-strand complementary deoxyribonucleic acid (cDNA) synthesis with random primers. The cDNA 3&#8242; ends were adenylated, followed by adaptor ligation and PCR to enrich DNA fragments. The cDNA libraries were quantified using a Qubit2.0 Fluorometer and an Agilent 2100 bioanalyzer. The cDNA libraries were pooled at a final concentration of 1.5&#8239;ng/&#956;L. Paired-end sequencing was performed by Shanghai Novogene Co., Ltd. (Beijing, China) using an Illumina novaseq6000 (Illumina, CA, United States). Differential expression analysis was performed using DESeq2. Differential gene expression enrichment was analyzed using Gene Ontology (GO) tools.<xref rid="fn0001" ref-type="fn"><sup>1</sup></xref> Differentially expressed genes (DEGs) were considered significantly enriched at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values &lt;0.05. The Profiler R package was used to test the statistical enrichment of genes in the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) pathway.<xref rid="fn0002" ref-type="fn"><sup>2</sup></xref></p></sec><sec id="sec11"><label>2.9</label><title>RT-qPCR analysis of genes at mRNA levels</title><p>IPEC-J2 cells were grown in 24-well plates, infected with ETEC strains at an MOI of 100, and cultured in a cell incubator for 2&#8239;h. Negative control cells were treated with the same dose of DMEM. Total RNA was extracted using an RNAprep Pure Cell/Bacteria Kit (Tiangen Biotech, Beijing, China). RNA was quantified using a Nano-300 (Hangzhou Allsheng Instruments Co., Ltd., Zhejiang, China), and 1.0&#8239;&#956;g RNA was reverse transcribed with 5&#215; FastKing-RT SuperMix (Tiangen Biotech, Beijing, China). The RT-qPCR was performed using a Light Cycler<sup>&#174;</sup> 480 System (Roche, Basel, Switzerland) and 2&#215; SYBR Green qPCR Master Mix (Bimake, Shanghai, China) according to the reaction system and conditions (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Five of the most significant DEGs between the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142-infected and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> groups according to RNA sequencing data (log<sub>2</sub>(fold change) &gt;&#177;1.0; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt;0.05) were selected for RT-qPCR. Three replicates per sample were performed for each RT-qPCR assay and &#946;-actin was used as the housekeeping gene for normalization. Specific primers for RT-qPCR were designed using the assembled RNA-Seq sequence data (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The gene&#8217;s relative abundance of mRNA was determined using the comparative threshold cycle (Ct) method by 2<sup>&#8722;&#916;&#916;CT</sup>: &#916;Ct (test)&#8239;=&#8239;Ct (target gene, test)&#8239;&#8722;&#8239;Ct (&#946;-actin, test), &#916;Ct (control)&#8239;=&#8239;Ct (target gene, control)&#8239;&#8722;&#8239;Ct (&#946;-actin, control), &#916;&#916;CT&#8239;=&#8239;&#916;Ct (test)&#8239;&#8722;&#8239;&#916;Ct (control). Only one peak was observed for each PCR product in the melting curve analysis.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>RT-qPCR reaction system and conditions.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Composition</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dosage per reaction (&#956;L)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Application setting</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature (&#176;C)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time (s)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cycle</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#215; SYBR green qPCR master mix</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hot-start DNA polymerase activation</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cDNA template</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100&#8239;ng</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="3" colspan="1">40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upstream primer (10&#8239;&#956;M)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Downstream primer (10&#8239;&#956;M)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ddH<sub>2</sub>O</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Add to 20</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Melt Curve</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="3" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total reaction volume</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The primers used in the present study for IPEC-J2.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Target gene</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank ID</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer sequence (5&#8242;&#8211;3&#8242;)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#946;-actin</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="XM_003124280.5">XM_003124280.5</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: CAGGTCATCACCATCGGCAACG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: GACAGCACCGTGTTGGCGTAGAGGT</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NC_000845">NC_000845</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: TGCCTCCACTATCAGGATTTAT</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: ATTGTCATTTTATTTTTATGTTGTT</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COXII</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NC_000845">NC_000845</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: CGCCACTTCACCCATCATA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: GCTAGTGTGTGTCAGTTTTGTTGT</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NC_000845">NC_000845</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: ATTTGCCTCTTTTATTGCCC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: TATTATTTGTTTGGATGTTAGTTGG</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CYTB</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NC_000845">NC_000845</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: AAAATTATCAACAACGCATTCATTG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: TAGGATTTGCAAGATTAGGCAGAT</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Three-day-old suckling mice were orally administered 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup> CFU of the bacterial suspension. Nine hours later, the jejunal tissue was collected. Negative control suckling mice were treated with the same dose of PBS. Total RNA was extracted using the RNAprep Pure Tissue Kit (Tiangen Biotech, Beijing, China). RT-qPCR was performed as previously described. Specific primers for RT-qPCR were designed using assembled RNA-Seq sequence data (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The primers used in the present study for mice.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Target gene</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GenBank ID</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer sequence (5&#8242;&#8211;3&#8242;)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#946;-actin</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_007393.5">NM_007393.5</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: TTTCCAGCCTTCCTTCTTG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: ACAGCACTGTGTTGGCATAGA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NC_005089">NC_005089</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: TATCACCCTTGCCATCATCT</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: GCTGCTTCAGTTGATCGTG</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COXII</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NC_005089">NC_005089</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: CAAGCACAATAGATGCACAAG</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: TATGGTTTTAACGGTTAATACG</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NC_005089">NC_005089</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: CTATTTGCCTCATTCATTACCC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: GGAAAGAATGGAGACGGTTG</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CYTB</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NC_005089">NC_005089</ext-link></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward: AATAGTCCAAATCATTACAGGTCTT</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse: TTTGCGTGTATATATCGGATTAGT</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec12"><label>2.10</label><title>Western blot</title><p>IPEC-J2 cells were grown in 25&#8239;cm<sup>2</sup> cell flasks, infected with ETEC strains at an MOI of 100, and cultured in a cell incubator for 2&#8239;h. Negative control cells were treated with the same volume of DMEM. The medium in each flask was removed and cells were washed three times with sterile PBS. Total protein was extracted using 100&#8239;&#956;L Radio Immunoprecipitation Assay (RIPA) lysis buffer (Beyotime Biotechnology, China) containing 1&#8239;&#956;L phenylmethanesulfonyl fluoride (PMSF, Beyotime Biotechnology, China). The cells were incubated on ice for 1&#8239;min, scraped off with a cell scraper, and aspirated into an EP tube using a micropipette. Tubes were incubated at 4&#176;C for 15&#8239;min, and total protein was isolated by centrifugation (12,000&#8239;rpm, 10&#8239;min, 4&#176;C) in a high-speed low-temperature centrifuge (Thermo Scientific). The supernatant was transferred to a new tube to obtain total protein.</p><p>Cytoplasmic and mitochondrial protein extraction from IPEC-J2 cells: at least 5&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>7</sup> cells were collected and added to the mitochondrial extraction reagent. After centrifugation at 3,000&#8239;rpm for 15&#8239;min at 4&#176;C, the supernatant was collected and centrifuged at 20,000&#8239;rpm for 20&#8239;min at 4&#176;C. The supernatant was collected as the cytoplasmic protein. The precipitate was added to RIPA lysis buffer, sonicated in an ice-water bath, centrifuged at 10,000&#8239;rpm for 10&#8239;min, and the supernatant was collected as the mitochondrial protein.</p><p>Three-day-old suckling mice were orally administered 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup> CFU of the bacterial suspension. Nine hours later, the jejunum tissue was ground using the Bioprep-24 Homogenizer tissue grinding instrument (Hangzhou Allsheng Instruments Co., Ltd., Zhejiang, China) in 1&#8239;mL RIPA containing 10&#8239;&#956;L PMSF. Tissue homogenate was sonicated followed by centrifugation at 12,000&#8239;rpm for 10&#8239;min at 4&#176;C. The supernatant was collected as total protein. Small intestine tissue from suckling mice supplemented with mitochondrial extraction reagent was ground in a grinding tube, and the tissue homogenate was extracted according to the IPEC-J2 cell protocol. An Enhanced BCA Protein Assay Kit (Beyotime Biotechnology) was used to determine protein concentration. All samples were mixed with 5&#215; sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) Sample Loading Buffer (Beyotime Biotechnology) and boiled for 10&#8239;min. The protein samples were stored at &#8722;20&#176;C.</p><p>Western blotting was used to detect the effect of STa on protein expression in the intestinal epithelial cells (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). An equal amount of 60&#8239;&#956;g protein was loaded and separated using 12% SDS-PAGE. Proteins were transferred to a nitrocellulose (NC) membrane. Membranes were blocked with Tris-buffered saline-0.1% Tween 20 (TBST) containing 5% fat-free milk powder at room temperature (RT) on a horizontal shaker for 2&#8239;h. The membranes were then rinsed thrice with TBST for 10&#8239;min. The membranes were incubated overnight with diluted primary antibodies. Thereafter, membranes were washed in TBST three times for 10&#8239;min, followed by incubation with the corresponding HRP-linked secondary antibodies (dilution, 1:1,000) for 1&#8239;h at RT, then washed with TBST as described above. Protein bands were visualized using an electrochemiluminescence (ECL) detection system (Wanleibio Co., Ltd., Shengyang, Liaoning, China) and quantitatively analyzed using a Quantity One image densitometer (Clinx Science Instruments Co., Ltd., Shanghai, China). The blots shown in the figures are representative of at least three biological replicates and were quantified using ImageJ software. The primary and secondary antibodies were diluted in TBST at different concentrations (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The &#946;-actin content was analyzed as the loading control of the total cell protein. Mitochondrial protein levels were standardized by comparison with voltage dependent anion channel protein 1 (VDAC1) levels.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>The antibodies used in the present study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antibody name</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dilution ratio</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-Bcl-2 antibody</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-Bax antibody</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-COX II antibody</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-Cyt-c antibody</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-caspase-9 antibody</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-caspase-3 antibody</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-cleaved caspase-9 antibody</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-cleaved caspase-3 antibody</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-MT-ND2 antibody</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-NDUFS8 antibody</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-&#946;-actin antibody</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:1,000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anti-VDAC1 antibody</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Goat anti-rabbit antibody of IgG-HRP</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:8,000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Goat anti-mouse antibody of IgG-HRP</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:8,000</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Rabbit polyclonal antibodies against B-cell lymphoma 2 (Bcl-2), Bcl-2 associated X (Bax), cytochrome C (Cyt c), caspase-9, caspase-3, cleaved caspase-9, cleaved caspase-3, and VDAC1 were purchased from Wanleibio (Shenyang, China). Rabbit polyclonal antibodies against COX-II and MT-ND2 were purchased from ImmunoWay Biotechnology (Plano, TX, United States). &#946;-actin was purchased from Abmart (Shanghai, China). Goat anti-rabbit IgG-horseradish peroxidase antibody was obtained from Cell Signaling Technology (Danvers, MA, United States). Goat anti-rabbit IgG-horseradish peroxidase and goat anti-rabbit IgG-horseradish peroxidase antibodies were purchased from Nachuan Biotechnology (Harbin, Heilongjiang, China).</p></sec><sec id="sec13"><label>2.11</label><title>ROS measurement</title><p>The ROS assay kit was purchased from Beyotime Biotech Co., Ltd. (Nantong, China) and was used to evaluate the generation of intracellular ROS with the fluorescent probe, 2&#8242;,7&#8242;-dichlorofluorescin diacetate (DCFH-DA). IPEC-J2 cells were seeded in a 24-well cell culture plate, infected with ETEC strains at an MOI of 100, and cultured in a cell incubator for 2&#8239;h. Negative control cells were treated with the same dose of DMEM. After treatment with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 or <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic>, the cells were incubated with DCFH-DA at 37&#176;C for 30&#8239;min and then washed with PBS. Cells were observed using a Lionheart LX Automated Microscope (Biotek, Winooski, Vermont, United States).</p></sec><sec id="sec14"><label>2.12</label><title>Superoxide dismutase, catalase, glutathione, 8-OHDG (8-hydroxy-2-deoxyguanosine), and mitochondrial respiratory chain complex I activity</title><p>IPEC-J2 cells were collected, and the superoxide dismutase (SOD)/catalase (CAT)/glutathione (GSH)/8-OHDG (8-hydroxy-2-deoxyguanosine)/adenosine triphosphate (ATP) of different treatment groups was determined using ELISAs according to the kit instructions (Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute, Nanjing, China). Mitochondrial respiratory chain complex I activity was determined according to the manufacturer&#8217;s instructions (Beijing Solarbio Science &amp; Technology Co., Ltd., Beijing, China).</p></sec><sec id="sec15"><label>2.13</label><title>Determination of mitochondrial membrane potential</title><p>A mitochondrial membrane potential Detection Kit (JC-1) (Beijing Solarbio Science &amp; Technology Co., Ltd., Beijing, China) was used to determine the MMP of IPEC-J2 cells. JC-1 is an ideal fluorescent probe widely used to detect mitochondrial membrane potential (&#916;&#936;m, MMP). JC-1 aggregates in the mitochondrial matrix to form polymers and produces red fluorescence when the mitochondrial membrane potential is high. JC-1 cannot aggregate in the mitochondrial matrix with a low mitochondrial membrane potential, but instead emits green fluorescence as a monomer. A decrease of mitochondrial membrane potential is a landmark event in the early stages of apoptosis and can be easily detected by the transition of JC-1 from red to green fluorescence. IPEC-J2 cells were collected after ETEC treatment, incubated with JC-1 at 37&#176;C for 20&#8239;min, washed twice with JC-1 staining buffer, and observed under a Lionheart LX Automated Microscope (Biotek).</p></sec><sec id="sec16"><label>2.14</label><title>Immunofluorescence</title><p>IPEC-J2 cells were grown in a 24-well cell plate at 37&#176;C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Cells were cultured in a monolayer, inoculated with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916; or <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> at a 1:100 MOI, and further cultured for 2&#8239;h. The supernatant was discarded and the cells were washed with PBS three times (5&#8239;min/wash). The cells in the control group were treated with the same volume of DMEM. Two hours post infection, IPEC-J2 cells were fixed with 4% cold paraformaldehyde for 30&#8239;min at room temperature. After three PBS washes (3&#8239;min/wash), IPEC-J2 cells were permeabilized with 0.2% Triton-100 in PBS for 10&#8239;min at room temperature. Then cells were washed with PBS buffer, and blocked with 5% BSA in PBS for 30&#8239;min at 37&#176;C. After three PBS washes, IPEC-J2 cells were incubated with a 1:500-diluted Cyt c rabbit polyclonal antibody at 4&#176;C overnight, and treated with a 1:100 dilution of FITC-labeled goat anti-rabbit IgG for 1&#8239;h. Thereafter, cells were stained with a 1:4-diluted 4&#8242;,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole dihydrochloride (DAPI) solution for 15&#8239;min at room temperature. After three rinses, the samples were covered with PBS and visualized using a microscope and software as described above.</p></sec><sec id="sec17"><label>2.15</label><title>Immunohistochemistry</title><p>Three-day-old suckling mice were orally given 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 or <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> bacterial suspension, separately. Negative control suckling mice were treated with the same volume of PBS. The paraffin sections are described in section 2.7. Immunohistochemistry was performed using a DAB Horseradish Peroxidase Color Development Kit (Beijing Leagene Biotechnology Co., Ltd., Beijing, China) and a Streptavidin-Peroxidase Immunohistochemical staining kit (Beijing Biosynthesis Biotechnology Co., Ltd., Beijing, China). The sections were visualized using Lionheart LX Automated Microscope (BioTek, Vermont, United States), the images were obtained by Gene5 3.05 Imager.</p></sec><sec id="sec18"><label>2.16</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Experiments were conducted in triplicate on at least three separate occasions with similar results. The data were analyzed using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA followed by Tukey&#8217;s multiple comparisons), using Graph Pad Prism software (version 7.0, Graph Pad Software Inc., San Diego, CA, United States), and reported as the mean&#8239;&#177;&#8239;standard error of the mean. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values of 0.01 to 0.05, 0.001 to 0.01, 0.0001 to 0.001, and &#8804;0.0001 were considered significant and represented with *, **, ***, and ****.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec19"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec20"><label>3.1</label><title>STa infection induces apoptosis in IPEC-J2 cells and small intestinal villi injury in mice</title><p>The LDH released by the cells increases with the increase of the MOI and the prolongation of the infection time; therefore, it was used to test the cytotoxicity of STa in IPEC-J2 cells (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>). When the MOI was 1:100 and the infection time was 2&#8239;h, the difference between LDH released in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142- and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic>-infected cells was the largest. We used these conditions to investigate the effect of STa infection on apoptotic cell death using Annexin V and PI assays. The percentage of early apoptotic cells in IPEC-J2 cells infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 was 13.9%, which was significantly higher than the number of cells infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> (1.8%) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 infection significantly increased apoptosis, and the percentage of apoptotic cells increased upon STa treatment, reaching 21.4%. Taken together, these data demonstrated that STa induces apoptosis in IPEC-J2 cells.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Toxicity of STa on IPEC-J2 cells and suckling mice. <bold>(A)</bold> Cell cytotoxicity analysis by LDH assay. <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 or <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> were applied to IPEC-J2 cells for MOI of 1:25, 1:50, 1:75, 1:100, 1:200, 1:300, and for 1-, 2-, 4-, or 6-h. After infection, aliquots were collected from the supernatants and assessed for cell cytotoxicity by ELISA. As shown, STa intoxication significantly increases the amount of LDH measured in supernatants. This data shows that STa induces epithelial cell apoptosis. (Error bars is on behalf of mean&#8239;&#177;&#8239;SEM (standard error of mean), <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05, <sup>**</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.01, <sup>***</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.001, and <sup>****</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.0001, one-way ANOVA). <bold>(B)</bold> Cell apoptosis analysis by flow cytometry with Annexin V-FITC/PI cell labeling. IPEC-J2 cells were collected after, respectively, infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> and were dual-labeled with Annexin V-FITC and PI and analyzed by flow cytometry. Lower left quadrants represent intact cells (Annexin V-FITC and PI double negative, Annexin V-FITC<sup>&#8722;</sup>/PI<sup>&#8722;</sup>); lower right quadrants represent early apoptotic cells (Annexin V-FITC positive and PI negative, Annexin V<sup>+</sup>/PI<sup>&#8722;</sup>); upper right quadrants indicate late apoptotic cells (Annexin V-FITC PI double positive, Annexin V<sup>+</sup>/PI<sup>+</sup>); upper left quadrants indicate necrotic cells (Annexin V-FITC PI double positive, Annexin V<sup>+</sup>/PI<sup>+</sup>). The percentage of cells were shown in each quadrant. Left is control group; middle is <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 infected group; right is <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> group. <bold>(C)</bold> The effect of STa on the morphology of IPEC-J2 cells (500&#8239;nm). <bold>(D)</bold> Observation of the state of suckling mice after perfusion with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 or <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic>. <bold>(a)</bold> PBS. <bold>(b)</bold> Fed with 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> bacteria suspension. <bold>(c)</bold> Fed with 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>7</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 bacteria suspension. <bold>(d)</bold> Fed with 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>8</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 bacteria suspension. <bold>(e)</bold> Fed with 7.5&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>8</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 bacteria suspension. <bold>(f)</bold> Fed with 1.5&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 bacteria suspension. <bold>(g)</bold> Fed with 2.25&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 bacteria suspension. <bold>(h)</bold> Fed with 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> C O142 bacteria suspension. <bold>(i)</bold> Diarrhea feces. <bold>(E)</bold> HE staining of small intestine of suckling mice after perfusion of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 or <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> (100&#8239;&#956;m). <bold>(a)</bold> PBS. <bold>(b)</bold> Fed with 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> bacteria suspension. <bold>(c)</bold> Fed with 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>7</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 bacteria suspension. <bold>(d)</bold> Fed with 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>8</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 bacteria suspension. <bold>(e)</bold> Fed with 7.5&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>8</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 bacteria suspension. <bold>(f)</bold> Fed with 1.5&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 bacteria suspension. <bold>(g)</bold> Fed with 2.25&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 bacteria suspension. <bold>(h)</bold> Fed with 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 bacteria suspension.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1545696-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>Transmission electron microscopy (TEM) was applied to detect the microstructure and more intuitively observe morphological changes to the cells after infection with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 or <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic>. IPEC-J2 cells in the control group displayed a normal structure, uniform distribution of nuclear chromatin, and normal cristae structure in the mitochondria (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref>). After 2&#8239;h infection with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic>, respectively, IPEC-J2 cells showed varying degrees of injury. IPEC-J2 cells infected with ETEC O142 showed a typical apoptotic morphology, with large vacuoles appearing in the cytoplasm. The mitochondria were swollen, rounded, and vacuolated, and the mitochondrial cristae had disappeared. Many mitochondria appeared to be surrounded by vesicles, and chromatin aggregated near the edge of the nuclear envelope (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref>). The chromatin of IPEC-J2 cells infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> was slightly gathered, and the mitochondria showed a normal structure, clear bilayer, and cristae. Small vesicles were observed around the nucleus and holes were observed in the cytoplasm (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref>).</p><p>Compared with the control group, mice given 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>8</sup> and 7.5&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>8</sup> and 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142, and 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> bacterial suspension group showed no obvious symptoms. The skin of the mice was naturally pink, there was no diarrhea or feces in the anus, and the intestine was not filled after autopsy (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figures 1D</xref>,<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">a&#8211;e</xref>). The mice given 1.5&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 had slightly cyanotic skin and mild swelling of the small intestine (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figures 1D</xref>,<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">f</xref>). The mice given 2.25&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 occasionally had mild diarrhea, were cyanotic, and lacked energy. The small intestine exhibited mild swelling (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figures 1D</xref>,<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">g</xref>). The mice administered 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 were cyanotic, lethargic, and unwilling to move, with watery diarrheal stool at the anus, and intestinal swelling and filling were observed at autopsy (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figures 1D</xref>,<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">h</xref>,<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">i</xref>). Small-intestinal segments from each group were stained with HE to observe the shape of the small-intestinal villi. Compared with the control group, there were no significant changes in small intestinal villi of mice in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> group (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figures 1E</xref>,<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">a,b</xref>). In the group that received various oral concentration of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142, with an increase in the bacterial suspension concentration, the small intestinal villi of the mice showed atrophy, fracture, and increased villus spacing (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figures 1E</xref>,<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">c&#8211;h</xref>). These results show that STa damages the intestinal villi in a concentration-dependent manner.</p></sec><sec id="sec21"><label>3.2</label><title>Differential gene expression of IPEC-J2 cells and GO and KEGG enrichment analyses</title><p>Differences in expression levels between the groups were considered significant after adjusting for multiple testing based on a <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt;0.05. We first filtered the genes based on <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values &lt;0.05 and an absolute difference &gt;&#177; 2-fold (i.e., log<sub>2</sub>(fold change) &gt;&#177;1.0). In the volcano plot, red points indicate that the expression of genes increased, green points show the opposite, and blue points indicate no significant variation. In total, 18,977 DEGs were normalized and 795 significant DEGs were detected between the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142-infected and control groups, including 353 upregulated and 442 downregulated genes (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). The 18,896 DEGs were normalized and 819 significant DEGs were detected between the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic>-infected and control groups, including 309 upregulated and 510 downregulated genes (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). Moreover, 18,678 DEGs were normalized and 58 significant DEGs were detected between the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142-infected and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic>-infected groups, including 17 upregulated and 41 downregulated genes (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Volcanic map of DEGs distribution by RNA-seq. Volcano plots reflect overall gene expression. The abscissa represents log<sub>2</sub>(fold change), and the ordinate represents &#8722;log10 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value). log<sub>2</sub>FoldChange represents the ratio of gene expression levels in the treatment group and the control group, and then takes the logarithm with 2 as the base. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value represents the <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value for the significance test. Each dot represents a gene, and the color is used to distinguish differentially expressed genes. Red indicates up-regulated genes, green indicates down-regulated genes, and gray dots indicates genes that are not differentially expressed. (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt;0.05, |log<sub>2</sub>FoldChange| &gt;0).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1545696-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>GO is a comprehensive database that describes gene functions. GO function enrichment considers an adjusted <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>adj) of less than 0.05, which is the threshold for significant enrichment. GO functional cluster analysis divided the DEGs between control, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142-infected, and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic>-infected groups into three categories involving biological process (BP), cellular component (CC), and molecular function (MF) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). From the GO enrichment analysis results, the most significant 10 terms in each function were selected to draw a histogram for display. The similarity in enrichment of GO functions between the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142- and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic>-infected groups was leukocyte and lymphocyte differentiation. The difference between <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142- and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic>-infected groups enriched in GO function was that the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142-infected group was significantly enriched in term related to OXPHOS and mitochondrial respiratory chain complexes. It was speculated that STa mainly affected the OXPHOS function of IPEC-J2 cells and may cause apoptosis by inhibiting the expression of this gene, which needs to be further verified by KEGG pathway enrichment analysis.</p><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>GO classification and functional annotation of MF, CC, and BP. The abscissa in the figure is GO term; the ordinate is the significance level of GO term enrichment, the higher the value, the more significant; the different colors represent the three GO subclasses of BP, CC, and MF, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1545696-g003.jpg"/></fig><p>KEGG is a comprehensive database that integrates genome, chemistry, and system function information. KEGG pathway enrichment considers a <italic toggle="yes">p</italic><sub>adj</sub> of less than 0.05 as the threshold for significant enrichment. From the KEGG enrichment, the most significant 20 KEGG pathways were selected to draw a scatter plot. KEGG pathway analysis was performed to evaluate the biological and ontological significance of DEGs. The results showed that the DEGs were involved in a variety of biological activities. Both <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> infection altered gene expression levels of cancer-related cytokine-cytokine receptor interaction, TNF signaling pathway, and OXPHOS pathway (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). However, DEGs in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142-infected group were more enriched, and the differences in DEGs were more significant.</p><fig position="float" id="fig4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>KEGG pathway classification and functional enrichment. The abscissa is the ratio of the number of differential genes annotated to the KEGG pathway to the total number of differential genes, the ordinate is the KEGG pathway, the size of the dots represents the number of genes annotated to the KEGG pathway, and the color from red to purple represents the significance of enrichment.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1545696-g004.jpg"/></fig><p>Compared with the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic>-infected group, NADH dehydrogenase (ND2), cytochrome C oxidase (COX2), cytochrome B (CYTB), and ATP synthase (ATP6) were significantly downregulated in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142-infected cells (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>). These genes are related to OXPHOS phosphorylation.</p><fig position="float" id="fig5" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>DEGs enrichment analysis between <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1545696-g005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec22"><label>3.3</label><title>Detection of OXPHOS related genes and proteins</title><p>To assess the influence of OXPHOS-related genes on STa-stimulated IPEC-J2 cells, we performed RT-qPCR to examine the changes in ND2, COX2, ATP6, and CYTB. We observed a clear decrease in ND2, COX2, CYTB, and ATP6 in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142-infected group (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6A</xref>) compared with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic>-infected cells. This trend was also observed for ND2 and COX2 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6B</xref>). Similar results were obtained for the jejunum of suckling mice (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figures 6C</xref>,<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">D</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig6" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Mitochondrial respiratory chain gene expression levels. <bold>(A)</bold> mRNA expression by RT-qPCR of IPEC-J2. <bold>(B)</bold> The abundance of ND2 and COXII in IPEC-J2 by WB. <bold>(C)</bold> mRNA expression by RT-qPCR of jejunal tissue in mice. <bold>(D)</bold> The abundance of ND2 and COXII in mice by WB. *means <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, **means <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1545696-g006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec23"><label>3.4</label><title>STa promoted mitochondrial oxidative stress and DNA damage and induced mitochondrial dysfunction</title><p>The antioxidant system maintains the balance of redox reactions, and destruction of this system leads to oxidative stress in cells. SOD, CAT, and GSH are important components of the antioxidant system. Compared with the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic>-infected group, SOD content was increased in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142-infected group, but CAT and GSH content decreased significantly (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7A</xref>). A decreased GSH content is a significant marker of early apoptosis. The above results indicated that STa altered the antioxidant function of cells, and the instability of antioxidant function prevented cells from scavenging ROS over time. The stronger green fluorescence in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 group indicated that STa increased ROS levels (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7B</xref>). If excess ROS cannot be removed in time, it will attack intracellular DNA, causing damage to cell structure and function, or even death. The effect of STa on DNA damage was investigated by measuring deoxyguanosine (8-OHdG) content. Compared with the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> group, the 8-OHdG content in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 group increased significantly (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7C</xref>), which proved that STa induced DNA damage in IPEC-J2 cells. These results suggest that STa causes oxidative damage to cells.</p><fig position="float" id="fig7" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Effects of STa on oxidative damage in IPEC-J2 cells. <bold>(A)</bold> STa increased SOD and decreased GSH and CAT content in IPEC-J2 cells. <bold>(B)</bold> ROS fluorescence of IPEC-J2 cells. ROS generation was increased in IPEC-J2 cells by STa. Left is control group; middle is <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 infected group; right is <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> group. <bold>(C)</bold> Effects of STa on DNA damage in IPEC-J2 cells. STa escalated 8-OHdG level in IPEC-J2, causing DNA damage. <bold>(D)</bold> MMP in IPEC-J2 cells by JC-1. STa decreased MMP in IPEC-J2 cells. <bold>(E)</bold> ATP generation in IPEC-J2 cells increased after treatment with STa. <bold>(F)</bold> STa raised mitochondrial complex I activity. *means <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, **means <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1545696-g007.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec24"><label>3.5</label><title>STa induces mitochondrial dysfunction</title><p>Mitochondrial complex I activity, MMP, and ATP levels were evaluated to examine whether STa induces mitochondrial dysfunction in IPEC-J2 cells. We observed increased green fluorescence in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 group compared with that in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> group, indicating that the MMP decreased (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7D</xref>). Consistent with the effect of STa on the MMP, the production of ATP and mitochondrial complex I activity decreased significantly in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142-infected group (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figures 7E</xref>,<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">F</xref>). These results suggest that STa disrupts mitochondrial integrity and energy production.</p><p>We measured Bax protein expression in IPEC-J2 cells. The expression of the pro-apoptotic protein Bax was remarkably raised and that of the anti-apoptotic protein Bcl-2 was lowered in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142-infected group, compared with the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> -infected group (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8A</xref>). The level of Cyt c in the mitochondria decreased, whereas in the cytoplasm, it showed the opposite trend in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142-infected group (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8A</xref>). Total CYTC protein levels increased (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8B</xref>). These results suggest that the pro-apoptotic molecule Cyt c is released from the mitochondria into the cytoplasm, suggesting that STa-induced apoptosis is associated with the mitochondria. As a downstream molecule of Cyt c, the cleavage of caspase-9 in IPEC-J2 cells was significantly enhanced in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142-infected group compared to the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic>-infected group. As a key executioner of apoptosis, caspase-3 was cleaved and activated in IPEC-J2 cells in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 group, but not in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> group (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8A</xref>). The same results were observed in suckling mice jejunum tissue (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figures 8C</xref>,<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">D</xref>). These results indicate that STa induces the mitochondrial apoptotic pathway.</p><fig position="float" id="fig8" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Effects of STa on the mitochondrial pathway of apoptosis. <bold>(A)</bold> The abundance of mitochondrial apoptosis pathway-related proteins in IPEC-J2 by WB. <bold>(B)</bold> The abundance of Cyt c in IPEC-J2 by immunofluorescence (IF). <bold>(C)</bold> The abundance of mitochondrial apoptosis pathway-related proteins in mice by WB. <bold>(D)</bold> The abundance of Cyt c in mice by immunohistochemistry (IHC). Three-day-old suckling mice were given 3&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>9</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> bacterial suspension, orally and, respectively. The negative control suckling mice were treated with the same dose of PBS.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1545696-g008.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec25"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, we investigated the mechanism of STa action on intestinal epithelial cells by comparing the differences after infection with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 (STa<sup>+</sup>) or <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> (STa<sup>&#8722;</sup>) both <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> (three-day-old suckling mice) and <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> (IPEC-J2 cell line). Studies on the enterotoxins of ETEC could not be conducted in humans, and either suckling mice or piglets in an <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> model were substituted. Studies on the enterotoxins of ETEC usually use suckling mice or piglets as <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> model (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). STa shows biological activity in suckling mice and piglets (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Zhou et al. (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) showed that STa produced the same effect on mouse and porcine enteroids <italic toggle="yes">ex vivo</italic>. The suckling mouse model is traditionally used for detecting STa activity (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19&#8211;21</xref>). Schulz et al. (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) showed that 10<sup>7</sup> CFU <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> 1,676, which produced STa and expressed F41, caused sucking mouse death within 72&#8239;h after oral gavage. The results of STa-induced intestinal edema, diarrhea, and death were consistent with those of previous studies. Some studies have shown that mice show damage to the jejunal villi after treatment with STa, and that the damage caused by STa is dose dependent (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Our results showed that with an increase in the intragastric dose of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142, suckling mice gradually showed intestinal swelling and diarrhea symptoms, and the intestinal villi gradually atrophied and ruptured, all of which support the above views.</p><p>STa generally exerts its effect on the small intestine, particularly the jejunum. The IPEC-J2 cell line is an undifferentiated jejunal epithelial cell line. The <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 strain used in this study contains both K99 and F41 pili, and the ETEC strain expressing these two types of pili bound heavily to IPEC-J2 (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Zhou et al. (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) used IPEC-J2 and <italic toggle="yes">C. elegans</italic> to study cell death caused by DH5&#945; expressing STa, STb, and LT. Our study found that STa damages the cell wall and increases LDH secretion, which proves STa cytotoxicity. Annexin V-FITC/PI staining further indicated that STa increased the apoptosis of IPEC-J2 cells.</p><p>Apoptosis regulates the pathogenesis of several infectious diseases (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Goncalves et al. (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) used the JC-1 probe to characterize NIH-3T3 cells after STb treatment and found that red fluorescence increased, which indicated that MMP decreased and mitochondrial-dependent cell apoptosis increased. RNA-seq data showed that STa significantly decreased the expression of mitochondrial respiratory chain-related genes and downregulated the OXPHOS signaling pathway in IPEC-J2 epithelial cells. OXPHOS is performed by the mitochondrial respiratory chain located in the inner membrane to produce the energy molecule ATP. The mitochondrial respiratory chain consists of five polymeric protein complexes (mitochondrial respiratory chain membrane protein complexes I-V), ubiquinone, and cytochrome C. Complex I is encoded by at least 37 nuclear and seven mitochondrial genes (ND1, ND2, ND3, ND4, ND4L, ND5, and ND6) (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Mitochondrial complex I performs the first step in OXPHOS by converting NADH to NAD<sup>+</sup> to generate the MMP required for ATP production, and produces ROS as a by-product (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Antioxidant enzymes, such as SOD, CAT, glutathione peroxidase (GPX), and GSH, can remove ROS and maintain cell homeostasis. Our study showed that STa reduced CAT and GSH activity and increased ROS levels and SOD activity. Although the increase in SOD activity helps scavenge superoxide radicals, it generates H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and superoxide radicals can generate harmful hydroxyl radicals through the Fenton reaction (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>).</p><p>Excess ROS can attack intracellular biological macromolecules, such as proteins, lipids, and DNA. DNA damage in IPEC-J2 cells was observed by comparing the level of 8-OHdG in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O142 and O142&#916;<italic toggle="yes">estA</italic> groups after Sta exposure, suggesting that DNA damage is likely to be one of the response mechanisms of IPEC-J2 cells to STa. However, ROS and apoptotic protein upregulation damage the mitochondrial membrane and alter membrane permeability, thereby decreasing the MMP (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Krzymi&#324;ska et al. (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) observed that the <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> enterotoxin increased intracellular ROS in HT29 intestinal epithelial cells, leading to a loss of MMP and apoptosis of epithelial cells via mitochondrial depolarization. Our results showed that STa induced ROS to disrupt MMP and lower ATP production, significantly increased the pro-apoptotic protein Bax, and decreased the anti-apoptotic protein Bcl-2. Changes in Bax and Bcl-2 lead to mitochondrial membrane permeability transition, causing nuclear translocation of Cyt c and its release into the cytoplasm, thus increasing cleaved caspase-9/caspase-9 and cleaved caspase-3/caspase-3, suggesting that STa initiates apoptosis via mitochondrial OXPHOS signaling pathways. T-2 toxin (1 and 2&#8239;ng/mL) also reduced MMP, induced Cyt c escape, caspase-3 and caspase-9 activation, and increased the Bax/Bcl-2 ratio after incubating mouse embryonic stem cells for 24&#8239;h (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>).</p><p>Although in this study it was found that STa can activate apoptosis both <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>, and previous bacterial sequencing indicated that STa is the only known toxin component in ETEC O142 bacteria, due to the complex composition of bacteria and their metabolites and secreted substances, it is highly necessary to rule out the influence of other components of the bacterial cells on intestinal epithelial cells. It is essential to use purified STa to infect intestinal epithelial cells.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec26"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, we demonstrated STa toxicity in intestinal epithelial cells <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. We demonstrated that STa cytotoxicity was associated with excessive ROS production. Increased ROS attacks the mitochondria, leading to DNA damage and a decline in ATP, MMP, and Complex I activity. Changes in MMP lead to the release of apoptosis-inducing factors that activate the mitochondrial-mediated apoptosis pathway. Apoptosis of epithelial cells led to the destruction of intestinal epithelial integrity; thus, STa induced small intestinal edema, diarrhea, atrophy, rupture of small intestinal villi, and cell death in a dose-dependent manner.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="fn0001"><p>
<sup>1</sup>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://github.com/tanghaibao/GOatools" ext-link-type="uri">https://github.com/tanghaibao/GOatools</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn id="fn0002"><p>
<sup>2</sup>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.genome.jp/kegg/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.genome.jp/kegg/</ext-link>
</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec27"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are publicly available. These data can be found in CNGBdb repository, accession number CNP0007299.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="sec28"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The animal study was approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) of Northeast Agricultural University (NEAU). The study was conducted in accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="sec29"><title>Author contributions</title><p>MH: Writing &#8211; original draft. WY: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. NL: Data curation, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. SS: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. QF: Methodology, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. BS: Formal analysis, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. JL: Software, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. XD: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec31"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ai-statement" id="sec32"><title>Generative AI statement</title><p>The authors declare that no Gen AI was used in the creation of this manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec33"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec34"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2025.1545696/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2025.1545696/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_1.XLSX" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Receptor for the F4 fimbriae of enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> (ETEC)</article-title>. <source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>4953</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-015-6643-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25967654</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fairbrother</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadeau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gyles</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> in postweaning diarrhea in pigs: an update on bacterial types, pathogenesis, and prevention strategies</article-title>. <source>Anim Health Res Rev</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>39</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/ahr2005105</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16164007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fekete</surname><given-names>PZ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> in veterinary medicine</article-title>. <source>Int J Med Microbiol</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>295</volume>:<fpage>443</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>54</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijmm.2005.07.003</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16238018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Intestinal microbiota mediates enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>-induced diarrhea in piglets</article-title>. <source>BMC Vet Res</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>385</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12917-018-1704-9</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30518356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6282381</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubreuil</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isaacson</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schifferli</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Animal enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>EcoSal Plus</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/ecosalplus.ESP-0006-2016</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27735786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5123703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Injury and mechanism of recombinant <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> expressing STa on piglets colon</article-title>. <source>J Vet Med Sci</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>80</volume>:<fpage>205</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.17-0528</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29187713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5836754</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Establishment of a recombinant <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>-induced piglet diarrhea model</article-title>. <source>Front Biosci</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>1517</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2741/4658</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29293448</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary supplementation with sodium gluconate improves the growth performance and intestinal function in weaned pigs challenged with a recombinant <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> strain</article-title>. <source>BMC Vet Res</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>303</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12917-022-03410-5</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35933350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9356463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alcantara</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oria</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Caspase and bid involvement in <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium difficile</italic> toxin A-induced apoptosis and modulation of toxin a effects by glutamine and alanyl-glutamine in vivo and in vitro</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.74.1.81-87.2006</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16368960</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1346681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>CQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Heat-stable enterotoxin inhibits intestinal stem cell expansion to disrupt the intestinal integrity by downregulating the Wnt/beta-catenin pathway</article-title>. <source>Stem Cells</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>482</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>96</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/stem.3324</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33373490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Heat-labile enterotoxin-induced PERK-CHOP pathway activation causes intestinal epithelial cell apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Front Cell Infect Microbiol</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>244</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2017.00244</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28642847</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5463185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Masso-Welch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Girald Berlingeri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>King-Lyons</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mandell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>LT-IIc, a bacterial type II heat-labile enterotoxin, induces specific lethality in triple negative breast cancer cells by modulation of autophagy and induction of apoptosis and necroptosis</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>85</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms20010085</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30587795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6337683</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shrestha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehdizadeh Gohari</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McClane</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>RIP1, RIP3, and MLKL contribute to cell death caused by <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic> enterotoxin</article-title>. <source>mBio</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e02985</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.02985-19</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31848291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6918092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galindo</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gutierrez</surname><given-names>C</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chopra</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chopra, potential involvement of galectin-3 and SNAP23 in <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila</italic> cytotoxic enterotoxin-induced host cell apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Microb Pathog</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>56</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>68</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2005.11.001</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16426811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic editing of the virulence gene of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> using the CRISPR system</article-title>. <source>PeerJ</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e8881</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.8881</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32292652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7144585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Tannic acid induces the mitochondrial pathway of apoptosis and S phase arrest in porcine intestinal IPEC-J2 cells</article-title>. <source>Toxins</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>397</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins11070397</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31323908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6669611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubreuil</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pig vaccination strategies based on enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> toxins</article-title>. <source>Braz J Microbiol</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>2499</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>509</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s42770-021-00567-3</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34244980</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8270777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreyfus</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frantz</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chemical properties of heat-stable enterotoxins produced by enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> of different host origins</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>. (<year>1983</year>) <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>539</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>48</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/iai.42.2.539-548.1983</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6358024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC264462</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Majali</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asem</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saeed</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Insulin modulates intestinal response of suckling mice to the <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> heat-stable enterotoxin</article-title>. <source>Adv Exp Med Biol</source>. (<year>1999</year>) <volume>473</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4615-4143-1_9</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10659348</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Majali</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asem</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saeed</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Age-dependent variation in the density and affinity of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> heat-stable enterotoxin receptors in mice</article-title>. <source>Adv Exp Med Biol</source>. (<year>1999</year>) <volume>473</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4615-4143-1_12</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10659351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruth</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mainil</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roupie</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frere</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galleni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huygen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>DNA vaccination for the priming of neutralizing antibodies against non-immunogenic STa enterotoxin from enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Vaccine</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>3618</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2004.11.080</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15855022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garbers</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Disruption of the guanylyl cyclase-C gene leads to a paradoxical phenotype of viable but heat-stable enterotoxin-resistant mice</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>. (<year>1997</year>) <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>1590</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI119683</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9294128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC508341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hellemans</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Optimization of a small intestinal segment perfusion model for heat-stable enterotoxin a induced secretion in pigs</article-title>. <source>Vet Immunol Immunopathol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>152</volume>:<fpage>82</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetimm.2012.09.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23159147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brozel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moxley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaushik</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Porcine intestinal epithelial cell lines as a new in vitro model for studying adherence and pathogenesis of enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Vet Microbiol</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>130</volume>:<fpage>191</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2007.12.018</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18261863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabour</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Investigation into <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> models using intestinal epithelial IPEC-J2 cells and <italic toggle="yes">Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> for selecting probiotic candidates to control porcine enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>J Appl Microbiol</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>117</volume>:<fpage>217</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>26</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.12505</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24674595</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Porcine epidemic diarrhea virus induces caspase-independent apoptosis through activation of mitochondrial apoptosis-inducing factor</article-title>. <source>Virology</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>460&#8211;461</volume>:<fpage>180</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2014.04.040</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25010284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7127720</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goncalves</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubreuil</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> STb toxin on NIH-3T3 cells</article-title>. <source>FEMS Immunol Med Microbiol</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>432</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-695X.2009.00541.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19222570</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsukamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Complete mitochondrial DNA sequence of <italic toggle="yes">Conger myriaster</italic> (Teleostei: Anguilliformes): novel gene order for vertebrate mitochondrial genomes and the phylogenetic implications for anguilliform families</article-title>. <source>J Mol Evol</source>. (<year>2001</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>311</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002390010161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11343127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pagniez-Mammeri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loublier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Legrand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benit</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rustin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mitochondrial complex I deficiency of nuclear origin I. Structural genes</article-title>. <source>Mol Genet Metab</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>105</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>72</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymgme.2011.11.188</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22142868</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moncol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Izakovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazur</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Free radicals, metals and antioxidants in oxidative stress-induced cancer</article-title>. <source>Chem Biol Interact</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>160</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cbi.2005.12.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16430879</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dar</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anees</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zargar</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masood</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sofi</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Oxidative stress, mitochondrial dysfunction and neurodegenerative diseases; a mechanistic insight</article-title>. <source>Biomed Pharmacother</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>101</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2015.07.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26349970</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krzymi&#324;ska</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaznowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> spp. induce apoptosis of epithelial cells through an oxidant-dependent activation of the mitochondrial pathway</article-title>. <source>J Med Microbiol</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>60</volume>:<fpage>889</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>98</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.030833-0</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21436367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>T-2 toxin induces apoptosis in differentiated murine embryonic stem cells through reactive oxygen species-mediated mitochondrial pathway</article-title>. <source>Apoptosis</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>895</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>907</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10495-012-0724-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22614820</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Immunomodulation and signaling mechanism of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> GG and its components on porcine intestinal epithelial cells stimulated by lipopolysaccharide</article-title>. <source>J Microbiol Immunol Infect</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>700</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmii.2015.05.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26055689</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><glossary><def-list><title>Glossary</title><def-item><term>ETEC</term><def><p>Enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OXPHOS</term><def><p>Oxidative phosphorylation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LT</term><def><p>Heat-labile enterotoxins</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GC-C</term><def><p>Guanylate cyclase C</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CFTR</term><def><p>Cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulators</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CPE</term><def><p><italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic> enterotoxin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SNAP23</term><def><p>Synaptosomal-associated protein 23</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LB</term><def><p>Luria-Bertani</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CFU</term><def><p>Colony-forming units</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LDH</term><def><p>Lactate dehydrogenase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PI</term><def><p>Propidium iodine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HE</term><def><p>Hematoxylin-eosin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GO</term><def><p>Gene Ontology</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KEGG</term><def><p>Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SDS-PAGE</term><def><p>Sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TBST</term><def><p>Tris-buffered saline-0.1% Tween 20</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VDAC1</term><def><p>Voltage dependent anion channel protein 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Bax</term><def><p>Bcl-2 associated X</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DCFH-DA</term><def><p>2&#8242;,7&#8242;-Dichlorofluorescin diacetate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CAT</term><def><p>Catalase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>8-OHDG</term><def><p>8-Hydroxy-2-deoxyguanosine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IF</term><def><p>Immunofluorescence</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IHC</term><def><p>Immunohistochemistry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BP</term><def><p>Biological process</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MF</term><def><p>Molecular function</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>COX2</term><def><p>Cytochrome C oxidase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ATP6</term><def><p>ATP synthase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>STa</term><def><p>Heat-stable enterotoxins</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ROS</term><def><p>Reactive oxygen species</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ST</term><def><p>Heat-stable enterotoxins</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>cGMPKII</term><def><p>cGMP-dependent protein kinase II</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LT-IIc</term><def><p>Heat-labile enterotoxin IIc</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Act</term><def><p>Cytotoxic enterotoxin of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic></p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ATP</term><def><p>Adenosine triphosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DMEM</term><def><p>Dulbecco&#8217;s modified Eagle&#8217;s medium</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PBS</term><def><p>Phosphate buffered saline</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MOI</term><def><p>Multiplicity of infection</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TEM</term><def><p>Transmission electron microscopy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>cDNA</term><def><p>Complementary deoxyribonucleic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DEGs</term><def><p>Differentially expressed genes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RIPA</term><def><p>Radio immunoprecipitation assay</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NC</term><def><p>Nitrocellulose</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RT</term><def><p>Room temperature</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Bcl-2</term><def><p>B-cell lymphoma 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Cyt c</term><def><p>Cytochrome C</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SOD</term><def><p>Superoxide dismutase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GSH</term><def><p>Glutathione</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>&#916;&#936;m, MMP</term><def><p>Mitochondrial membrane potential</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DAPI</term><def><p>4&#8242;,6-Diamidino-2-phenylindole dihydrochloride</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>adj</term><def><p>Adjusted <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CC</term><def><p>Cellular component</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ND2</term><def><p>NADH dehydrogenase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CYTB</term><def><p>Cytochrome B</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GPX</term><def><p>Glutathione peroxidase</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></back></article></pmc-articleset>