<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12315916</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12315916.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12315916</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12315916</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40756807</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2025.1615674</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> on growth performance, immune functions, cecal microbiota, and brain metabolites in Sansui ducks</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yongcai</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2695196/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/resources/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qiaoqun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names initials="L">Linli</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/resources/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names initials="S">Shenglin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2022537/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/funding-acquisition/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/visualization/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Key Laboratory of Animal Genetics, Breeding and Reproduction in the Plateau Mountainous Region, Ministry of Education, Guizhou University</institution>, <addr-line>Guiyang</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>School of Animal Technology and Innovation, Institute of Agricultural Technology, Suranaree University of Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Nakhon Ratchasima</addr-line>, <country>Thailand</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0002"><p>Edited by: Sadarman Sadarman, State Islamic University of Sultan Syarif Kasim Riau, Indonesia</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0003"><p>Reviewed by: Baseer Ahmad, Muhammad Nawaz Shareef University of Agriculture, Pakistan</p><p>Gholib Gholib, Syiah Kuala University, Indonesia</p><p>Mohammad Miftakhus Sholikin, National Research and Innovation Agency (BRIN), Indonesia</p><p>Mochamad Dzaky Alifian, IPB University, Indonesia</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Shenglin Yang, <email>Shenglinyang@126.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ecorrected"><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">480746</issue-id><elocation-id>1615674</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>09</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>08</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-08-04 15:25:26.480"><day>04</day><month>08</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2025 Zhu, Wu, Luo and Yang.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Zhu, Wu, Luo and Yang</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-12-1615674.pdf"/><abstract><p><italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic>, recognized for their antioxidant and immunomodulatory properties, have demonstrated potential benefits. However, the specific mechanisms by which these herbs impact poultry health, particularly regarding alterations in gut microbiota and brain metabolite profiles, remain insufficiently investigated. This study aimed to investigate the effects of <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> supplementation on the growth performance, immunity, cecal microbiota, and brain metabolites in Sansui ducks. A total of 216 one-day-old ducks were randomly assigned to three treatments for a 35-day trial, each with 6 replicates of 12 ducks. The dietary treatments included a basal diet (T3), a basal diet supplemented with 40&#8239;mg/kg <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> (T1), and a basal diet supplemented with 40&#8239;mg/kg <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> (T2). The results showed that both <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum</italic> treatments significantly improved final body weight (by 3.0 and 4.1%, respectively) and increased serum IgG and IgM levels by 7.4 and 9.0%, and decreased feed conversion rates by 5.4 and 5.0%, respectively, compared to the control (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;&#8239;0.05). Notably, <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> supplementation significantly increased the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Saccharibacteria</italic>, and significantly decreased the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Actinobacteria</italic> compared to the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;&#8239;0.05). <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> treatment increased the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Megamonas</italic> compared to the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;&#8239;0.05). Brain metabolite analysis showed that <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> increased glutamine (Gln) levels by 18.4% and decreased <italic toggle="yes">&#947;</italic>-aminobutyric acid (GABA), tyrosine (Tyr), and acetylcholine (Ach) by 19.7, 14.6, and 22.5%, respectively (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;&#8239;0.05). <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> increased 5-Hydroxyindoleacetic acid (5-HIAA) concentration by 31.2% (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;&#8239;0.05). Correlation analysis indicated associations between gut microbiota (<italic toggle="yes">Villanella</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Anaerosporobacter</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Anaerofustis</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Flavonifractor</italic>) changes and brain metabolites (GABA, Ach, and Glutamic [Glu]), suggesting the potential influence of these herbs through the microbiota-gut-brain axis. Supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Verbena officinalis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> enhanced growth performance, immunity, and brain neurochemical profiles, potentially through gut microbiota modulation. These herbs show promise as functional feed additives in duck production.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Verbena</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic></kwd><kwd>duck</kwd><kwd>immunity</kwd><kwd>growth performance</kwd><kwd>brain metabolite</kwd><kwd>microbiota</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that financial support was received for the research and/or publication of this article. This study was supported by the General Program of the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 31960682).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="59"/><page-count count="13"/><word-count count="8844"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Animal Nutrition and Metabolism</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Antibiotics are commonly employed in the poultry industry to enhance growth and improve feed efficiency by promoting intestinal health (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). However, the widespread and prolonged use of antibiotics has led to the rise of resistance, and the presence of antibiotic residues in poultry meat and waste poses direct or indirect risks to both human and animal health, and countries are taking antibiotics more seriously (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Therefore, these concerns have prompted an increasing interest in finding natural and efficient alternatives to antibiotics, particularly those that can enhance intestinal health and promote growth performance (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>).</p><p>Natural feed additives, including herbal supplements, have shown promise as potential alternatives to antibiotics in poultry. Previous studies have indicated that the beneficial effects of Chinese herbs on poultry include promoting growth (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), enhancing immunity (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), and regulating intestinal microbiota (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Among these, <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic>, two Chinese herbs, are also utilized as feed supplements owing to their distinct biological activities, including antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, antibacterial, and growth-promoting properties. Studies have indicated that bioactive compounds in these herbs, including flavonoids, verbascoside (from <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic>), and resveratrol (from <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic>), play crucial roles in promoting growth, improving feed efficiency, and maintaining intestinal health in animals (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). The flavonoids in hawthorn have pharmacological effects, including improving intestinal flora and preventing neuronal cytopathy, hypertension, hyperlipidemia, hyperglycemia, and tumors (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). The main active components of <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> are polyphenols, in particular verbascoside, that improve gut health in poultry, with a stabilizing effect on gut microbiota and a positive effect on productive parameters (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Its neuroprotective effects suggest a potential influence on neurotransmitter pathways relevant to the gut-brain axis. Previous studies have shown that pigs fed a diet enriched with verbascoside had improved growth and feed efficiency (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Additionally, studies have shown that dietary resveratrol supplementation can enhance the immune response, modulate the intestinal microbiota, and improve feed efficiency in poultry (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Moreover, resveratrol has been reported to influence gut microbiota composition and increase central serotonin and dopamine levels, further supporting its relevance in gut-brain axis modulation (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). However, the precise mechanisms through which these herbal supplements exert their effects on poultry performance and gut health, particularly the connection between gut microbiota and brain metabolites, remain underexplored.</p><p>The bidirectional communication between the gut microbiota and the brain is termed the microbiota&#8211;gut&#8211;brain axis. The gut microbiota is known to influence brain function through the production of metabolites, which in turn affect various physiological processes, including immune modulation, behavior, and metabolism (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). While studies have primarily focused on the gut&#8217;s role in influencing metabolic processes, less is known about how dietary supplements like <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> affect this microbiome-brain communication. It is hypothesized that herbal supplementation could impact the composition of the gut microbiota, which may subsequently alter the levels of brain metabolites involved in neurotransmission and neurophysiological processes. Key neurotransmitters implicated in this axis include GABA, dopamine (DA), norepinephrine (NE), serotonin (5-HT), and histamine (His), which are either produced or modulated by intestinal microbes and have been shown to affect stress responses and cognitive functions (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Despite growing interest in this field, the precise mechanisms linking microbial shifts to neurochemical changes remain poorly defined, particularly in poultry models.</p><p>Indigenous poultry breeds such as the Sansui duck offer a promising model for gut-brain axis studies due to their distinctive gastrointestinal physiology and heightened sensitivity to dietary modulation. Moreover, their stable genetic background and consistent performance under varied feeding conditions make them suitable for investigating the interplay between herbal supplements, gut microbiota, and brain metabolites. By combining growth performance data, cecal microbiota analysis, and brain metabolite profiling, this research seeks to uncover the complex interplay between diet, gut ecology, and brain biochemistry, ultimately contributing novel insights into the potential of herbal supplementation as a natural alternative to antibiotics in poultry production. We hypothesize that dietary supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Verbena officinalis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> can improve growth performance and immune function in Sansui ducks by modulating cecal microbiota composition and altering brain neurotransmitter-related metabolites, thereby influencing the microbiota&#8211;gut&#8211;brain axis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec3"><label>2.1</label><title>Animal ethics</title><p>The experiment was carried out at the Guizhou University farm in accordance with the approved protocol, as authorized by the Animal Ethics Committee of Guizhou University (Guiyang, China; No. EAE-GZU-2022-E032).</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>2.2</label><title>Birds, experimental design, and diets</title><p>Herbs (<italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> powder) were purchased from Ju Chun Tang Chinese Herbal Medicine Sales Co., LTD., Bozhou City, Anhui Province, China. The feeding process was mixed in powder form. <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> (powder obtained from dried <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> roots) is rich in flavonoids and verbascoside (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> (powder obtained from dried <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> roots) is rich in resveratrol (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Both herbs were ground to pass through a 100-mesh sieve before being uniformly mixed into the diet. No further chemical standardization or quantification of the active compounds was performed in this study. A total of 216 female Sansui ducks (1-day-old) with similar body weight were supplied by Sanyuan Agricultural Development Co., Ltd., Guizhou, China. Sansui ducks are an indigenous Chinese breed known for stable genetics and sensitivity to dietary interventions, and randomly divided into three treatments of 12 ducks each (6 replicates/treatment), housed in individual cages (100&#8239;cm length &#215; 100&#8239;cm width &#215; 120&#8239;cm height). The dietary treatments were the control (T3) group: a basal diet; <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> (T1) group: a basal diet with 40&#8239;mg/kg <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic>; <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> (T2) group: a basal diet with 40&#8239;mg/kg <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic>. Ambient temperature was maintained at 33&#8239;&#177;&#8239;2&#176;C during the first week and gradually reduced to 25&#176;C by the end of the experiment. Humidity ranged between 55 and 70%. The composition and nutrient levels of the diets are shown in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The 40&#8239;mg/kg dose was based on an unpublished graduate thesis by the first author, which identified this level as optimal for improving growth, immunity, and gut microbiota in Sansui ducks. Diets were formulated to meet nutritional requirements according to the recommendations of the National Research Council (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), containing 2,800&#8239;kcal of metabolizable energy/kg and 15% crude protein, and were maintained on a 16-h light cycle daily, with water available ad libitum. At the end of 35&#8239;days of age, six ducks were randomly selected from each of the three groups following a 12-h fasting period. The pen number and individual body weight of each duck were recorded prior to their slaughter via cervical dislocation. Approximately 3&#8239;mL of blood was collected from the subwing vein using a vacuum coagulation tube, allowed to stand at 25&#176;C for 2&#8239;h, and then placed on ice. After coagulation, the serum was separated and centrifuged at 3,000&#8239;rpm for 10&#8239;min to eliminate impurities. The resulting supernatant was transferred to a clean centrifuge tube and stored at &#8722;20&#176;C for further analysis. Cecal content and brain tissue samples were collected from the same ducks immediately after slaughter on day 35, ensuring that microbial and neurochemical data used for correlation analysis originated from the same individuals. Whole brains were isolated, rinsed in ice-cold phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) to remove blood and other contaminants, immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen, and then stored at &#8722;80&#176;C for metabolite analysis. For metabolite analysis. The entire brain tissue was homogenized, and no dissection of specific brain regions (e.g., hypothalamus) was performed. The cecum contents samples were collected, quickly frozen in liquid nitrogen, and stored in a refrigerator at &#8722;20&#176;C for subsequent analyses.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Composition and nutrient levels of the experimental diets (air-dry basis).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Ingredients</th><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Nutrient level<xref rid="tfn2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corn</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.75</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP (%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean meal</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.40</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ME (MJ/kg)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat bran</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crude fiber (%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RaPeseed cake</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca (%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.37</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CaHPO<sub>4</sub></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P (%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limestone</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.25</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lysine (%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NaCl</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methionine (%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Premix<xref rid="tfn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn1"><label>a</label><p>Pemix provided per kilogram of diet: vitamin A, 4000&#8239;IU, vitamin E, 20&#8239;mg; vitamin K3, 2&#8239;mg; vitamin B1, 3.5&#8239;mg; vitamin B12, 0.01&#8239;mg; niacin, 50&#8239;mg; folic acid, 1.0&#8239;mg; Cu, 10&#8239;mg; Fe, 80&#8239;mg; Mn, 60&#8239;mg; Zn, 60&#8239;mg; I, 0.4&#8239;mg; Se, 0.2&#8239;mg; Calcium Pantotherate, 10&#8239;mg; Pyridoxol, 2.5&#8239;mg; biotin, 0.1&#8239;mg.</p></fn><fn id="tfn2"><label>b</label><p>ME is calculated, and the rest are measured values.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>2.3</label><title>Determination of immunoglobulin levels in the serum</title><p>An enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) was used to determine the levels of immunoglobulin (Ig)A, IgG, and IgM, levels in the serum. All commercial ELISA kits used for testing were purchased from Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute. The catalog numbers were: IgA &#8211; H197, IgG &#8211; H164, and IgM &#8211; H195. Assays were performed according to the manufacturer&#8217;s instructions. Briefly, 50&#8239;&#956;L of serum samples or standards were added to microplate wells pre-coated with specific antibodies and incubated at 37&#176;C for 1&#8239;h. After washing, horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated antibodies were added and incubated for an additional 30&#8239;min. The wells were washed again, followed by the addition of TMB substrate solution. After a 15-min incubation in the dark, the stop solution was added, and absorbance was read at 450&#8239;nm using a microplate reader (BioTek Instruments, USA). Immunoglobulin concentrations were calculated based on standard curves prepared for each analyte.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><label>2.4</label><title>Bacterial DNA extraction and 16S rRNA gene sequencing</title><p>DNA was extracted from the contents of the cecum using the QIAamp DNA Stool Mini Kit (catalog NO. 51504, Qiagen, CA, USA) following the manufacturer&#8217;s instructions. The V3-V4 region of the bacterial 16S rRNA gene was PCR amplified using primers 338F (5&#8242;-ACTCCTACGGGAGGCAGCA-3&#8242;) and 806R (5&#8242;-GGACTACHVGGGTWTCTAAT-3&#8242;). All PCR products have been recovered using the AxyPrep DNA gel recovery kit and quantified using the FTC-3000TM real-time PCR instrument. After obtaining the DNA fragment sequence, the QIAamp DNA Stool Mini Kit was used to construct the library, Illumina&#8217;s Miseq PE300 platform was used for sequencing, and the sequencing was completed at Shanghai Weiji Biotechnology Co., Ltd. (Shanghai, China). For 16S rRNA gene analysis, raw sequence data were subjected to quality control using QIIME2<xref rid="fn0001" ref-type="fn"><sup>1</sup></xref>, which removed low-quality sequences and potential contaminants. UPARSE software was used to cluster operational taxonomic units (OTUs) based on 97% sequence similarity. Alpha diversity of the microbial communities was assessed using Chao1, Shannon, and Simpson indices in QIIME2. Beta diversity was evaluated through principal coordinate analysis (PCoA). Differences in relative bacterial abundance were determined using the nonparametric Kruskal-Wallis sum-rank test. Bacterial biomarkers distinguishing the microbial communities across all groups were identified using linear discriminant analysis (LDA) effect size (LEfSe) (LDA&#8239;&gt;&#8239;2.5, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05). The co-occurrence of microbial communities was analyzed for the top 40 genera based on significant Spearman correlations (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05).</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><label>2.5</label><title>Brain metabolite analysis</title><p>Accurately weigh 15&#8239;mg of sample into a 2&#8239;mL EP tube, accurately add 200&#8239;&#956;L of 10% formic acid methanol solution-ddH<sub>2</sub>O (1:1. V/V) solution, add 50&#8239;mg of glass beads; put it into a high-throughput tissue grinder and oscillate at 60&#8239;Hz for 1&#8239;min, repeat twice; centrifuge at 12000 rpm and 4&#176;C for 5&#8239;min, take 50&#8239;&#956;L of supernatant, accurately add 50&#8239;&#956;L of dual isotope internal standard with a concentration of 100&#8239;ppb, vortex and oscillate for 30&#8239;s, filter the supernatant through a 0.22&#8239;&#956;m membrane, and add the filtrate to the detection bottle (detection of low-content substances). Take 10&#8239;&#956;L of the original supernatant, add 490&#8239;&#956;L of 10% formic acid methanol solution-ddH<sub>2</sub>O (1:1. V/V) solution, vortex and oscillate for 30&#8239;s, take 100&#8239;&#956;L of the diluted sample, add 100&#8239;&#956;L of 100&#8239;ppb dual isotope internal standard, vortex and oscillate for 30&#8239;s, filter the supernatant through a 0.22&#8239;&#956;m membrane, and add the filtrate to the detection bottle (detection of high-content substances) vial for liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry (LC&#8211;MS) analysis. Weigh appropriate amounts of 10 brain metabolites (GABA, Gln, Glu, His, L-Histidine [L-His], Tyr, Tryptamine [Trp], Ach, NE, and 5-HIAA) standards and prepare single standard stock solutions with 10% formic acid in methanol. Take appropriate amounts of each stock solution to prepare mixed standards, dilute each to the appropriate concentration with 10% formic acid in methanol, and prepare working standard solutions. For LC&#8211;MS analysis, chromatographic conditions: chromatographic column: ACQUITY UPLC BEH C18 column (2.1&#8239;&#215;&#8239;100&#8239;mm, 1.7&#8239;&#956;m, Waters, USA), injection volume 5&#8239;&#956;L, column temperature 40&#176;C, mobile phase A-10% methanol&#8211;water (containing 0.1% formic acid), B-50% methanol&#8211;water (containing 0.1% formic acid). Gradient elution conditions are 0&#8211;1&#8239;min, 20&#8211;100% B; 1&#8211;7&#8239;min, 100% B; 7&#8211;7.5&#8239;min, 100&#8211;20% B; 7.5&#8211;11&#8239;min, 20% B. Flow rate 0.4&#8239;mL/min. Mass spectrometry conditions: electrospray ionization (ESI) source, positive ionization mode. The ion source temperature is 500&#176;C, the ion source voltage is 5,500&#8239;V, the collision gas is 6&#8239;psi, the curtain gas is 30&#8239;psi, and the nebulizer gas and auxiliary gas are 50&#8239;psi. Multiple reaction monitoring (MRM) scanning was used.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><label>2.6</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data for growth performance, immunoglobulin levels, and brain metabolite concentrations were analysed using SPSS software (version 27.0). All data values were stated as mean &#177; SEM. One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) and Tukey&#8217;s <italic toggle="yes">post hoc</italic> test were employed to determine the significance of mean differences. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values were considered statistically different at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05. Alpha diversity analysis was calculated based on the Chao index, Shannon index, and Simpson index using QIIME2 (v1.9.1). Beta diversity was calculated based on the unweighted UniFrac distance, and statistical comparisons among groups were performed with permutational ANOVA. Figures were generated in GraphPad Prism 10.0 software (GraphPad Software Inc., San Diego, CA). Spearman rank correlation analysis assessed the relationship between microbiota and other brain metabolites.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec9"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec10"><label>3.1</label><title>Growth performance and serum immunoglobulins</title><p>The effect of <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> supplementation in duck diets on growth performance and serum immunoglobulins is shown in <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Dietary supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> significantly increased final body weight, as well as IgG and IgM levels, while decreasing the feed conversion ratio compared to the ducks fed with the control diets (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> on growth performance and plasma immunoglobulins of Sansui ducks.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Item</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Groups</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P-</italic>value</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T 3(Control)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1 (<italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic>)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T2 (<italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Body weight, g/duck</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205.67<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211.90<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214.11<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 35 d</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feed intake, g/ducks</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">790.40</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">798.61</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">792.32</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.307</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 35 d</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feed conversion ratio</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.52<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 35 d</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Serum immunoglobulins</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgA (g/L)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.112</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgG (g/L)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgM (g/L)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>T3: feed with the basic diet; T2: feed with basic diet and 40&#8239;mg/kg <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic>; T1: feed with basic diet and 40&#8239;mg/kg <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic>. <sup>a, b</sup> Means within each row with different superscripts are significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec11"><label>3.2</label><title>Microbial composition of the cecum</title><p>The composition of the microbial community in the cecal digesta using 16S rRNA amplicon sequencing is shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. The Chao index estimates the species&#8217; richness (i.e., the number of species present) in a treatment. Simpson&#8217;s index measures microbial richness or evenness, while Shannon entropy measures species richness and the community&#8217;s evenness in a sample or within a treatment. The Chao index, Simpson index, and Shannon index in the alpha diversity among the groups were not significantly different (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>). The Venn diagram (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>) shows that 3 groups contained a total of 340 shared OTUs, while the T3, T2, and T1 groups had 343, 386, and 647 unique OTUs, respectively. The PCoA by Unweighted UniFrac distance indicated that the control group was separated from the other groups (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Effect of dietary supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> on diversity of the cecal microbiota in Sansui ducks. <bold>(A)</bold> Chao index, Shannon index, and Simpson index. <bold>(B)</bold> A Venn diagram based on the OTU level. <bold>(C)</bold> Principal coordinate analysis (PCoA) based on Unweighted UniFrac. T3: feed with the basic diet; T2: feed with basic diet and 40&#8239;mg/kg <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic>; T1: feed with basic diet and 40&#8239;mg/kg <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1615674-g001.jpg"><alt-text content-type="machine-generated">Panel A shows three box plots comparing metrics (chao, shannon diversity, simpson diversity) for T1, T2, and T3, all with non-significant Kruskal-Wallis p-values. Panel B is a Venn diagram showing overlap among T1, T2, and T3 with specific numbers in each section, indicating shared and unique elements. Panel C presents a Principal Coordinates Analysis (PCoA) plot, displaying three groups (T1, T2, T3) with distinct clusters, based on two principal coordinates, PC1 and PC2.</alt-text></graphic></fig><p>Additionally, <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> were the major phylum species across all groups (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). Further analysis of the phylum composition of the top 25 ranked groups showed that a total of 5 differential bacteria were identified in each group, with a significant increase in the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Spirochaetae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Saccharibacteria</italic> in the <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> supplemented group compared to control group, and a significant decrease in the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Fimicutes</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Actinobacteria</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>). Taxon-based analysis at the genus level revealed <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroides</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Fusobacterium</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Megamonas</italic> as the predominant genera (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">Collinsella</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Subdoligranulum</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Peptoclostridium</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Sellimonas</italic> were significantly enriched in the <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> supplemented group at the genus level as compared to the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05), while supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> significantly increased the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Megamonas</italic> compared to the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2D</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Effect of dietary supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> on composition of the cecal microbiota in Sansui ducks. <bold>(A)</bold> Microbial composition at the phylum level. <bold>(B)</bold> Significantly abundant microbiota at the phylum level. <bold>(C)</bold> Microbial composition at the genus level. <bold>(D)</bold> Significantly abundant microbiota at the genus level. <sup>a,b</sup> indicates significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804;&#8239;0.05). T3: feed with the basic diet; T2: feed with basic diet and 40&#8239;mg/kg <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic>; T1: feed with basic diet and 40&#8239;mg/kg <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1615674-g002.jpg"><alt-text content-type="machine-generated">Four-panel image showing bacterial abundance data. Panel A: Bar chart of bacterial phylum abundance across T1, T2, T3, with Bacteroidetes and Firmicutes as major groups. Panel B: Bar chart of key phylum species differences with varying relative abundances. Panel C: Bar chart of bacterial genus abundance across T1, T2, T3, with unclassified and Megamonas groups notable. Panel D: Bar chart of key genus species differences with differing relative abundances across samples T1, T2, T3.</alt-text></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="sec12"><label>3.3</label><title>LEfSe analysis of species</title><p>To identify the specific bacteria that were characteristic of the 3 groups, LEfSe was used (expressed as values of linear discriminant analysis) in further evaluating the differences in bacterial composition among the different dietary treatments (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). At the phylum level, a great abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Actinobacteria</italic> in the control (T3) group, and <italic toggle="yes">Spirochaetae</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Saccharibacteria</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Verrucomicrobia</italic> in the <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> supplemented (T1) group were detected. At the genus level, <italic toggle="yes">Collinsella</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Peptoclostridium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Subdoligranulum</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Sellimonas</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Intestinmonas</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Anaerofustis</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Anaerosporobacter</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacteriales</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Enterorhabdus</italic> in the control (T3) group, and <italic toggle="yes">Megamonas</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Catenisphaera</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Anaeroplasma</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Eubacterium</italic> in the <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> (T2) group, and <italic toggle="yes">Treponema</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Succinatimonas</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Ruminoccus</italic> in the <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> supplemented (T1) group were detected.</p><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Linear discriminant analysis (LDA) effect size (LEfSe) of intestinal microbiota (LDA&#8239;&gt;&#8239;2.5, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05). T3: feed with the basic diet; T2: feed with basic diet and 40&#8239;mg/kg <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic>; T1: feed with basic diet and 40&#8239;mg/kg <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1615674-g003.jpg"><alt-text content-type="machine-generated">Bar chart showing bacterial taxa distinguished by LDA score across three groups: T1 (green), T2 (red), and T3 (blue). T3 taxa have highest scores, dominated by Firmicutes and Actinobacteria. T1 and T2 exhibit lower scores across various taxa.</alt-text></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="sec13"><label>3.4</label><title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> on the level of the brain metabolites of Sansui ducks</title><p>The effect of dietary <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> supplementation on the concentrations of brain metabolites in Sansui ducks is presented in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>. Tukey&#8217;s multiple comparison tests indicated that dietary supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> significantly reduced the GABA and Tyr concentrations (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05), and both <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> supplementation significantly increased the Gln concentrations compared to the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05). Based on Tukey&#8217;s multiple comparison tests, dietary supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> significantly decreased Glu and Ach concentrations (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05), while <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> supplementation significantly increased 5-HIAA concentration compared to the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05).</p><fig position="float" id="fig4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Effect of dietary supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> on brain metabolites in Sansui ducks. *Indicates significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804;&#8239;0.05). T3: feed with the basic diet; T2: feed with basic diet and 40&#8239;mg/kg <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic>; T1: feed with basic diet and 40&#8239;mg/kg <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1615674-g004.jpg"><alt-text content-type="machine-generated">Bar charts showing concentrations of different neurotransmitters in nanograms per milliliter for three treatment groups (T1, T2, T3). In the first chart: GABA, Gln, and Glu show significant differences. The second chart illustrates differences in Tyr. The third chart shows differences in Ach and 5-HIAA. Error bars indicate standard deviation, and asterisks denote statistically significant differences.</alt-text></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="sec14"><label>3.5</label><title>Correlation between brain metabolite concentrations and cecal microbiota in Sansui ducks</title><p>To find out the correlation between brain metabolites and cecal microbiota, we performed a Spearman correlation analysis between the top 40 differential bacteria and brain metabolite concentrations in Sansui ducks treated with <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum,</italic> as shown in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>. The level of Glu showed a positive correlation with 5 bacterial genera (<italic toggle="yes">Intestinimonas, Peptoclostridium, Tyzzerella, Lactobacillus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Gallibacterium</italic>) and a negative correlation with 3 major bacterial genera (<italic toggle="yes">Elusimicrobium, Coprococcus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Synergistes</italic>). The level of Ach showed a positive correlation with 2 main bacterial genera (<italic toggle="yes">Fusobacterium</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Flavonifractor</italic>) and a negative correlation with 3 bacterial genera (<italic toggle="yes">Olsenella, Megasphaera,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Shuttleworthia</italic>). The level of Gln had no negative correlation with all bacterial genera but showed a positive correlation with 4 bacterial genera (<italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus, Gallibacterium, Veillonella,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Anaerosporobacter</italic>). Moreover, the GABA level showed a positive correlation with 4 bacterial genera (<italic toggle="yes">Veillonella, Anaerosporobacter, Anaerofustis,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Flavonifractor</italic>) and a negative correlation with <italic toggle="yes">Weissella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Ruminococcus</italic>. The level of 5-HIAA showed a positive correlation with <italic toggle="yes">Anaerofustis</italic> and a negative correlation with 3 bacterial genera (<italic toggle="yes">Weissella, Staphylococcus,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Coprobacter</italic>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig5" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Spearman&#8217;s correlation analysis between the abundances of cecal microbiota and brain metabolite concentrations. Significant correlations are noted by 0.01&#8239;&lt;&#8239;<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&#8804;&#8239;0.05*, 0.001&#8239;&lt;&#8239;<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&#8804;&#8239;0.01**, Red represents positive correlation and blue represents negative correlation.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1615674-g005.jpg"><alt-text content-type="machine-generated">Heatmap showing hierarchical clustering of bacterial genera with neurotransmitter correlations. Genera are listed vertically, neurotransmitters horizontally. Colors range from blue (negative correlation) to red (positive correlation). Dendrograms indicate clustering relationships.</alt-text></graphic></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec15"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>In traditional herbal medicine, <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> are polyphenolic plants that have been reported to possess antioxidant and immunostimulant properties (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Our results showed that ducks fed <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> significantly increased final body weight and decreased feed conversion ratio, indicating improved feed efficiency. These improvements in growth performance align with previous studies on <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> bioactive substances, such as flavonoids and verbascoside from <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic>, and resveratrol from <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic>, which are known to enhance nutrient absorption, modulate gut health, and reduce oxidative stress in poultry (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), which also shows that it might be ascribed to these bioactive components from <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> improved overall growth performance in poultry. Some studies reported that supplementation of 400&#8239;mg/kg resveratrol in diets led to an improvement in the growth performance of broiler chickens (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Previous research has supplemented the diets of 25 to 42-day-old broiler chickens with <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> leaf powder at 0.5 and 1.0%. At the higher dose, verbena leaf powder increased average weight gain and feed intake, while decreasing feed conversion ratio, compared to the control group (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). However, although <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> are known to contain bioactive constituents such as resveratrol and verbascoside, we did not quantify these compounds in this study.</p><p>Owing to the crucial role in the immune system, immunoglobulins are commonly used to evaluate the immune status of animals, and three main types, IgA, IgG, and IgM, are present in birds, which could resist the intrusion of a variety of pathogens and toxins (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). The IgG is the major avian systemic antibody that acts upon infection with an immunoglobulin that occurs as a second antibody reaction after IgM production (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Our results showed that <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> enhanced the immune status, evidenced by elevated serum levels of IgG and IgM, suggesting that these herbs may exert immunomodulatory effects. Similar increases in IgG and IgM concentrations upon treatment with <italic toggle="yes">Lemon Verbena</italic> and resveratrol have been confirmed in broilers (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). In addition, a study showed that dietary supplementation of 300 or 600&#8239;mg resveratrol/kg enhanced total Ig and IgG in the broilers, compared to the control treatment at d 22 (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). The bioactive components from <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> have been shown to promote humoral immunity by activating lymphocyte proliferation and antibody production (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Although IgA levels did not change significantly, the increase in IgG and IgM supports the hypothesis that these herbal supplements may enhance mucosal and systemic immune responses, possibly contributing to better disease resistance and growth.</p><p>It is very important to study fecal microbiota for the growth and health of animals (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). The Chao1, Shannon, and Simpson indices reflect the richness and diversity of microbiota. In our study, despite no significant differences in alpha diversity indices (Chao1, Shannon, and Simpson), the beta diversity (PCoA analysis) clearly showed that the microbial communities in the control group were distinctly separated from those in the <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> groups. These observations are consistent with those of several studies on resveratrol supplementation (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). These findings suggest that <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> supplementation altered the composition of the cecal microbiota without substantially affecting overall diversity. The lack of significant changes in alpha diversity may be attributed to several factors. First, it is possible that the 35-day duration of the experiment, while appropriate for capturing early-life microbial shifts, may not be long enough to induce measurable changes in species richness or evenness, particularly if the existing microbiota is resilient or functionally redundant. Previous studies have shown that microbial colonization and community restructuring occur rapidly during the early life of poultry and can be influenced by various factors, including diet and environmental exposure (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Second, the gut microbiota of ducks during the early growth phase may possess a relatively stable core microbial structure that resists substantial disruption from short-term dietary interventions. This microbial stability could serve a protective function, allowing for compositional shifts (as seen in beta diversity) without compromising overall diversity. Therefore, future studies extending beyond this early-life window are needed to determine whether the observed compositional shifts lead to sustained changes in microbial ecology or neurobiological function.</p><p>Microbiota in the gut play an important role in digestion, metabolism, immunity, and pathogen defense in animals (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). In this study, <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> were identified as the dominant phyla in the cecal contents of Sansui ducks, a result that aligns with previous reports on the microbiota of ducks (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Studies have demonstrated that <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> negatively affect growth performance and intestinal barrier function, but <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> exert a positive influence in these areas (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> are crucial for carbohydrate fermentation and demonstrate inhibitory effects on pathogen colonization (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Furthermore, the <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> ratio serves as a key indicator of microbiota functionality (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Our results indicated that supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> significantly increased <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> abundance, while decreasing <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> abundance compared to the control group, thereby increasing the <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> ratio, a result that is consistent with previous studies (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Given the increased <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> ratio, alongside the elevated final body weight and decreased feed conversion ratio, we proposed that the changes in the <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> ratio induced by <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> supplementation may be responsible for the observed improvement in growth performance. Moreover, the study showed that rumen-protected lysine changed the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Proteobacteria</italic>, indicating that rumen-protected lysine affects the microbial community in the hindgut of dairy cows (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). These findings suggest that <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> affect the microbial community in the cecum of ducks. In addition, supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> significantly increased <italic toggle="yes">Saccharibacteria</italic> abundance, while decreasing <italic toggle="yes">Actinobacteria</italic> abundance compared to the control group. <italic toggle="yes">Actinobacteria</italic> are associated with dysbiosis and inflammation (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). On the other hand, <italic toggle="yes">Actinobacteria</italic> have the ability to effectively degrade cellulose, hemicellulose, and lignin (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>), indicating supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> enhances immunity and feed efficiency. To our best knowledge, the role of <italic toggle="yes">Saccharibacteria</italic> (a candidate bacterial phylum) in the duck intestinal microbiota remains inadequately understood (<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). At the genus level, supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> significantly increased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Collinsella</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Subdoligranulum</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Peptoclostridium</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Sellimonas</italic>, while supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> significantly increased <italic toggle="yes">Megamonas</italic> abundance, compared to the control group in this study, which is consistent with previous findings (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Collinsella</italic> primarily produces gases in the intestine, a process that has been linked to abnormal lipid metabolism and type 2 diabetes (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Subdoligranulum</italic> belongs to the Ruminococcaceae family. Previous studies have shown that <italic toggle="yes">Subdoligranulum</italic> has the ability to produce butyrate, which plays a key role in promoting intestinal health by supplying energy to host cells and maintaining the integrity of the intestinal barrier (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Similarly, studies suggested that <italic toggle="yes">Peptoclostridium</italic> plays a role in modulating immune responses, reducing inflammation, and stimulating the production of butyrate, a key factor in maintaining intestinal health (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Megamonas</italic> has also been shown to utilize amino acids or carbohydrates to produce acetic acid, which plays a crucial role in intestinal energy supply, maintenance of the intestinal mucosal barrier, and regulation of intestinal motility (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). These findings indicated that supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> promotes intestinal microbiota balance by increasing the abundance of beneficial bacteria and decreasing pathogenic bacterial populations, thereby enhancing intestinal health and indirectly improving production performance.</p><p>The LEfSe analysis further substantiated these shifts, identifying <italic toggle="yes">Treponema</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Succinatimonas</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Ruminococcus</italic> as biomarkers of the <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> group. <italic toggle="yes">Treponema</italic> is involved in fiber degradation (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>), while <italic toggle="yes">Succinatimonas</italic> can ferment glucose and other carbohydrates to generate short-chain fatty acids, especially acetate and succinate, that can benefit enterocyte development (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Moreover, <italic toggle="yes">Ruminococcus</italic> is involved in dietary fiber fermentation, producing butyrate, which plays a critical role in reducing inflammation and maintaining the health of the gut epithelium (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). These taxa suggest enhanced fermentation capacity, immunity, and microbial efficiency in ducks receiving <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic>.</p><p>Moreover, we further analyzed the changes in the levels of 10 brain metabolites related to neurotransmitter function. Supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> resulted in higher levels of Gln, while reducing the levels of GABA, Tyr, Glu, and Ach. In addition, supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> increased the levels of GABA, Gln, and 5-HIAA while decreasing Glu and Ach. Resveratrol, a bioactive polyphenol found in <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic>, has been shown to modulate GABAergic transmission by enhancing GABA receptor activity and exerting neuroprotective effects via antioxidant and anti-inflammatory mechanisms, including the activation of the Nrf2 pathway and the suppression of NF-&#954;B signaling (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). These mechanisms can lead to the upregulation of endogenous antioxidant enzymes such as superoxide dismutase (SOD) and glutathione peroxidase (GPx), which help mitigate oxidative damage in neural tissues. Resveratrol has also been reported to reduce pro-inflammatory cytokines like TNF-<italic toggle="yes">&#945;</italic> and IL-6, which are key mediators in neuroinflammation (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Similarly, verbascoside, a phenylethanoid glycoside abundant in <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic>, has been reported to influence cholinergic signaling by increasing Ach levels and inhibiting acetylcholinesterase activity, which may enhance cognitive and neurobehavioral functions (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). However, in this study, <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> supplementation led to decreased Ach, suggesting a context-dependent or dose-dependent modulation of the cholinergic system. This compound has also demonstrated nutrigenomic activity, potentially influencing gene expression related to oxidative stress and inflammation, including SOD, GPx, TNF-&#945;, and IL-6, thereby contributing to neural homeostasis (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>).</p><p>GABA and Glu are important inhibitory neurotransmitters in the central nervous system (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). GABA, in particular, is known to stimulate food intake in chicks via activation of the GABAergic system through GABA receptors (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). A reduction in GABA levels may therefore explain the observed changes in feeding behavior and reduced appetite in ducks during brooding. The concurrent increase in Gln may support intestinal health, as Gln serves as a primary energy substrate for enterocytes and helps maintain gut barrier integrity by reducing intestinal permeability (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Ach, as the primary neurotransmitter, is associated with cognition, learning, and memory in the neuromuscular and sensory systems for most vertebrates. AchE plays a critical role in Ach degradation and regulating cholinergic nervous transmission (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Importantly, these neurochemical changes may be mediated via the gut&#8211;brain axis, which enables bidirectional communication between the gut microbiota and the central nervous system. Changes in the cecal microbiota composition, such as the observed decrease in <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> following <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> supplementation, can influence microbial metabolite production, including short-chain fatty acids and tryptophan metabolites, which are known to impact brain function through vagal nerve signaling or systemic immune modulation. Inflammatory cytokines produced in response to gut dysbiosis may also cross the blood&#8211;brain barrier, influencing the synthesis and metabolism of key neurotransmitters. In addition, increased 5-HIAA, the main serotonin metabolite, in the <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> group suggests that this herb may enhance serotonin turnover. This aligns with the known effect of resveratrol (from <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic>) on serotonergic pathways, including its antidepressant-like effects in mammals (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). This could have implications for mood regulation and stress resilience in ducks. Furthermore, the observed reductions in GABA and Tyr in the Verbena group may represent a form of metabolic rebalancing or stress modulation induced by the herb&#8217;s phytochemicals. Tyr is a precursor for catecholamines such as dopamine and norepinephrine, which are central to arousal and stress responses. A decrease in Tyr may therefore reflect reduced catecholaminergic activity, potentially indicative of a calmer or less stressed physiological state. Taken together, the alterations in brain metabolites observed in response to <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> supplementation appear to be mediated by a combination of antioxidant and anti-inflammatory pathways, nutrigenomic effects, and gut&#8211;brain axis modulation. These changes likely contribute to improved neurophysiological balance, stress resilience, and possibly energy repartitioning in Sansui ducks. Further mechanistic studies, including gene expression analysis and microbial metabolite profiling, are warranted to fully elucidate these interactions and their implications for poultry performance and welfare.</p><p>Neurotransmitters are essential endogenous chemical messengers that govern fundamental nervous system functions, including communication via the brain-gut axis (<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). As such, they can directly influence the activity and composition of the gut microbiota community (<xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). The correlation analysis demonstrates that, upon exposure to <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic>, 3 altered metabolites (GABA, Ach, and Glu) involved in neurotransmitter production and function were highly related to changes in the microbial groups, including <italic toggle="yes">Veillonella</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Anaerosporobacter</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Anaerofustis</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Fusobacterium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Flavonifractor</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Intestinimonas</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Peptoclostridium</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic>, as compared to the control group. <italic toggle="yes">Veillonella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Anaerofustis</italic> are known to produce short-chain fatty acids and lactate, which can influence neurochemical production in the gut epithelium and enteric neurons (<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Previous studies found that <italic toggle="yes">Flavonifractor</italic> produces butyrate through lysine fermentation, which can reduce intestinal inflammation and improve intestinal barrier function (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). In this study, Ach was positively correlated with <italic toggle="yes">Flavonifractor. Lactobacillus</italic> are well-studied for their capacity to produce GABA directly from glutamate, a phenomenon observed in both mice (<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). The abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> is beneficial for strengthening the intestinal barrier by enhancing tight intestinal epithelial junctions (<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>), and relatively intact intestinal function should be beneficial for the absorption of nutrients. Previous studies have explored the interactions between brain metabolites, including neurotransmitters, and gut microbiota, such as <italic toggle="yes">Proteobacteria</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> (<xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). However, it remains unclear how <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> target key bacteria and metabolites to regulate gut health, and these metabolic phenotypes&#8217; changes need to be further explored in the mechanism (<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). Future studies using microbiota-targeted interventions, such as fecal transplantation or germ-free models, are needed to confirm causal microbiota&#8211;brain metabolite relationships. On the other hand, without direct molecular validation, the mechanistic pathways linking microbiota to neurochemical changes cannot be fully established. Future studies employing transcriptomic or proteomic analyses of gut and brain tissues are necessary to elucidate signaling pathways and gene expression patterns involved in microbiota&#8211;brain communication (<xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). Such multi-omics approaches would strengthen the understanding of how phytogenic interventions like <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> influence host neurobiology through the gut&#8211;brain axis in the ducks.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec16"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>To the best of our knowledge, this study is the first to establish a connection between dietary supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Verbena officinalis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> and both the gut microbiota composition and brain metabolite profiles in ducks. Dietary supplementation with both herbal sources in Sansui ducks improves growth performance and immune response, modifies the composition of cecal microbiota, and alters the brain metabolite (GABA, Gln, Glu, Tyr, Ach, and 5-HIAA) profile. The strong correlations between gut bacterial taxa (<italic toggle="yes">Veillonella</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Anaerofustis</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Fusobacterium</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Flavonifractor</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic>) and brain metabolites (GABA, Ach, and Glu) suggest that these herbs may influence duck physiology through the gut-brain axis. These findings contribute novel insights into how dietary phytogenic feed additives can shape animal health beyond gut-level changes, potentially impacting behavior, stress response, and neural function in poultry. Moreover, this study is also distinguished by its integration of growth data, gut microbiome, and brain metabolite analysis, which uncovers a complex interplay between diet, gut ecology, and brain biochemistry. One limitation of this study is the absence of cecal metabolomic analysis, which restricts our ability to fully characterize the functional link between microbial composition and brain metabolites. While we observed distinct changes in microbiota and brain metabolic profiles, the lack of gut metabolite data limits mechanistic interpretation of microbiota&#8211;metabolite&#8211;brain interactions. Future studies integrating gut content metabolomics are needed to clarify the metabolic pathways involved in gut-brain communication. Additionally, incorporating behavioral assessments and stress biomarkers (e.g., corticosterone) would further strengthen the link between microbial shifts, brain function, and animal welfare outcomes. Nonetheless, our results offer important initial insights into how <italic toggle="yes">Verbena</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> may influence host physiology via the gut-brain axis during early development.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="fn0001"><p>
<sup>1</sup>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://qiime2.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://qiime2.org/</ext-link>
</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec17"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The raw 16S rRNA gene and metagenomic sequencing data are available at the NCBI Sequence Read Archive (SRA), under BioProject PRJNA1145929.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="sec18"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The animal study was approved by Animal Ethics Committee of Guizhou University (Guiyang, China; No. EAE-GZU-2022-E032). The study was conducted in accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="sec19"><title>Author contributions</title><p>YZ: Data curation, Methodology, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Software, Writing &#8211; original draft, Resources, Investigation. QW: Writing &#8211; original draft, Investigation, Data curation, Methodology, Software. LL: Methodology, Conceptualization, Software, Data curation, Investigation, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Resources. SY: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Project administration, Supervision, Validation, Funding acquisition, Visualization.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec21"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ai-statement" id="sec22"><title>Generative AI statement</title><p>The authors declare that no Gen AI was used in the creation of this manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="correction-note" id="sec022"><title>Correction note</title><p>This article has been corrected with minor changes. These changes do not impact the scientific content of the article.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec23"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Progress on gut health maintenance and antibiotic alternatives in broiler chicken production</article-title>. <source>Front Nutr</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>692839</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnut.2021.692839</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34869510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8636040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernando-Amado</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coque</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baquero</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;nez</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antibiotic resistance: moving from individual health norms to social norms in one health and Global Health</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1914</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.01914</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32983000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7483582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayalew</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Potential feed additives as antibiotic alternatives in broiler production</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>916473</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.916473</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35782570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9247512</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadeghi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shafeie</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaziry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farhadi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effects of purslane (<italic toggle="yes">Portulaca oleracea</italic> L.) powder on growth performance, carcass characteristics, antioxidant status, and blood metabolites in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Livest Sci</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>184</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.livsci.2015.12.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Razek</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Awad</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Tawwab</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of dietary purslane (<italic toggle="yes">Portulaca oleracea</italic> L.) leaves powder on growth, immunostimulation, and protection of Nile tilapia, <italic toggle="yes">Oreochromis niloticus</italic> against <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>Fish Physiol Biochem</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1907</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10695-019-00685-8</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31350647</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary purslane (<italic toggle="yes">Portulaca oleracea</italic> L.) promotes the growth performance of broilers by modulation of gut microbiota</article-title>. <source>AMB Expr</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>31</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13568-021-01190-z</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33620605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7902751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawood</surname><given-names>MAO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gholamhosseini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakhaie</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banaee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of the extract of lemon verbena (<italic toggle="yes">Aloysia citrodora</italic>) on the growth performance, digestive enzyme activities, and immune-related genes in Siberian sturgeon (<italic toggle="yes">Acipenser baerii</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Aquaculture</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>541</volume>:<fpage>736797</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquaculture.2021.736797</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Recent advances in the extraction, purification and analytical techniques for flavonoids from plants: taking hawthorn as an example</article-title>. <source>J Food Compos Anal</source>. (<year>2025</year>) <volume>141</volume>:<fpage>107372</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jfca.2025.107372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehrparvar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazhari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esmaeilipour</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of Lippia citridora leaves powder on growth performance, carcass traits, blood metabolites and meat quality of broilers</article-title>. <source>Iran J Vet Med</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>307</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/09637486.2013.836742</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pastorelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corino</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of <italic toggle="yes">Lippia citriodora</italic> verbascoside on growth performance, antioxidant status, and serum immunoglobulins content in piglets</article-title>. <source>Czeh J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>312</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17221/6006-CJAS</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of dietary resveratrol supplementation on growth performance, antioxidant capacity, intestinal immunity and gut microbiota in yellow-feathered broilers challenged with lipopolysaccharide</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>977087</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.977087</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36090096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9453244</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L-Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>J-G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Y-S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y-C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary resveratrol supplementation on growth performance, immune function and intestinal barrier function in broilers challenged with lipopolysaccharide</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>102</volume>:<fpage>102968</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2023.102968</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37586190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10450988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sittipo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The function of gut microbiota in immune-related neurological disorders: a review</article-title>. <source>J Neuroinflammation</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>154</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12974-022-02510-1</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35706008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9199126</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strandwitz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Neurotransmitter modulation by the gut microbiota</article-title>. <source>Brain Res</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>1693</volume>:<fpage>128</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2018.03.015</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29903615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6005194</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#225;nchez-Marzo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lozano-S&#225;nchez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>C&#225;diz-Gurrea</surname><given-names>MDLL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herranz-L&#243;pez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Micol</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Segura-Carretero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Relationships between chemical structure and antioxidant activity of isolated phytocompounds from lemon verbena</article-title>. <source>Antioxidants</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>324</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antiox8080324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31434276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6719922</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Extraction of polydatin and resveratrol from <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> root: kinetics and modeling</article-title>. <source>Food Bioprod Process</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>518</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fbp.2014.07.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Applegate</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nutrient requirements of poultry publication: history and need for an update</article-title>. <source>J Appl Poult Res</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>567</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>75</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/japr.2014-00980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rafiee</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazhari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghoreishi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esmaeilipour</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of lemon verbena powder and vitamin C on performance and immunity of heat-stressed broilers</article-title>. <source>J Anim Physiol Anim Nutr</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>807</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jpn.12457</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26833391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Resveratrol beneficially affects meat quality of heat-stressed broilers which is associated with changes in muscle antioxidant status</article-title>. <source>Anim Sci J</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>1569</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/asj.12812</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28548224</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferket</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium butyricum</italic> on growth performance, immune function, and cecal microflora in broiler chickens challenged with <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> K88</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>93</volume>:<fpage>46</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.2013-03412</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24570422</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magor</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaspers</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Structure and evolution of avian immunoglobulins</article-title>. <source>Avian Immunol Elsevier</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>2004</volume>:<fpage>107</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-012370634-8.50009-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohebodini</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jazi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakhshalinejad</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shabani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashayerizadeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of dietary resveratrol supplementation on growth performance, immune response, serum biochemical indices, cecal microflora, and intestinal morphology of broiler chickens challenged with <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Livest Sci</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>229</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.livsci.2019.09.008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M-T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Advances for pharmacological activities of <italic toggle="yes">Polygonum cuspidatum</italic> - a review</article-title>. <source>Pharm Biol</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>177</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>88</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13880209.2022.2158349</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36620922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9833411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kogut</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The gut microbiota and host innate immunity: regulators of host metabolism and metabolic diseases in poultry?</article-title><source>J Appl Poult Res</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>637</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/japr.2013-00741</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Different rearing conditions alter gut microbiota composition and host physiology in Shaoxing ducks</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>7387</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-25760-7</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29743727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5943461</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative analysis of gut microbiota in incident and prevalent peritoneal dialysis patients with peritoneal fibrosis, correlations with PERITONEAL EQUILIBRATION TEST data in the peritoneal fibrosis cohort</article-title>. <source>Ther Apher Dial</source>. (<year>2024</year>)<comment>1744-9987.</comment>):<fpage>14226</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1744-9987.14226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39520210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Litsea cubeba</italic> essential oil on growth performance, blood antioxidation, immune function, apparent digestibility of nutrients, and fecal microflora of pigs</article-title>. <source>Front Pharmacol</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1166022</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2023.1166022</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37465523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10350539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Biogeography of microbiome and short-chain fatty acids in the gastrointestinal tract of duck</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>4016</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2020.03.040</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32731989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7597935</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary organic acids ameliorate high stocking density stress-induced intestinal inflammation through the restoration of intestinal microbiota in broilers</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci Biotechnol</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>124</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40104-022-00776-2</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36372893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9661804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stojanov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berlec</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#352;trukelj</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The influence of probiotics on the Firmicutes/Bacteroidetes ratio in the treatment of obesity and inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>Microorganisms</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1715</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms8111715</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33139627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7692443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of Total dietary Fiber on Cecal microbial community and intestinal morphology of growing White Pekin duck</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>727200</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.727200</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34539618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8440899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Y-L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>G-C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ameliorative effect of buckwheat polysaccharides on colitis via regulation of the gut microbiota</article-title>. <source>Int J Biol Macromol</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>227</volume>:<fpage>872</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>83</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2022.12.155</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36563806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rumen-protected lysine supplementation improved amino acid balance, nitrogen utilization and altered hindgut microbiota of dairy cows</article-title>. <source>Anim Nutr</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>320</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aninu.2023.08.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10694044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38053803</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oladokun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alizadeh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mallick</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fazel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doost</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Influenza a virus subtype H9N2 infection induces respiratory microbiota dysbiosis in chickens via type-I interferon-mediated mechanisms</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbes</source>. (<year>2025</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>xtaf001</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/femsmc/xtaf001</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39991080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11843552</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Steger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>&#197;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romantschuk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sundh</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of differing temperature management on development of Actinobacteria populations during composting</article-title>. <source>Res Microbiol</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>158</volume>:<fpage>617</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resmic.2007.05.006</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17683913</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Protective role of dryland rearing on netting floors against mortality through gut microbiota-associated immune performance in Shaoxing ducks</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>4530</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pez268</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31111923</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of dietary <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus licheniformis</italic> supplementation on growth performance and microbiota diversity of Pekin ducks</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>832141</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.832141</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35265695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8899091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Hul</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Roy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prifti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dao</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paquot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zucker</surname><given-names>J-D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>From correlation to causality: the case of Subdoligranulum</article-title>. <source>Gut Microbes</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/19490976.2020.1849998</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33323004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7744154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of L-&#946;-Galactoglucan supplementation on growth performance, palatability, and intestinal microbiota in adult beagle dogs</article-title>. <source>Meta</source>. (<year>2025</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>160</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/metabo15030160</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40137125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11944019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rychlik</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Composition and function of chicken gut microbiota</article-title>. <source>Animals</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>103</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani10010103</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31936291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7022619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dworkin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falkow</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schleifer</surname><given-names>K-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stackebrandt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>The prokaryotes</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer New York</publisher-name> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lakshmanan</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Zaidan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bangarusamy</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Shamari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elhag</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Terranegra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Increased relative abundance of Ruminoccocus is associated with reduced cardiovascular risk in an obese population</article-title>. <source>Front Nutr</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>849005</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnut.2022.849005</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35571941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9097523</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Resveratrol attenuates neuroinflammation by modulating the GABAergic system in a rat model of epilepsy</article-title>. <source>Neurochem Int</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>124</volume>:<fpage>183</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuint.2019.01.010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanna</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghelardini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galeotti</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Neuroprotective effect of verbascoside in models of Alzheimer&#8217;s disease: focus on neuroinflammation</article-title>. <source>Phytother Res</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1360</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ptr.6079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mainardi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vizzarri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corino</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Verbascoside-rich plant extracts in animal nutrition</article-title>. <source>Antioxidants</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antiox13010039</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38247465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10812750</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of dietary glutamine and gamma-aminobutyric acid on performance, carcass characteristics and serum parameters in broilers under circular heat stress</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>168</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2011.03.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jonaidi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noori</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Neuropeptide Y-induced feeding is dependent on GABAA receptors in neonatal chicks</article-title>. <source>J Comp Physiol A</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>198</volume>:<fpage>827</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00359-012-0753-y</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22972230</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Polystyrene nanoplastics toxicity to zebrafish: dysregulation of the brain&#8211;intestine&#8211;microbiota axis</article-title>. <source>ACS Nano</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>8190</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>204</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsnano.2c01872</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35507640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Phasic acetylcholine release and the volume transmission hypothesis: time to move on</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>383</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn2635</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19377503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2699581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mallick</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Plants affecting serotonergic neurotransmission</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhara</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group>, editors. <source>Role of herbal medicines</source>. <publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer Nature Singapore</publisher-name> (<year>2023</year>). <fpage>211</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dicks</surname><given-names>LMT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Gut bacteria and neurotransmitters</article-title>. <source>Microorganisms</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1838</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms10091838</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36144440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9504309</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Cunha</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezende</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cialic</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bry</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The host shapes the gut microbiota via fecal micro RNA</article-title>. <source>Cell Host Microbe</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>32</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2015.12.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26764595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4847146</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S-M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S-L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The commensal anaerobe <italic toggle="yes">Veillonella dispar</italic> reprograms its lactate metabolism and short-chain fatty acid production during the stationary phase</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Spectr</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e0355822</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/spectrum.03558-22</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36975840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10100942</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bibi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Din</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Behavioral alterations in antibiotic-treated mice associated with gut microbiota dysbiosis: insights from 16S rRNA and metabolomics</article-title>. <source>Front Neurosci</source>. (<year>2025</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1478304</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnins.2025.1478304</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40092066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11906700</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacokinetics effects of chuanxiong rhizoma on warfarin in pseudo germ-free rats</article-title>. <source>Front Pharmacol</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1022567</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2022.1022567</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36686675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9849362</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Strategy for an association study of the intestinal microbiome and brain metabolome across the lifespan of rats</article-title>. <source>Anal Chem</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>2475</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>83</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.7b02859</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29353471</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szeto</surname><given-names>IM-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Hydrolyzed protein formula improves the nutritional tolerance by increasing intestinal development and altering cecal microbiota in low-birth-weight piglets</article-title>. <source>Front Nutr</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1439110</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnut.2024.1439110</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39555191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11565607</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cryan</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Riordan</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandhu</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinan</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The gut microbiome in neurological disorders</article-title>. <source>Lancet Neurol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>136</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>48</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(18)30313-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31753762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sampson</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazmanian</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Control of brain development, function, and behavior by the microbiome</article-title>. <source>Cell Host Microbe</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>565</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>76</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2015.04.011</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25974299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4442490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>