<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10076730</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10076730.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10076730</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10076730</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37035821</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1123573</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Aflatoxin contamination of animal feeds and its predictors among dairy farms in Northwest Ethiopia: One Health approach implications</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tadele</surname><given-names initials="F">Fitalew</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1709912/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Demissie</surname><given-names initials="B">Biruk</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amsalu</surname><given-names initials="A">Alebachew</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Demelash</surname><given-names initials="H">Habtamu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2126246/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mengist</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zelalem</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ambelu</surname><given-names initials="A">Argaw</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/646030/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yenew</surname><given-names initials="C">Chalachew</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1127498/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Biomedical Sciences, College of Health Sciences, Debre Tabor University</institution>, <addr-line>Gondar</addr-line>, <country>Ethiopia</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Public Health, College of Health Sciences, Debre Tabor University</institution>, <addr-line>Gondar</addr-line>, <country>Ethiopia</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Animal Health, College of Veterinary Medicine, Mekelle University</institution>, <addr-line>Mek'ele</addr-line>, <country>Ethiopia</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Division of Water and Health, Ethiopian Institute of Water Resources, Addis Ababa University</institution>, <addr-line>Addis Ababa</addr-line>, <country>Ethiopia</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Junqing Tang, Peking University, China</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Ahrar Khan, Shandong Vocational Animal Science and Veterinary College, China; Rakhi Gangil, Nanaji Deshmukh Veterinary Science University, India</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Chalachew Yenew <email>chalachewyenew50@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Veterinary Epidemiology and Economics, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">427755</issue-id><elocation-id>1123573</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>02</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>07</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-04-11 05:10:23.263"><day>11</day><month>04</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 Tadele, Demissie, Amsalu, Demelash, Mengist, Ambelu and Yenew.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Tadele, Demissie, Amsalu, Demelash, Mengist, Ambelu and Yenew</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-10-1123573.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>In dairy farming, animal feed is the first line of food safety. Animal feed can become contaminated and spoiled on farms or in storage facilities due to the diverse microorganisms that are naturally present around or on various animal feeds. This study aims to assess the level of aflatoxin and predictors in animal feeds among dairy farms in the South Gondar Zone of Ethiopia.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>A total of 100 samples of each animal feed ingredient (atella, hay, commercial concentrates, and cut and carry pasture) were obtained. A total of 400 animal feed ingredient samples were tested separately among 100 randomly chosen dairy farmers for aflatoxin analysis. Simultaneously, swabs from cow udders and water samples were also collected. Using a structured and pretested questionnaire, the knowledge and practices of animal feed administrators responsible for managing animal feed were also evaluated. Descriptive statistics and logistic regression models were used to identify determinants.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>From the total animal feed analyzed, 96% was positive for aflatoxins. Feed storage facilities, feed storage duration, education of animal feed administrators, mixed concentrates, and previous training were found to be associated with aflatoxin contamination levels in animal feeds.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>The levels of aflatoxin contamination in animal feeds were found to be higher than the recommended limit; these findings suggest the spread of aflatoxin contamination between humans and animals. Furthermore, the occurrence of aflatoxins in the environment results from milk becoming contaminated with aflatoxins. A One Health strategy should therefore receive special consideration to tackle such problems and safeguard consumer safety.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>zoonotic pathogens</kwd><kwd>contamination</kwd><kwd>One Health approach</kwd><kwd>Ethiopia</kwd><kwd>environmental factor</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="48"/><page-count count="8"/><word-count count="5811"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Background</title><p>The dairy sector is of the atmost importance in the developing world, where more than 80% of people live in rural areas (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). In Ethiopia, traditional methods account for 97% of dairying (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), using on-farm animal feed formulations, traditional feed and feed storage, and on-farm milking processes and materials (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), and there is also an excessive call for using unprocessed raw milk due to a lack of refrigeration centers on farms and in households and ambient temperatures, as spoiled and contaminated milk causes significant food wastage and food-borne disease (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p><p>Aflatoxins (AFs) and other derivatives present in milk and milk products are challenging health issues in food safety because they are unaffected by pasteurization and processing. This toxin induces cancer in experimental animals, and the relatively large consumption of milk by children makes this food contaminant a worldwide concern (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p><p>Animal feed is the beginning of the food safety chain in the dairying process (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). A wide variety of naturally occurring microbes contaminate and spoil animal feed on the farm and at the storage site (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p><p>Animals used for food trigger over five million illnesses, 46,000 hospitalizations, and 1,458 human fatalities annually due to contamination with numerous pathogenic microbes (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Dairy animals may become exposed to pathogenic microbes through the ingestion of contaminated feed, drinking contaminated water, udder infections, and directly from the environment. Such contamination may transmit disease-causing microbes or toxic metabolites to humans, leading to foodborne illness, cancer, and childhood stunting (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>).</p><p>Animal feeds are contaminated with mycotoxins (aflatoxins), which are harmful by-products of the Aspergillus fungus species, and are particularly significant (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Animal feed mycotoxin contamination could occur on the farm before harvest or during storage (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>).</p><p>Animal feeds can become contaminated with microbes from industrial activity, fecal contamination, environmental pollution, inadequate temperatures, insect activity, and endogenous toxins during harvesting, storing, processing, mixing, or transportation (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). The US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act of 1906 have recommended that animal feed provided to animals be appropriately made and labeled, in a way that poses no risk to human health (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). The US Department of Transportation (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) and Agriculture's Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) have also advised that animal feed be safely transported to ensure healthy animals and improve productivity while also contributing to the nation's economy (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>).</p><p>In Ethiopian farm forage and formulations of hay, cut and carry pasture, home-grown cereals, commercial concentrates (noug seed cake, maize, and concentrate mixture of wheat bran), and cultural home-brewed beer by-products (atella) are the most common groups of livestock feeds (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). In the locality, atella is usually stored in large quantities and used for a longer time, and in all parts of Ethiopia, especially in the study area, it is increasingly replacing commercial concentrates (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Tella is one of the most commonly home-brewed traditional local beers and its by-product or residue (atella) is used in dairy cattle feed (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>).</p><p>Due to the low hygienic standards in the processing facility and the high chance of microorganisms from bioaerosols, floors, and contamination of the food equipment, Ethiopian dairy farm animal feed practices of handling, storing, and feeding are currently susceptible to contamination (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Dairy farmers are forced to buy and store animal feed in hazardous conditions on a floor that has frequent exposure to the contaminated environment and human waste due to the scarcity and high cost of animal feed and the small number of food processing companies that produce feed by-products (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>).</p><p>Despite the livestock sector's contribution to the livelihood and economy of the Ethiopian population, having been identified as a new source of economic growth in the Second Growth and Transformation Plan (GTP) (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>), livestock productivity remains very low due to the inefficiency of feed, genetic material, and veterinary services. The constraints related to feed shortage, in quantity and quality; environmental conditions; human waste contamination; and traditional feed storage practices have been critical problems in Ethiopian livestock production (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p><p>With inadequate harvesting, storage, transportation, and processing methods, the generation of AFs in animal feed significantly increases, with toxicogenic, hepatogenic, carcinogenic, nephrotoxic, immunosuppressive, and mutagenic effects. Acute aflatoxicosis in humans is more likely to occur in developing nations due to factors like insufficient food supplies, a lack of infrastructure for AF management, and environmental factors that encourage AF growth (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>).</p><p>Therefore, this study aims to evaluate animal feed AF contamination and its predictors among dairy farms in the South Gondar Zone (SGZ) of Ethiopia. This offers insight into how to lessen the risk of zoonosis, food hazards, and other public health issues, using a One Health strategy.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Study area, study design, setting, and period</title><p>The study was conducted in the South Gondar zone of the Amhara National Regional State. The South Gondar zone is located 660 km northwest of Addis Ababa. The geographic location of the zone lies between 11&#176; 02&#8242;-12&#176; 33&#8242; North latitude and 37&#176; 25&#8242;-38&#176; 43&#8242; East longitude. The zone is characterized agro-ecologically as highland (Dega) and mid-altitude (Woina Dega), and the altitude ranges from 1,500 to 3,200 meters above sea level. The study area is generally characterized by its rugged topography from the place called Gunna Mountain (4,231 m) to the mid-altitude of the Dera district at the Lake Tana border. The annual minimum and maximum temperatures are ~17 and 27 degrees Celsius, respectively. Rainfall distribution is largely monomodal from June to mid-September. The heaviest rain usually occurs during July and August, and the mean annual rainfall varies widely from 500 to 1,600 mm.</p><p>A community-based experimental cross-sectional study was conducted from February 2021 to September 2021. In this study, 1,338 dairy farmers living in SGZ, Ethiopia, participated. The total sample size (100 dairy farmers) was proportionally allocated to each of the selected woredas using the total dairy farms of each selected woreda, total dairy farms of SGZ, and total sample size.</p><p>A systematic random sampling technique was used to enroll the dairy farms using the K<sup>th</sup> interval (1,338/100 = within the 13 intervals). Of the 10 woredas of SGZ, Ethiopia (Debre Tabor Town, Dera, Ebenat, Farta, Fogera, Lay Gayint, Libo Kemekem, Esite, Simada, Tach Gayint,), three woredas (Libo Kemekem, Esite, Lay Gayint) were randomly selected using the lottery method, and the total numbers of dairy farms selected were 39, 32, and 29, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Sampling and sample preparation</title><sec><title>Sample size determination</title><p>Due to the high cost of microbiological analysis and economic constraints, to determine the sample size, 90% standard error, 0.83 probability of occurrence, design effect equals 1, and desired confidence of 0.1 were used. An average AF prevalence of 83% in feeds around Addis Ababa by Gizachew et al. (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) was used. The sample size was determined using the method described by Fisher et al. (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>), as detailed below. <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = z<sup>2</sup>pqD/d2 Where: <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = Sample size to be calculated, <italic toggle="yes">Z</italic> = 1.96 at 90% standard error, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = probability of occurrence 0.83, <italic toggle="yes">q</italic> = 1-p, <italic toggle="yes">D</italic> = design effect equals 1 (around Addis Ababa City), d2 = desired confidence of 0.1, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 1.962 &#215; 0.83 &#215; 0.17 &#215; 1/0.12. Therefore, the total number of samples was 108. The final sample size (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic><sub>f</sub>) of the study was 100.</p></sec><sec><title>Animal feed collection and sample preparation</title><p>Among the 100 dairy farms, samples of each ingredient (100 atella samples, 100 hay samples, 100 commercial concentrates samples, and 100 cut and carry pasture samples) were obtained and analyzed separately. One of the main aims of this study is to assess the <italic toggle="yes">AF</italic> contamination levels of the most commonly used animal feed types. Animal feed samples were collected from animal farms. In the locality, atella (local brewery end-product), hay, mixed commercial concentrates, and cut and carry pastures were the major feed types used. Samples were cut into three-inch pieces and quartered to reduce the sample size. The cut samples were placed in a plastic bag; the air was excluded and the bag was then tightly sealed and promptly shipped. Approximately 250 g representative feed samples, one feed sample from each dairy farm, were collected aseptically in a universal sample container: a strong molded glass bottle (3<sup>1</sup>/<sub>4</sub> in height &#215; 11/8 in diameter) of one oz. (28 ml) capacity with a flat base and wide mouth. It was sterilized with a loose cap, which was then tightened. Samples were transported to the laboratory in a cold box with ice packs immediately after collection for processing and analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Survey on knowledge and practice</title><p>The knowledge and practices of dairy farmers related to animal feed handling, aflatoxin animal feed contamination, and animal feed storage were assessed using a pretested structured questionnaire. Their knowledge was assessed using 14 pretested structured questionnaires, whereas the practices pretested structured questionnaire consisted of 9 of 100 samples adapted from previous studies (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). After the pretest, the knowledge and practices questionnaires were narrowed down to 9 and 6 pretested structured questionnaires, respectively. We employed the Crombath alpha to check the internal consistency, and the value was 0.8.</p></sec><sec><title>Determination of <italic toggle="yes">AFs</italic> from animal feed</title><p>The quantitative measurement of the <italic toggle="yes">AF</italic> concentration of animal feed samples was determined by competitive Enzyme immunoassay, using the RIDASCREEN<sup>&#174;</sup> aflatoxin Total Art. No.: R4701 for <italic toggle="yes">AF</italic> determination in cereals and feed. An enzyme immunoassay kit was used, which cross-reacts between the different AFs that appear in the feed. Therefore, reference should be made to the total AFs (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Data processing and statistical analysis</title><p>The data were entered into Epi-Data version 3.1 and then exported to SPSS (version 21.0) for analysis. <italic toggle="yes">AF</italic> levels in feed were categorized legally and highly based on the laboratory results by comparing the internationally accepted limit set by the EU (5 &#956;g/kg). The Percentage, frequency, mean, and standard deviation were calculated. Binary logistic regression analysis was used to assess statistical associations between the predictors and the outcome variables. Therefore, variables with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value &lt; 0.25 in the bi-variable logistic regression analysis were included in the multivariable logistic regression analysis. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values &#8804; 0.05 were considered statistically significant, and an adjusted odds ratio (AOR) with 95% confidence intervals was used to examine associations between predictors and outcome variables.</p></sec><sec><title>Data quality assurance</title><p>To validate the data, Triplicate laboratory analysis was performed and sample collection, handling, storage, and extraction were conducted based on scientific protocols. All feed sample analysis was done in accordance with scientific standard laboratory procedures. Sterilization and disinfection of the instruments were conducted in accordance with international standard procedures (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Socio-demographic and household characteristics</title><p>The number of cattle owned by the households ranged between 1 and 16, with a mean (SD) of 6 (2) per household. On average, 26% of dairy farms used atella as the main feed for their animals and only 27% of dairy farms had training in animal feed handling (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Socio-demographic characteristics of dairy farms in the locality of SGZ, Ethiopia (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 100).</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919497;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Variables</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Characteristics</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Value</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Age (in years)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.22 (13.5)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23&#8211;37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38&#8211;57</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58&#8211;77</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gender of respondent</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Men</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Women</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Marital status of the respondent</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Married</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Widowed/widower</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Educational level</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No formal education</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Can read and write</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Up to secondary school</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">College/university</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The average number of cattle/households</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total milk production in litter per day</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (SD)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.61 (0.083)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Had training in dairy production</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Have a separate animal house</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Types of animal feed used</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hay</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cu and carry pasture</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atella</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed Concentrates</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Most-used animal feed (&#8805;3 days/ week)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hay</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cut and carry pasture</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atella</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed Concentrates</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The average area available for cutting and supplying pasture, as well as for grazing livestock in Hectares per cattle/household</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Type of grazing system</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zero grazing</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Open grazing</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed grazing</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Have animal feed storage facilities</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Animal feed storage time</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8804;3 months</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#8211;6 months</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;6 months</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>NA, not applicable; up to secondary school, primary and secondary school; SD, standard deviation.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">AF</italic> contamination levels of animal feed</title><p>Of the total 100 feed samples analyzed, 96% (96/100) were positive for <italic toggle="yes">AFs</italic>, ranging from LOD ( &#8804; 1.75 &#956;g/kg) to 306.9 &#956;g/kg (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The European Union (EU) limit of 5 &#956;g/kg was exceeded by 52% (52/100) of feeds. A total of 67 feed samples used concentrates with at least 22.8 ug/kg of AFs, which is higher than the legally allowable limit, but only 23 samples were reported to have an AF level lower than 5 ug/kg. Finally, the analysis of variance (ANOVA) showed that the mean <italic toggle="yes">AF</italic> contamination was significantly different across the four animal feed samples analyzed with a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value of 0.001 (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Contamination level of AFs in different animal feed ingredients.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919497;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>AFs (&#956;g/kg)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="5" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>Animal feed ingredients</bold>
</th></tr><tr style="background-color:#919497;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Hay</bold>, <italic toggle="yes"><bold>N</bold></italic> = <bold>100</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cut and carry pasture</bold>, <italic toggle="yes"><bold>N</bold></italic> = <bold>100</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Concentrates</bold>, <italic toggle="yes"><bold>N</bold></italic> = <bold>100</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Atella</bold>, <italic toggle="yes"><bold>N</bold></italic> = <bold>100</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>ANOVA</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#177; SD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.00 &#177; 8.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.89 &#177; 8.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.00 &#177; 33.71</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.10 &#177; 21.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.59</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112.88</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.34</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">306.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;5 &#956;g/kg (number of samples)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>LOD, lowest detection limit; SD, Standard Deviation.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Associated factors of AF contamination in animal feed</title><p>In the final model, logistic regression analysis showed that educational status; having no formal education and only being able to read and write were more likely to increase the AF contamination level of animal feed ingredients by 6 times and 5 times, respectively. While having no animal feed storage facilities, having longer feed storage durations (&#8805;6 months), using mixed concentrates as the main source of animal feed, and having no training in dairy production were more likely to increase the AF contamination level of animal feed ingredients by 5 times, 5 times, 7 times, and 8 times, respectively (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Logistic regression analysis of factors associated with <italic toggle="yes">AF</italic> levels in animal feed ingredients &#8805;5 &#956;g/kg among dairy farms in SGZ, Northwest Ethiopia, 2021 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 100).</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919497;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>Factors</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>AFs</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</bold>
</th></tr><tr style="background-color:#919497;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &#8804; <bold>5</bold> &#956;<bold>g/kg</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;<bold>5</bold> &#956;<bold>g/kg</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>COR (95%CI)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AOR (95%CI)</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" style="background-color:#dee1e1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Educational status</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No formal education</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8 (0.9, 3.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4 (3.4, 9.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.036</bold>
<xref rid="TN1" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>
<bold>*</bold>
</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Can read and write</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4 (1.2, 4.5)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2 (1.9, 8.9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.031</bold>
<xref rid="TN1" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>
<bold>*</bold>
</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Secondary school</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8 (0.2, 16.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6 (0.2, 52.9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.779</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Above college</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" style="background-color:#dee1e1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Feed storage facility</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7 (1.7, 12.8)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5 (1.7, 8.1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.001</bold>
<xref rid="TN1" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>
<bold>*</bold>
</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" style="background-color:#dee1e1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Feed storage duration</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &#8804; 3 months</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#8211;6 months</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.8 (11.5, 23.8)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5 (0.6, 10.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8805;6 months</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5 (1.5, 23.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.8 (3.3, 8.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.011</bold>
<xref rid="TN1" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>
<bold>*</bold>
</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" style="background-color:#dee1e1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Type of animal feed commonly used</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hay</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cut and carry pasture</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8 (0.4, 33.1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7 (0.6, 13.76)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atella</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5 (1.5, 23.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.8 (3.3, 4.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.711</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed concentrates</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8 (0.4, 33.1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.8 (0.6, 11.76)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.011</bold>
<xref rid="TN1" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>
<bold>*</bold>
</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" style="background-color:#dee1e1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Had training in dairy production</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9 (2.4, 6.3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2 (2.4, 15.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.03</bold>
<xref rid="TN1" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>
<bold>*</bold>
</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" style="background-color:#dee1e1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Animal feed administrator knowledge of animal feed aflatoxin contamination</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.56 (3.6, 6.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0 (4.2, 5.61)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.025</bold>
<xref rid="TN1" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>
<bold>*</bold>
</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><label>*</label><p>The association is significant at a P-value &#8804; 0.05. A crude odds ratio (COR) is an odds ratio of one independent variable for predicting the dependent variable, whereas the adjusted odds ratio (AOR) holds other relevant variables constant and provides the odds ratio for the potential variable of interest, which is adjusted for the other independent variables included in the model.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Microorganisms found in animal feed can be transmitted to humans through the consumption of milk or milk products that are contaminated with animal feces and uncooked foods that have been contaminated by contact with uncooked milk products. Disease-causing infectious agents can be transmitted to animals through contaminated animal feed (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p><p>Dairy farmers' knowledge of the processing of animal feed and the microbiological contamination of feed was found to be generally insufficient; only 22% were aware of this issue, and only 6% accurately described feed aflatoxin contamination. This result was low when compared to studies conducted in other parts of Ethiopia (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>), Nairobi (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>), and Kenya (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). The adoption of technology to prevent and control animal feed AF contamination may be severely impacted by a lack of understanding about the risks associated with animal feed, which could also result in improper handling of animal feed and harm both animal and human health (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>).</p><p>In this study, of the 100 feed samples analyzed, 96 (96%) were contaminated with <italic toggle="yes">AFs</italic>, and the contamination level obtained in this study was comparable with many country-specific studies (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) but higher than the findings of other studies conducted in Egypt (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>) two studies in Turkey (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). The study also revealed that 52% of feeds exceeded the European Union (EU) limit of 5 &#956;g/kg, which is comparable with a study conducted in Addis Ababa, higher than the results reported in Peru (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>) and Argentina (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>), and lower than the results of studies in Egypt (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) and Turkey (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). This variation could be due to feed originating from different agroecological conditions, under different feeding practices, different climates, and feed storage conditions.</p><p>In an analysis of associated factors, several factors may impact the occurrence and levels of <italic toggle="yes">AFs</italic> in animal feed. In this study, animal feed from dairy farmers who had no formal education and who could only read and write had a 6.4 and 5.2 times higher risk of <italic toggle="yes">AF</italic> contamination above the limit set by the EU than dairy farmers who had attended secondary and college education, respectively. The lack of sufficient knowledge, i.e., a poor understanding of the concept of AFs is common in many developing countries, which may facilitate high aflatoxin exposure through contaminated feeds, leading to human disease (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>).</p><p>Dairy farmers with awareness of feed <italic toggle="yes">AFs</italic> may have information on the source and will protect feed and cows from <italic toggle="yes">AF</italic> exposure and, ultimately, safeguard feed from contamination. Furthermore, this result is supported by the fact that dairy farmers with no training in dairy production were 8.2 times more likely to experience AF contamination in animal feed above the limit set by the EU. AF intoxication leads to a decrease body weight and feed intake. The gross and microscopic changes in the aflatoxin groups were more pronounced with the increase in the level of the toxin present in the feed. Decreases in testicular size and volume and reproductive hormones like LH, prolactin, and testosterone were evident with increased levels of AFs in animal feed (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>).</p><p>In comparison to those who had feed storage facilities, dairy farmers who had no animal feed storage facilities were shown to be 5 times more likely to have <italic toggle="yes">AF</italic> contamination above the limit set by the EU. High-humidity and high-temperature exposure, indoor storage in plastic bags, long-term storage, and the lack of raised ventilated platforms for storage may be conducive to the accumulation of molds and aflatoxins (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>).</p><p>In this study, feed storage duration was also found to be a major factor in high AF contamination. Animal feed stored for a longer duration (&#8805;6 months) was 5.8 times more likely to have AF contamination levels above the EU limit than animal feed stored for a shorter duration (&#8804; 6 months). This finding is supported by a study conducted in Kenya (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>), which reasoned that the lengthy storage of animal feed due to a shortage of animal feed and lack of grazing fields and storing animal feed in restricted, closed rooms may favor and facilitate mold growth and contamination of the feed.</p><p>A Kenyan study revealed that concentrate feeds increase the likelihood of higher AF levels in comparison to other feeds, indicating that the transfer of veterinary and milk-borne pathogens from the environment of dairy farms to milk is a highly connected and complex process (the spread of AFs between humans and animals and their occurrence in the environment can result in milk becoming contaminated with pathogens). Despite its great importance, the dairy industry is challenged by many complicated technical and non-technical constraints. Feed shortage and microbial contamination due to easily preventable and avoidable factors are the key problems in livestock production, particularly among smallholder farmers (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). To prevent animal feed contamination, it is crucial to take into account a One-Health approach with relevant food safety and quality laws (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>).</p><sec><title>Limitations of the study</title><p>Our study is one of the few in Ethiopia to provide information on the problem of animal feed microbial contamination. The limitations of this study include the small sample size, which was limited to 100 animal feed samples due to the high cost of reagents and supply, and the fact that AF levels in milk were not measured. Another limitation was that the study was conducted during the dry seasons due to resources and time constraints, and the contamination of AFs may vary throughout the seasons.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The level of AF contamination in the most common feedstuffs, cow udders, and water used to wash milkers' hands and utensils used on dairy farms in the South Gondar zone of Ethiopia was relatively high. Low educational status, long feed storage durations, using mixed concentrates as the main source of animal feed, and having no training in dairy production were the significant factors associated with animal feed <italic toggle="yes">AF</italic> contamination levels.</p><p>Therefore, dairy farmers should be educated on the prevention mechanisms and physical detection methods of animal feed spoilage and on animal feed preparation and feeding. Ethiopia is known for different non-conventional animal feeds in different parts of the country, like atella in the study area, and efforts should be made to consider these as a major alternative, as cheap sources of feed. However, further investigation and research are needed to ascertain the nutritional value and improve the nutritive quality of feed in the interest of better livestock production. The One Health strategy should therefore receive special consideration.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be made available by the authors, without undue reservation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="s7"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>Ethical approval was obtained from the Institutional Review Board, the Research Committee of Debre Tabor University, College of Health Sciences. The sampling of atella, hay, commercial concentrates, cut and carry pasture, swabs from cow udders, and water was carried out with the full consent of the head of the Farm.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s8"><title>Author contributions</title><p>FT, ZM, and CY conducted the survey, conceived the design, interpreted the findings, and were responsible for the overall content as a guarantor. AAms, BD, AAmb, and HD planned the study, selected and assessed the quality of the study, extracted the data, interpreted the results, and reviewed the manuscript. All authors read and approved the manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to thank the College of Health Sciences and Debre Tabor University for their cooperation and administrative support for this study.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s9"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garedew</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berhanu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mengesha</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsegay</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of gram-negative bacteria from critical control points of raw and pasteurized cow milk consumed at Gondar town and its suburbs, Ethiopia</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>950</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-12-950</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23131015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3527359</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Godefay</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Molla</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bacteriological quality of raw milk from four dairy farms and milk collection center in and around Addis Ababa</article-title>. <source>Berl M&#252;nch Tierarztl Wschr</source>. (<year>2000</year>) <volume>113</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10994252</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abebe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zelalem</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ajebu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hygienic and microbial quality of raw whole cow's milk produced in Ezha district of the Gurage zone, Southern Ethiopia</article-title>. <source>Wudpecker J Agric Res</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>459</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mennane</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ouhssine</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khedid</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elyachioui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hygienic quality of raw cow's milk feeding from domestic</article-title>. <source>Int J Agri Biol</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1560</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8530</lpage>.31132590</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Felleke</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Milk and dairy products, post-harvest losses and food safety in Sub Saharan Africa and the near east</article-title>. In: <source>FAO Prevention of Food Losses Programme</source>. <publisher-loc>Rome</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>FAO</publisher-name> (<year>2003</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yitaye</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azage</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zollitsch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Performance and limitation of two dairy production System in the North western Ethiopian highlands</article-title>. <source>Trop Anim Health Prod</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>1143</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11250-008-9294-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19083118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aneja</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muthur</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banerejee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Technology of Indian milk products</article-title>. New Delhi. In: <source>Dairy Indian Yearbook</source>. (<year>2002</year>). <fpage>p. 183</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>96</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouazza</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassikou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohmani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hmmamouchi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ennadir</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qasmaoui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hygienic quality of raw milk at Sardi breed of sheep in Morocco</article-title>. <source>Afr J Microbiol Res</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>2768</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>72</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5897/AJMR11.1396</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gebrewold</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alemayehu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demeke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dediye</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tadesse</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Tatus of dairy research in Ethiopia</article-title>. In: <source>Small Holder Dairy Development</source>. <publisher-loc>Addis Ababa</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ministry of Agriculture (MOA)</publisher-name> (<year>2000</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roshdy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sayed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanafy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soliman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Reduction of milk contamination with aflatoxin-M1 through vaccination of dairy cattle with aflatoxin-B1 vaccine</article-title>. <source>Int J Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>528</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>.24714096</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crump</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angulo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bacterial contamination of animal feed and its relationship to human foodborne illness</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>859</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/342885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12228823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>D'Mello</collab></person-group>. <source>Microbiology of Animal Feeds - J.P.F. D'MELLO.</source><publisher-loc>Edinburgh, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Formerly of the Scottish Agricultural College (SAC)</publisher-name> (<year>2000</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mead</surname><given-names>p</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slutsker</surname><given-names>l</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>v</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Food-related illness and death in the United States</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>. (<year>1999</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>607</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid0505.990502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10511517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2627714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szonyi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gizachew</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tegegne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grace</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Aflatoxin contamination of milk and feeds in the greater Addis Ababa milk shed in Ethiopia</article-title>. <source>ILRI Res Brief</source> . (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrunhosa</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calado</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vila-Ch&#227;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A Review of mycotoxins in food and feed products in Portugal and estimation of probable daily intake</article-title>. <source>Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>249</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10408398.2012.720619</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24987806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bullerman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bianchini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Stability of mycotoxins during food processing</article-title>. <source>J Food Microbiol</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>119</volume>:<fpage>140</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2007.07.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17804104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>US General Accounting Office</collab></person-group>. <source>Food Safety: Controls Can be Strengthened to Reduce the Risk of Disease Linked to Unsafe Animal Feed 2000, 2000 Washington, DCUS General Accounting Office Report GAO/RCED-00-255</source> (<year>2000</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Food Agriculture Organization of the United Nations. FAOSTAT Nutrition Data.</collab></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://appsfaoorg/page/collections?subset=nutrition" ext-link-type="uri">http://appsfaoorg/page/collections?subset=nutrition</ext-link> (accessed November 2021).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>USA</collab></person-group>. <source>Feed Marketing and Distribution, Feedstuffs</source>. (<year>2001</year>). Vol. 73. <fpage>p. 6</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Negash</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Review on compound animal feed processing in ethiopia: condition, challenges and opportunities</article-title><source>Food Process Technol</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>60</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15406/mojfpt.2018.06.00145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Binitu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Indigenous processing methods of cheka: a traditional fermented beverage in southwestern Ethiopia</article-title>. <source>J Food Process Technol</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zewdie</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoseph</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bram</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of productive and reproductive performance of dairy cattle nexus with feed availability in selected peri-urban areas of Ethiopia</article-title>. <source>J Cell Anim Biol</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>308</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5897/JCAB11.037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Demeke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative nutritive value of Atella and industrial brewers grains in chicken starter ration in Ethiopia</article-title>. <source>Livestock Res Rural Dev</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Getabalew</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alemneh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akeberegn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dairy production in ethiopia - existing scenario and constraints</article-title>. <source>Biomed J Sci Techn Res</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>12304</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26717/BJSTR.2019.16.002903</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mogus</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Current Status of Dairy Cow Feeding in the Ethiopian Central Highlands and Some Recommendations for Promising Technologies</source>. <publisher-loc>Addis Ababa</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Livestock Research Institute</publisher-name> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bediye</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nemi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Makkar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Ethiopian Feed Industry: Current Status, Challenges and Opportunities</source>. <publisher-name>Broadening Horizons N&#176;50</publisher-name> (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Livestock feed supply situation in Ethiopia</article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings of the 16th Annual Conference of the Ethiopian Society of Animal Production (ESAP) on Commercialization of Livestock Agriculture</source>. <publisher-loc>Addis Ababa, Ethiopia</publisher-loc> (<year>2009</year>). <fpage>p. 21</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tegegne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurtu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gebremedhin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Traditional Cow and Camel Milk Production and Marketing in Agropastoral and Mixed Crop-Livestock Systems: The Case of Mieso District, Oromia Regional State, Ethiopia</source>. IPMS Working Paper. <publisher-loc>Nairobi</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ILRI</publisher-name> (<year>2008</year>). Vol. 13. <fpage>p. 56</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Imran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saleemi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mycotoxins&#8211;a global One Health concern: a review</article-title>. <source>Agrobiol Rec</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.47278/journal.abr/2020.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gizachew</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szonyi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tegegne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grace</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Aflatoxin contamination of milk and dairy feeds in the Greater Addis Ababa milk shed, Ethiopia</article-title>. <source>Food Control</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>773</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2015.06.060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Statistical inference for self-designing clinical trials with a one-sided hypothesis</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source>. (<year>1999</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>190</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0006-341X.1999.00190.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11318154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulusoy</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hecer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sayiner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaya Yildirim</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Presence of aflatoxins and ochratoxin A in samarella (tsamarella), a traditional dried-cured meat of Cyprus</article-title>. <source>J Food Sci Technol</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13197-022-05374-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35872743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9304510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>U.S. Food and Drug adminstraion</collab></person-group>. <source>BAM Chapter 4: Enumeration of Escherichia coli and the Coliform Bacteria. Bacteriological Analytical Manual (BAM) Main Page</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S. Food and Drug Administration</publisher-name> (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Bergey's Manual of Determinative Bacteriology</source>. 8<sup>th</sup> ed. <publisher-loc>Baltimore, MD, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name> (<year>1989</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Markey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Clinical Veterinary Microbiology</source>. <publisher-loc>Maryland Heights, MI, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Mosbey</publisher-name> (<year>2004</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kibret</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Knowledge, attitude and practice of farmers' towards aflatoxin in cereal crops in Wolaita Zone</article-title>. <source>EC Nutr.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>247</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>54</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kubokaa</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imungia</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Njuea</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mutuab</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grace</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johanna</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Occurrence of aflatoxin M1 in raw milk traded in peri-urban Nairobi, and the effect of boiling and fermentation</article-title>. <source>Infect Ecol Epidemiol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1625703</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/20008686.2019.1625703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31258853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6586110</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiama</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindahl</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sirma</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Senerwa</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waithanji</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ochungo</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Kenya dairy farmer perception of moulds and mycotoxins and implications for exposure to aflatoxins: a gendered analysis</article-title>. <source>Afr J Food Agric Nutr Dev</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>11106</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18697/ajfand.75.ILRI10</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anyango</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mutua</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kagera</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andang&#8216;O</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeliaGrace</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindahl</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A survey of aflatoxin M1 contamination in raw milk produced in urban and peri-urban areas of Kisumu County, Kenya</article-title>. <source>Infect Ecol Epidemiol</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1547094</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/20008686.2018.1547094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6263096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30598736</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ismaiel</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tharwat</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sayed</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gameh</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Two-year survey on the seasonal incidence of aflatoxin M1 in traditional dairy products in Egypt</article-title>. <source>Assoc Food Sci Technol</source>. (<year>2020</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13197-020-04254-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32431344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7230085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tekinsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eken</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Aflatoxin M1 levels in UHT milk and kashar cheese consumed in Turkey</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>3287</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2008.07.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18700163</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puga-Torres</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salazar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cachiguango</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cisneros</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#243;mez-Bravo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Determination of aflatoxin M1 in raw milk from dierent provinces of ecuador</article-title>. <source>Toxins</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>498</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins12080498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32756414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7472276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Costamagna</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaggiottia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiericatti</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costabel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Audero</surname><given-names>GML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taverna</surname></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Quantification of aflatoxin M1 carry-over rate from feed to soft cheese</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Rep.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>782</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxrep.2019.07.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31428566</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6695269</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tahoun</surname><given-names>ABMB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elez</surname><given-names>RMMA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>AbdEllatif</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Aflatoxin M1 in milk and some dairy products: level, effect of manufature and public health concerns</article-title>. <source>Zagazig Vet J</source>. (<year>2017</year>) 45 97&#8211;105. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21608/zvjz.2017.7891</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Temamogullari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanici</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Aflatoxin M1in dairy products sold in Sanliurfa, Turkey</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>97</volume>:<fpage>162</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2012-6184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24239070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayo</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matemu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laswai</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimanya</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Socioeconomic characteristics influencing level of awareness of aflatoxin contamination of feeds among livestock farmers in Meru District of Tanzania</article-title>. <source>Scientifica.</source> (<year>2018</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2018/3485967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29854566</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5952434</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saleemi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohsin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gul</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zubair</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muhammad</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pathological effects of graded doses of aflatoxin B1 on the development of the testes in juvenile white leghorn males</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollut Res</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>53158</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>67</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-022-19324-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35278182</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez-Valdivia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valdivia-Flores</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz-Vazquez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;nez-Salda&#241;a</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quezada-Tristan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rangel-Mu&#241;oz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Diagnosis of subclinical aflatoxicosis by biochemical changes in dairy cows under field conditions</article-title>. <source>Pak Vet J</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>2074</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7764</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.29261/pakvetj/2020.075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>