<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10797704</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10797704.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10797704</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10797704</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38249562</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1351318</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial: Current knowledge on camelids infectious and parasitic diseases</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalafalla</surname><given-names initials="AI">Abdelmalik Ibrahim</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/543256/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dadar</surname><given-names initials="M">Maryam</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c002" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn003" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/399645/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sazmand</surname><given-names initials="A">Alireza</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c003" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn004" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1034381/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Biosecurity Affairs Division, Development, and Innovation Sector, Abu Dhabi Agriculture and Food Safety Authority (ADAFSA)</institution>, <addr-line>Abu Dhabi</addr-line>, <country>United Arab Emirates</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Agricultural Research, Education and Extention Organization (AREEO), Razi Vaccine and Serum Research Institute</institution>, <addr-line>Karaj</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Pathobiology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Bu-Ali Sina University</institution>, <addr-line>Hamedan</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited and reviewed by: Michael Ward, The University of Sydney, Australia</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Abdelmalik Ibrahim Khalafalla <email>abdokhlf@yahoo.co.uk</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Maryam Dadar <email>dadar.m77@gmail.com</email></corresp><corresp id="c003">Alireza Sazmand <email>alireza.sazmand@basu.ac.ir</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>&#8224;ORCID: Abdelmalik Ibrahim Khalafalla <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9156-1361" ext-link-type="uri">orcid.org/0000-0001-9156-1361</ext-link></p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn003"><p>Maryam Dadar <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5831-801X" ext-link-type="uri">orcid.org/0000-0001-5831-801X</ext-link></p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn004"><p>Alireza Sazmand <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8450-2993" ext-link-type="uri">orcid.org/0000-0002-8450-2993</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>04</day><month>1</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">427755</issue-id><elocation-id>1351318</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>19</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-01-30 20:25:22.537"><day>30</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2024 Khalafalla, Dadar and Sazmand.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Khalafalla, Dadar and Sazmand</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-10-1351318.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="commentary-article" xml:lang="en" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/29565/current-knowledge-on-camelids-infectious-and-parasitic-diseases"/><kwd-group><kwd>editorial</kwd><kwd>current knowledge</kwd><kwd>camelids</kwd><kwd>infectious diseases</kwd><kwd>parasitic diseases</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that no financial support was received for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="0"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="1605"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Veterinary Epidemiology and Economics</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>We invited camelid scientists across the globe to submit their research on camelid diseases to highlight the importance of diseases of camelids, including Old World camels (OWC; one-humped dromedary and two-humped Bactrian camels) and New World camels (NWC; llama, alpaca, guanaco, vicuna) also known as South American camelids (SAC). We welcomed submissions in the broad subject area of endo- and ectoparasitic, bacterial, viral, and fungal infections of old and new world camelids. Finally, we accepted 10 articles on dromedaries (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7), Bactrians (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 2), and NWCs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 1) written by 83 authors from 11 countries.</p><p>Tick infestation of camels is a significant challenge, impacting not only their productivity and wellbeing but also several pathogens they may transmit, some of which are zoonotic. Although chemical acaricides have been the primary means of controlling ticks, there is growing interest in developing environment-friendly herb-based acaricides. In this Research Topic, a groundbreaking study by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2022.946702" ext-link-type="uri">Gareh et al.</ext-link> explored the acaricidal potential of neem seed extracts (<italic toggle="yes">Azadirachta indica</italic>) on the camel tick <italic toggle="yes">Hyalomma dromedarii</italic>, which is considered the most prevalent tick-infesting dromedaries. The hexane extract was the most effective, showing 100% tick mortality within 1 day at a 20% concentration. This research points to a natural alternative for tick control and emphasizes the economic viability of using neem seed extracts.</p><p>Intestinal protozoan parasites of dromedary camels have yet to be extensively studied to clarify their occurrence, diversity, and zoonotic potential since most of the research on the subject has relied on microscopic examination of fecal material. In this Research Topic, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2023.1139388" ext-link-type="uri">Elmahallawy et al.</ext-link> investigated PCR positivity of camels' fecal specimens in Egypt for <italic toggle="yes">Cryptosporidium</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">Giardia duodenalis</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Enterocytozoon bieneusi</italic>. Although <italic toggle="yes">E. bieneusi</italic> was not detected, identification of zoonotic <italic toggle="yes">C. parvum, C. bovis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Giardia duodenalis</italic> implies the role of camels as sources of oo (cyst)/spore contamination in the environment. In this article global occurrence and genetic diversity of <italic toggle="yes">Cryptosporidium</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">Giardia duodenalis</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">E. bieneusi</italic> reported in OWCs is summarized in a table.</p><p>The protozoan parasite <italic toggle="yes">Neospora caninum</italic> which infects many species of warm-blooded animals is a major cause of bovine abortion worldwide. Although there is lots of information about neosporosis of dromedaries, there is shortage of knowledge regarding Bactrians exposed to <italic toggle="yes">N. caninum</italic>. In the first epidemiological study on neosporosis in camels in China, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2022.953380" ext-link-type="uri">Qi et al.</ext-link> examined serum samples from nine animal species including <italic toggle="yes">Camelus bactrianus</italic> by indirect ELISAs detecting <italic toggle="yes">N. caninum</italic>-specific IgG and IgM antibodies. The findings suggested significant exposure, emphasizing the need for further exploration into the role of different animals in the epidemiology of this ubiquitous parasite.</p><p>Eimeriosis is an economically important parasitic disease in all camelid species. In an article from Mongolia, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2023.1296335" ext-link-type="uri">Khatanbaatar et al.</ext-link> examined 536 fresh fecal samples from Bactrians to identify <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> parasites diversity, then screened the genetic diversity in a functional important immune response gene of the major histocompatibility complex (MHC). This research not only identifies <italic toggle="yes">E. cameli, E. rajasthani</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">E. dromedarii</italic> but also delves into the immunogenetic response of infected and non-infected camels. Understanding the host-parasite interactions is crucial for developing effective strategies against this parasitic disease.</p><p>Mastitis, an inflammatory condition of the mammary gland, one of the most significant infectious diseases affecting camels, causes substantial financial losses since it lowers the quantity and quality of milk produced. Bacterial infections are a common cause of mastitis in these animals. The primary pathogens involved in camelid mastitis include <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus, Streptococcus</italic> species, and <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>. An efficient immune response to mastitis pathogens depends on the mammary glands' resistant cell makeup and function being in balance. In this Research Topic, mastitis is explored at the cellular level by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2022.885523" ext-link-type="uri">Alhafiz et al.</ext-link> The study reveals changes in immune cell composition and function in camels with subclinical mastitis. These insights into the mammary gland's immune response contribute to a better understanding of host-pathogen interactions.</p><p>Globally, tuberculosis (TB) is a significant public health concern, particularly in developing countries with tropical climates. However, there are very few reports of congenital tuberculosis in people and animals. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2022.956368" ext-link-type="uri">Narnaware et al.</ext-link> reported congenital TB caused by <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> in a dromedary camel fetus with a possible vertical transmission. Authors suggested regular screening of camels for mycobacterial infection to minimize the risk associated with the spread of TB in endemic areas.</p><p>The study of coronaviruses has grown significantly in recent years. MERS-CoV replicates in various cell types, and quick development has been made of assays for its growth and quantification. However, only a few viral isolates with complete characterization are available for investigation. Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) has been a focus of global health concern. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2023.1182165" ext-link-type="uri">Khalafalla et al.</ext-link> isolated and genetically characterized MERS-CoV from Dromedary Camels in the UAE in this Research Topic. The isolates contained several amino acid substitutions, and the analysis further identified a recombination event in one of the reported sequences. The findings underscore the importance of continuous monitoring and characterization of MERS-CoV for effective control measures.</p><p>Camels have been long implicated in transmitting various zoonotic diseases but the discovery of MERS-CoV sparked interest in camels as reservoirs of zoonotic pathogens. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2023.1244833" ext-link-type="uri">Khalafalla</ext-link> reviewed the literature on zoonotic diseases transmitted from camels, focusing on those with epidemiological or molecular evidence of transmission from camels to humans. This comprehensive review highlights diseases such as MERS, brucellosis, and anthrax, emphasizing surveillance, preventive measures, and a one-health approach to mitigate risks.</p><p>Apart from the pathogens and diseases, one of the most critical aspects of infection prevention and animal disease control is livestock farmers' Knowledge, Attitude and Practices (KAP). In the heart of camel-keeping regions in Kenya, the KAP survey by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2022.1022146" ext-link-type="uri">Othieno et al.</ext-link> sheds light on the challenges faced by camel herders. Respiratory diseases, indiscriminate drug use, and various constraints are identified, emphasizing the need for targeted interventions and heightened awareness. According to the authors, watering points, grazing areas, and marketing points are the primary areas for congregating camels and have a significant potential for disease spread.</p><p>Although the husbandry of South American camelids (SAC) is becoming more popular and different diseases and conditions cause emaciation, there is lack of a standardized guideline for the body condition score (BCS) in llamas or alpacas. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2023.1126399" ext-link-type="uri">Wagener et al.</ext-link> evaluated comparability of BCS assessment of six examiners including veterinarian, veterinary student and animal keeper given to 20 llamas and nine alpacas in Germany. The findings highlight the reliability of palpation of the lumbar vertebrae as a method for determining nutritional status in llamas and alpacas and that reproducibility increases with training and experience.</p><p>In conclusion, these articles collectively contribute to our understanding of camel health, revealing insights into camel health from the molecular world of parasites to the broader context of zoonotic risks. The findings underscore the importance of comprehensive research, surveillance, and awareness to ensure the wellbeing of camels and mitigate potential health risks to humans.</p><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>AK: Writing &#8211; original draft, Conceptualization. MD: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Conceptualization. AS: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Conceptualization.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. The author(s) declared that they were an editorial board member of Frontiers, at the time of submission. This had no impact on the peer review process and the final decision.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s3"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></back></article></pmc-articleset>