<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10014789</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10014789.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10014789</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10014789</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36937020</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1143744</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ballistic study on the penetration potential and injury potential of different bullet types in the use of a newly developed bullet shooting stunner for adequate stunning of heavy cattle</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gascho</surname><given-names initials="D">Dominic</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/967229/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephan</surname><given-names initials="R">Roger</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/97621/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zoelch</surname><given-names initials="N">Niklaus</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/791262/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names initials="M">Michael</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oesch</surname><given-names initials="MA">Michelle Aim&#233;e</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1830026/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thali</surname><given-names initials="M">Michael</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richter</surname><given-names initials="H">Henning</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/523865/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Forensic Medicine and Imaging, Institute of Forensic Medicine, University of Zurich</institution>, <addr-line>Zurich</addr-line>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Institute for Food Safety and Hygiene, Vetsuisse Faculty, University of Zurich</institution>, <addr-line>Zurich</addr-line>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Vogt Waffen AG</institution>, <addr-line>Oberglatt</addr-line>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Scientific Communication and Public Relations, Vetsuisse Faculty, University of Zurich</institution>, <addr-line>Zurich</addr-line>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Diagnostic Imaging Research Unit, Clinic for Diagnostic Imaging, Vetsuisse Faculty, University of Zurich</institution>, <addr-line>Zurich</addr-line>, <country>Switzerland</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Katarina Nenadovi&#263;, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Belgrade, Serbia</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Nikola Cobanovi&#263;, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Belgrade, Serbia; Marcelo Ghezzi, Universidad Nacional del Centro de Buenos Aires, Argentina</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Dominic Gascho <email>dominic.gascho@irm.uzh.ch</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Animal Behavior and Welfare, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>3</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">427755</issue-id><elocation-id>1143744</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>16</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-03-20 10:10:24.700"><day>20</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 Gascho, Stephan, Zoelch, Vogt, Oesch, Thali and Richter.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Gascho, Stephan, Zoelch, Vogt, Oesch, Thali and Richter</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-10-1143744.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Recently, a special bullet shooting stunner for heavy cattle has been developed that fires a bullet instead of a bolt. In the search for a suitable ammunition, the following criteria must be met: First, the energy of the bullet must be sufficient to penetrate the thick frontal bones of heavy cattle. Second, the injury potential at the corresponding penetration depth should preferably be large in order to damage brain tissue relevant to stunning. Third, the bullet must not perforate the occipital bone (over-penetration).</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Four different bullet types [<italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX, Hydra-Shok, Black Mamba</italic>, and a common full metal jacket (<italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic>) bullet] were evaluated in a series of experiments on soap blocks and removed bone plates followed by computed tomography examinations. Penetration potential was evaluated in terms of kinetic energy relative to the caliber of the bullet, i.e., mean energy density (<italic toggle="yes">ED</italic>). Injury potential was evaluated by the mean extent of the cavity volume (<italic toggle="yes">e</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">CV</italic></sub>) at the relevant penetration depth of 5.5 to 7.5 cm in the soap block.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>All four bullet types passed through the frontal bone plate. The <italic toggle="yes">ED</italic> was 17.50 J/mm<sup>2</sup> (<italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic>), 17.46 J/mm<sup>2</sup> (<italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic>), 13.47 J/mm<sup>2</sup> (<italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>), and 13.47 J/mm<sup>2</sup> (<italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic>). The <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> each fragmented heavily. The <italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic> was excluded after three experiments due to over-penetrations. The <italic toggle="yes">e</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">CV</italic></sub> was <italic toggle="yes">e</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">CV</italic></sub> = 3.77 cm<sup>2</sup> (<italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic>), 2.71 cm<sup>2</sup> (<italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic>), and 1.31 cm<sup>2</sup> (<italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>), with a significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.006) between the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>For use in heavy cattle, the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> are recommended due to the larger <italic toggle="yes">e</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">CV</italic></sub> than the <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="G1"><title>Graphical Abstract</title><p>
<graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1143744-g0005.jpg"/>
</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>stunning effectiveness</kwd><kwd>concussion</kwd><kwd>animal welfare</kwd><kwd>slaughter</kwd><kwd>heavy cattle</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic></kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Humane Killer</italic></kwd><kwd>injury potential</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="5"/><ref-count count="15"/><page-count count="9"/><word-count count="6466"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>For stunning of cattle, a captive-bolt gun is typically used to damage brain regions that have critical functions for consciousness and the sensation of pain. The goal here is that the animal is no longer sensitive to pain, which is why the term &#8220;desensitization&#8221; is used for the intended effect of stunning (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). The brain structures to be destroyed are located in the region of the brain stem and thalamus (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), and thus centrally located deep in the brain. A bolt length of 120 mm is sufficient to damage the corresponding brain regions of cattle, except in water buffaloes due to their large frontal sinuses and occasionally in heavy cattle due to their larger skull size (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). In addition, ordinary captive-bolt guns may be insufficient to punch through the frontal bones of heavy cattle with a live weight of up to 1,500 kg, so that adequate stunning is not assured. A previous study (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) has shown that beef bulls and older cull bulls are at higher risk for inferior stunning quality compared to dairy cows, female beef classes, or steer cattle classes. Improper stunning at slaughter causes pain and distress to animals, raising animal welfare concerns (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). To overcome problems in slaughtering water buffaloes and heavy cattle due to the insufficient bolt length and penetrating power of conventional stunning equipment, ordinary handguns are often used (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Although an improvement in the quality of water buffalo stunning has recently been demonstrated by the use of a pneumatic bolt gun (operating pressure: 200&#8211;220 psi; length of ejected bolt: 90 mm) at a newly proposed entry point located 8 cm above the reference point for cattle, a handgun ultimately had to be used in individual cases, even after a second follow-up shot with the bolt (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). In addition, such pneumatic bolt guns are not financially feasible for smaller slaughterhouses.</p><p>Since the use of ordinary handguns is not in the sense of our <italic toggle="yes">Federal Food Safety and Veterinary Office</italic> a newly developed 9 mm bullet-shooting stunner, named <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic>, was recently presented for adequate stunning of heavy cattle (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Instead of a bolt, this device fires 9 mm bullets to damage the corresponding brain regions. In this study (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), two different types of ammunition were used, a light full metal jacket (<italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic>) truncated cone .3<italic toggle="yes">8 Special</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>) and a semi-jacketed .3<italic toggle="yes">57 Magnum</italic> with a soft tip (<italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic>). Based on three velocity measurements and the mass of the bullet, the mean kinetic energy of the respective bullet type when fired with the <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic> was calculated (<italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>: 527.69 J, <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic>: 1133.63 J). As a common measure for the penetration potential in ballistics, the respective energy density (ED), i.e., the kinetic energy per unit reference area, was also given (<italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>: 8.18 J/mm<sup>2</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic>: 17.56 J/mm<sup>2</sup>), since this quantity is considered proportional to the penetration depth of a bullet into the tissue (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). For handguns, the caliber squared of the bullet is usually considered the reference surface (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). However, deformation and fragmentation can considerably change the reference area of the bullet, which then affects the penetration depth (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Since a bullet for adequate stunning of heavy cattle must pass through their thick frontal bones to reach the relevant brain regions, it can be assumed that, with the <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> used, a deformed or fragmented bullet will penetrate the brain tissue. This was shown in the computed tomography (CT) examinations of the severed heads of the heavy cattle, which were stunned with the <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic> (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). The data showed that the <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic> penetrated deeper into the tissue on average and over-penetrations were observed. The <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> fragmented in each case. Since both types of bullets perforated the frontal bones and reached the relevant brain regions, the recommendation was made for the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> because of the distribution of fragments and because no over-penetration was observed. However, this alone does not allow a valid statement to be made about the effectiveness of the individual bullet types, since the respective injury potential could not be determined. For a solid recommendation of a bullet type and regulatory endorsement, the potential for injury to the brain regions relevant to stunning is critical. In addition, the bullet type evaluated and finally endorsed should be easily available.</p><p>The injury potential of interest depends on how much of the kinetic energy is eventually transferred to the brain tissue at the relevant section of the penetration depth (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). This can be expressed indirectly by the volume of the temporary cavity that is temporarily formed along the bullet path (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). With the extension of this cavity per distance, the deformation forces cause the injury to the tissue, which is stretched and torn in the process. In wound ballistics, this is described as local energy transfer, which is represented by the extent of this cavity (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Therefore, the extent of the cavity volume at the relevant penetration depth is an indirect measure of the injury potential (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Glycerin soap is typically used in ballistic experiments as a soft tissue simulant to investigate the extent of the temporary cavity. Such ballistic soap deforms mainly plastically, which means that the maximum extent of the temporary cavity in the soap block is &#8220;frozen&#8221; and consequently can be well studied and analyzed (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p><p>The objective of this study was to assess the injury potential of the different bullet types when shot with the <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic> based on the cavities created in ballistic soap after passing through frontal bone plates from heavy cattle. In addition to the bullet types previously used (<italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>), two additional bullet types were evaluated in this study. First, the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> as an alternative to the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic>, due to its limited availability, and second, an ordinary full metal jacket bullet compared to the full-jacketed <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>, in order to point out the increased danger when using an ordinary full metal jacket bullet. For this purpose, shooting experiments were performed and subsequent CT scans of the soap blocks allowed quantitative study of the cavities created by the individual bullet types at the corresponding penetration depth. Accordingly, this study presents the relevant ballistic characteristics of four different bullet types when used with the <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic> and provides an assessment of the injury potential, respectively, the stunning potential when using the <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic> in the slaughter of heavy cattle.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Bullet specifications</title><p>Four different types of 9 mm bullets were tested for the use with the <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic> bullet-shooting stunner (<italic toggle="yes">Vogt Waffen AG, Oberglatt, Switzerland</italic>). The four bullet types are shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. The first type of bullet was the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic>, a .3<italic toggle="yes">57 Magnum</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Hornady</italic><sup>&#174;</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">LEVERevolution</italic><sup>&#174;</sup><italic toggle="yes">, Grand Island, Nebraska, U.S.A</italic>.) with a mass of 140 grains (gr) and a special tip (<italic toggle="yes">Flex Tip</italic><sup>&#174;</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">Technology</italic>) to transfer more energy than conventional bullets with a flat tip. The second type of bullet was the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Federal Premium</italic><sup>&#174;</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">Ammunition, Anoka, Minnesota, U.S.A</italic>.), a readily available ammunition not previously used with the <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic>. This hollow point bullet with a mass of 158 gr and a notched jacket is designed for controlled expansion when penetrating tissue. The third type of bullet was the <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>, a full metal jacket truncated cone .3<italic toggle="yes">8 Special</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba, Fiocchi Ammunition, Lecco, Italia</italic>), which has a slight curvature toward the inside at the flat tip and, in addition, this curvature toward the inside also has only a thin layer of the jacket. The <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic> is an effective hunting bullet with a low mass of 110 gr. The fourth bullet type was a conventional full metal jacket .3<italic toggle="yes">57 Magnum</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Sellier</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bellot, Vla&#353;im, Czech Republic</italic>). This type of bullet, referred to as <italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic> in this study, was selected to demonstrate potential danger of a conventional full metal jacket bullet when used for stunning cattle in an abattoir. It was assumed that the penetrating depth of this type of bullet with a mass of 158 gr is far too high and over-penetration is very likely. All bullets were fired by one and the same person using the <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic>. The different types of bullets were evaluated in two separate experiment series.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The four different 9 mm bullets evaluated in this study in terms of their injury potential when used with the <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic> for stunning heavy cattle. Note the different design of the tip and the length of each bullet. The <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic> (110 gr) is shorter and has a lower mass than the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady</italic> (140 gr), the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> (158 gr), and the <italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic> (158 gr).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1143744-g0001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Experiment series A</title><p>The first series of experiments (experiment series A) served to determine the kinetic energy and energy density, the basic data for bullet types used with the gun in question. These quantities were also determined for the bullet types already classified in the earlier study (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), since the data already collected were based on only three velocity measurements.</p><p>In the present study, velocities of the bullets were measured at a distance of approximately 50 cm from the barrel using a ballistic chronograph (<italic toggle="yes">Model M-1, Shooting CHRONY Inc., Mississauga, Canada</italic>). This distance was chosen to avoid erroneous measurements due to the expelled propellant gas. In the <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref> the experimental setup is illustrated. The measured velocity of the bullet was considered the muzzle velocity, i.e. the velocity the bullet has immediately after leaving the barrel. For each type of bullet ten velocity experiments were performed. From the velocity <italic toggle="yes">v</italic> and the mass <italic toggle="yes">m</italic> of the bullet, the kinetic energy <italic toggle="yes">E</italic> in joule (J) was calculated as follows:
<disp-formula id="E1"><label>(1A)</label><mml:math id="M1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
For the mass of the corresponding bullet type, the value of the manufacturer's weight specification was used in the equation.</p><p>In ballistics, the kinetic energy density <italic toggle="yes">ED</italic> (also abbreviated as <italic toggle="yes">KED</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>&#8242;) in J/mm<sup>2</sup> is typically expressed as the kinetic energy per cross-sectional area <italic toggle="yes">A</italic>, where the cross-sectional area can be calculated from the caliber of the bullet (<italic toggle="yes">cal</italic>) (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>):
<disp-formula id="E2"><label>(2A)</label><mml:math id="M2" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo class="qopname">max</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#960;</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
For the caliber of all bullet types, a value of 9.07 cm (the conversion value of 0.357 inches rounded to two digits) was used for the calculations of the energy densities.</p><p>To account for the propagation of uncertainty in the calculation of the mean kinetic energy <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> and the mean energy density <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>, the mean error of the kinetic energy (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M5" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>&#916;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>), and the mean error of the energy density (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M6" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>&#916;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>) was determined as follows:
<disp-formula id="E3"><label>(1B)</label><mml:math id="M7" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#916;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#916;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>&#274;</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
respectively,
<disp-formula id="E4"><label>(2B)</label><mml:math id="M8" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#916;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#916;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>&#916;</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> is the mean error of the velocity measurements, which was calculated by the standard deviation of the velocities divided by the square root of the number of measurements.</p></sec><sec><title>Experiment series B</title><p>In the second series of experiments (experiment series B) the cavity volume created when the bullet penetrated the soap block was investigated. The extent of the cavity over the relevant section of the penetration depth was the measure for the injury potential.</p><p>For this purpose, contact shots were performed on ballistic soap blocks (<italic toggle="yes">Mettler-Seifen SA, Henniez, Switzerland</italic>) to which postmortem removed skull bone plates from heavy cattle were attached, namely the frontal bone plate at the front end of the soap block and the corresponding occipital bone plate at its rear end. The soap blocks had a dimension of approximately 25 &#215; 25 &#215; 20 cm and a weight of 13.5 kg. The bone plates were fixed to the soap block with a tension belt. A new pair of bone plates was used for each experiment. For the shot, the <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic> was placed on the frontal bone plate. In the <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref> the experimental setup is illustrated. Eight contact shot experiments were intended for each type of bullet. Over-penetration, i.e., penetration of the occipital bone plate and onward flight of the bullet, was considered a major hazard in actual use of the <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic>. Therefore, a bullet type that over-penetrated three times was excluded from further experiments.</p><p>After these shot experiments, the soap blocks were packaged and transported to a clinical CT scanner (<italic toggle="yes">SOMATOM</italic><sup>&#174;</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">Definition Flash, Siemens Healthineers, Erlangen, Germany</italic>), where CT scans of the individual soap blocks were performed. The scan parameters were 120 kV, 400 mAs, and a pitch of 0.35 for reconstructions with an almost isotropic voxel size of approximately 0.6 mm<sup>3</sup> using a soft kernel (Br38) and a hard kernel (Br60). In addition, reconstructions with extended CT scale were made to visualize the lodged bullets and bullet fragments. The reconstructed CT data were visualized and analyzed using medical image registration software (<italic toggle="yes">syngo.via VB30A_HF07, Siemens Healthineers, Erlangen, Germany</italic>). The total volume (<italic toggle="yes">V</italic>) of this cavity was measured with a region-based image segmentation method (region growing). The penetration depth (<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>) was measured using a linear distance measuring tool.</p><p>To estimate the injury potential, the mean extent of the cavity volume along the relevant section of the penetration depth was measured. The relevant penetration depth was derived from mean values of CT-based distance measurements (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M10" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>) between the skin and the thalamus (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M11" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> = 10.2 cm) and between the skin to the inner table of the frontal bone (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M12" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> = 3.65 cm) in cattle older than 30 months (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Taking the difference of the mean distances, the relevant penetration depth from the inner table of the frontal bone to the thalamus was 6.55 cm. Since neither standard deviations of the measurements nor the exact number of CT measurements were given, a deviation of 1 cm was assumed. To estimate the corresponding mean extent of the cavity volume, cross-sectional images with 0.5 cm slice thickness were reconstructed from the CT data along the bullet path starting from the entrance hole. Then, the cross-sectional area (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>) of the cavity volume was measured on CT images No. 11&#8211;15 corresponding to a penetration depth of 5.5&#8211;7.5 cm, respectively. A software-based freehand region-of-interest measurement tool was used for these volume measurements. Finally, the mean cross-sectional extent of the cavity volume (<italic toggle="yes">e</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">CV</italic></sub>) in cm<sup>2</sup> was calculated along the relevant section of the penetration depth (&#948;<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>), which is proportional to the injury potential (<italic toggle="yes">IP</italic>):
<disp-formula id="E5"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M13" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#948;</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover accentunder="false" accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#8721;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover></mml:mstyle><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> is the number of images.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>For the measured data (<italic toggle="yes">v</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">V</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">d</italic>) and for <italic toggle="yes">e</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">CV</italic></sub>(&#948;<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>) the mean values (standard deviations) are given. For the calculated physical quantities (<italic toggle="yes">E</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ED</italic>), the mean values (mean errors) are given. The mean values, standard deviations, and mean errors given in this study were rounded to two decimal places.</p><p>The Shapiro-Wilk test was used to test for normal distribution. Analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to test whether the mean values of the bullet types differ from each other in terms <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">ED</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">V</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">e</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">CV</italic></sub>(&#948;<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>). When the ANOVA test showed a significant difference, pairwise <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-tests with <italic toggle="yes">Bonferroni</italic> correction were used as <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> tests to check between which bullet types there was a significant difference. A <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value of &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. The <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values given are rounded to three decimal places, respectively, very small <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values are given as &lt;0.001. An outlier is defined as such if the value is smaller than the first quartile by 1.5 times the interquartile range or larger than the third quartile by 1.5 times the interquartile range. The statistical analyses were done in <italic toggle="yes">RStudio (RStudio, Inc., Boston, MA, USA</italic>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>Mean values are listed in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> (experiment series A) and <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> (experiment series B). Individual values are listed in the <xref rid="SM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref>. In addition, there are CT reconstructions of all soap blocks in the <xref rid="SM3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Results of experiment series A given as mean value (standard deviation) for <italic toggle="yes">v</italic> and mean value (mean error) for <italic toggle="yes">E</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">ED</italic>.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Type</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">v</italic> (m/s)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">E</italic> (J)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">ED</italic> (J/mm<sup>2</sup>)</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">499.13 (7.74)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1130.28 (11.09)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.50 (0.17)<xref rid="TN1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">469.32 (6.10)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1127.71 (9.28)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.46 (0.14)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">377.39 (6.78)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">507.74 (5.77)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.86 (0.09)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">412.17 (5.53)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">869.79 (7.25)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.47 (0.11)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">v</italic>, velocity; <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>, kinetic energy; <italic toggle="yes">ED</italic>, energy density.</p><fn id="TN1"><label>*</label><p>w/o outlier: 17.64 (0.11).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Results of experiment series B given as mean value (standard deviation).</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Type</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">d</italic> (cm)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">V</italic> (cm<sup>3</sup>)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">e</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">CV</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">&#948;d</italic>) (cm<sup>2</sup>)</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.50 (2.43)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.34 (23.39)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.77 (1.96)<xref rid="TN2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.38 (3.66)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.13 (17.99)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.71 (1.41)<xref rid="TN3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>**</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.42 (3.15)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.31 (5.82)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 (0.33)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">d</italic>, penetration depth; <italic toggle="yes">V</italic>, total volume of the cavity; <italic toggle="yes">e</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">CV</italic></sub>(&#948;<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>), cross sectional extent of the cavity volume over the penetration depth section of 9&#8211;10.5 cm. w/o outlier:</p><fn id="TN2"><label>*</label><p>3.22 (1.29),</p></fn><fn id="TN3"><label>**</label><p>2.30 (0.84).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec><title>Results of experiment series A</title><p>With a mean value of 7.86 (0.09) J/mm<sup>2</sup> the energy density of the <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic> was more than twice as low as that of the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> at 17.50 (0.17) J/mm<sup>2</sup> and that of the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> at 17.46 (0.14) J/mm<sup>2</sup>, and almost twice as low as that of the <italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic> at 13.47 (0.11) J/mm<sup>2</sup> (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> had an outlier with a value of 16.28 J/mm<sup>2</sup>. Excluding this outlier, the Hornady FTX had a mean energy density of 17.64 (0.11) J/mm<sup>2</sup>.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Boxplots of the calculated energy densities in J/mm<sup>2</sup> for the individual bullet types. The <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> demonstrated almost two and a half times more energy density than the <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>. The energy density of the <italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic> was almost twice as high as that of the <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>. There were significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) in energy density between the individual bullet types, except between the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic>. The <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> had an outlier with a value of 16.28 J/mm<sup>2</sup>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1143744-g0002.jpg"/></fig><p>The Shapiro-Wilk test showed that the kinetic energies and the energy densities of the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic>, the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic>, the <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>, and the <italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic> were normally distributed. The ANOVA test revealed a significant difference between the bullet types in terms of their kinetic energy (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.002) and in terms of their energy density (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). The <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> tests revealed significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) in the kinetic energy and the energy density between the <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic> and each other bullet type, and between the <italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic> and each other type of bullet. There were no significant differences between the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Results of experiment series B</title><p>Soap block shootings were successfully carried out as each bullet perforated the frontal bone plate. However, while for the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX, Hydra-Shok</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic> all eight experiments were performed without over-penetration, no further experiments were performed for the <italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic> after three experiments, as this bullet also perforated the occipital bone sample on the back of the soap block. The over-penetrated <italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic> formed a narrow channel in all three experiments with a total volume of 68.66, 44.89, and 42.76 cm<sup>3</sup>, respectively. After passing through the frontal bone plate only tiny bullet fragments were visible along the narrow channel in the soap block (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). Due to the small number of experiments with the <italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic>, this bullet type was excluded from the statistical evaluation.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Transverse cross-sectional CT image through the cavity immediately after the perforation of the frontal bone sample and penetration into the soap block (for each bullet type, the left image in grayscale), volume rendering to show the entire cave in the soap block (for each bullet type, the right image kept in the color of the soap block), and maximum intensity projection to highlight bullet fragments along the cavity (for each bullet type, the right small image in black and white).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1143744-g0003.jpg"/></fig><p>The <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Sho</italic>k presented numerous fragments along funnel-shaped cavities that started from a large diameter immediately after the frontal bone sample and narrowed as the bullet penetrated the soap block. The <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic> exhibited few fragments along a narrow channel. The ANOVA test revealed a significant difference between the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic>, the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic>, and the <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). The mean volume of the <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic> was significantly smaller than those of the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.001) and the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.037).</p><p>The mean extent of the cavity volume along the relevant section of the penetration depth was 3.77 (1.96) cm<sup>2</sup> for the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic>, 2.71 cm<sup>2</sup> (1.41) cm<sup>2</sup> for the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic>, and 1.31 (0.33) cm<sup>2</sup> for the <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>. The ANOVA test showed a significant difference between these three bullet types (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.002). The <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> tests revealed a significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.006) in the cross-sectional extent of the cavity volume between the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>. The <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> showed outliers with values of 7.63 and 5.61 cm<sup>2</sup>, respectively (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). After exclusion of the outlier, the mean volume extent was 3.22 (1.29) cm<sup>2</sup> for the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and 2.30 (0.84) cm<sup>2</sup> for the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic>. For the <italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic>, the cross-sectional extents of the cavity volume were 5.92, 2.37, and 2.38 cm<sup>2</sup>.</p><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Boxplots of the mean cross-sectional extent of the cavity volume (e<sub>CV</sub>) in cm<sup>2</sup> along the relevant section of the penetration depth into the soap block (5.5&#8211;7.5 cm). The mean volume extent of the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> was larger than that of the <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>. Outlier were observed for the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> (7.63 cm<sup>2</sup>) and the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> (5.61 cm<sup>2</sup>). The <italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic> achieved values comparable to the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic>, assuming an outlier at 5.92 cm<sup>2</sup>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1143744-g0004.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study shows the difference between four bullet types when shot with the <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic> through frontal bone plates of heavy cattle into ballistic soap, which allows for assessing the injury potential based on the cross-sectional extent of the cavity volume along the relevant section of penetration depth.</p><p>Both, the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> demonstrated similar mean energy densities. This may seem astonishing at first glance, since the mass of the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> was only a factor of 1.13 heavier than the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic>, but the latter reached a velocity almost 30 m/s higher (&#916;<italic toggle="yes">v</italic> = 29.81 m/s), and the velocity is squared in the equation for the kinetic energy. In fact, the mean velocity of the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> was only a factor of 0.94 less than that of the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic>, and since the velocity is squared in the kinetic energy equation, the differences in mass and velocity equalize in the result, i.e., the mean kinetic energy. Regarding the <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>, the low velocity together with the low mass resulted in significantly lower energy values compared to the other three bullet types. The results of the velocity measurements were similar to those of the previous study mentioned in the Section Introduction (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), in which the mean velocity was 499.89 m/s for the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and 384.79 m/s for the <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>.</p><p>The energy density showed the same ratios between the bullet types as the kinetic energy due to the same reference areas, respectively, the same caliber. Consequently, due to the proportionality between energy density and penetration depth, the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> are expected to penetrate more than twice as far into tissue, assuming that the trajectory of the projectiles is stable. A stable trajectory means that the bullets do not rotate, nor deform or fragment. However, especially due to fragmentation, the penetration depth can decrease considerably. This is mainly due to the strongly decreasing kinetic energy due to fragmentation. A portion of the kinetic energy is converted for the process of fragmentation and remaining kinetic energy is distributed to the individual fragments. From the results of this study, it is obvious that the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> began to fragment as they penetrated the bone plate, while the other two bullet types were largely unfragmented. Therefore, a large proportion of the kinetic energy has likely been dissipated by the time the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> penetrated the bone plate. As a result, these two bullet types did not pass through the soap block and eventually perforate the occipital bone plate behind it despite their high energy density, while the <italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic> with a significantly lower energy density did so in every experiment. The question therefore arises as to the informative value of the energy density for determining the penetration depth through bone structures. In the end, the decisive factor is whether and how much energy was released at the relevant penetration depth, which can be inferred from the extent of the cavity volume.</p><p>Based on the extent of the cavity volumes at the relevant penetration depth of 5.5&#8211;7.5 cm in the soap block, the injury potential of the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> is significantly and considerably greater than that of the <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>, respectively. The <italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic> in comparison showed comparable values to the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> despite the narrow channel. This may seem surprising at first glance, since the extent of the cavity volume of the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> is very large due to fragmentation upon entry into the soap block, but decreases substantially with increasing penetration depth. Despite the comparable injury potential of the <italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic>, the use of this type of bullet for the stunning of heavy cattle is strongly discouraged because over-penetration was observed in all experiments. In the previous study (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>) where the <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic> was used in regular slaughtering, over-penetration was observed even with the <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>, although not so in the present study. Consequently, bullets that fragment but reach the relevant penetration depth are preferable for safety reasons.</p><p>Safety and proper use are important criteria for the use of a bullet shooting stunner such as the <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic> and therefore a gun purchase license is required. In fact, already at the beginning of the twentieth century stunning devices for cattle have been developed, which discharged a bullet previously inserted into the barrel by striking the firing pin with a wooden hammer; but with these devices, accidents involving gunshot wounds to butchers soon became more frequent, so many butchers were already switching to the safer captive-bolt stunners (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Today, such bullet shooting stunners are occasionally still in use to stun cattle. A study in the 1980s showed that the <italic toggle="yes">Humane Killer</italic> could fire a 10-g bullet at a velocity of 165 m/s, corresponding to a kinetic energy of 136 J, which was considered sufficient for stunning cattle, based on preliminary studies that showed it would take about 127 J to penetrate the skull of a cattle (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). In this study, a 10-g bullet with 49 lead pellets in a polyethylene casing similar to a shotgun shell was used so that the bullet fragments and the individual lead pellets distribute in the brain, thus preventing over-penetration. Results recently published data (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) showed a kinetic energy of 164 J for an 8-g bullet with a caliber of 7.5 mm when use a <italic toggle="yes">Humane Killer</italic> resulting in an energy density of 3.71 J/mm<sup>2</sup> (note: in the study an energy density of 2.9 J/mm<sup>2</sup> is given, which is based on the kinetic energy divided by the caliber squared), which, was enough to pass through the bone plates of water buffaloes, but the bullet had only 8% of its initial kinetic energy left. In the case of heavy cattle, it can therefore be assumed that the <italic toggle="yes">Humane Killer</italic> does not provide the required energy density for the bullet to penetrate the thicker skull plates. Bullet shooting stunners recently developed for water buffaloes (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) are capable of giving a bullet the required energy density, but to our knowledge these are only prototypes so far and are not commercially available. The <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic> used in this study is commercially available and has already shown satisfactory results in the context of regular slaughtering of heavy cattle. In the end, however, it all comes down to the conscientious and practiced handling of the butcher. On the one hand, the butcher must be aware that the stunning device is firing a bullet and, on the other hand, the bullet shooting stunner must be placed at the correct position and operated at the correct angle so that the relevant brain regions are appropriately injured in the process of creating the temporary wound cavity.</p><p>In the present study, the cavity volume determined on the CT data was not related to the transferred energy. Although the proportionality factor between cavity volume and energy transferred to the medium is considered to be independent of the shape and size of a metallic projectile when the transferred energy is &lt;2,500 J (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), it is not described how this proportionality between cavity volume and transferred energy behaves when a bullet fragments along its path through the medium. Since both the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> were highly fragmented in the present study, no conversion of the resulting cavity volume to the transferred energy was carried out.</p><p>This study has some limitations. First, it should be pointed out that a homogeneous soft tissue simulant was used, which represents tissue very well, but is not identical in its material properties. Although the experimental data of this study are in agreement with the data on the use of the <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic> in the earlier applied study, deviations in routine application cannot be excluded. Second, there are discrepancies between experimental setting and anatomical conditions. Thus, the brain tissue is enclosed by the bony skull and is also smaller in volume compared to the soap block. These discrepancies were considered negligible for the purpose of comparing the four bullet types in terms of their injury potential. Third, the distance between the muzzle of the bullet shooting stunner and the object may show variations in the results. In the event of a contact shot, the propellant gas can penetrate the tissue, contributing to its destruction. At a distance of a few centimeters, this additional effect is lost. In this study, the <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic> was applied directly to the removed forehead plates. However, since the soap block was not fully surrounded by bony structure, the effect of propellant gases may be reduced. Fourth, metal artifacts of the larger fragments on the CT images might influence the segmented cavity volume. However, these deviations in the exact determination of individual volumes are considered negligible in view of the differences in volumes in individual experiments for one and the same bullet type. The method of segmentation itself instead of measuring directly on the soap block is considered accurate. A recent study showed very high accuracy for CT-based determinations of the cavity volume compared to a common method using silicone castings, which turned out to be far less accurate (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Based on the results of this study, we recommend two bullet types for stunning heavy cattle with the <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic>, namely the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic>. First, these bullet types have a high energy density and thus a high penetration potential to pass through the thick frontal bones of heavy cattle. Second, over-penetration is unlikely due to the high fragmentation of the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic>. Third, at the relevant penetration depth, these two bullet types caused extents of the cavity volumes equivalent to and greater than those of the <italic toggle="yes">FMJ</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Black Mamba</italic>, respectively, and therefore the injury potential of the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> is considered adequate for stunning heavy cattle. Approval of the <italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic> with the <italic toggle="yes">Hornady FTX</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Hydra-Shok</italic> for stunning heavy cattle can now form the basis for further large-scale field studies.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be made available by the authors, without undue reservation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="s7"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>Ethical review and approval was not required for the animal study because no study was performed on live animals. However, we would like to mention here that frontal bone plates of heavy cattle, taken after regular slaughtering, were used for the experiments. No animal was killed for the purpose of the study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s8"><title>Author contributions</title><p>DG: conceptualization, investigation, methodology, formal analysis, writing and editing, and visualization. RS and NZ: review and editing. MV: investigation. MO: visualization. MT: resources. HR: project administration, conceptualization, investigation, review, and editing. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors would like to thank Paul M&#252;ller and Lukas Fuchs for their help in transporting and storing the soap blocks.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>MV was employed by the company Vogt Waffen AG. The remaining authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s9"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s10"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2023.1143744/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2023.1143744/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM2" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_2.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM3" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_3.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mota-Rojas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Napolitano</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strappini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orihuela</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghezzi</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hern&#225;ndez-&#193;valos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pain at the slaughterhouse in ruminants with a focus on the neurobiology of sensitisation</article-title>. <source>Animals.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1085</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani11041085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33920244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8068923</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Penetrating captive bolt stunning and exsanguination of cattle in abattoirs</article-title>. <source>J Appl Anim Welf Sci.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>215</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1207/S15327604JAWS0303_3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gascho</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oesch</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">BigBovid</italic>-Evaluation of a newly developed 9 mm bullet-shooting stunner for adequate stunning of heavy cattle</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>949198</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.949198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35968016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9363664</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwenk</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lechner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gascho</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kneubuehl</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glardon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Magnetic resonance imaging and computer tomography of brain lesions in water buffaloes and cattle stunned with handguns or captive bolts</article-title>. <source>Meat Sci.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>113</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2015.11.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26610289</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Velarde</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Algers</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of stun quality at commercial slaughter in cattle shot with captive bolt</article-title>. <source>Anim Welf.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>473</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7120/09627286.22.4.473</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mota-Rojas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghezzi</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Napolitano</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosmini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerrero-Legarreta</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;nez-Burnes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Quality of death in the river buffalo (<italic toggle="yes">Bubalus bubalis</italic>)</article-title>. <source>J Anim Behav Biometeorol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>2115</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.31893/jabb.21015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glardon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwenk</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riva</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>von Holzen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kneubuehl</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Energy loss and impact of various stunning devices used for the slaughtering of water buffaloes</article-title>. <source>Meat Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>135</volume>:<fpage>159</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2017.09.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29035813</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Molnar-Fern&#225;ndez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mu&#241;oz-Vargas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romero-Z&#250;&#241;iga</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Araya-Rodr&#237;guez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Highly effective frontal stunning procedure using a pneumatic penetrating captive bolt in water buffaloes</article-title>. <source>Animals.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>177</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani13010177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36611785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9817958</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sellier</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kneubuehl</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Wound Ballistics and the Scientific Background</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name> (<year>1994</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kneubuehl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>editor</surname></name></person-group>. <article-title>General wound ballistics</article-title>. In: <source>Wound Ballistics: Basics and Applications</source>. <publisher-loc>Berlin; Heidelberg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name> (<year>2011</year>). p. <fpage>87</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>162</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pollak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saukko</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Humane killing tools</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Houck</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group>, editor. <source>Firearm and Toolmark Examination and Identification</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name> (<year>2015</year>) p. <fpage>228</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackmore</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Energy requirements for the penetration of heads of domestic stock and the development of a multiple projectile</article-title>. <source>Vet Rec.</source> (<year>1985</year>) <volume>116</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/vr.116.2.36</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3976138</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gascho</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stephan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oesch</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of a newly designed double-barreled bullet-shooting stunner for adequate stunning of water buffaloes</article-title>. <source>Meat Sci.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>193</volume>:<fpage>108933</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2022.108933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35961127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meichtry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glauser</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glardon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lechner</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kneubuehl</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of a specifically developed bullet casing gun for the stunning of water buffaloes</article-title>. <source>Meat Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>135</volume>:<fpage>74</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2017.09.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28938106</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgos-D&#237;ez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zapata</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chamorro-Sancho</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruano-Rando</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrando-Gil</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garc&#237;a-Ruiz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison between computed tomography and silicone-casting methods to determine gunshot cavities in ballistic soap</article-title>. <source>Int J Legal Med</source>. (<year>2020</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00414-020-02464-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33190163</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>