<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11776088</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11776088.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11776088</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11776088</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">39881723</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2024.1473688</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Soybean and avocado unsaponifiables: a review of their potential use in the treatment of osteoarthritis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabucedo-Su&#225;rez</surname><given-names initials="A">Ana</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn0001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2802465/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#243;pez-Pe&#241;a</surname><given-names initials="M">M&#243;nica</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn0001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1096063/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/resources/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Permuy</surname><given-names initials="M">Mar&#237;a</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn0001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1120949/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/resources/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/visualization/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mu&#241;&#243;z</surname><given-names initials="F">Fernando</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn0001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1222218/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Departamento de Anatom&#237;a, Producci&#243;n Animal e Ciencias Cl&#237;nicas Veterinarias, Facultade de Veterinaria, Campus Terra, Universidade de Santiago de Compostela</institution>, <addr-line>Lugo</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>IboneLab S.L., Laboratory of Biomaterials</institution>, <addr-line>Lugo</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0005"><p>Edited by: Ramesh Chandra Gupta, Murray State University, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0006"><p>Reviewed by: Begum Yurdakok Dikmen, Ankara University, T&#252;rkiye</p><p>Claudia Interlandi, University of Messina, Italy</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: M&#243;nica L&#243;pez-Pe&#241;a, <email>monica.lopez@usc.es</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn0001"><p><sup>&#8224;</sup>ORCID: Ana Sabucedo-Su&#225;rez, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0009-0003-6798-0154" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0009-0003-6798-0154</ext-link></p><p>M&#243;nica L&#243;pez-Pe&#241;a, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6387-4790" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6387-4790</ext-link></p><p>Fernando Mu&#241;&#243;z, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4130-1526" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4130-1526</ext-link></p><p>Mar&#237;a Permuy, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3708-4821" ext-link-type="uri">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3708-4821</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">454084</issue-id><elocation-id>1473688</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>9</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>29</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-02-01 11:25:14.640"><day>01</day><month>02</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2025 Sabucedo-Su&#225;rez, L&#243;pez-Pe&#241;a, Permuy and Mu&#241;oz.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sabucedo-Su&#225;rez, L&#243;pez-Pe&#241;a, Permuy and Mu&#241;oz</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-11-1473688.pdf"/><abstract><p>Recent research has shown that Avocado-Soybean Unsaponifiables (ASU) greatly reduce the symptoms of osteoarthritis (OA). It&#8217;s yet unknown exactly how ASU works, however, it has been demonstrated to have analgesic and anti-inflammatory effects. These qualities can potentially lessen the need for non-steroidal anti-inflammatory medicines (NSAIDs) and their secondary effects. This review aims to examine the current literature on ASU, focusing on their efficacy, mechanism of action, and potential utility in treating OA for managing chronic pain associated with this condition. The literature review was conducted manually through Pubmed, Scopus and Web of Science (WOS) databases, covering studies from 2000 to 2022 with terms like &#8220;osteoarthritis,&#8221; &#8220;OA,&#8221; &#8220;animal models,&#8221; &#8220;ASU,&#8221; and &#8220;soy/avocado.&#8221; Two reviewers independently screened each article using inclusion and exclusion criteria and categorized the studies into <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>, preclinical, and clinical groups. According to in vitro research, ASU affect the regulation of molecules related to OA, increasing structural elements like collagen and aggrecan and decreasing pro-inflammatory mediators. Although results vary, pre-clinical research in different animal models has demonstrated positive effects, such as ameliorating histopathological changes and reduced inflammation. Despite some discrepancies regarding structural changes in the joints, clinical trials typically demonstrate symptom relief and slow down the disease progression. While ASU demonstrates significant promise in alleviating OA symptoms and reducing reliance on NSAIDs, further research is essential to fully understand its mechanisms of action. More studies are needed to determine the precise pathways through which ASU exerts its effects and to establish the most effective dosages for its administration, either alone or in combination with other treatments.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>osteoarthritis</kwd><kwd>OA</kwd><kwd>cartilage</kwd><kwd>soybean</kwd><kwd>unsaponifiables</kwd><kwd>ASU</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that financial support was received for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This study was funded by the GRC support program from Xunta de Galicia (GRC ED431C 2021/19) and the UE project IBEROS+ (0072_IBEROS_MAIS_1_E) financed by the POCTEP 2021-2027 FEDER program.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="50"/><page-count count="11"/><word-count count="7634"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Veterinary Pharmacology and Toxicology</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Osteoarthritis (OA) is an inflammatory disorder characterized by chronic progression. In humans, it has been reported that approximately 15% of the total population and more than 50% of the population over 60&#8239;years of age may suffer from OA at some point in their lives. In companion animals, it is one of the most common diseases, however, prevalence data are unclear, and the results of some authors contradict each other (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), estimating annual period prevalence of appendicular osteoarthritis in 2.5% (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). It is usually found in weight-bearing joints such as the hips and knees, adding to the belief that mechanical stress plays a major role in OA (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). It can be caused by trauma, metabolic, infectious or nutritional disorders, or congenital diseases affecting young individuals. Joint dysplasia, osteochondrosis dissecans, ununited ankle process, and patellar dislocation are examples of disorders that can lead to secondary OA (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>).</p><p>The Osteo Arthritis Research Society International (OARSI) defines it as a disorder affecting mobile joints, characterized by cellular stress and extracellular matrix (ECM) degradation. This disorder involves different mechanisms such as articular cartilage damage, bone remodeling, new bone formation, synovial inflammation, and fibrosis of ligaments, tendons, menisci, and capsules (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>); following an order which molecular level mechanisms are affected first, followed by anatomical and physiological disorders. These micro- and macro-injuries will result in maladaptive repair responses, causing the body&#8217;s attempts to compensate for the damage to result in a worsening of the process.</p><p>These maladaptive responses can be described as three bubbles or vicious circles involved in the pathophysiology of OA (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) and in the evolution of the process (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Each of these three loops affects a specific structure of the joint architecture: cartilage, subchondral bone, and synovial membrane, respectively.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The maladaptive responses of the pathophysiology of OA. In blue the cartilage-cartilage loop. In orange the cartilage-subchondral bone loop. In green the cartilage-synovial membrane loop.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-11-1473688-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>The first step is the presence of abnormal mechanical joint stress which will cause cartilage lesions and in turn, the activation of chondrocytes. Consequently, levels of proinflammatory cytokines such as interleukins (IL-1, IL-6, IL-8) and tumor necrosis factor (TNF-<italic toggle="yes">&#945;</italic>) increase, releasing catabolic factors such as nitric oxide (NO), matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs), collagenases, aggrecanases, prostaglandin E2 (PGE2) and cyclooxygenase 2 (COX-2). In addition, IL-1 will play a major role in stimulating chondrocytes to produce more MMPs, promoting the continuation of matrix degradation. This corresponds to the first loop: cartilage-cartilage. At the same time, the mechanical stress will stimulate the osteoblasts present in the subchondral bone, which will release IL-6, also helping to stimulate the chondrocytes to produce more MMPs. This constitutes the second loop: cartilage-subchondral bone, leading to the appearance of fibrillation and erosion of the articular surface. Finally, as a product of matrix degradation, pro-inflammatory mediators (PGE-2, NO, or cytokines) also appear, which promote inflammation of the synovial membrane, stimulating the activation of chondrocytes and forming the third loop: cartilage-synovial membrane.</p><p>Specifically, PGE2 stimulates the production of degradative enzymes and inhibits the synthesis of cartilage components, particularly proteoglycans, and perpetuates the inflammatory response and cartilage damage by inducing the production of other pro-inflammatory mediators.</p><p>As the process evolves and in the later stages of OA, macroscopic lesions will become increasingly evident: erosions will occur throughout the cartilage reaching the subchondral bone, chondrocyte hypertrophy and clustering will lead to calcium deposition and osteophyte formation, catabolic factors will eventually lead to chondrocyte apoptosis, and all of this will eventually lead to sclerosis of the subchondral bone (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). In either case, it is a cause of reduced quality of life and its management can be complicated (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). It is known that in humans&#8217; osteoarthritis can be extremely painful and in animals, it is no different. Several studies have shown that the positive response to analgesic therapy (versus other factors) may indicate that, for example, dogs experience a similar level of pain as humans (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>).</p><p>Current strategies to combat OA are aimed at relieving pain, improving function and quality of life, and slowing down the process (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Unfortunately, currently available medications cause numerous side effects and, in addition, a high number of patients do not achieve sufficient pain relief even with the combination of several analgesics (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p><p>The American College of Rheumatology (ACR) Arthritis Foundation and the Osteoarthritis Society International (OARSI) in their guidelines both agree in strongly recommending exercise, weight loss and, cognitive behavioral therapy from a physical approach. On the other hand, topical and oral NSAIDs are also strongly recommended in patients with knee OA (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p><p>However, for the use of oral NSAIDs, they are recommended but only in the absence of comorbid conditions and, if possible, with the addition of a proton pump inhibitor or selective COX-2 inhibitors (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Therefore, research into new formulations is needed to clarify the mechanisms of pain and open new opportunities for targeted and more effective treatments.</p><p>Herbal medicines have a longstanding tradition in treating osteoarthritis, and recent research highlights their potential to alleviate pain and inflammation, through the interaction with inflammatory mediators and cartilage destruction, however, the mechanism of action of these is not yet fully understood (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Despite this, evidence of their effectiveness in several studies provides a strong rationale for using them to treat OA symptoms (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Related to this, it is important to note how other natural products, such as cannabidiol (CBD), are gaining popularity (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). The therapeutic use of CBD as an anti-inflammatory and immunomodulatory agent to treat chronic pain in both horses (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), and dogs is showing promising results, and there are already several studies describing pain relief related to OA (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Therefore, herbal anti-inflammatory drugs provide a broad-spectrum mechanism of action. They interact to varying degrees in the inflammatory cascade, but experimental data also indicate interaction with the production of mediators of cartilage destruction. Other mechanisms of action include inhibition of elastase or hyaluronidase or antioxidant efficacy (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>).</p><p>More specifically, avocado-soybean unsaponifiables (ASU) are made from avocado and soybean oil extracts in a 1:2 ratio and are among the slow-acting anti-inflammatory drugs (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Its main components are the phytosterols beta-sitosterol, campesterol, and stigmasterol (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p><p>Many studies agree that ASU has an important role in inhibiting MMP activity and release (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), in its function as a chondroprotector by stimulating the synthesis of matrix components and promoting cartilage repair (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), decreasing the production of inflammatory cytokines (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) and increasing the production of collagen and aggrecan. Other authors suggest that ASU may act on osteoblasts present in the subchondral bone favoring the cartilage repair (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). However, most studies focus on various nutraceuticals and dietary supplements including ASU. They describe symptom improvement, but none focus on investigating structural changes in OA following treatment (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23&#8211;26</xref>). Others, however, while agreeing that ASU treatment has a positive impact on symptomatology, do not observe significant changes in cartilage architecture (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>).</p><p>In <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> studies the model generally used to test ASU is based on reducing and controlling the activity of agents involved in the pathophysiology of OA by degrading cartilage and promoting tissue inflammation (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28&#8211;32</xref>). In these studies, targeted IL-1 and IL-6 (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) inducing MMP activity, TNF-<italic toggle="yes">&#945;</italic>, and the increased secretion of TGF-&#946;1 and TGF-&#946;2 (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Au et al. (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) found that ASU blocks the activation of COX-2 transcripts and lowers PGE2 secretion to basal levels.</p><p>Therefore, ASU has demonstrated chondroprotective, anabolic, and anticatabolic effects. It can promote the synthesis of extracellular matrix components (including collagen and aggrecan) in chondrocytes while suppressing the production of pro-inflammatory cytokines (IL-1&#946;, IL-6, IL-8), PGE2, NO, and matrix metalloproteinases like MMP-13 (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). These promote tissue maintenance and regeneration while reducing cartilage degeneration. Additionally, by blocking nitric oxide synthase (iNOS) and MMP-13 activity, ASU protects subchondral bone, halting bone resorption, and preserving bone density (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p><p>On a clinical level, oral administration of ASU has been shown to alleviate OA symptoms by preventing cartilage destruction and reducing pain and stiffness by improving the function of the affected joint (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Therefore, it makes it possible to reduce the dependence and use of common analgesics (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>).</p><p>Ultimately, although both anti-inflammatory and chondroprotective properties are described in a wide variety of studies, further studies are needed to support the efficacy of ASU. Furthermore, data on the concentrations of ASU components achieved in the blood (<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) and on the most effective and efficient doses of ASU are unfortunately lacking.</p><p>The aim of this article is therefore to review the literature published so far on ASUs, their efficacy, their routes of action, and their potential effect in treating OA.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><p>The literature included in this review was conducted manually between September and December 2022.</p><sec id="sec3"><label>2.1</label><title>Search strategy</title><p>The search for this review was performed through the following online scientific databases: Pubmed, Scopus and Web of Science (WOS). This search included studies published from 2000 to 2022.</p><p>The different publications were searched and identified, based on different search strategies, by permutations of the following terms: &#8220;osteoarthritis,&#8221; &#8220;OA,&#8221; &#8220;animal models,&#8221; &#8220;ASU&#8221; and/or &#8220;soy/avocado&#8221; as keywords.</p><p>We also included all articles found in the cross-references and bibliographies seen to be helpful or relevant.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>2.2</label><title>Inclusion and exclusion criteria</title><sec id="sec5"><label>2.2.1</label><title>Inclusion criteria</title><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Articles in English.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The presence of OA or simulation of its conditions*.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Use of ASU as a substance to test its effect alone or in combination with other substances.</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> studies.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Preclinical studies in different animal species.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Clinical studies in human and veterinary medicine.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Chemical or surgical OA induction**.</p></list-item></list><p>*The study developed by de Paula et al. (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>), which deals with Rheumatoid Arthritis (RA) rather than OA, was also included. The reasons for this are based on the common objective in both pathologies to investigate whether the effects of ASU include pain relief and slowing the progression of the pathology.</p><p>**As an exception, the article by Goudarzi et al. (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>), in which a chemical induction of oedema was performed instead of OA, was also included. However, the study is directed toward OA and related to the presence of oedema in this pathology.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><label>2.2.2</label><title>Exclusion criteria</title><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Reviews.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Abstracts and book chapters.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Articles in a language other than English.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Studies using substances other than ASU.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Studies where the dose used of ASU is not specified.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec><sec id="sec7"><label>2.3</label><title>Screening method and data extraction</title><p>The screening was carried out manually in two stages. First the titles and abstracts of each article were selected from the search results of the different databases. Then, duplicates were removed and two reviewers (A.S. and F.M.) independently screened them using the inclusion and exclusion criteria.</p><p>The same two reviewers (A.S. and F.M.) reviewed the full text of the articles for eligibility. For each study, relevant data were examined and extracted by dividing them into three distinct groups: <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> studies, preclinical studies and clinical studies. Within the latter, they were subdivided into clinical studies conducted in humans and animals.</p><p>The materials and methods were later analyzed in depth, focusing on the species used, the type of induction, treatment used, and the results obtained for each article (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Classification of the studies included in this review into their three corresponding.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-11-1473688-g002.jpg"/></fig><p>To conclude, the final selection of the studies included in this review was based on the inclusion and exclusion criteria explained above.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec8"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><p>The initial search yielded 126 articles from the different databases. Once the duplicates were removed, the remaining 65 were screened. The title and abstract were reviewed, and the exclusion/inclusion criteria mentioned above were applied. A total of 22 articles were excluded at this stage. Finally, the full-text analysis of 39 studies was carried out of which, 22 articles were selected for this review (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Flow chart of the final selected studies.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-11-1473688-g003.jpg"/></fig><sec id="sec9"><label>3.1</label><title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> studies</title><p>A summary of the tests included in this section can be found in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. They are explained in more detail below.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of the characteristics of the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> studies included.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> studies</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">References</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Material and methods</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment (concentrations&#8239;+&#8239;time of incubation)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Results</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Henrotin et al. (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model of isolated OA chondrocytes + IL-1&#946;</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8239;&#956;g/mL ASU<break/>+ 15&#8239;days</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASU promoted the recovery of aggrecan synthesis after 3&#8239;days of IL-1&#946; treatment. It inhibited the basal production of MMP-3, IL-6, IL-8, NO and PGE2.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Au et al. (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monocyte/macrophage-like cell model<break/>Biomarkers: IL-1&#946;, TNF-<italic toggle="yes">&#945;</italic>, COX-2 and iNOS</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#8239;&#956;g/mL ASU<break/>+ 3&#8239;days</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASU suppresses gene expression of potent pro-inflammatory cytokines</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gabay et al. (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mouse/human chondrocytes + IL-1&#946;&#8239;+&#8239;mechanical stress with/without ASU</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8239;&#956;g/mL ASU<break/>+ 2&#8239;days</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASU decreases MMP-3 and MMP-13 expression and PGE2 release</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lippiello et al. (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model of cow metacarpal joint chondrocytes</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30&#8239;&#956;g/mL ASU&#8239;+&#8239;1&#8239;day<break/>75&#8239;&#956;g/mL ASU&#8239;+&#8239;3&#8239;days</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The results suggest a relationship between ASU content and biological activity</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grzanna et al. (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monocyte/macrophage-like cell model<break/>Combination of ASU&#8239;+&#8239;CS</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,3&#8239;&#956;g/mL ASU<break/>+ 1&#8239;day</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASU and CS reduces TNF-&#945; expression but does not block cytokine expression</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ownby et al. (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model of equine chondrocytes pre-incubated with ASU&#8239;+&#8239;EGCG<break/>+ IL-1&#946; and TNF-&#945;</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,3&#8239;&#956;g/mL ASU<break/>0,04&#8239;&#956;g/mL EGCG<break/>+ 1&#8239;day</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASU&#8239;+&#8239;EGCG activity affects a wide range of inflammatory molecules in addition to decreasing PGE2 synthesis in activated chondrocytes</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frondoza et al. (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model of equine chondrocytes<break/>Combination of ASU&#8239;+&#8239;LA</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,3&#8239;&#956;g/mL ASU<break/>2,5&#8239;&#956;g/mL LA<break/>+ 1&#8239;day</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LA: inhibits IL-1&#946; and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub><break/>ASU: inhibits IL-1&#946; activity, but not H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub><break/>ASU&#8239;+&#8239;LA: inhibits PGE2 production</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grzanna et al. (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model of chondrocyte microcarriers + IL-1&#946;<break/>Biomarkers: PGE2, IL-6, IL-8 and MCP-1<break/>Combination of carprofen (ASU&#8239;+&#8239;GLU&#8239;+&#8239;CS)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,3&#8239;&#956;g/mL ASU<break/>11&#8239;&#956;g/mL GLU<break/>20&#8239;&#956;g/mL CS<break/>+ 1&#8239;day</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carprofen + (ASU&#8239;+&#8239;GLU&#8239;+&#8239;CS): inhibits PGE2 production more than the agents alone</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Teimourinejad et al. (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hADSC model in fibrin<break/>Combination of PFE&#8239;+&#8239;ASU</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#8239;&#956;g/mL ASU<break/>10&#8239;&#956;g/mL PFE<break/>5&#8239;&#956;g/mL ASU&#8239;+&#8239;5&#8239;&#956;g/mL PFE<break/>+ 14&#8239;days</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PFE&#8239;+&#8239;ASU produced a smaller effect than PFE alone, but larger than ASU</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Of the nine articles included in this section, Henrotin et al. (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), Au et al. (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), and Gabay et al. (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) share very similar lines of research. These three studies use human chondrocytes stimulated or not with IL-1&#946;. In the case of Au et al. (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) they also tested multiple cell types involved in joint inflammation, i.e., monocytes/macrophages and fibroblasts. As biomarkers, they used a wide range, of IL-1&#946;, TNF-<italic toggle="yes">&#945;</italic>, COX-2, and iNOS, PGE2, and NO. Henrotin et al. (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) and Gabay et al. (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) tested the efficacy of ASU on MMP-3 and -13 and PGE2 expressions. As for the results, they showed that ASU suppresses gene expression of potent proinflammatory cytokines, including TNF-a, IL-1b, COX-2, and iNOS, as well as MMP-3 and -13 and PGE2 release. Notably, Au et al. (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) showed for the first time that the anti-inflammatory effects of ASU are not limited to chondrocytes and fibroblasts but extend to surrogate cells, and monocytes/macrophages.</p><p>A similar study to the previous ones was designed by Lippiello et al. (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), to clarify whether the sterol content in ASU could play a role in the biological activity of articular chondrocytes. Different analytical tools were used, for samples with ASU and before culture with bovine chondrocytes, to observe the variation in sterol content. Anabolic and anti-inflammatory activity was then analyzed, suggesting a dose- and time-dependent relationship between ASU content and chondrocyte biological activity.</p><p>On the other hand, the articles by Grzanna et al. (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>), Ownby et al. (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), Frondoza et al. (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>), Grzanna et al. (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>), and Teimourinejad et al. (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>) use different supplements in combination with ASUs to test whether their effect is greater together or alone. These supplements include chondroitin sulfate (CS) (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>), epigallocatechin gallate (EGCG) (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">&#945;</italic>-lipoic acid (LA) (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>), or pomegranate extract (PFE) (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). In addition, the article by Grzanna et al. (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>) used a combination of ASU, glucosamine (GLU), and chondroitin sulfate (CS) with Carprofen. These studies showed that ASU decreases various types of cytokines expression, and PGE2 synthesis in chondrocytes, and inhibits H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>.</p><p>To sum up, all articles reported that the combination of ASU with other supplements has more effect than alone. Therefore, the main objective should be to reduce or inhibit the expression of all these molecules without blocking the expression of cytokines, enhancing the potential to attenuate inflammation without reducing cytokines below the levels necessary for normal physiological function. In other words, these combinations could be used as an alternative or complement to conventional pharmacological treatments for the treatment of OA and could reduce the dose of NSAIDs and their side effects.</p></sec><sec id="sec10"><label>3.2</label><title>Preclinical studies</title><p>A summary of the studies included in this section can be found in <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. However, they are explained in more detail below.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Summary of the characteristics of the preclinical studies included.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Preclinical studies</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">References</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study groups</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study size (adults)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosis/induction</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment (orally administrated)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Results</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cake et al. (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MenX+ASU: 8<break/>MenX+Placebo:8<break/>NOC:8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 sheeps</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgical induction: bilateral lateral meniscectomy</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">900&#8239;mg/working day ASU<break/>For 3 or 6&#8239;months</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Partial preservation of cartilage integrity in ASU-treated individuals versus the placebo and NOC groups</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Altinel et al. (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control:8<break/>ASU high dose: 8<break/>ASU low dose: 8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 dogs</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Knee joint fluid sampling post-treatment</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300&#8239;mg/day ASU or 300&#8239;mg/3 times a day ASU<break/>For 3&#8239;months</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASU-treated groups show increases levels of TGF-&#946;1 and TGF-&#946;2 in joint fluid. However, TGF levels were not significantly altered by the different dosages</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kawcak et al. (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo group: 8<break/>ASU group:8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 horses</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgical induction: osteochondral fragmentation</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300&#8239;mg/day ASU or placebo<break/>For 70&#8239;days</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASU group did not show a reduction in clinical signs compared with the placebo group</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boileau et al. (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo group: 8<break/>ASU group:8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 dogs</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgical induction: anterior cruciate ligament section</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200&#8211;250&#8239;mg/day ASU* or placebo<break/>For 8&#8239;weeks</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The severity of the lesions was significantly decreased in the ASU-treated group compared with the placebo group</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Al-Alfify et al. (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control: 10<break/>MIA:10<break/>MIA&#8239;+&#8239;ASU:10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 rats</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chemical induction of OA: intraarticular injection of MIA</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,5&#8211;6,9&#8239;mg/day ASU*<break/>For 3&#8239;weeks</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASU maintained matrix staining, decreased cellular abnormalities, and stopped cartilage structural degradation induced by MIA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">de Paula et al. (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control: 30<break/>ASU:30<break/>Arthritis: 30<break/>Arthritis+ASU: 30</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120 rats</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgical induction: Systemic immunization + implant placement</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180&#8211;198&#8239;mg/day ASU*<break/>For 15, 30 or 60&#8239;days</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The ASU-treated group showed an improvement in osseointegration compared with the arthritic group</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Goudarzi et al. (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control:6<break/>ASU:6<break/>Nanopliposome:6<break/>NANOCEN:6<break/>Ibuprofen: 6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 mice</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Paw inflammation</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Topical administration**<break/>0,4&#8239;mg/day ASU<break/>For 30&#8239;days</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NANOCEN showed robust anti-inflammatory and analgesic effect superior to ibuprofen</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*These dosages vary according to the weight of each animal.</p><p>**All the studies administrated ASU orally except for Goudarzi et al. (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To investigate the effect of oral ASU, Cake et al. (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>) and Kawcak et al. (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) conducted their studies in sheep and horses respectively, inducing OA chirurgically. Both studies divided the animals into two groups: one treated with placebo and the other with ASU. In the case of Cake et al. (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>) they used a dose of 900&#8239;mg/day of ASU significantly higher than that used in the study by Kawcak et al. (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) 300&#8239;mg/day of ASU. In terms of clinical signs, Kawcak et al. (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) observed that these did not disappear with ASU treatment, but by macroscopic examination, they were able to conclude that it did reduce the severity of articular cartilage erosion and synovial hemorrhage. Cake et al. (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>) performed histomorphometry tests on histological sections measuring the areas of total cartilage, non-calcified cartilage, and subchondral bone thickness, as well as the intensity of toluidine blue. However, they failed to demonstrate any significant effect of ASU treatment. However, imaging analysis demonstrated that cartilage integrity was partially preserved in ASU-treated individuals (although other causes could not be excluded).</p><p>On the other hand, Boileau et al. (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>) and Al-Afify et al. (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), used immunohistochemical techniques to evaluate the expression of MMP-13 and iNOS (nitric oxide synthase). Both articles revealed a significant reduction in the level of iNOS and MMP-13 in the ASU-treated groups. This finding is consistent with other studies describing NO as one of the important mediators of articular cartilage and subchondral bone damage. It was also found to modulate the activity of MMP-13. MMPs and other catabolic enzymes, particularly MMP-1 and 13, mediate cartilage collagen degradation during OA. In terms of histological evaluation, both studies showed a reduction in lesion severity and a decrease in subchondral bone volume loss (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>), and articular cartilage showed increased cellularity and a higher degree of matrix staining (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p><p>It is important to highlight that Altinel et al. (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>) conducted a different study by dividing the 24 dogs in the study into three groups: a control group (with a normal diet), a group treated with high doses of ASU (300&#8239;mg/day) and another group treated with low doses (300&#8239;mg/3&#8239;days). They analyzed TGF-<italic toggle="yes">&#946;</italic> levels in joint fluid samples. They concluded that ASU treatment does, indeed, increase TGF-&#946;1 and TGF-&#946;2 levels in joint fluid for 3&#8239;months, but further studies are needed to define the mechanism of the symptomatic effects of ASU treatment on osteoarthritic joints.</p><p>In 2018, the study by de Paula et al. (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>) evaluated osseointegration <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> (120 rats) in an experimental model of rheumatoid arthritis. Previous studies have shown that the usefulness of ASU in pathologies in which the formation of new bone tissue is beneficial is subtle. However, this study proposes that their use could have a greater impact on individuals with altered bone tissue metabolism. The results showed a higher osseointegration potential in the ASU-treated groups (180&#8211;198&#8239;mg/day ASU for 15, 30 or 60&#8239;days). The study comments that this finding may be because, with the anti-inflammatory potential of ASU, bone resorption around the implant is reduced by stimulating connective tissue proliferation. Increased expression of TGF-&#946;1 was also observed, indicating increased connective tissue proliferation and coinciding with the findings of Goudarzi et al. (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) and G&#322;uszko and Stasiek (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). It can be concluded from this study that treatment with the ASU improved osseointegration, particularly in animals with induced arthritis.</p><p>Finally, Goudarzi et al. (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) carried out a topical study conducted in mice to formulate nanoliposomes that facilitate the cutaneous administration (NANOCEN) of ASU (0.4 mg/day for 30&#8239;days) and then evaluate its anti-inflammatory and analgesic effects in comparison with 5% ibuprofen gel. The results revealed effective inhibition of inflammation and even better pain relief than ibuprofen 5%.</p></sec><sec id="sec11"><label>3.3</label><title>Clinical studies</title><p>The summary of the tests included in this section can be found in <xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Summary of the characteristics of the clinical studies included.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Clinical studies</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">References</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study groups</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Study size</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diagnosis</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment (Orally administrated)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Results</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Human clinical trials</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Appelboom and Schuerman (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASU300: 86<break/>ASU600: 86<break/>Placebo: 86</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">260 patients (45&#8211;80&#8239;years)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Femoro-tibial OA</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300&#8239;mg/day ASU<break/>600&#8239;mg/day ASU<break/>Or placebo<break/>For 3&#8239;months</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significant differences between the ASU 300 and 600 groups versus the placebo group.<break/>No significant differences between the 300 and 600 ASU groups</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lequesne et al. (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASU: 54<break/>Placebo: 54</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108 patients</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hip OA</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300&#8239;mg/day ASU<break/>Or placebo<break/>For 2&#8239;years</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No structural effect</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pavelka et al. (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASU 300:142<break/>CS 400: 121</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">263 patients (45 or&#8239;&gt;&#8239;45&#8239;years)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Femoro-tibial OA</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300&#8239;mg/day ASU<break/>400&#8239;mg 3 times/day CS<break/>For 6&#8239;months</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No difference between CS and ASU</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maheu et al. (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Placebo: 179<break/>ASU:166</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">345 patients</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hip OA</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300&#8239;mg/day ASU<break/>Or placebo<break/>For 3&#8239;years</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No significant differences between the two groups. But slower progression in the ASU group.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G&#322;uszko and Stasiek (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single group</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,186 patients (average age 60&#8239;years)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Knee OA</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300&#8239;mg/day ASU<break/>For 6&#8239;months</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASU achieves significant clinical improvement</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jangravi et al. (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PD: 20<break/>DP: 20</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 patients (&lt;60&#8239;years)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bilateral knee OA</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300&#8239;mg/day ASU<break/>PD: placebo 3&#8239;months + ASU 3&#8239;months<break/>DP: ASU 3&#8239;months + placebo 3&#8239;months</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASU is effective as an antioxidant</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Veterinary clinical trials</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kwananocha et al. (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single group</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 dogs (adults)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hip OA</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">900&#8239;mg/day GLU<break/>350&#8239;mg/day CS<break/>900&#8239;mg/day ASU<break/>For 4&#8239;weeks</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inconclusive. Possible insufficient dose.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="sec12"><label>3.3.1</label><title>Human clinical trials</title><p>The seven articles included in this section evaluated the function of ASUs in the knee or hip but in different ways.</p><p>Appelboom and Schuerman (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>), Pavelka et al. (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>), and G&#322;uszko and Stasiek (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>) evaluated symptomatic effects in different groups of patients. In the case of Appelboom and Schuerman (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>), they separated patients into three groups: a control group, one treated with 300&#8239;mg/day ASU, and another with 600&#8239;mg/day ASU for 3&#8239;months. Pavelka et al. (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>), on the other hand, compared the effects of ASU (300&#8239;mg/day) with those of CS (400&#8239;mg/day). Despite their differences, the results of these three articles are similar: they proved the efficacy of ASU in relieving symptoms. However, Appelboom and Schuerman (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>) and Pavelka et al. (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>) find no differences between the different doses of ASU used or between ASU and CS, respectively. Of note, Appelboom and Schuerman (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>) also found that 71% of patients had reduced their NSAIDs intake by more than 50%, proving that ASU can help to reduce the side effects of painkillers by reducing their consumption.</p><p>Structural joint effects were analyzed by Lequesne et al. (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>) and Maheu et al. (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) in the hip joint in both cases. The dose used in these studies is 300&#8239;mg/day for 2&#8239;years or 6&#8239;months. Lequesne et al. (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>) used the joint space width as the main criteria, and could not demonstrate any structural effect, however, the results suggested that ASU breaks joint space loss. Maheu et al. (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) also used radiographs and clinical observations, they also showed that ASU reduced the progression of joint space loss and concluded that ASU may have a role as a modifier of joint structure in OA.</p><p>Unlike the other studies, Jangravi et al. (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) evaluated the effects of ASU on oxidative stress and serum antioxidant levels in two groups of patients, those who were treated with placebo and then with ASU and those who were treated first with ASU and then with placebo. Both groups were given 300&#8239;mg/day of ASU for 3&#8239;months. The results showed a decrease in the serum level of a marker of oxidative stress, significantly reduced levels of antioxidants after 3&#8239;months of treatment and demonstrated the independence of the order of treatment administration concerning the effect of the ASU.</p></sec><sec id="sec13"><label>3.3.2</label><title>Veterinary clinical trials</title><p>In 2016, Kwananocha et al. (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>) conducted a study on 40 dogs with a history of lameness that aimed to evaluate and compare the effectiveness of disease-modifying osteoarthritis agents (DMOAAs). For this purpose, 40 dogs were included in the study and assigned into 4 treatment groups (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;10). In one of the groups, a combination of glucosamine-chondroitin sulfate (GC) and avocado/soybean unsaponifiables (ASU) were used. The combination GC-ASU contained glucosamine 900&#8239;mg, chondroitin sulfate 350&#8239;mg and ASU 90&#8239;mg. Finally, after 4&#8239;weeks of treatment, the results of the study were inconclusive. However, based on the literature and the results of other preclinical studies in which the efficacy of ASU was proven, they justify this result by a possible insufficient dose of the combination of GC.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec14"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><sec id="sec15"><label>4.1</label><title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> studies</title><p>All included articles used isolated chondrocytes or similar cells such as monocytes or macrophages, but not all enriched the culture medium with IL-1&#946;. Three of them do not use IL-1&#946; as activation in contrast to the rest of the literature. Henrotin et al. (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), however, unites the two approaches and tests in the same study, the culture using IL-1&#946; on the one hand and without using it on the other.</p><p>Another difference observed is the combination or not of ASU with other substances. Some supplemented ASU with LA others with PFE and, finally, one study tried combining them with CS.</p><p>Most of the studies agree in selecting common biomarkers: MMP-13, PGE2, and different ILs with some exceptions. Three articles also measure TNF-<italic toggle="yes">&#945;</italic>, others also measure NO and three more deviate and measure ECGC and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, respectively. In addition, Au et al. (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) also add the measurement of COX-2 and iNOS.</p><p>On the other hand, they all use different methods to get the results, ranging from immunoassays, electrophoresis, immunotransfer or immunohistochemistry; to spectrometry and chromatography, rPCR, and Western blotting. However, the results are similar in all articles. In one way or another, they all agree on either a decrease in proinflammatory molecules or an increase in structural molecules, such as aggrecan or collagen, and reach the same conclusion by different routes and methods. The 7 <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> studies included in this review claim that there is clear evidence that ASU affects the regulation of these molecules and, therefore, sufficient reasons to test its efficacy in preclinical studies.</p></sec><sec id="sec16"><label>4.2</label><title>Preclinical studies</title><p>The first difference observed in the preclinical studies is the variety of species used. A total of 7 studies including in this review 2 used dogs, two rats, one horses, one sheep and, finally one conducted their study in mice.</p><p>It should be noted that most authors used surgical induction as a method to induce OA. However, they used different vias. For example, Cake et al. (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>) performed a bilateral lateral meniscectomy, Kawcak et al. (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) osteochondral fragmentation at the carpal joint and Boileau et al. (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>) sectioned the anterior cruciate ligament of the knee. Contrary to the rest of the literature, two studies did not use surgical but chemical induction. The first one used an intraarticular injection of MIA to induce OA and the other one injected carrageenan into the subplantar tissue of the right paw to induce edema.</p><p>On the other hand, we found no similarities between the different studies in the duration of the treatment, or the doses used. In this last case, they vary from 900&#8239;mg per day to 10&#8239;mg per kg and day, and if we look at the duration of treatment, from 70&#8239;days to 6&#8239;months, there is also a significant difference.</p><p>In terms of outcomes, there is also controversy. While some articles did not observe a decrease or disappearance of clinical signs, the rest of the authors describe the results as positive. Goudarzi et al. (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) revealed a decrease in inflammation and pain relief and Boileau et al. (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>) an improvement of the histopathology of the lesion. Furthermore, and as an example of contradiction within the same study, although Cake et al. (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>) found no significant differences in the macroscopic study and histology, once the statistics were performed, they did find significant differences.</p><p>To conclude, some of the authors point out the variation in biomarkers. Three of them agree on the increased expression of TGF-1&#946; and two describe the decreased expression of both iNOS and MMP-13. However, all the publications agree on the beneficial effects of ASU on the OA.</p></sec><sec id="sec17"><label>4.3</label><title>Clinical studies</title><p>In contrast to the pre-clinical studies where there was a great deal of variety in the species included in the investigations, almost all the articles included in this review are studies conducted in human medicine. The exception is Kwananocha et al. (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>), which is the only case of a clinical trial conducted on dogs and focused on veterinary medicine.</p><p>The same is true for the doses used. All the articles are unanimous in the use of 300&#8239;mg per day except Kwananocha et al. (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>) who used 90&#8239;mg. In addition, Appelboom and Schuerman (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>) formed two groups and administered 600&#8239;mg per day to the second group, although, in the end, the results found no difference between the two.</p><p>In terms of the joint affected, there are differences. Two of the studies focused on the femorotibial joint, two on the hip and the other two on the knee.</p><p>Finally, the results all agree that they indicate a slowing of the progression of the pathology and alleviation of symptoms. Although, it is true that both Lequesne et al. (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>) and Maheu et al. (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>), who studied structural effects, failed to prove any positive change after treatment. Importantly, Kwananocha et al. (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>) cannot be compared on this point as their results were inconclusive due to a possibly insufficient dose.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec18"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>Based on the literature found and consulted, we can affirm that most of the studies reach a common answer: ASU alone or in combination with other substances helps to a great extent to reduce the symptoms of OA, but without locating all the ways of action in which it participates. In other words, it produces an analgesic and anti-inflammatory effect capable of reducing the doses of NSAIDs and therefore their side effects, which are necessary to control the chronic pain caused by this pathology. However, as it acts on multiple types of cells involved in inflammation and other mechanisms not yet fully understood, further studies are needed to find out how it produces these beneficial effects and by which pathways, as well as to establish effective doses for the administration of ASU, alone or in combination with other drugs or supplements.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="sec19"><title>Author contributions</title><p>AS-S: Writing &#8211; original draft, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. ML-P: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Methodology, Resources, Supervision, Validation. FM: Methodology, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Supervision, Validation. MP: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Resources, Supervision, Visualization.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec21"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>AS-S, ML-P, MP, and FM were employed by IboneLab S.L.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec22"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henrotin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balligand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmaceutical and nutraceutical management of canine osteoarthritis: present and future perspectives</article-title>. <source>Vet J</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>170</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tvjl.2004.08.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15993795</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O&#8217;Neill</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brodbelt</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Church</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meeson</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sargan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence, duration and risk factors for appendicular osteoarthritis in a UK dog population un- der primary veterinary care</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>5641</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-23940-zt</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29618832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5884849</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goudarzi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yazdi</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>In vitro effects of arthrocen, an Avocado/soy unsaponifiables agent, on inflammation and global gene expression in human monocytes</article-title>. <source>IJC</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>31</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5539/ijc.v9n4p31</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5903287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29675116</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goudarzi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yazdi</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of Arthrocen, an avocado/soy unsaponifiables agent, on inflammatory mediators and gene expression in human chondrocytes</article-title>. <source>FEBS Open Bio</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/2211-5463.12176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5292663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28174685</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edgard Henrotin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Avocado/soybean unsaponifiables (Piacledine<sup>&#174;</sup>300) show beneficial effect on the metabolism of osteoarthritic cartilage, synovium and subchondral bone: an overview of the mechanisms</article-title>. <source>AIMS Med Sci</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3934/medsci.2018.1.33</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Primorac</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Molnar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rod</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jele&#269;</surname><given-names>&#381;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#268;ukelj</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mati&#353;i&#263;</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Knee osteoarthritis: a review of pathogenesis and state-of-the-art non-operative therapeutic considerations</article-title>. <source>Genes</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>854</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/genes11080854</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32722615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7464436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rychel</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Diagnosis and treatment of osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Top Companion Anim Med</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>20</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.tcam.2009.10.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20188335</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll1">American College of Rheumatology Subcommittee on Osteoarthritis Guidelines</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Recommendations for the medical management of osteoarthritis of the hip and knee: 2000 update</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>. (<year>2000</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>1905</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/1529-0131(200009)43:9&amp;#x0003c;1905::AID-ANR1&amp;#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-P</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11014340</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Challenging the catechism of therapeutics for chronic neuropathic pain: targeting CaV2.2 interactions with CRMP2 peptides</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Lett</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>557</volume>:<fpage>27</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neulet.2013.06.057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23831344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3849117</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolasinski</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neogi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oatis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Block</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>2019 American College of Rheumatology/Arthritis Foundation guideline for the Management of Osteoarthritis of the hand, hip, and knee</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Care Res</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>72</volume>:<fpage>149</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/acr.24131</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31908149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11488261</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bannuru</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osani</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaysbrot</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arden</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bierma-Zeinstra</surname><given-names>SMA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>OARSI guidelines for the non-surgical management of knee, hip, and polyarticular osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Osteoarthr Cartil</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1578</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>89</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joca.2019.06.011</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31278997</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chrubasik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Oral herbal therapies for treating osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>2014</volume>:<fpage>CD002947</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD002947.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24848732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4494689</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gagnier</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Little</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bl&#252;mle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chrubasik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evidence of effectiveness of herbal medicinal products in the treatment of arthritis</article-title>. <source>Phytother Res</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>1497</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>515</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ptr.3007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19856319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Interlandi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabb&#236;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>di</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#8217;Angelo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arfuso</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Improved quality of life and pain relief in mature horses with osteoarthritis after oral transmucosal cannabidiol oil administration as part of an analgesic regimen</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1341396</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2024.1341396</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38379920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10876772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#225;nchez-Aparicio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flor&#225;n</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodr&#237;guez Vel&#225;zquez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibancovichi</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varela Guerrero</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Recillas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cannabinoids CB2 receptors, one new promising drug target for chronic and degenerative pain conditions in equine veterinary patients</article-title>. <source>J Equine Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>85</volume>:<fpage>102880</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jevs.2019.102880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31952645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gugliandolo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Licata</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peritore</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siracusa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#8217;Amico</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cordaro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of Cannabidiol (CBD) on canine inflammatory response: an ex vivo study on LPS stimulated whole blood</article-title>. <source>Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>185</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vetsci8090185</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34564578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8473042</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chrubasik</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roufogalis</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chrubasik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evidence of effectiveness of herbal anti- inflammatory drugs in the treatment of painful osteoarthritis and chronic low back pain</article-title>. <source>Phytother Res</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>675</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>83</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ptr.2142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17444576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Afify</surname><given-names>ASA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Akabawy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Sherif</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Safty</surname><given-names>FENA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Habiby</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Avocado soybean unsaponifiables ameliorates cartilage and subchondral bone degeneration in mono-iodoacetate-induced knee osteoarthritis in rats</article-title>. <source>Tissue Cell</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>108</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tice.2018.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29857819</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lippiello</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nardo</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harlan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Metabolic effects of avocado/soy unsaponifiables on articular chondrocytes</article-title>. <source>Evid Based Complement Alternative Med</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>191</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ecam/nem132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2396479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18604259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simental-Mend&#237;a</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#225;nchez-Garc&#237;a</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Acosta-Olivo</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilchez-Cavazos</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osuna-Garate</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pe&#241;a-Mart&#237;nez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy and safety of avocado-soybean unsaponifiables for the treatment of hip and knee osteoarthritis: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized placebo-controlled trials</article-title>. <source>Int J Rheum Dis</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1607</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1756-185X.13658</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31328413</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henrotin</surname><given-names>YE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Labasse</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaspar</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guillou</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Ef- fects of three avocado/soybean unsaponifiable mixtures on metalloproteinases, cytokines and prostaglandin E2 production by human articular chondrocytes</article-title>. <source>Clin Rheumatol</source>. (<year>1998</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>31</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01450955</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9586676</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DiNubile</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A potential role for avocado- and soybean-based nutritional supplements in the Management of Osteoarthritis: a review</article-title>. <source>Phys Sportsmed</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3810/psm.2010.06.1785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20631466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Avocado soybean unsaponifiables (ASU) for osteoarthritis? A systematic review</article-title>. <source>Clin Rheumatol</source>. (<year>2003</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>285</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10067-003-0731-4</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14576991</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartels</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Astrup</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bliddal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Symptomatic efficacy of avocado&#8211; soybean unsaponifiables (ASU) in osteoarthritis (OA) patients: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>Osteoarthr Cartil</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>399</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>408</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joca.2007.10.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18042410</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maheu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cadet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marty</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moyse</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerloch</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coste</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Randomised, controlled trial of avocado&#8211;soybean unsaponifiable (Piascledine) effect on structure modification in hip osteoarthritis: the ERADIAS study</article-title>. <source>Ann Rheum Dis</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>73</volume>:<fpage>376</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/annrheumdis-2012-202485</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23345601</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3913295</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eyles</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ravi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary supplements for treating osteoarthritis: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Br J Sports Med</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>75</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjsports-2016-097333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29018060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trifunovic-K&#246;nig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klose</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langhorst</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Phytotherapy for osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Z Phytother</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>242</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0042-121567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gabay</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gosset</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salvat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pigenet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Stress-induced signaling pathways in hyalin chondrocytes: inhibition by avocado&#8211;soybean unsaponifiables (ASU)</article-title>. <source>Osteoarthr Cartil</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>373</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joca.2007.06.016</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17707661</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#322;uszko</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stasiek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Symptom-modifying effects of oral avocado/soybean unsaponifiables in routine treatment of knee osteoarthritis in Poland. An open, prospective observational study of patients adherent to a 6-month treatment</article-title>. <source>Reumatologia</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>217</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>26</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5114/reum.2016.63661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5149568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27994265</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goudarzi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dehpour</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Partoazar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Estimation of anti-inflammatory and analgesic effects of topical NANOCEN (Nanoliposomal Arthrocen) on mice</article-title>. <source>AAPS PharmSciTech</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>233</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1208/s12249-019-1445-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31236745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henrotin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Couchourel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ripoll</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiotelli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nutraceuticals: do they rep- resent a new era in the management of osteoarthritis? &#8211; a narrative review from the lessons taken with five products</article-title>. <source>Osteoarthr Cartil</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joca.2010.10.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21035558</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henrotin</surname><given-names>YE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deberg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crielaard</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piccardi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Msika</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Avocado/soybean unsaponifiables prevent the inhibitory effect of osteoarthritic subchondral osteoblasts on aggrecan and type II collagen synthesis by chondrocytes</article-title>. <source>J Rheumatol</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1668</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1678</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16832844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Au</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Talib</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Au</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phan</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frondoza</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Avocado soybean unsaponifiables (ASU) suppress TNF-&#945;, IL-1&#946;, COX-2, iNOS gene expression, and prostaglandin E2 and nitric oxide production in articular chondrocytes and monocyte/macrophages</article-title>. <source>Osteoarthritis Cartilage</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1249</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joca.2007.07.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17845860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jangravi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basereh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaree Mahmoudabadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saberi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alishiri</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Korani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Avocado/soy unsaponifiables can redress the balance between serum antioxidant and oxidant levels in patients with osteoarthritis: a double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, crossover study</article-title>. <source>J Complement Integr Med</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>769</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/jcim-2020-0265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33794080</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhatti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goudarzi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Emami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Management of Osteoarthritis with avocado/soybean Unsaponifiables</article-title>. <source>Cartilage</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>30</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1947603514554992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25621100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4303902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Comblain</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Serisier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barthelemy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balligand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henrotin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Review of dietary sup- plements for the management of osteoarthritis in dogs in studies from 2004 to 2014</article-title>. <source>J Vet Pharmacol Therap</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvp.12251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26205697</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Paula</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinotti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grecchi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Aquino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marcantonio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of avocado/soybean Unsaponifiables (ASU) on Osseointegration in rats with experimental arthritis</article-title>. <source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>603</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11607/jomi.6124</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29763498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grzanna</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ownby</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinecke</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Au</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frondoza</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Inhibition of cytokine expression and prostaglandin E2 production in monocyte/macrophage-like cells by avocado/soybean unsaponifiables and chondroitin Sulfate</article-title>. <source>J Complement Integr Med</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2202/1553-3840.1338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ownby</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fortuno</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Au</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grzanna</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rashmir-Raven</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frondoza</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Expression of pro-inflammatory mediators is inhibited by an avocado/soybean unsaponifiables and epigallocatechin gallate combination</article-title>. <source>J Inflamm</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-9255-11-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3983882</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24678847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frondoza</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fortuno</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grzanna</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ownby</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Au</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rashmir-Raven</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>&#945;- Lipoic acid potentiates the anti-inflammatory activity of avocado/soybean unsaponifiables in chondrocyte cultures</article-title>. <source>Cartilage</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>304</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1947603516686146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29156944</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6042030</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grzanna</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Secor</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fortuno</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Au</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frondoza</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anti-inflammatory effect of Carprofen is enhanced by avocado/soybean Unsaponifiables, glucosamine and chondroitin Sulfate combination in chondrocyte microcarrier spinner culture</article-title>. <source>Cartilage</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>108</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1947603518783495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29938530</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6921959</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teimourinejad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashemibeni</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salehi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mostafavi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kazemi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahramian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chondrogenic activity of two herbal products; pomegranate fruit extract and avocado/soybean unsaponifiable</article-title>. <source>Res Pharma Sci</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>358</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/1735-5362.293514</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33312214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7714020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cake</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Read</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guillou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Modification of articular cartilage and subchondral bone pathology in an ovine meniscectomy model of osteoarthritis by avocado and soya unsaponifiables (ASU)</article-title>. <source>Osteoarthr Cartil</source>. (<year>2000</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>404</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/joca.1999.0315</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11069724</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawcak</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frisbie</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McIlwraith</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Werpy</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of avocado and soybean unsaponifiable extracts for treatment of horses with experimentally induced osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Am J Vet Res</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>598</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>604</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/ajvr.68.6.598</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17542691</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boileau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martel-Pelletier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Msika</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guillou</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baudouin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Protective effects of total fraction of avocado/soybean unsaponifiables on the structural changes in experimental dog osteoarthritis: inhibition of nitric oxide synthase and matrix metallopro- teinase-13</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Res Ther</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>R41</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/ar2649</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19291317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2688188</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altinel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saritas</surname><given-names>ZK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kose</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pamuk</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aksoy</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Serteser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Treatment with unsaponifiable extracts of avocado and soybean increases TGF-beta1 and TGF-beta2 levels in canine joint fluid</article-title>. <source>Tohoku J Exp Med</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>211</volume>:<fpage>181</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1620/tjem.211.181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17287602</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Appelboom</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuerman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Symptoms modifying effect of avocado/soybean unsaponifia- bles (ASU) in knee osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Scand J Rheumatol</source>. (<year>2001</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>242</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/030097401316909602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11578021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavelka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coste</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#233;her</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krejci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy and safety of piascledine 300 versus chondroitin sulfate in a 6 months treatment plus 2 months observation in patients with osteoarthritis of the knee</article-title>. <source>Clin Rheumatol</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>659</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10067-010-1384-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20179981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lequesne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maheu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cadet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreiser</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Structural effect of avocado/soybean unsaponifiables on joint space loss in osteoarthritis of the hip</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art1.10239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11932878</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwananocha</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vijarnsorn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kashemsant</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lekcharoensuk</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness of disease modifying osteoarthritis agents and carprofen for treatment of canine osteoarthritis. Thai</article-title>. <source>J Vet Med</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>363</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>371</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.56808/2985-1130.2750</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>