<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12052939</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12052939.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12052939</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12052939</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40331221</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2025.1602402</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial: Rodent-borne diseases: &#8220;One Health&#8221; perspectives</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duong</surname><given-names initials="V">Veasna</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1360218/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morand</surname><given-names initials="S">Serge</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/130466/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchy</surname><given-names initials="P">Philippe</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1620220/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Institut Pasteur du Cambodge, Pasteur Network</institution>, <addr-line>Phnom Penh</addr-line>, <country>Cambodia</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>IRL2021 HealthDEEP, Centre National Recherche Scientifique - Kasetsart University - Mahidol University</institution>, <addr-line>Bangkok</addr-line>, <country>Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Faculty of Veterinary Technology, Kasetsart University</institution>, <addr-line>Bangkok</addr-line>, <country>Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Department of Environmental and Social Medicine, Mahidol University</institution>, <addr-line>Bangkok</addr-line>, <country>Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Institut Pasteur du Laos, Pasteur Network</institution>, <addr-line>Vientiane</addr-line>, <country>Lao People's Democratic Republic</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited and reviewed by: Michael Kogut, United States Department of Agriculture, United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Veasna Duong <email>dveasna@pasteur-kh.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">480746</issue-id><elocation-id>1602402</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>06</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-05-07 09:25:38.040"><day>07</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2025 Duong, Morand and Buchy.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Duong, Morand and Buchy</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-12-1602402.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="commentary-article" xml:lang="en" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/49032/rodent-borne-diseases-one-health-perspectives"/><kwd-group><kwd>rodents</kwd><kwd>One Health</kwd><kwd>zoonotic diseases</kwd><kwd>pet animals</kwd><kwd>climate change</kwd><kwd>habitat change</kwd><kwd>rodent-borne diseases</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="15"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="1792"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Veterinary Infectious Diseases</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>The One Health approach, as defined by the <italic toggle="yes">One Health High Level Expert Panel (OHHLEP)</italic>, is a collaborative, multisectoral strategy that acknowledges the interdependence of human, animal, and environmental health (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). This holistic perspective is particularly critical in addressing zoonotic diseases, which account for over 60% of emerging infectious diseases worldwide (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Given their close association with the human environment rodents play a pivotal role in zoonotic disease transmission, necessitating an integrated approach for effective surveillance and control.</p><p>Rodents act as reservoirs for a wide array of viral, bacterial, and parasitic pathogens, contributing to both endemic and outbreak-prone diseases. Leptospirosis, caused by <italic toggle="yes">Leptospira</italic> spp., is one of the most widespread rodent-borne zoonotic infections, responsible for an estimated 1.03 million human cases and 58,900 deaths annually (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Hantaviruses, transmitted through rodent urine and feces, lead to Hemorrhagic Fever with Renal Syndrome (HFRS) and Hantavirus Pulmonary Syndrome (HPS), with mortality rates reaching 40% (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Arenaviruses from the Old World and New World groups of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Mammarenavirus</italic> are transmitted to humans primarily following contact with the excreta of infected rodents and represent a significant burden of disease with an estimated 100,000 to 300,000 cases of Lassa Fever recorded each year in Africa (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Plague, caused by <italic toggle="yes">Yersinia pestis</italic>, persists in rodent populations and remains an ongoing public health concern, particularly in Africa, Asia, and South America (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Rat-bite fever (RBF), a bacterial zoonosis caused by <italic toggle="yes">Streptobacillus moniliformis</italic>, is underreported but can lead to severe septicemia and arthritis if left untreated (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p><p>Several environmental and anthropogenic factors exacerbate the risk of rodent-borne diseases. Climate change and habitat changes have been linked to alterations in rodent population dynamics and increased pathogen transmission (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Warmer temperatures and extreme weather events have been associated with hantavirus outbreaks in the Americas and Europe, as changing environmental conditions extend rodent breeding cycles and virus transmission rates (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Rapid urbanization further exacerbates the problem, as poorly managed waste disposal and inadequate sanitation in densely populated cities facilitate rodent proliferation, increasing the risk of pathogen spillover (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Additionally, the rise of antimicrobial resistance (AMR) in rodent-associated pathogens has become an emerging concern, with multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella spp</italic>. detected in urban rodent populations, complicating treatment strategies for zoonotic infections (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).</p><p>Given these challenges, this Research Topic of <italic toggle="yes">Frontiers in Veterinary Science</italic> adopts a One Health perspective to explore rodent-borne diseases, featuring four pivotal studies that advance our understanding of their clinical implications, ecological dynamics, and surveillance strategies within the One Health framework.</p><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1235183" ext-link-type="uri">Arpin et al.</ext-link> investigate the role of inter- and transdisciplinary approaches in rodent-borne disease research within an Ecohealth framework. Conducted in a polycrisis era&#8212;marked by climate change, biodiversity loss, and global health threats&#8212;the study underscores the necessity of integrating ecological, social, and health sciences to develop effective rodent-borne disease mitigation strategies. The authors highlight the challenges of collaborative research, including data-sharing limitations, disciplinary silos, and funding constraints, which hinder comprehensive disease management. They advocate for systems-thinking models and community-based participatory approaches, demonstrating how long-term, integrated strategies can enhance rodent-borne disease surveillance and control. This study underscores the importance of cross-sector partnerships between veterinarians, ecologists, public health experts, and policymakers in developing effective disease prevention efforts.</p><p>Building on the theme of clinical challenges, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fmed.2024.1345354" ext-link-type="uri">Giraudon et al.</ext-link> present a case report of rat-bite fever (RBF), a neglected zoonotic disease that can cause severe systemic infections. The report describes a severe case of RBF complicated by septic arthritis, emphasizing the diagnostic challenges and the risk of delayed treatment. The case highlights the importance of early recognition and clinical suspicion, especially in patients with rodent exposure or pet rat ownership. Since <italic toggle="yes">S. moniliformis</italic> does not grow well on standard agar media, misdiagnosis is common, leading to delays in treatment. The authors emphasize the need for improved diagnostic tools, clinician awareness, and early antibiotic intervention to prevent life-threatening complications such as endocarditis and septicemia. The study also points to gaps in public health messaging about zoonotic risks associated with pet rodents.</p><p>Extending the scope to broader surveillance efforts, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2024.1301959" ext-link-type="uri">Ricardo et al.</ext-link> conduct a systematic review and meta-analysis of the seroprevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Leptospira</italic> in asymptomatic domestic dogs and cats, exploring their potential role as silent reservoirs of infection. Their findings reveal significant <italic toggle="yes">Leptospira</italic> exposure rates among domestic animals, particularly in urban slums and flood-prone regions. These results suggest that dogs and cats may contribute to human leptospirosis transmission cycles, emphasizing the need for routine veterinary screening, vaccination programs, and public awareness campaigns. The study calls for closer collaboration between veterinarians and public health professionals to reduce the spread of leptospirosis.</p><p>Shifting the focus to vector-borne pathogens, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2023.1268440" ext-link-type="uri">Wang et al.</ext-link> present a longitudinal surveillance study investigating rodent and tick populations in Zhejiang Province, China. Their research provides critical insights into pathogen circulation and transmission dynamics in rodent hosts, including <italic toggle="yes">Leptospira</italic>, Hantavirus, and <italic toggle="yes">Orientia tsutsugamushi</italic>, with multiple co-infections detected. Notably, Severe Fever with Thrombocytopenia Syndrome Virus (SFTSV) was found in ticks but not in rodents, suggesting a complex ecological interplay between hosts and vectors. The study calls for integrated rodent-vector surveillance programs that incorporate genetic, ecological, and epidemiological data to predict and prevent emerging zoonotic disease threats.</p><p>This Research Topic on Rodent-Borne Diseases: One Health Perspectives highlights the critical need for interdisciplinary collaboration, proactive surveillance, and clinical awareness to mitigate rodent-associated health threats. Key takeaways include:</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>- Strengthening transdisciplinary research to improve zoonotic disease management.</p></list-item><list-item><p>- Integrating veterinary and human medicine for early diagnosis and treatment.</p></list-item><list-item><p>- Addressing factors such as climate, changing landscapes and urbanization that influence rodent-borne disease transmission.</p></list-item><list-item><p>- Enhancing surveillance programs for early pathogen detection and outbreak prevention.</p></list-item></list><p>As rodent-borne and other zoonotic diseases continue to pose global health challenges, embracing a One Health approach is essential to mitigate risks and safeguard both human and animal populations.</p></body><back><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>VD: Writing &#8211; original draft, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. SM: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. PB: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s2"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>One Health High-Level Expert Panel (OHHLEP) Adisasmito WB Almuhairi S Behravesh CB Bilivogui P Bukachi SA</collab></person-group>. <article-title>One Health: a new definition for a sustainable and healthy future</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>e1010537</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1010537</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35737670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9223325</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Storeygard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gittleman</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Global trends in emerging infectious diseases</article-title>. <source>Nature.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>451</volume>:<fpage>990</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature06536</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18288193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5960580</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagan</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calcagno</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torgerson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez-Silveira</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Global morbidity and mortality of leptospirosis: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e0003898</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0003898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26379143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4574773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jonsson</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Figueiredo</surname><given-names>LTM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vapalahti</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A global perspective on hantavirus ecology, epidemiology, and disease</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>412</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00062-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20375360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2863364</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>CDC</collab></person-group>. <source>Lassa Fever Suspected in Death of U.S. Traveler Returning from West Africa</source>. (<year>2025</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/lassa-fever/about/index.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/lassa-fever/about/index.html</ext-link> (accessed April 12, 2025).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallam</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paessler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Review of mammarenavirus biology and replication</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1751</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.01751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30123198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6085440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neerinckx</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertherat</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leirs</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Human plague occurrences in Africa: an overview from 1877 to 2008</article-title>. <source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>104</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>103</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.trstmh.2009.07.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19716148</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rat bite fever and Streptobacillus moniliformis</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00016-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17223620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1797630</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blasdell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bordes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buchy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carcy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaisiri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Changing landscapes ofSoutheast Asia and rodent-borne diseases: decreased diversity but increased transmission risks</article-title>. <source>Ecol Appl.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>e01886</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/eap.1886</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30986339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Douglas</surname><given-names>KO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Payne</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabino-Santos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of climatic factors on human hantavirus infections in Latin America and the Caribbean: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Pathogens.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/pathogens11010015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35055965</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8778283</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klempa</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hantaviruses and climate change</article-title>. <source>Clini Microbiol Infect.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>518</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2009.02848.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19604276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blasdell</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laurance</surname><given-names>SGW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doggett</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hahs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trinh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rats and the city: Implications of urbanization on zoonotic disease risk in Southeast Asia</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>119</volume>:<fpage>e2112341119</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2112341119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36122224</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9522346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deutsch</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corrigan</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munshi-South</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Trends in urban rat ecology: a framework to define the prevailing knowledge gaps and incentives for academia, pest management professionals (PMPs) and public health agencies to participate</article-title>. <source>J Urban Ecol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>jux005</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jue/jux005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Himsworth</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zabek</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desruisseau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parmley</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid-Smith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jardine</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella spp</italic>. in the feces of wild urban Norway and black rats (<italic toggle="yes">Rattus norvegicus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Rattus rattus</italic>) from an inner-city neighborhood of Vancouver</article-title>. <source>Canada J Wildl Dis.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>589</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>600</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7589/2014-09-242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25932669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guenther</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bethe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fruth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Semmler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ulrich</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wieler</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Frequent combination of antimicrobial multiresistance and extraintestinal pathogenicity in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> isolates from urban rats (<italic toggle="yes">Rattus norvegicus</italic>) in Berlin, Germany</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e50331</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0050331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23189197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3506595</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>