<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10470888</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10470888.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10470888</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10470888</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37662989</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1095877</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Enhancement of protective vaccine-induced antibody titer to swine diseases and growth performance by Amino-Zn, yucca extract, and &#946;-mannanase feed additive in wean-finishing pigs</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sampath</surname><given-names initials="V">Vetriselvi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names initials="S">Sungbo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1415911/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names initials="BR">Byung Ryol</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c002" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="NH">Nam-Hun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="IH">In Ho</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1368566/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Animal Resources, Dankook University</institution>, <addr-line>Cheonan</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>ZinexBio Corporation</institution>, <addr-line>Asan</addr-line>, <country>Republic of Korea</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0001"><p>Edited by: Javier Polo, APC Europe S.L., Spain</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0002"><p>Reviewed by: Zhigang Song, Shandong Agricultural University, China; Caimei Wu, Sichuan Agricultural University, China</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: In Ho Kim, <email>inhokim@dankook.ac.kr</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Byung Ryol Lee, <email>ceo@bt-n.co.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">427755</issue-id><elocation-id>1095877</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>09</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-10-16 15:25:22.350"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 Sampath, Cho, Lee, Kim and Kim.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sampath, Cho, Lee, Kim and Kim</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-10-1095877.pdf"/><abstract><p>The primary purpose of this research is to determine the effect of Amino-Zn (AZn), <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract (YE), and &#946;-mannanase enzyme supplementation on growth performance, nutrient digestibility, fecal gas emission, and immune response in pigs. A total of 180 crossbred pigs (6.57&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1&#8201;kg) were randomly assigned to one of three dietary treatments: CON-corn soybean meal (basal diet); TRT1-CON +1,000&#8201;ppm AZn&#8201;+&#8201;0.07% yucca extract (YE)&#8201;+&#8201;0.05% &#946;-mannanase; and TRT2-CON +2,000&#8201;ppm AZn&#8201;+&#8201;0.07% YE+ 0.05% &#946;-mannanase for 22&#8201;weeks. Each treatment had 12 replicates with 5 pigs per pen. Pigs fed a diet supplemented with AZn, YE, and &#946;-mannanase linearly increased (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) BW and average daily gain at weeks 6, 12, 17, and 18. In contrast, the gain-to-feed ratio showed a linear increase (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) from weeks 6 to 17 and the overall trial period. Moreover, the inclusion of experimental diets linearly decreased (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05) noxious gas emissions such as ammonia, hydrogen sulfide, acetic acid, carbon dioxide, and methyl mercaptans. The dietary inclusion of AZn, YE, and &#946;-mannanase significantly increased the serological immune responses to <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma hyopneumoniae</italic> (MH) and foot-and-mouth disease virus (FMDV-O type) at the end of week 6 and porcine circovirus-2 (PCV-2) at week 19. Based on this result, we infer that the combination of AZn, YE, and &#946;-mannanase supplement would serve as a novel in-feed additive to enhance growth performance and act as a boosting agent and immune stimulatory to increase the efficacy of swine vaccinations.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Amino-Zn</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract</kwd><kwd>&#946;-mannanase</kwd><kwd>antibody</kwd><kwd>vaccination</kwd><kwd>pigs</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="5"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="69"/><page-count count="12"/><word-count count="8540"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Animal Nutrition and Metabolism</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><label>1.</label><title>Introduction</title><p>It has been well documented that weaning is the most complicated part of pig production. During weaning, piglets may be exposed to various stressors, such as introducing new litter mates and a change of diet from liquid to solid, which leads to disruption of intestinal flora disorder, diarrhea, declined growth performance, preweaning diarrhea, and mortality (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). These problems represent a substantial economic loss to the livestock industry. In this regard, plants and their extracts play a vital role in promoting animal growth, enhancing immunity, and maintaining gut health (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Notably, <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract (YE), a natural plant product derived from the <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> plant, native to Southern California and Mexico, contains insoluble fibers, and high cellulose helps to improve feed efficiency and increases poultry production (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Previously, Sahoo et al. (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) reported that YE additives significantly improved the growth performance of broilers. For more than 30&#8201;years, YE has been used to reduce ammonia and improve the biodegradation of animal waste (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Moreover, &#946;-Mannan, an anti-nutritional factor found in soybean meal (SBM), has also received much attention in swine nutrition (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). For instance, Kim et al. (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) reported that the graded level (400&#8211;1,600&#8201;U/kg) of &#946;-mannanase supplementation improved the performance of growing pigs. Similarly, a study by Pettey et al. (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) demonstrated that pigs fed a corn&#8211;SBM diet supplemented with 0.05% &#946;-mannanase improved the growth performance of wean-finishing pigs with minimal effects on nutrient digestibility. In addition, Jo et al. (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) concluded that 0.05% &#945;-amylase + &#946;-mannanase + protease blends improved the growth performance of growing pigs. On the other hand, Upadhaya et al. (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>) reported that a corn&#8211;SBM diet supplemented with &#946;-mannanase reduced the population of fecal coliforms and tended to reduce the NH<sub>3</sub> concentration of fecal slurry after 24&#8201;h fermentation.</p><p>Generally, animals need an adequate amount of trace minerals to avoid deficiencies such as low appetite, poor growth, and diarrhea. In particular, zinc oxide becomes an innate micromineral to regulate the growth and immune function of animals (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) as it plays a vital role in growth and cell proliferation. Previously, Roselli et al. (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) reported that Zn exhibits an antibacterial agent; for example, it prevents the adhesion and internalization of enterotoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> into enterocytes. Owing to its antibacterial, disinfecting, and anti-inflammation properties, it plays an imperative role in pharmaceuticals and agriculture, also widely used as a dietary supplement (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>).</p><p>Porcine circovirus type 2 (PVC-2) is one of the most important pathogens in the pig industry. Apart from this, foot-and-mouth disease (FMD) causes extensive financial loss and devastating effects on pig production (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Furthermore, <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma hyopneumoniae</italic> (MH), a severe respiratory problem, leads to reduced weight gain and poor feed conversion in pigs (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Previously Van Heugten et al. (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) stated that endotoxin injection helped to induce the immune response in pigs. However, Hevener et al. (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) reported that the acute effects of endotoxin treatment rarely mimic the long-term detrimental influence of infectious diseases in grow-finish pigs. To prevent severe diseases, vaccines have been applied to pigs, but those vaccines do not prevent the outbreak of diseases. Probably these vaccines have a poor cell-mediated immune (CMI) response and a short duration of immunity (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Thus, there is a growing need to explore alternative anti-PCV, anti-FMD, and anti-<italic toggle="yes">M. hyopneumoniae</italic> agents with different mechanisms of action. In 2014, Chai et al. (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) reported that the inclusion of high levels (2,500&#8201;mg/kg) of Zn supplementation in pigs&#8217; diets showed enhanced protection in the intestinal tract and stimulated the systemic humoral immune response against transmissible gastroenteritis viral infection. The above-mentioned literature (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) has prompted us to hypothesize that the inclusion of AZn, YE, and &#946;-mannanase supplements might enhance the growth performance, nutrient digestibility, and immune response and reduce fecal gas emission in pigs. To the best of our knowledge, this would be the first study to explore the efficacy of dietary AZn, YE, and &#946;-mannanase blends on performance and antibody titers in pigs with response to vaccination (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Thus, this study investigated the impacts of in-feed additive blends on growth performance, nutrient digestibility, fecal gas emission, and serological immune responses to swine diseases in weaning to finishing pigs.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Schematic view of the experiment design.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1095877-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><label>2.</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec3"><label>2.1.</label><title>Ethical endorsement</title><p>Husbandry practices were strictly performed according to the guidelines of animal welfare, and the research protocol (No: DK-2-2203) was approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) of Dankook University (Cheonan, Republic of Korea) prior to the trial.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>2.2.</label><title>Research site and source of the main additive</title><p>This experiment was carried out at the Dankook University &#8220;Swine research unit&#8221; located in Gongju City (Republic of Korea). The main supplements AZn, <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract, and &#946;-mannanase enzyme (powdered form) used in this study were obtained from BTN Co. Ltd. (Asan-si, Republic of Korea).</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>2.3.</label><title>Animals, trial design, and husbandry management</title><p>A total of 180 crossbred [(Landrace &#215;Yorkshire)&#8201;&#215;&#8201;Duroc] pigs were used in this 22-week trial. The mean body weights of pigs for all the pens were made to be approximately 6.57&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1&#8201;kg. There were three treatment groups with 12 replicates with 5 pigs (2 barrows and 3 gilts) per pen. Pigs were arranged in a complete randomized block design at the weanling stage, and this arrangement was continued until the finishing stage. The weaning room temperature was set up to 33&#176;C at first, and later it was reduced to 28&#176;C (83&#176;F), and 60% humidity was maintained. Meanwhile, the growing&#8211;finishing facility was equipped with natural ventilation and completely slatted concrete floors, and the room temperature was fixed at 21.5&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1.12&#176;C until week 22. The bite-type nipple drinkers and commercial feeder hopper with three feeder spaces were fixed at the corner of each pen, allowing the weaning pigs to access free feed and water throughout the trial. Meanwhile, single-space feeders and water drinkers were fixed at the corner of each pen (1.8&#8201;m&#8201;&#215;&#8201;1.8&#8201;m) for the growing&#8211;finishing pigs to access <italic toggle="yes">ad libitum</italic> feed and water, respectively. The experimental animals were vaccinated with four different vaccines: porcine circovirus type 2 (PCV-2), classical swine fever virus (CSFV), <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma hyopneumoniae</italic> (MH), and foot-and-mouth disease-type (FMDV) at initial (3&#8201;weeks old) to 19&#8201;weeks (22&#8201;weeks old) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). The breeding room was strictly monitored by the trainees thrice a day (9:00 AM, 2:00&#8201;PM, and 7:00&#8201;PM) to check whether the feeder had sufficient feeds, any leakage in the water trough, and occurrence of health issues.</p><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Vaccination and blood collection schedule of pigs from weaning to finishing stage. A total of 180 pigs (12 replicates &#215; 3 treatemet, with 5 pigs/pen) were vaccinated at different periods, and the blood samples were randomly drawn from <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;24/treatment.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1095877-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec6"><label>2.4.</label><title>Experimental diets and dietary schedule</title><p>According to initial body weight (6.57&#8201;&#177;&#8201;1&#8201;kg) and sex, pigs were randomly assigned into one of three dietary treatment groups, i.e., CON, TRT 1, and TRT2. The experimental diets were as follows.</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>CON-Basal diet (corn and soybean meal)</p></list-item><list-item><p>TRT1-CON +1,000&#8201;ppm AZn&#8201;+&#8201;0.07% yucca extract (YE)&#8201;+&#8201;0.05% &#946;-mannanase</p></list-item><list-item><p>TRT2-CON +2,000&#8201;ppm AZn&#8201;+&#8201;0.07% YE+ 0.05% &#946;-mannanase</p></list-item></list><p>The basal diet (mash form) for each growth phase, i.e., weaning Phase I (weeks 0&#8211;1), Phase II (weeks 1&#8211;3), and Phase III (weeks 3&#8211;6), was formulated to meet the recommendation of NRC, 2021 (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), while growing (weeks 6&#8211;12) and finishing [Phase I (weeks 12&#8211;18) and Phase II (weeks 18&#8211;24)] were formulated to meet the recommendation of NRC, 1988 (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The basal diet and additives were blended using a DDK-801 feed mixer (Daedong Tech, Gyeonggi-do, Republic of Korea).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Ingredient composition of experimental diets on as-fed basis.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Weaning</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Items</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase 1</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase 2</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase 3</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corn</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.70</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.03</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.83</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean meal, 48%</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.25</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.68</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fermented SBM</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood plasma protein</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tallow</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.90</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.69</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lactose</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.46</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.78</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sugar</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whey protein</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDCP</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limestone</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salt</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methionine (99%)</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-lysine (78%)</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vit/Min premix<xref rid="tfn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Choline (25%)</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AZn (80%)</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total (%)</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" char="." colspan="4" rowspan="1">Calculated value</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP, %</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ME, kcal/kg</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,450</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,400</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,350</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FAT, %</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.56</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.79</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.66</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca, %</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P, %</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LYS, %</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MET, %</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lactose, %</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn1"><label>a</label><p>Provided per kg of complete diet: 16,800&#8201;IU vitamin A; 2,400&#8201;IU vitamin D<sub>3</sub>; 108&#8201;mg vitamin E; 7.2&#8201;mg vitamin K; 18&#8201;mg Riboflavin; 80.4&#8201;mg Niacin; 2.64&#8201;mg Thiamine; 45.6&#8201;mg D-Pantothenic; 0.06&#8201;mg Cobalamine; 12&#8201;mg Cu (as CuSO4); 60&#8201;mg AZn (as amino&#8211;AZn complex); 24&#8201;mg Mn (as MnSO4); 0.6&#8201;mg I (as Ca (IO3)2); 0.36&#8201;mg Se (as Na2SeO3).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Ingredient composition of experimental diets on as-fed basis.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Items</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Growing</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Finishing</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase 1</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phase 2</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corn</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.57</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.98</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rice bran</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat bran</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Palm kernel meal</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean meal</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dehulled soybean meal</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.11</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.34</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rape seed meal</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sesame meal</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brown rice</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Animal fat</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.79</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.26</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.89</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Molasses</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limestone</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MCP</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salt</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methionine 98%</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Threonine 98%</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lysine 25%</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Choline Chloride 50%</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mineral<xref rid="tfn2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>/Vit premix<xref rid="tfn3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Calculated value</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digestible energy (kcal/kg)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,560</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,540</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,510</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolic energy (kcal/kg)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,280</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,260</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,250</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP (%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.50</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.00</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C. Fat (%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.70</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.90</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C. Ash (%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.40</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.20</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">C. fiber</italic> (%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.80</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.90</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.90</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total lysine (%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcium (%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phosphorus (%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn2"><label>a</label><p>Provided per kg diet: Fe, 100&#8201;mg as ferrous sulfate; Cu, 17&#8201;mg as copper sulfate; Mn, 17&#8201;mg as manganese oxide; AZn, 100&#8201;mg as zinc oxide; I, 0.5&#8201;mg as potassium iodide; and Se, 0.3&#8201;mg as sodium selenite.</p></fn><fn id="tfn3"><label>b</label><p>Provided per kilograms of diet: vitamin A, 10,800&#8201;IU; vitamin D3, 4,000&#8201;IU; vitamin E, 40&#8201;IU; vitamin K3, 4&#8201;mg; vitamin B1, 6&#8201;mg; vitamin B2, 12&#8201;mg; vitamin B6, 6&#8201;mg; vitamin B12, 0.05&#8201;mg; biotin, 0.2&#8201;mg; folic acid, 2&#8201;mg; niacin, 50&#8201;mg; D-calcium pantothenate, 25&#8201;mg.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec7"><label>2.5.</label><title>Specimen collection and clinical analyses</title><sec id="sec8"><label>2.5.1.</label><title>Growth performance</title><p>The growth performance variables, namely, body weight (BW), average daily gain (ADG), average daily feed intake (ADFI), and gain-to-feed ratio (G: F), were recorded at different growth stages. Individual body weight was measured using a GL-6000S machine (G-Tech Inc., LTD., Seoul, Republic of Korea) at the beginning and end of weeks 6, 12, 18, and 22 to determine their average daily gain (ADG). The feeders were filled in the morning (9:00&#8201;AM), and the remaining feeds in the feeders were collected and weighed in the evening (5:00&#8201;PM) to calculate the ADFI. The G: F was determined by dividing the ADFI and ADG.</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><label>2.5.2.</label><title>Nutrient digestibility</title><p>Seven days prior to the fecal collection (end of each growth stage), i.e., week 6, 12, and 22, 0.5% chromium oxide (Cr2O3) as an indigestible marker was added to the pigs&#8217; diet in order to measure the nutrient digestibility of dry matter (DM), nitrogen (N), and gross energy (GE). After mixing the chromium oxide, the representative feed samples from each treatment group were collected and stored in sterilized plastic bags for further analysis. At the end of weeks 6, 12, and 22 (10:00&#8201;AM and 3:00&#8201;PM), approximately 200&#8201;g of fresh fecal specimens were randomly collected from two pigs per pen (one barrow and one gilt) by rectal palpation and homogenized. Within 45&#8201;min, the collected specimens were taken to the laboratory and stored at &#8722;20&#176;C to prevent changes in nutrients. Before starting the analysis, the fecal samples were kept in the WOF-L800 hot air convection drying oven (Daehan Scientific Co. Ltd., Wonju, Republic of Korea) for 2&#8201;days at 105&#176;C. Then, the samples were taken from the dryer and grounded well (Willey Mill, United States) to pass through a 1-mm screen sieve. Simultaneously, the feed samples were also grounded. The nutrient digestibility of DM, N, and GE was analyzed according to the AOAC guidelines (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). The chromium concentration in the sample was analyzed using UV spectrophotometry (Shimadzu, UV-1201, Kyoto, Japan), and the readings were noted. Nutrient digestibility (ND) was analyzed using the following formula: ND (%) = 100&#8722;[(NF/ND) &#215; (CrD/CrF)] &#215; 100]. Here NF, ND, CrD, and CrF stand for nutrient concentration in the feces sample, nutrient concentration in the diet, chromium concentration in the diet, and chromium concentration in the feces sample, respectively. The gross energy in the feed and fecal sample was measured using the Parr 6,400 (Parr instrument, Moline, IL, United States) oxygen calorimeter. The crude protein (N) levels in the feed and fecal samples were determined using the Tector Kjeltec&#8482; 8,400 (FOSS Co. LTD., Hilleroed, Denmark) automatic analyzer.</p></sec><sec id="sec10"><label>2.5.3.</label><title>Fecal gas emission</title><p>At the end of weeks 6, 12, and 22, approximately 300&#8201;g of stock feces were collected (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;2 pen/treatment) and placed in plastic boxes with a small hole in the middle and sealed with plaster. The samples were fermented for 1 day at room temperature (25&#176;C), and 100&#8201;mL of the sample was taken from the headspace (approximately 2.0&#8201;cm) above the fecal sample for air circulation. Later, the box was re-sealed to measure the noxious fecal content. Before measurement, the slurry samples were manually shaken for around 30&#8201;s to measure the crust formation on the surface and homogenized. The adhesive plaster was punctured, and 100&#8201;mL of the headspace air was sampled approximately 2.0&#8201;cm above the fecal surface. NH<sub>3</sub>, H<sub>2</sub>S, methyl mercaptan, CO2, and acetic acid concentrations were measured using a Multi-RAE Lite-gas search 121 probe (model PGM-6208, RAE, United States).</p></sec><sec id="sec11"><label>2.5.4.</label><title>Antibody titer analyses</title><p>For the antibody titer analysis, at the end of weeks 6,15, and 19, blood samples were collected after 12&#8201;h of fasting from the jugular vein (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;24 pigs/treatment) using 10&#8201;mL vacutainer glass tubes (Venoject<sup>&#174;</sup>, Terumo Europe N.V., Leuven, Belgium). The collected specimens were taken to the laboratory and centrifuged at 3,000&#215;<italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 15&#8201;min at 4&#176;C (centrifuge MF-550, Hanil Science Industrial Co. LTD, Incheon, Republic of Korea). Then, the plasma was carefully transferred to 1.5&#8201;mL microtubes and tested with PCV-2 (SERELISA<sup>&#174;</sup> PCV2 Ab Mono Blocking, Synbiotics Corp., Lyon, France) and CSFV (IDEXX CSFV Ag Serum Plus, IDEXX Laboratories, Inc., Maine, United States) using enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) kits following the manufacturer&#8217;s protocol. The MH serum samples were tested with an ELISA (DAKO <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma hyopneumoniae</italic> ELISA<sup>&#174;</sup>; DAKO A/S, Glostrup, Denmark). The anti-FMDV serotype O antibody level of the serum sample was determined using a Prio-CHECK FMDV type O ELISA kit (Prionics, Switzerland).</p></sec><sec id="sec12"><label>2.5.5.</label><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>Experimental data were analyzed using the GLM procedure of SAS Inst. (Inc., Cary, NC, United States). Growth performance analysis was performed using GraphPad Prism statistical software version 5.0. Orthogonal polynomial contrasts were used to evaluate the linear and quadratic effects of dietary AZn, YE, and &#946;-mannanase supplementation. The pen was used as the experimental unit for the analysis of growth performance, nutrient digestibility, fecal gas emission, and antibody titers. A probability value of less than 0.05 was considered significant, and less than 0.10 was considered a trend.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec13"><label>3.</label><title>Results</title><p>Pigs fed diet supplements with AZn, YE, and &#946;-mannanase linearly increased (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) BW and average daily gain at weeks 6, 12, 17, and 18. Also, the gain-to-feed ratio showed a linear increase (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) at the end of weeks 6, 12, 17, and the overall experimental period compared to those fed CON diet. There was no difference in feed intake (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>) and nutrient digestibility of DM, N, and GE throughout the trial (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). However, the inclusion of experimental diets linearly decreased (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) noxious gas emissions such as NH<sub>3</sub>, H<sub>2</sub>S, acetic acid, Methyl mercaptans, and CO<sub>2</sub> at the end of week 22 (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The dietary inclusion of AZn, YE, and &#946;-mannanase significantly reduced the S/P ratio for <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma hyopneumoniae</italic> (MH) compared with control. However, at the end of week 6 and 19 pigs showed linearly increased (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) serological immune responses for foot-and-mouth disease virus (FMDV-O type) and porcine circovirus-2 (PCV-2), respectively (<xref rid="tab5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Effects of dietary AZn, <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract, and &#946;-mannanase on growth performance of pigs at different growth stages. Data are presented as standard means of error. *, **, and *** indicate statistically significant at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;&#8201;0.05, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;&#8201;0.001, and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;&#8201;0.0001, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1095877-g003.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The effect of dietary AZn, <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract, and &#946;-mannanase supplementation on nutrient digestibility in pigs.<xref rid="tfn4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Items, %</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">CON</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">TRT1</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">TRT2</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">SEM<xref rid="tfn5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linear</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quadratic</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Week 6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dry matter</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.15</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.80</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.41</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.323</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.988</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogen</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.26</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.67</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.44</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.362</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.867</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gross energy</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.2</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.75</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.54</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.323</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.917</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Week 12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dry matter</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.07</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.61</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.17</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.443</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.994</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogen</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.80</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.47</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.98</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.392</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.948</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gross energy</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.91</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.49</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.87</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.467</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.928</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Week 22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dry matter</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.57</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.72</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.21</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.225</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.770</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogen</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.66</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.89</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.58</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.155</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.810</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gross energy</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.71</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.70</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.29</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.256</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.867</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn4"><label>a</label><p>CON, Basal diet; TRT1, Basal diet +1,000&#8201;ppm AZn&#8201;+&#8201;0.07% YE&#8201;+&#8201;0.05% &#946;-mannanase; TRT2, Basal diet +2,000&#8201;ppm AZn&#8201;+&#8201;0.07% YE&#8201;+&#8201;0.05% &#946;-mannanase.</p></fn><fn id="tfn5"><label>b</label><p>Standard error of means.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>The effect of dietary AZn, <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract, and &#946;-mannanase supplementation on gas emission in pigs.<xref rid="tfn6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>1</sup></xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Items, ppm</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">CON</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">TRT1</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">TRT2</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">SEM<xref rid="tfn7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>2</sup></xref></th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value<xref rid="tfn8" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>3</sup></xref></th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linear</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quadratic</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Week 6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NH<sub>3</sub></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.50<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.88<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.38<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.821</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H<sub>2</sub>S</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.20</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.63</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.50</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.261</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.661</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methyl mercaptans</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.13</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.25</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.50</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.582</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.567</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetic acid</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.38</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.38</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.065</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.575</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CO<sub>2</sub></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,375<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,050<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,150<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Week 12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NH<sub>3</sub></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.25<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.63<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.25<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.627</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H<sub>2</sub>S</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.03<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.40<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.25<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.385</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methyl mercaptans</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.88</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.13</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.312</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.665</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetic acid</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.63a</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.75<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.50<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.448</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CO<sub>2</sub></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,775<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,975<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,000<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">298</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Week 22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NH<sub>3</sub></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.25<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.50<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.13<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.453</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H<sub>2</sub>S</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.18<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.35<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.05<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.511</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methyl mercaptans</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.13<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.13<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.88<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.407</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetic acid</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.13<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.63<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.38<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.248</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CO<sub>2</sub></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,100<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,825<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,325<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">239</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.233</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn6"><label>1</label><p>CON, Basal diet; TRT1, Basal diet +1,000&#8201;ppm AZn&#8201;+&#8201;0.07% YE&#8201;+&#8201;0.05% &#946;-mannanase; TRT2, Basal diet +2,000&#8201;ppm AZn&#8201;+&#8201;0.07% YE&#8201;+&#8201;0.05% &#946;-mannanase.</p></fn><fn id="tfn7"><label>2</label><p>Standard error of means.</p></fn><fn id="tfn8"><label>3</label><p>Means in the same row with different superscripts differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>The effect of dietary AZn, <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract, and &#946;-mannanase supplementation on the immune response of pigs.<xref rid="tfn9" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>1</sup></xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Items</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">CON</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">TRT1</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">TRT2</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">SEM<xref rid="tfn10" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>2</sup></xref></th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value<xref rid="tfn11" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>3</sup></xref></th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linear</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quadratic</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>Week 6</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>PCV-2</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S/P ratio</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.289</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.844</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>MH</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S/P ratio</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.048</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.817</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>CSFV</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blocking (%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.29</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.77</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.59</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.065</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.543</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>FMDV-O type</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blocking (%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.93<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.56<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.70<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.33</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.533</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>Week 15</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>PCV-2</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S/P ratio</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.267</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.632</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>MH</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S/P ratio</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.763</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.534</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>CSFV</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blocking (%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.16</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.06</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.24</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.183</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.450</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>FMDV-O type</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blocking (%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.39</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.08</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.11</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.630</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.955</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>Week 19</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>PCV-2</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S/P ratio</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.84<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.874</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>MH</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S/P ratio</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.615</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.647</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>CSFV</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blocking (%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.34</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.70</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.55</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.32</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.513</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.874</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>FMDV-O type</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blocking (%)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.74</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.51</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.42</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.65</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.199</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.746</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn9"><label>1</label><p>CON, Basal diet; TRT1, Basal diet +1,000&#8201;ppm AZn&#8201;+&#8201;0.07% YE&#8201;+&#8201;0.05% &#946;-mannanase; TRT2, Basal diet +2,000&#8201;ppm AZn&#8201;+&#8201;0.07% YE&#8201;+&#8201;0.05% &#946;-mannanase. PCV-Porcine circovirus type 2; CSFV-Classical swine fever virus, FMDV-foot-and-mouth disease serotype O, MH-<italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma hyopneumoniae.</italic></p></fn><fn id="tfn10"><label>2</label><p>Standard error of means.</p></fn><fn id="tfn11"><label>3</label><p>Means in the same row with different superscripts differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). S/P ratio defined optical density of serum (S) /optical density of positive control (P).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussions" id="sec14"><label>4.</label><title>Discussion</title><sec id="sec15"><label>4.1.</label><title>Growth performance</title><p>Zn at pharmacological doses (1,500&#8211;3,000&#8201;mg/kg) is widely used in the swine industry as an effective tool for managing post-weaning diarrhea (PWD), which causes significant economic losses to the production cycle of piglets (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). In addition, it exerts an optimistic effect along the total intestinal tract by targeting digestive secretions, intestinal architecture, and antioxidant systems (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Though Zn has a moderate antibacterial effect against PWD, the environmental impact of Zn and emerging threats raise serious questions about the sustainability of its extensive utilization. Accordingly, the long-term use of Zn at the pharmaceutical level (2,500&#8211;3,000&#8201;ppm) in pigs resulted in potential toxic effects and raised several anxieties such as environment pollution, antimicrobial resistance, and modification of intestinal microbiota (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Concerning this, the European Union (EU) has prohibited the use of Zn at the pharmaceutical level in pig production since June 2022 (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>); therefore, novel strategies to manage PWD are urgently needed. Indeed, plant-derived products that contain secondary metabolites could help the animals to improve their health and production by reducing microbial resistance exhibited by pharmacological drugs (AZn) used in animal feed. Previously, Z&#250;&#241;iga-Serrano et al. (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) reported that secondary plant metabolites are cost-effective for improving the production efficiency of non-ruminants. Feed costs play a determining factor in profitable and sustainable animal production. In an earlier report, Kiarie et al. (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) pointed out that using exogenous enzymes (&#946;-mannanase) has gained wide acceptance in feed cost management through the application of resourceful feed ingredients and the reduced environmental impact in animal production. Taking all the aspects into consideration, we have initiated this research. As anticipated, the current research reveals linearly increased (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) BW, ADG, and gain-to-feed ratio in pigs fed a diet supplemented with AZn, YE, and &#946;-mannanase blends. The present finding is in partial agreement with Case and Carlson (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>), who noted greater ADG in weaning pigs fed a diet supplemented with 2,000&#8211;3,000&#8201;ppm of Zn. Moreover, Hong et al. (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) reported that increased (120&#8201;ppm) YE concentration in pigs&#8217; diets improved daily feed intake and gain-to-feed ratio.</p><p>Similarly, Bae et al. (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) stated that pigs fed the yucca extract (125&#8201;ppm) diet significantly improved average daily gain. Moreover, Lv et al. (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>) pointed out that adding 600&#8201;U/kg &#946;-mannanase to the diet of growing pigs increased daily weight gain (quadratic effect; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01) and feed efficiency (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01) during the second phase and the overall experimental period. In addition, Pettey et al. (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) noted a 3.4% increased weight gain and 3.9% feed efficiency in growing&#8211;finishing pigs fed diets supplemented with &#946;-mannanase. On the contrary, Holen et al. (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) reported that growing&#8211;finishing pigs receiving 60 to 140&#8201;mg/kg of organic and inorganic AZn sources had no impact on growth performance. Furthermore, Patience et al. (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) found no differences in growing&#8211;finishing pigs&#8217; growth parameters with the inclusion of 50&#8201;mg/kg of AZn to lysine to calorie ratios. Yen and Pond (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) and Gipp et al. (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>) also stated that yucca extract additions had no effects on average daily gain, average daily feed intake, and gain/feed in pigs, and this finding partially agreed with the present results in which pigs fed dietary supplement with AZn, YE, and &#946;-mannanase showed no effect on their daily intake. Overall, there is little evidence in the literature to support differences in growth performance using these three additive blends in the pig&#8217;s diet; thus, we made the majority of comparisons with AZn, YE, and &#946;-mannanase individually. Together, we speculated that the inclusion of experimental diets might satisfy the nutritional requirements of pigs to reveal better growth performance, i.e., increased body weight, daily gain, and gain-to-feed ratio. As a natural feed additive, <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> (YS) has been shown to have a positive effect on promoting animal growth and improving feed utilization in livestock (<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). In the current study, pigs fed YE failed to enhance the feed intake, yet this null effect is consistent with Gurbuz et al. (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>) who also observed this in laying hens fed <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract (YSE). However, the additive blends increased the daily gain and feed conversion efficiency, and this is consistent with the studies on the effects of YSE on broiler chickens, which showed that extracts of YS plants increased the daily gain and feed conversion efficiency (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). It is not known which phytochemicals of YS are responsible for the decreased nutrient utilization, but we supposed that active groups of phytochemicals contained in YS might be one of the reasons for the reduction of nutrient absorption in the digestive tract that resulted in no improvement in feed intake; thus, further study is needed to understand the exact cause for the lack of this result.</p></sec><sec id="sec16"><label>4.2.</label><title>Nutrient digestibility</title><p>A great deal of research on pig nutrition has focused on the utilization of different in-feed additives. Still, no work has been carried out on pigs using a combination of AZn, YE, and &#946;-mannanase supplements. Enzyme supplementation with &#946;-mannanase to degrade &#946;-mannan fibers in the diet has been shown to improve swine performance (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>) and upregulate the metabolic functions related to digestion, metabolism, and immunity in broilers (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). In an earlier study, Qian et al. (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>) reported that pigs fed a diet supplement with chitosan&#8211;Zn chelates had higher DM. However, Cho et al. (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>) reported that the apparent total tract digestibility of DM, N, and GE was unaffected by dietary Zn, which was consistent with the present findings. Furthermore, Hong (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) reported that the digestibility of DM and N was not affected by the YE supplementation. In contrast, Jo et al. (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) and Kim et al. (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>) reported that dietary supplements with &#946;-mannanase or enzyme complex with &#946;-mannanase improved the nutrient digestibility of growing pigs. The probable differences in the magnitude of the response to enzyme supplementation in the current experiment and previous results could be due to the alterations in enzyme purity, level of supplementation, thermostability, and the pH optimum of the various products used. Previously, the study of Hedemann et al. (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) demonstrated that the inclusion of 2,500&#8201;ppm Zn in weaned pigs&#8217; diet increased the activity of several pancreatic digestive enzymes such as carboxypeptidases, trypsin, and chymotrypsin, guaranteeing a higher nutrient digestibility; in this sense, we supposed that the inclusion of AZn might not be sufficient to increase the activity of pancreatic digestive enzymes to enhance nutrient absorption. Moreover, we speculated that the direct action of this combined supplementation on digestive physiology, regulation of the intestinal development, and remodeling of the gut microbiota might not be closely associated to improved digestibility. The non-starch polysaccharides (NSP, &#946;-mannan) content in the swine diet could depress lipid metabolism by the inhibition of lipolysis and nutrient absorption (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). From this, we speculated that NSP could impair the diffusion and connective transport of lipase, oil, and bile salt micelles within the gastrointestinal contents, leading to a change in the viscosity of the digesta and thus resulting in decreased digestibility.</p></sec><sec id="sec17"><label>4.3.</label><title>Fecal gas emission</title><p>Ammonia emissions from animal facilities are frequently subjected to odor complaints and public anxiety due to the possibility of their adverse health effects on both humans and animals. Prolonged exposure to high ammonia levels may also lead to various disorders (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). Therefore, it is imperative to develop efficient strategies to reduce noxious emissions from livestock manure. Zn is related to considerable risks to the environment, deriving from the application of Zn-rich manure to land: manure comes from facilities employing pharmacological doses of Zn (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). Previously, Zhang et al. (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>) reported that dietary supplements with 0.1% chelate copper and Zn showed no difference in fecal noxious gas production in weaning pigs. However, in this study, 0.2% of Zn combined with YE and &#946;-mannanase highly suppressed the odor emission. The rationale behind the decreased gas emission in pigs is attributed to the inclusion of Zn, which enhances the intestinal antioxidant capacity and reduces the intestinal cell apoptotic index, thus resulting in decreased noxious gas production. In an earlier study, Cha et al. (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>) reported that ammonia concentration in feces was significantly reduced by YE (0.02%) addition. Similarly, Colina et al. (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>) noted that pigs fed 125&#8201;ppm of YE reduced aerial ammonia concentration by 22%. Moreover, Sutton et al. (<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>) pronounced that ammonia emission was significantly suppressed by 55.5% in manure by the inclusion of saponin extract. However, Upadhaya et al. (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>) reported that &#946;-mannanase supplementation to corn&#8211;SBM diets tended to reduce the NH<sub>3</sub> concentration of fecal slurry after 24&#8201;h fermentation. On the other hand, Yeo and Kim (<xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>) noted a tendency to decrease ammonia emission in broilers, while Rowland et al. (<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>) pointed out that yucca extract significantly reduced ammonia release in pig feces. YE has been shown to improve livestock and poultry performance, thereby increasing their daily weight gain and feed efficiency (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>), reducing ammonia emissions from animal manure, and consequently controlling the odor emitted from animal facilities (<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). The possible reason behind the reduction of harmful gas emissions in this study could be due to the beneficial effect of the YE supplement, whose saponin fractions inhibit the activity of urease in the decomposition of urea nitrogen into ammonia, and/or due to the presence of a glycoprotein and the ammonia-binding properties of YE, which play an important role in reducing ammonia release from animal excretions, helping animals to improve their performance.</p></sec><sec id="sec18"><label>4.4.</label><title>Vaccine-induced antibody titer</title><p>Antibodies of maternal origin are normally present in all piglets due to the adequate intake of colostrum (<xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>), but these antibodies in serum gradually decrease during the lactation and rearing stages (<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). Porcine circovirus-2 (PCV-2) usually appears between the final phase of the nursery and the start of the fattening phase (<xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). Furthermore, foot-and-mouth disease (FMD), an acute infectious disease caused by an RNA virus belonging to <italic toggle="yes">Picornaviridae</italic> family, which affects 77% of the global livestock population (<xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>), and classical swine fever (CSF), a highly contagious disease caused by the classical swine fever virus (CSFV), bring huge economic loss worldwide (<xref rid="ref60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). The immunologic mechanisms whereby zinc modulates increased susceptibility to infection have been studied for several decades. For instance, Mishra et al. (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) stated that zinc plays an important role in controlling the immune system, particularly in zinc-deficient animals who experience increased susceptibility to various pathogens. In addition, Saura and Crowe (<xref rid="ref61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>) reported that zinc has broad-spectrum anti-viral activity against a variety of viruses, such as transmissible gastroenteritis virus (TGEV), equine arteritis virus, and severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus. Many potential mechanisms have been suggested to explain the beneficial effect of Zn against virus infections. Overbeck et al. (<xref rid="ref62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>) demonstrated that Zn contributes to initiating and maintaining robust immune responses, thereby producing cytokine and modulating the activity of immune cells. Correspondingly, Martin et al. (<xref rid="ref63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>) demonstrated that high levels of dietary Zn provided as Zn outbalanced Zn homeostasis with increased accumulation of Zn in various organs, including the small intestine of piglets. In recent years, herbal immune modulators have been considered safe alternatives, and they are totally free from animal or human pathogens and have been reported to show some beneficial effects in terms of cost, distribution, and production (<xref rid="ref64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>). Moreover, exogenous &#946;-mannanase enzymes have been developed to inhibit innate immune stimulators in pigs (<xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>). Here, the effect of AZn, YE, and &#946;-mannanase supplement on the serological immune response of PCV-2, CSFV, MH, and FMDV stereotype O vaccination was studied in pigs of different ages; as a result, a significant increase of the antibody level specific to FMD O type and a tendency of increase of the antibody level specific to CSFV were observed in their serum samples at week 6. This result was constant with that of Kar et al. (<xref rid="ref66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>) who observed similar effects in Tamworth and Desi crossbred piglets after they were fed a diet containing 150&#8201;ppm of Zn sulfate for 60&#8201;days from 1&#8201;month of age to vaccination at 56&#8201;days of age with a cell culture-adapted lapinized CSFV strain. A study by Fu et al. (<xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>) demonstrated the effectiveness of a Chinese herbal extract made from licorice, luhanguo, chrysanthemum, and Chinese tea in inhibiting the FMD virus in suckling mice. Furthermore, experimental diets significantly increased the antibody level in pigs at the end of week 19 and suppressed the shedding of PCV-2. Previously, Zhao et al. (<xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>) reported on zinc-deficient states, a reduced immune response to hepatitis B vaccination in offspring mice, suggesting a possible enhancement of antibody formation by zinc supplementation (<xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>). Though Zn, YE, and &#946;-mannanase additives showed certain benefits for pig health and performance in earlier studies, to date their direct impact on antibody production against various virus is not well elucidated. Herein, we speculated that timely vaccination with appropriate vaccines targeting these specific viruses along with experimental diets might prevent them from shedding FMDV type O and PCV-2 viruses. Therefore, the influence of these stimulants needs further trials to discern the pertaining mechanism of action on these supplement blends.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec19"><label>5.</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our study demonstrates that the inclusion of 2,000&#8201;ppm of AZn, 0.07% of yucca extract, and 0.05% of &#946;-mannanase enzyme supplement blends could be beneficial in decreasing noxious gas production and increasing the growth performance (BW, ADG, G: F) of pigs without adverse effects on nutrient digestibility. Moreover, adding these three additive blends to pigs&#8217; diets along with timely vaccination could significantly reduce the S/P ratio for <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma hyopneumoniae</italic> and increase the serological immune responses to foot-and-mouth disease virus and porcine circovirus-2. Based on this result, we infer that a blend of AZn, YE, and &#946;-mannanase would serve as a novel in-feed additive to enhance the performance of pigs. It also acts as a boosting agent and immune stimulatory to increase the efficacy of swine vaccination.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec20"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/supplementary materials, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec id="sec21"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by the Experimental was conducted with strict guidelines of the Institutional Animal care and use Committee (IACUC), and the research protocol (DK-2-2203) was approved by Dankook University (Cheonan, Republic of Korea), prior to the trial.</p></sec><sec id="sec22"><title>Author contributions</title><p>BRL and IK: conceptualization. VS, NHK, and SC: methodology. VS, BRL, and NHK: formal analysis. VS and SC: writing-original draft preparation. IK: investigation, reviewing, and editing. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="sec23"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the International Science &amp; Business Belt support program, through the Korea Innovation Foundation funded by the Ministry of Science and ICT(1711150853).</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec24"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>Authors BRL and NHK were employed by ZinexBio Corporation.</p><p>The remaining authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec100"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sampath</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duk Ha</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kibria</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of low-nutrient-density diet with probiotic mixture (<italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> ms1, <italic toggle="yes">B. licheniformis</italic> SF5-1, and <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>) supplementation on performance of weaner pigs</article-title>. <source>J Anim Physiol Anim Nutr</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>106</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jpn.13544</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33779004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alagawany</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Hack</surname><given-names>MEA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of rosemary herb as a dietary supplement on performance, egg quality, serum biochemical parameters, and oxidative status in laying hens</article-title>. <source>J Anim Feed Sci</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>341</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22358/jafs/65617/2015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Latheef</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samad</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karthik</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Multiple beneficial applications and modes of action of herbs in poultry health and production-a review</article-title>. <source>Int J Pharmacol</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>152</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>76</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3923/ijp.2015.152.176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayasan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yurtseven</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baylan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Canogullari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effects of dietary <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> on egg yield parameters and egg shell quality of laying Japanese quails (<italic toggle="yes">Coturnix coturnix</italic> japonica)</article-title>. <source>Int J Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>159</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3923/ijps.2005.159.162</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahoo</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sethi</surname><given-names>APS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract as feed additive on performance of broiler chicks in winter season</article-title>. <source>Vet World</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>556</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14202/vetworld.2015.556-560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27047134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4774811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of yucca extract and (or) far infrared emitted materials supplementation on the growth performance, serum characteristics and ammonia production of growing and finishing pigs</article-title>. <source>Asian Australas J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2001</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1299</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>303</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5713/ajas.2001.1299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Content of soluble non-starch polysaccharides &#946;-mannan and xylan in legume meals, non-legume meals, and cereal grains or cereal grain by-products</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>Abstract-328</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingale</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosseindoust</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chae</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of mannan level and &#946;-mannanase supplementation on growth performance, apparent total tract digestibility and blood metabolites of growing pigs</article-title>. <source>Animal</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>202</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1751731116001385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27411968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pettey</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Senne</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shriver</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of beta-mannanase addition to corn-soybean meal diets on growth performance, carcass traits, and nutrient digestibility of weanling and growing-finishing pigs</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>80</volume>:<fpage>1012</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/2002.8041012x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12002307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingale</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lohakare</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of exogenous enzyme supplementation to corn- and soybean meal-based or complex diets on growth performance, nutrient digestibility and blood metabolites in growing pigs</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>3041</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/jas.2010-3430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22585797</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Upadhaya</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of &#946;-mannanase supplementation to corn&#8211;soya bean meal-based diets on growth performance, nutrient digestibility, blood urea nitrogen, faecal coliform and lactic acid bacteria and faecal noxious gas emission in growing pigs</article-title>. <source>Arch Anim Nutr</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1745039X.2015.1117697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26635142</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wellinghausen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirchner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rink</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The immunobiology of zinc</article-title>. <source>Immunol Today</source>. (<year>1997</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>519</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0167-5699(97)01146-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9386346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roselli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finamore</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garaguso</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Britti</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mengheri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Zinc oxide protects cultured enterocytes from the damage induced by <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source>. (<year>2003</year>) <volume>133</volume>:<fpage>4077</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jn/133.12.4077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14652351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekielski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Talegaonkar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaidya</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Zinc oxide nanoparticles: a promising nanomaterial for biomedical applications</article-title>. <source>Drug Discov Today</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1825</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.drudis.2017.08.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28847758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koonpaew</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teeravechyan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frantz</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chailangkarn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jongkaewwattana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>PEDV and PDCoV pathogenesis: the interplay between host innate immune responses and porcine enteric coronaviruses</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>34</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2019.00034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30854373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6395401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobisch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friis</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Swine mycoplasmoses</article-title>. <source>Rev Sci Tech (International Office of Epizootics)</source>. (<year>1996</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1569</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>605</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.20506/rst.15.4.983</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9190026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Heugten</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spears</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of dietary protein on performance and immune response in weanling pigs subjected to an inflammatory challenge</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>1994</year>) <volume>72</volume>:<fpage>2661</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/1994.72102661x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7883625</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hevener</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Routh</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Almond</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of immune challenge on concentrations of serum insulin-like growth factor-I and growth performance in pigs</article-title>. <source>Can Vet J</source>. (<year>1999</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>782</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10563236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1540011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajam</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dar</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandra Sekar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nanda</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kishore</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhanuprakash</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Co-administration of flagellin augments immune responses to inactivated foot-and-mouth disease virus (FMDV) antigen</article-title>. <source>Res Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>95</volume>:<fpage>936</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rvsc.2013.07.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23941960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zakrzewski</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#252;nzel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pieper</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Twardziok</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>High-dose dietary zinc oxide mitigates infection with transmissible gastroenteritis virus in piglets</article-title>. <source>BMC Vet Res</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-6148-10-75</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24673930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3986850</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll1">National Research Council</collab></person-group>. <source>Nutrient requirement of swine</source>. <edition>11th</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academy Press</publisher-name> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll2">National Research Council</collab></person-group>. <source>Nutrient requirements of swine</source>. <edition>10th</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academy Press</publisher-name> (<year>1998</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll3">AOAC</collab></person-group>. <source>Official method of analysis</source>. <edition>16th</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Washington DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Association of Official Analytical Chemists</publisher-name> (<year>1995</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tugnoli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grilli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Towards zero zinc oxide: feeding strategies to manage post-weaning diarrhea in piglets</article-title>. <source>Animals</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>642</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani11030642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33670980</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7997240</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cordero</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pineiro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Durosoy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Zinc oxide at low supplementation level improves productive performance and health status of piglets</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>436</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/jas.53833</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23365402</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of the combined effects of different dose levels of zinc oxide with probiotics complex supplementation on the growth performance, nutrient digestibility, faecal microbiota, noxious gas emissions, and faecal score of weaning pigs</article-title>. <source>J Anim Physiol Anim Nutr</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>105</volume>:<fpage>286</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jpn.13493</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33423308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Z&#250;&#241;iga-Serrano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrios-Garc&#237;a</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hume</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz-Albarr&#225;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bautista-Mart&#237;nez</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial and digestive effects of <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extracts related to production and environment implications of ruminant and non-ruminant animals: a review</article-title>. <source>Agriculture</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1198</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/agriculture12081198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiarie</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steelman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Does supplementing &#946;-mannanase modulate feed-induced immune response and gastrointestinal ecology in poultry and pigs? An appraisal</article-title>. <source>Front Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>875095</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fanim.2022.875095</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Case</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of feeding organic and inorganic sources of additional zinc on growth performance and zinc balance in nursery pigs</article-title>. <source>Journal Animal Science</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>80</volume>:<fpage>1917</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/2002.8071917x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12162660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Use of metabolically active substances to substitute for antibiotics in finishing pigs</article-title>. <source>Korean J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>1999</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piao</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of supplementation of &#946;-mannanase in corn-soybean meal diets on performance and nutrient digestibility in growing pigs</article-title>. <source>Asian Australas J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>579</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>87</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5713/ajas.2012.12612</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25049826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4093390</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holen</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rambo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hilbrands</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of dietary zinc source and concentration on performance of growing-finishing pigs reared with reduced floor space</article-title>. <source>Prof Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>133</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15232/pas.2017-01684</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patience</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chipman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of the lysine: calorie ratio on the response to zinc supplementation in late finishing diets containing ractopamine hydrochloride</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>91</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pond</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of carbadox, copper, or Yucca shidigera extract on growth performance and visceral weight of young pigs</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>1993</year>) <volume>71</volume>:<fpage>2140</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/1993.7182140x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8376238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gipp</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elliot</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of dietary <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract and antibiotic on starter pig performance</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>1988</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>330</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheeke</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piacente</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oleszek</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anti-inflammatory and anti-arthritic effects of <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic>: a review</article-title>. <source>J Inflamm</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1186/1476-9255-3-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1440857</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16571135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gurbuz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balevi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurtoglu</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oznurlu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of adding yeast cell walls and <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract to diets of layer chicks</article-title>. <source>Br Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>625</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00071668.2011.619517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22029790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract improved growth performance and liver antioxidative function in broilers</article-title>. <source>Ital J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>677</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1828051X.2017.1302826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30702164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vangroenweghe</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poulsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thas</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Supplementation of a &#946;-mannanase enzyme reduces post-weaning diarrhea and antibiotic use in piglets on an alternative diet with additional soybean meal</article-title>. <source>Porc Health Manag</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40813-021-00191-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7798280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33431048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arsenault</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Latham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kogut</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in immune and metabolic gut response in broilers fed &#946;-mannanase in &#946;-mannan-containing diets</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>4307</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pex246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29053819</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in diarrhea, nutrients apparent digestibility, digestive enzyme activities of weaned piglets in response to chitosan-zinc chelate</article-title>. <source>Anim Sci J</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>87</volume>:<fpage>564</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/asj.12460</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26304729</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Upadhaya</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of dietary supplementation of modified zinc oxide on growth performance, nutrient digestibility, blood profiles, fecal microbial shedding and fecal score in weanling pigs</article-title>. <source>Anim Sci J</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>617</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/asj.12329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25473794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingale</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of energy levels of diet and &#223;-mannanase supplementation on growth performance, apparent total tract digestibility and blood metabolites in growing pigs</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>186</volume>:<fpage>64</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2013.08.008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedemann</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poulsen</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of dietary zinc and copper on digestive enzyme activity and intestinal morphology in weaned pigs</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>84</volume>:<fpage>3310</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/jas.2005-701</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17093223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lairon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Senft</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chautan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lafont</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Wheat bran and wheat germ: effect on digestion and intestinal absorption of dietary lipids in the rat</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr</source>. (<year>1989</year>) <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>1192</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>202</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ajcn/49.6.1192</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2543204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matusiak</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oleksy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borowski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Korczy&#324;ski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobrza&#324;ski</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The use of Yucca schidigera and microbial preparation for poultry manure deodorization and hygienization</article-title>. <source>J Environ Manag</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>170</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2016.01.007</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26797046</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindemann</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cromwell</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monegue</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inocencio</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of pharmacological levels of zinc as zinc oxide on fecal zinc and mineral excretion in weanling pigs</article-title>. <source>Prof Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>162</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15232/S1080-7446(15)31506-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of chelated copper and zinc supplementation on growth performance, nutrient digestibility, blood profiles, and fecal noxious gas emission in weanling pigs</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci Technol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>295</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>301</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5187/JAST.2013.55.4.295</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwag</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of feeding enzymes, probiotics or yucca powder on pig growth and odor-generating substances in feces</article-title>. <source>Korean J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>1996</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>58</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colina</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary manipulation to reduce aerial ammonia concentrations in nursery pig facilities</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2001</year>) <volume>79</volume>:<fpage>3096</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>103</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11811465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.2527/2001.79123096x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodall</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyerholtz</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of odor control compounds on urease activity in swine manure</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>1992</year>) <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>160</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of feeding diets containing an antibiotic, a probiotic, or yucca extract on growth and intestinal urease activity in broiler chicks</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>1997</year>) <volume>76</volume>:<fpage>381</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ps/76.2.381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9057222</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rowland</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plyler</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Yucca-schidigera extract effect on egg-production and house ammonia levels</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>1976</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>2086</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erdogan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erdogan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of different dietary levels of <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> powder on the performance, blood parameters and egg yolk cholesterol of laying quails</article-title>. <source>J Veterinary Med Ser A</source>. (<year>2003</year>) <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>14</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1439-0442.2003.00487.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12650503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saeed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arain</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naveed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alagawany</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Hack</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ezzat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> can mitigate ammonia emissions from manure and promote poultry health and production</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollut Res</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>35027</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-018-3546-1</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30368697</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rooke</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bland</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The acquisition of passive immunity in the new-born piglet</article-title>. <source>Livest Prod Sci</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>78</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0301-6226(02)00182-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodr&#237;guez-Arrioja</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Segal&#233;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calsamiglia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Resendes</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balasch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plana-Dur&#225;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dynamics of porcine circovirus type 2 infection in a herd of pigs with postweaning multisystemic wasting syndrome</article-title>. <source>Am J Vet Res</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>354</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/ajvr.2002.63.354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11911570</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sibila</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calsamiglia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Segal&#233;s</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Badiella</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Dimna</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Use of a polymerase chain reaction assay and an ELISA to monitor porcine circovirus type 2 infection in pigs from farms with and without postweaning multisystemic wasting syndrome</article-title>. <source>Am J Vet Res</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>88</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/ajvr.2004.65.88</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14719708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Summerfield</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruggli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Immune responses against classical swine fever virus: between ignorance and lunacy</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2015.00010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26664939</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4672165</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight-Jones</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rushton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The economic impacts of foot and mouth disease&#8211;what are they, how big are they and where do they occur?</article-title><source>Prev Vet Med</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>112</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.prevetmed.2013.07.013</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23958457</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3989032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suara</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crowe</surname><given-names>JE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of zinc salts on respiratory syncytial virus replication</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>783</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.48.3.783-790.2004</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14982765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC353050</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Overbeck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rink</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haase</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Modulating the immune response by oral zinc supplementation: a single approach for multiple diseases</article-title>. <source>Arch Immunol Ther Exp</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00005-008-0003-8</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18250973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7079749</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lodemann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bondzio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gefeller</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vahjen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aschenbach</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A high amount of dietary zinc changes the expression of zinc transporters and metallothionein in jejunal epithelial cells in vitro and in vivo but does not prevent zinc accumulation in jejunal tissue of piglets</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>143</volume>:<fpage>1205</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3945/jn.113.177881</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23761649</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khajuria</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suri</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qazi</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Immunological adjuvant effect of <italic toggle="yes">Boswellia serrata</italic> (BOS 2000) on specific antibody and cellular response to ovalbumin in mice</article-title>. <source>Int Immunopharmacol</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>968</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>75</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2011.02.011</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21371582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huntley</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patience</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of the effect of &#946;-mannanase supplementation and mannans on nursery pig growth performance and serum acute-phase protein concentrations</article-title>. <source>Can J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/cjas-2018-0248</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kar</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarma</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Medhi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nath</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of zinc on the humoral immune response of piglets after classical swine fever virus vaccination</article-title>. <source>Indian J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>83</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anti-foot-and-mouth disease virus effects of Chinese herbal kombucha in vivo</article-title>. <source>Braz J Microbiol</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>1245</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1517-838246420140701</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26691487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4704643</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Gestational zinc deficiency impairs humoral and cellular immune responses to hepatitis B vaccination in offspring mice</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e73461</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0073461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24069198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3775768</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qadri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahed</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamidur Rahman</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Supplementation with zinc, but not vitamin a, improves seroconversion to vibriocidal antibody in children given an oral cholera vaccine</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis</source>. (<year>2003</year>) <volume>187</volume>:<fpage>909</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/368132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12660937</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>