<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12128608</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12128608.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12128608</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12128608</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40458759</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2025.1563031</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Semiquantitative acid&#8211;base analysis in hypokalemic dogs with immune-mediated hemolytic anemia</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Philp</surname><given-names initials="HS">Helen S.</given-names></name><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2131620/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names initials="SE">Steven E.</given-names></name><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/438881/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/funding-acquisition/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hopper</surname><given-names initials="K">Kate</given-names></name><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/594850/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/funding-acquisition/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff><institution>Department of Veterinary Surgical and Radiological Sciences, School of Veterinary Medicine, University of California, Davis</institution>, <addr-line>Davis, CA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0004"><p>Edited by: Caroline Tonozzi, Mission Veterinary Partners, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0005"><p>Reviewed by: DoHyeon Yu, Gyeongsang National University, Republic of Korea</p><p>Suzy Gray, American College of Veterinary Internal Medicine, United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Helen S. Philp, <email>hsphilp@ucdavis.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">480746</issue-id><elocation-id>1563031</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>02</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-06-03 10:25:14.500"><day>03</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2025 Philp, Epstein and Hopper.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Philp, Epstein and Hopper</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-12-1563031.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="sec1"><title>Objective</title><p>To describe and compare the traditional and semiquantitative acid&#8211;base status of dogs with immune-mediated hemolytic anemia (IMHA) and hypokalemia to those with normokalemia.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Methods</title><p>Medical records of dogs with IMHA from a single institution over a 10-year period from January 1st, 2012 to December 31st, 2021 were retrospectively reviewed. Dogs were included if they met diagnostic criteria for IMHA based on the 2019 ACVIM consensus guidelines and had at least 1 blood potassium concentration measurement performed within 24&#8239;h of initial presentation. The dogs were divided into normokalemic and hypokalemic groups. Hypokalemia was categorized as mild (3&#8211;3.5&#8239;mEq/L [3&#8211;3.5 mmmol/L]), moderate (2&#8211;2.9&#8239;mEq/L [2&#8211;2.9&#8239;mmol/L]), or severe (&lt;2&#8239;mEq/L [&lt;2&#8239;mmol/L]). Population data, clinicopathologic data, and outcome were collected and recorded. Traditional and semiquantitative acid&#8211;base diagnoses were attributed to patients with sufficient data.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Results</title><p>305 client-owned dogs with IMHA met the inclusion criteria. 186 dogs (61.0%) were normokalemic and 119 (39.0%) were hypokalemic (blood potassium concentration &#8804; 3.5&#8239;mEq/L [&#8804; 3.5&#8239;mmol/L]) on presentation. The median blood potassium concentration in the hypokalemic group was 3.2&#8239;mEq/L (3.2&#8239;mmol/L) (interquartile range: 2.8&#8211;3.4&#8239;mEq/L [2.8&#8211;3.4&#8239;mmol/L]). Hypokalemia was mild in 78/119 (65.5%) dogs, moderate in 40/119 (33.6%) and severe in 1/119 (0.84%) cases. Metabolic acidosis was the most common traditional acid&#8211;base disorder identified in both normokalemic (26/82, 31.7%) and hypokalemic (44/92, 47.8%) dogs but the proportion was significantly higher in the hypokalemic group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.03). The semiquantitative approach identified acid&#8211;base abnormalities in 82/83 (98.8%) hypokalemic dogs. The most common abnormalities among the hypokalemic group were an unmeasured ion effect (74/83, 89.2%) and an alkalotic albumin effect (69/83, 83.1%). In the normokalemic group, the semiquantitative approach identified acid&#8211;base abnormalities in 62/63 (98.4%) dogs with unmeasured ions (55/63, 87.3%) and an alkalotic albumin effect (42/63, 66.7%) being the most common. Survival to discharge was significantly lower in the hypokalemic dogs (85/119, 71.4%) compared to the normokalemic population (163/186, 87.6%) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.02).</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Hypokalemia is common in dogs with IMHA within the first 24&#8239;h of presentation and is associated with a variety of acid&#8211;base abnormalities. Hypokalemic dogs with IMHA appear more likely to develop metabolic acidosis and less likely to survive to hospital discharge.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>autoimmune</kwd><kwd>canine</kwd><kwd>electrolyte</kwd><kwd>potassium</kwd><kwd>traditional</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that no financial support was received for the research and/or publication of this article.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="54"/><page-count count="8"/><word-count count="6382"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Veterinary Emergency and Critical Care Medicine</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec5"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Immune-mediated hemolytic anemia (IMHA) results from a spontaneous immune response directed against antigens expressed on the cell surface of erythrocytes and is one of the most common autoimmune diseases of dogs (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Mortality ranges from 7 to 50%, and IMHA is frequently associated with adverse sequelae including hypercoagulability, systemic inflammation, and organ dysfunction (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2&#8211;16</xref>).</p><p>Previous studies have investigated associations between survival and various hematologic and biochemical parameters which might have prognostic value (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2&#8211;7</xref>, <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Hypokalemia has been documented in dogs with IMHA and was associated with increased mortality in 2 retrospective studies (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), while other studies found no influence of blood potassium concentration on outcome (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). An association between hypokalemia and increased mortality has already been established in a more general population of dogs presenting to an emergency room, as well as in people with acute medical conditions and the critically ill (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20&#8211;22</xref>). Hypokalemia may have a direct causal relationship with mortality through detrimental effects on the cardiovascular system, nerve impulse conduction, muscle function and/or renal function (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Alternatively, hypokalemia may simply represent a nonspecific finding due to the stress of illness and associated epinephrine release (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>).</p><p>The cause(s) of hypokalemia in dogs with IMHA is unknown. One case report attributed hypokalemia to distal renal tubular acidosis in 3 dogs with IMHA (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). However, the acid&#8211;base status of a larger population of dogs with IMHA has not been further investigated to the authors&#8217; knowledge and may help to determine if renal tubular acidosis is a common causative factor of hypokalemia. Hypokalemia is frequently accompanied by acid&#8211;base disturbances due to effects on renal acid handling, aldosterone release, and the reciprocal relationship of potassium with hydrogen ions and anions such as bicarbonate and chloride (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Semiquantitiative acid&#8211;base analysis builds on the traditional approach by consideration of some individual contributors to complex acid&#8211;base disorders (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). An improved understanding of the acid&#8211;base abnormalities in hypokalemic dogs with IMHA may offer some insight into the underlying etiology, and aid clinicians in guiding therapy for this patient population.</p><p>The aim of this retrospective study was to describe a population of dogs with IMHA and hypokalemia on presentation and to characterize their traditional and semiquantitative acid&#8211;base status and associated outcome in an effort to improve understanding of the potential underlying etiologic processes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec6"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec7"><label>2.1</label><title>Case selection</title><p>A computerized search of the medical records database at the University of California Davis, William R. Pritchard Veterinary Medical Teaching Hospital was conducted to identify dogs that were diagnosed with IMHA based on their clinical diagnosis in the medical record from January 2012 through December 2021. The case records were reviewed to verify the clinical diagnosis of IMHA. Diagnostic criteria for IMHA were based on the 2019 ACVIM consensus guidelines and required the combination of anemia, at least 2 signs of immune-mediated destruction, and at least 1 sign of hemolysis to confirm IMHA (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Evidence of immune-mediated destruction included the combination of at least 2 of the following: spherocytes on blood smear evaluation, positive slide agglutination test and/or positive direct antiglobulin test. Alternatively, persistently positive slide agglutination after washing satisfied this criteria. Signs of hemolysis included at least one of the following: hyperbilirubinemia in the absence of an alternate hepatic or post-hepatic cause, hemoglobinemia, hemoglobinuria or erythrocyte ghosts on blood smear exam. Cases were excluded if these diagnostic criteria were not met. Repeat presentations due to persistence or recurrence of IMHA in the same patient were treated as a single case and only the first visit was included. Patients were diagnosed with primary IMHA if they had undergone a reasonable diagnostic workup to exclude an underlying trigger. Typical investigations included complete blood count, serum biochemistry, thoracic and abdominal imaging, PCR testing for tick-borne infections, echocardiography for vegetative lesions and urine culture. Cases without at least 1 blood potassium concentration measurement performed within 24&#8239;h of initial presentation were excluded. Population data including age, sex, reproductive status, bodyweight, breed, and outcome were recorded. Outcome was defined as survival to discharge or non-survival. Non-survivors included those patients that were euthanized or died in hospital. Clinicopathologic data collected included blood gas panels and serum biochemistry. The earliest measurement was utilized in cases where multiple measurements were collected.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><label>2.2</label><title>Blood potassium concentration</title><p>The study included plasma potassium concentrations measured on a point-of-care analyzer<xref rid="fn0001" ref-type="fn">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref> and serum potassium concentrations measured as part of a serum biochemistry profile through a reference laboratory.<xref rid="fn0002" ref-type="fn">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref> For the purpose of this study, the term &#8216;blood potassium concentration&#8217; abbreviated as [K<sup>+</sup>] will be used to describe all sample results for simplicity. The earliest measured [K<sup>+</sup>] following presentation was included for analysis. If both plasma and serum [K<sup>+</sup>] were measured concurrently, the point of care value was used to allow evaluation of acid&#8211;base and electrolyte abnormalities. Hypokalemia was categorized as mild (3&#8211;3.5&#8239;mEq/L [3&#8211;3.5 mmmol/L]), moderate (2&#8211;2.9&#8239;mEq/L [2&#8211;2.9&#8239;mmol/L]), or severe (&lt;2&#8239;mEq/L [&lt;2&#8239;mmol/L]) based on a previous study of dyskalemia in dogs and cats (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><label>2.3</label><title>Acid&#8211;base analysis</title><p>Traditional and semiquantitative acid&#8211;base diagnoses were attributed to each patient where the relevant data was available. Traditional acid&#8211;base analysis was based on pH, PCO<sub>2,</sub> standardized base excess, and anion gap and required a blood gas panel for analysis (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). The reference intervals for anion gap, venous pH, standardized base excess, and pCO<sub>2</sub> from a previous publication were used (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>).</p><p>Semiquantitative acid&#8211;base analysis was based on standardized base excess and the concentrations of sodium, chloride, and plasma lactate from the point of care panel and serum albumin and phosphate measured on a biochemistry panel. Serum albumin and phosphate concentrations were required to be measured on a chemistry analyzer (see text footnote 2) within 24&#8239;h of the venous blood gas measurement for this analysis with institutional reference intervals used. Calculated semiquantitative acid&#8211;base variables were derived from measured acid&#8211;base, electrolyte, and metabolite values using previously established equations (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Bicarbonate concentration and standard base excess were calculated by the blood gas analyzer using the Henderson&#8211;Hasselbalch and van Slyke equations, respectively. The value for CO<sub>2</sub> solubility in plasma used by the blood gas machine was 0.03&#8239;mmol/L/mmHg. The mid-normal values utilized in the semiquantitative formulae were determined as the central values of the appropriate reference interval for the machine utilized.</p></sec><sec id="sec10"><label>2.4</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Statistics were performed using commercially available software.<xref rid="fn0003" ref-type="fn">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref> Numerical data were assessed for normality with the Shapiro&#8211;Wilk test and QQ plots. Continuous parametric data were described as mean (&#177; standard deviation) and non-parametric data as median (25th-75th percentile). A Fisher&#8217;s exact test was performed to evaluate the relationship between categorical variables. Groups were compared with the Wilcoxon rank sum test. A <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value &lt; 0.05 was considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec11"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec12"><label>3.1</label><title>IMHA population</title><p>A total of 305 dogs satisfied the diagnostic criteria for IMHA. The mean age of the entire population was 7.1 (&#177;3.2) years. The predominant breeds were mixed breeds (106/305, 34.8%), chihuahuas (12/305, 3.9%), and dachshunds (12/305, 3.9%). In 2 dogs, sex was not recorded. Among the remaining 303 dogs, there were 178/303 (58.7%) females (18 intact) and 125/303 (41.3%) males (14 intact). In 119 dogs, bodyweight was not captured by the computerized search. In the remaining dogs, median bodyweight was 14.8 (6.9&#8211;26.5) kg. Of the 305 dogs with IMHA, 186 (61.0%) were normokalemic and 119 (39.0%) were hypokalemic.</p></sec><sec id="sec13"><label>3.2</label><title>Hypokalemic population</title><p>Among the 119 hypokalemic dogs, median [K<sup>+</sup>] was 3.2&#8239;mEq/L (3.2&#8239;mmol/L), (2.8&#8211;3.4&#8239;mEq/L [2.8&#8211;3.4&#8239;mmol/L]). Hypokalemia was mild in 78/119 (65.5%) dogs, moderate in 40/119 (33.6%) and severe in 1/119 (0.84%) cases. The mean age of the hypokalemic population was 6.5 (&#177;3.1) years. The predominant breeds were mixed breeds (45/119, 37.8.%), chihuahuas (6/119, 5.0%), and poodles (6/119, 5.0%). Tere were 76/119 (63.9%) females (9 intact) and 43/119 (36.1%) males (7 intact). In 3 dogs, bodyweight was not recorded. In the remaining 116 dogs, median bodyweight was 13.3 (6.3&#8211;26.4) kg. Among the 119 dogs, 93 (78.2%) were diagnosed with primary IMHA, 5/119 (4.2%) were diagnosed with secondary IMHA and in the remaining 21/119 (17.6%) dogs definitive categorization was not possible. The most commonly reported comorbidities among the hypokalemic population included hepatopathy (18/119, 15.1%), myxomatous mitral valve disease (16/119, 13.4%), and acute kidney injury (7/119, 5.9%).</p></sec><sec id="sec14"><label>3.3</label><title>Outcome</title><p>There was a significant difference in outcome between groups with 85/119 (71.4%) hypokalemic dogs and 163/186 (87.6%) normokalemic dogs surviving to discharge (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.02).</p></sec><sec id="sec15"><label>3.4</label><title>Total serum magnesium concentration</title><p>Total serum magnesium concentration was measured in 30/119 (25.2%) hypokalemic dogs with a mean of 2.23 (&#177;0.42) mg/dL (0.92 [&#177;0.17] mmol/L). Total serum magnesium concentration was measured in 21/186 (11.3%) normokalemic dogs with a median of 2.1 (1.9&#8211;2.2) mg/dL (0.86 [0.78&#8211;0.91] mmol/L). There was no significant difference between groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.45).</p></sec><sec id="sec16"><label>3.5</label><title>Traditional acid&#8211;base analysis</title><p>Blood gas analysis was available in 174/305 (57.0%) of the total population including 92/119 (77.3%) hypokalemic dogs and 82/186 (44.1%) normokalemic dogs. Traditional acid&#8211;base values for the whole population are summarized in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Traditional acid&#8211;base analysis in 174 dogs with immune-mediated hemolytic anemia based on blood gas evaluation within 24&#8239;h of presentation and subdivided into hypokalemic and normokalemic cases.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acid&#8211;base diagnosis</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 hypokalemic dogs<break/><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82 normokalemic dogs<break/><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Normal acid&#8211;base balance</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (39.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (58.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Simple disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolic acidosis with normal anion gap</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (12.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (9.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolic alkalosis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory acidosis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (2.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory alkalosis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Mixed disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolic acidosis with normal anion gap and respiratory acidosis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (3.3)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (6.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolic acidosis with normal anion gap and respiratory alkalosis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (25.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (14.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolic acidosis with increased anion gap and respiratory alkalosis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (9.8)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolic alkalosis and respiratory acidosis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolic alkalosis and respiratory alkalosis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (12.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (4.9)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Among the 92 hypokalemic dogs with blood gas analysis available, 36/92 (39.1%) had a normal traditional acid&#8211;base status. Metabolic acidosis was the most common disorder identified, occurring in 44/92 (47.8%) of cases when both primary and mixed disorders were considered. The majority of cases with a metabolic acidosis were associated with a normal anion gap (35/44, 79.5%). Twelve of the 92 patients (13.0%) had a metabolic alkalosis.</p><p>Of the 186 normokalemic dogs with IMHA, blood gas analysis was available in 82 cases (44.1%). A normal traditional acid&#8211;base status was found in 48/82 (58.5%). When both primary and mixed disorders are considered, metabolic acidosis was the most common disorder, occurring in 26/82 (31.7%) of dogs. Most cases of metabolic acidosis were associated with a normal anion gap (25/26, 96.2%). Five dogs had a metabolic alkalosis (5/82, 6.1%) while respiratory acidosis was found in 7 cases (7/82, 8.5%) and respiratory alkalosis was identified in 18 patients (18/82, 22.0%).</p><p>There was no significant difference in the proportion of dogs with a metabolic alkalosis in the hypokalemic population when compared to those with normokalemia (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.2) while the proportion of patients with a metabolic acidosis was higher in the hypokalemic group (47.8% vs. 31.7% [<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;0.03]).</p></sec><sec id="sec17"><label>3.6</label><title>Semiquantitative acid&#8211;base analysis</title><p>Both venous blood gas analysis and serum biochemistry results were available in 146/305 (47.9%) of the total population including 83/119 (69.7%) hypokalemic dogs and 63/186 (33.9%) normokalemic dogs. Acid&#8211;base, electrolyte and plasma lactate values for both groups are summarized in <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and specific acid&#8211;base disorders are listed in <xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Acid&#8211;base, electrolyte, and plasma lactate values in 146 dogs with immune-mediated hemolytic anemia measured within 24&#8239;h of presentation and subdivided into hypokalemic and normokalemic cases.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Hypokalemic (83 dogs)</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Normokalemic (63 dogs)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter (Reference range)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median (25th-75th percentile) in conventional units</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median (25th-75th percentile) in SI units</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median (25th-75th percentile) in conventional units</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median (25th-75th percentile) in SI units</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sodium (143&#8211;151&#8239;mEq/L; 143&#8211;151&#8239;mmol/L)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">149 (146&#8211;151.5) mEq/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">149 (146&#8211;151.5) mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148 (146&#8211;150.5) mEq/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148 (146&#8211;150.5) mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potassium (3.6&#8211;4.8&#8239;mEq/L; 3.6&#8211;4.8&#8239;mmol/L)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2 (2.85&#8211;3.35) mEq/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2 (2.85&#8211;3.35) mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 (3.7&#8211;4.2) mEq/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 (3.7&#8211;4.2) mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloride (108&#8211;116&#8239;mEq/L; 108&#8211;116&#8239;mmol/L)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120 (114.5&#8211;123.5) mEq/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120 (114.5&#8211;123.5) mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117 (114&#8211;121) mEq/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117 (114&#8211;121) mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corrected chloride (108&#8211;116&#8239;mEq/L; 108&#8211;116&#8239;mmol/L)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116.8 (113.9&#8211;119.1) mEq/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116.8 (113.9&#8211;119.1) mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116.2 (113.4&#8211;117.2) mEq/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116.2 (113.4&#8211;117.2) mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Albumin (3.4&#8211;4.3&#8239;g/dL; 34&#8211;43&#8239;g/L)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (2.7&#8211;3.25) g/dL</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (27&#8211;32.5) g/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1 (2.85&#8211;3.45) g/dL</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (28.5&#8211;34.5) g/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phosphorus (2.6&#8211;5.2&#8239;mg/dL; 0.84&#8211;1.68&#8239;mmol/L)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9 (3.05&#8211;4.5) mg/dL</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26 (0.98&#8211;1.45) mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.2 (3.45&#8211;5.1) mg/dL</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 (1.11&#8211;1.65) mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH (7.361&#8211;7.444)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.382 (7.343&#8211;7.412)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.382 (7.343&#8211;7.412)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.375 (7.342&#8211;7.406)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.375 (7.342&#8211;7.406)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PvCO<sub>2</sub> (27.1&#8211;38.7&#8239;mmHg)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.1 (26.5&#8211;34.75) mmHg</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.1 (26.5&#8211;34.75) mmHg</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (30.2&#8211;38.05) mmHg</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (30.2&#8211;38.05) mmHg</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bicarbonate (17.2&#8211;23.0&#8239;mEq/L; 17.2&#8211;23.0&#8239;mmol/L)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.7 (14.8&#8211;19.65) mEq/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.7 (14.8&#8211;19.65) mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.6 (16.65&#8211;20.65) mEq/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.6 (16.65&#8211;20.65) mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standardized base excess (&#8722;5.5 &#8211; &#8722;0.9&#8239;mEq/L; &#8722;5.5 &#8211; &#8722;0.9&#8239;mmol/L)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;6.4 (&#8722;9.7&#8211;&#8722;4.65) mEq/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;6.4 (&#8722;9.7&#8211;&#8722;4.65) mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;5.6 (&#8722;7.75&#8211;&#8722;3.45) mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;5.6 (&#8722;7.75&#8211;&#8722;3.45) mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lactate (&lt;22.5&#8239;mg/dL; &lt; 2.5&#8239;mmol/L)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.7 (15.3&#8211;31.1) mg/dL</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3 (1.7&#8211;3.45) mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9 (15.76&#8211;30.18) mg/dL</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1 (1.75&#8211;3.35) mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anion gap (12&#8211;21&#8239;mEq/L; 12&#8211;21&#8239;mmol/L)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5 (13.2&#8211;17.75) mEq/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5 (13.2&#8211;17.75) mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5 (14&#8211;18.9) mEq/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5 (14&#8211;18.9) mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Free water effect</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 (0&#8211;1.38) mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 (0&#8211;1.125) mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloride effect</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;5.8 (&#8722;8.1&#8211;&#8722;2.9) mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;5.2 (&#8722;6.2&#8211;&#8722;2.4) mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Albumin effect</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.33 (2.41&#8211;4.44) mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.96 (1.665&#8211;3.885) mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phosphorus effect</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (&#8722;0.35&#8211;0.49) mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.174 (&#8722;0.696&#8211;0.261) mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lactate effect</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;2.3 (&#8722;3.5&#8211;&#8722;1.7) mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;2.1 (&#8722;3.35&#8211;&#8722;1.75)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sum of effects</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;3.80 (&#8722;7.51 to &#8722;1.58) mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;3.77 (&#8722;6.25&#8211;&#8722;1.42) mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unmeasured ions</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;2.31 (&#8722;4.90&#8211;&#8722;0.68) mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.78 (&#8722;3.58&#8211;&#8722;0.136) mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unmeasured anions</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;3.8 (&#8722;5.3&#8211;&#8722;2.0) mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.8 (&#8722;4.3&#8211;&#8722;1.7) mmol/L</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unmeasured cations</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.95&#8211;2.9) mmol/L</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 (0.93&#8211;3.3) mmol/L</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Semiquantitative acid&#8211;base analysis in 146 dogs with immune-mediated hemolytic anemia based on venous blood gas and serum biochemical evaluation within 24&#8239;h of presentation and subdivided into hypokalemic and normokalemic cases.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolic acid&#8211;base diagnosis</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 Hypokalemic dogs<break/><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 Normokalemic dogs<break/><italic toggle="yes">N</italic> (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">One or more acidotic processes</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79 (95.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (95.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">One or more alkalotic processes</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76 (91.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (84.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Both alkalotic and acidotic processes</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (88.0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (81.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dilutional acidosis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contraction alkalosis</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (34.9)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (25.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acidotic chloride effect</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (61.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (50.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alkalotic chloride effect</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (1.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acidotic albumin effect</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alkalotic albumin effect</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 (83.1)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 (66.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acidotic phosphate effect</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (8.4)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (11.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acidosis with hyperlactatemia</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (56.6)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (55.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unmeasured ions</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (89.2)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55 (87.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unmeasured anions</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (74.7)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (68.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unmeasured cations</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (14.5)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (19.0)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The semiquantitative approach identified acid&#8211;base abnormalities in 82/83 (98.8%) hypokalemic dogs. One or more acidotic processes were identified in 79/83 (95.2%) dogs while 76/83 (91.6%) dogs had one or more alkalotic processes. The most common abnormalities among the hypokalemic group were an unmeasured ion effect (74/83, 89.2%), alkalotic albumin effect (69/83, 83.1%), acidotic chloride effect (51/83, 61.4%), and acidosis with hyperlactatemia (47/83, 56.6%). Unmeasured anions (62/83, 74.7%) were more frequent than unmeasured cations (12/83, 14.5%).</p><p>The semiquantitative approach identified acid&#8211;base abnormalities in 62/63 (98.4%) normokalemic dogs. One or more acidotic processes were identified in 60/63 (95.2%) dogs while 53/63 (84.1%) dogs had one or more alkalotic processes. The most common abnormalities were unmeasured ions (55/63, 87.3%), an alkalotic albumin effect (42/63, 66.7%), acidosis with hyperlactatemia (35/63, 55.6%), and an acidotic chloride effect (32/63, 50.8%). Unmeasured anions (43/63, 68.3%) were more frequent than unmeasured cations (12/63, 19.0%).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec18"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>Hypokalemia was relatively common within the first 24&#8239;h of presentation in this population of dogs with IMHA, with a prevalence of 39.0%. This is similar to a previous report of hypokalemia in dogs with IMHA which found that 42% of cases had a [K<sup>+</sup>]&#8239;&lt;&#8239;3.6&#8239;mEq/L (&lt; 3.6&#8239;mmol/L) on presentation (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). In most of the dogs presenting with hypokalemia in our study population, the degree of hypokalemia was mild. The study population signalment as a whole was similar to that previously reported with a mean age of 6.5&#8239;years and a predominance of females (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10&#8211;12</xref>, <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14&#8211;16</xref>, <xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>).</p><p>In this study, 85/119 (71.4%) hypokalemic dogs and 163/186 (87.6%) normokalemic dogs survived to discharge. These appear broadly similar to those previously reported in dogs with IMHA which range from 44 to 93% depending on the timeline evaluated (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5&#8211;8</xref>, <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10&#8211;17</xref>, <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). In agreement with two previous studies of dogs with IMHA (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), our study found a significant difference in outcome between dogs with normokalemia and those with hypokalemia on presentation. There are a number of potential adverse effects of hypokalemia. Potassium is essential for maintaining normal cell membrane potential, nerve impulse transmission, and muscle function. Hypokalemia leads to enhanced neuromuscular excitability via increased permeability of sodium channels in the cell membrane. Possible clinical manifestations include muscle cramps, gastrointestinal ileus, rhabdomyolysis, paralysis and even respiratory failure in severe cases (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Hypokalemia may promote diastolic cardiac dysfunction as well as increase the risk of arrhythmias by enhancing automaticity and delaying repolarization (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Endothelial dysfunction, and increased rates of thrombosis and platelet aggregation have also been described (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Additional adverse effects of hypokalemia may relate to the vasoactive role of potassium. For example, release of potassium from skeletal muscle enhances vasodilation and perfusion during exercise. In experimental murine models, hypokalemia has been associated with alterations in vasoactive mediators which favor renal vasoconstriction and could theoretically lead to tubular damage via intrarenal ischemia (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34&#8211;36</xref>). Over time, hypokalemia can lead to both structural and functional changes in the kidneys resulting in reduced urine concentrating ability, increased ammoniagenesis, altered sodium reabsorption, and enhanced bicarbonate reabsorption. Tubulointerstitial lesions have been reported in people and cats with chronic hypokalemia (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Despite the potential negative consequences of hypokalemia, it is also possible that hypokalemia in dogs with IMHA simply represents a marker of disease severity rather than playing any direct pathophysiologic role (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>).</p><p>Possible causes of hypokalemia in dogs with IMHA include stress of illness with associated cortisol and/or epinephrine release, inappetence, intravenous fluid therapy, gastrointestinal loss through vomiting and/or diarrhea, renal losses secondary to intrinsic kidney disease, medications including corticosteroids, endocrine disorders and hypomagnesemia (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38&#8211;44</xref>). Total serum magnesium concentration did not differ between groups, making hypomagnesemia a less likely contributor to the development of hypokalemia, but given the small population in which serum magnesium concentration was measured in this study a definitive conclusion cannot be made. Ideally, ionized magnesium would have been measured. Unfortunately, the retrospective nature of this study limits our ability to determine the etiology of hypokalemia and the precise mechanisms behind hypokalemia in these dogs remain speculative. Future prospective studies with measurement of plasma cortisol, aldosterone, and evaluation of urinary potassium excretion would improve understanding of hypokalemia in dogs with IMHA. The potential for treatment to modify any association between [K<sup>+</sup>] and mortality over time and thus present an opportunity for intervention is also worthy of further exploration. Acid&#8211;base changes can influence [K<sup>+</sup>]. For example, alkalemia promotes intracellular translocation and hypokalemia (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). However, the proportion of metabolic alkalosis did not differ between the normokalemic and hypokalemic groups and as such is unlikely a significant contributor to hypokalemia in the dogs in this study. Normal anion gap metabolic acidosis was the most common acid&#8211;base abnormality and was more frequent in the hypokalemic group. Normal anion gap metabolic acidosis is common in small animal patients and may have been caused by bicarbonate loss via the kidney or gastrointestinal tract (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). One possible cause of a normal anion gap metabolic acidosis is distal renal tubular acidosis which has been documented in 3 dogs with IMHA, all of which were hypokalemic (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Distal renal tubular acidosis results from inability of the renal tubules to excrete hydrogen ions and has been linked with both autoimmune disease and hemolytic anemia in people (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46&#8211;50</xref>). Interestingly, potassium depletion has also been observed to cause a metabolic acidosis in canine experimental studies which is reversible on potassium repletion (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). The cause appears to be a distal renal tubular acidification defect and may involve decreased aldosterone release (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). Unfortunately, given the retrospective nature of this study it was not possible to further evaluate these potential mechanisms.</p><p>Semiquantitative acid&#8211;base analysis identified the presence of multifactorial metabolic acid&#8211;base abnormalities in both the normokalemic and hypokalemic populations. The most common acid&#8211;base influences identified in the hypokalemic group were an unmeasured ion effect, an alkalotic albumin effect and acidotic processes associated with hyperchloremia and hyperlactatemia. Unmeasured anions were more frequent than unmeasured cations. Although the semiquantitative approach identified unmeasured anions frequently in this population, the quantity present was relatively small. The value for unmeasured ions as determined by the semi-quantitative approach is the result of multiple calculations, making it prone to compounded error and the clinical relevance of this parameter has not been validated. Possible causes of unmeasured anions such as propylene glycol or d-lactate could not be evaluated in this retrospective study (<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Hypoalbuminemia has been reported previously in dogs with IMHA and attributed to an acute phase response, impaired hepatic function, and/or hemorrhage (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Hypoalbuminemia may obscure the presence of unmeasured acids and an increased anion gap on traditional acid&#8211;base analysis. Hyperchloremia may reflect bicarbonate losing processes such as renal tubular acidosis or gastrointestinal losses. Hyperlactatemia is well described in dogs with IMHA and was documented in 84% of patients on admission in one study (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>).</p><p>Understanding these individual processes may allow a more tailored treatment plan. For example, due to the frequent occurrence of unmeasured acids and hyperchloremia, fluid therapy using a balanced isotonic crystalloid solution may be more suitable than 0.9% saline for hypokalemic dogs with IMHA. This approach may help to prevent the acidifying and renal vasoactive effects associated with excessive chloride, especially when hypokalemia is managed with intravenous potassium chloride supplementation (<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>).</p><p>This study has a number of limitations, many of which are inherent to its retrospective nature. Our overall number of cases is likely an underestimation of the true prevalence of hypokalemia in dogs with IMHA. We only included cases where a diagnosis of IMHA was confirmed or supported, excluding many cases where the history, clinical findings and histopathology were very suggestive of IMHA. Measurement of [K<sup>+</sup>] and blood gas analysis within 24&#8239;h of presentation to the hospital were only performed within a subset of patients at the discretion of the primary clinician. It is possible that clinicians are more likely to measure electrolytes and perform blood gas analysis in animals considered to have more severe disease leading to selection bias and overestimation of theassociation between hypokalemia and mortality. In addition, serum chemistry and blood gas analysis were performed in a greater proportion of hypokalemic dogs than normokalemic dogs which may have further affected our findings. Future research in a randomly selected population with standardized protocols for measurement of [K<sup>+</sup>], serum chemistry, and acid&#8211;base analysis is necessary to confirm the relationship between hypokalemia and patient outcomes.</p><p>In order to better understand the potential causes of hypokalemia in this population, it would also have been ideal to measure urine pH and electrolytes at the time of blood gas analysis in all patients. Finally, blood gas and serum chemistry panels were not collected at the same time in each patient and some patients may have received treatment prior to blood sampling. Our aim was to limit the effect of this variation by only including dogs with sampling performed within the first 24&#8239;h of presentation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec19"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, hypokalemia is common in dogs presenting with IMHA and is associated with a variety of acid&#8211;base abnormalities for which the etiology is likely multifactorial. These results suggest that hypokalemic dogs with IMHA may be more likely to develop metabolic acidosis and may be less likely to survive to hospital discharge although a direct causative effect cannot be confirmed. Future prospective studies are needed to further evaluate the possible underlying causes and to determine if this effect is modified with treatment.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="fn0001"><p><sup>1</sup>ABL 815, Radiometer Medical A/S, Copenhagen, Denmark.</p></fn><fn id="fn0002"><p><sup>2</sup>Chemistry analyzer, Hitachi 917, Roche Diagnostics, Indianapolis, IN.</p></fn><fn id="fn0003"><p><sup>3</sup>Graph Pad Prism v 8.0, La Jolla, CA.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec20"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article may be made available by the authors on request. Requests to access the datasets should be directed to HP, <email>hsphilp@ucdavis.edu</email>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="sec21"><title>Author contributions</title><p>HP: Writing &#8211; original draft, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. SE: Data curation, Formal analysis, Funding acquisition, Methodology, Supervision, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. KH: Conceptualization, Funding acquisition, Methodology, Supervision, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec23"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ai-statement" id="sec24"><title>Generative AI statement</title><p>The authors declare that no Gen AI was used in the creation of this manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec25"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swann</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skelly</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Systematic review of prognostic factors for mortality in dogs with immune-mediated hemolytic Anemia</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.12514</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25586014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4858088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goggs</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Bella</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Predicting outcome in dogs with primary immune-mediated hemolytic Anemia: results of a multicenter case registry</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>1603</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.13642</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26473338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4864895</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishihara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Setoguchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of prognostic factors and establishment of a prognostic scoring system for canine primary immune-mediated hemolytic Anemia</article-title>. <source>J Vet Med Sci</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>72</volume>:<fpage>465</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.09-0283</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20009421</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Piek</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Canine idiopathic immune-mediated haemolytic anaemia: a review with recommendations for future research</article-title>. <source>Vet Q</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01652176.2011.604979</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22029883</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alaimo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Feo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lubas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gavazza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Utility and prognostic significance of leukocyte ratios in dogs with primary immune-mediated hemolytic Anemia</article-title>. <source>Vet Res Commun</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>305</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11259-022-09935-2</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35553339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holahan</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drobatz</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Retrospective study: the association of blood lactate concentration with outcome in dogs with idiopathic immune-mediated hemolytic anemia: 173 cases (2003&#8211;2006)</article-title>. <source>J Vet Emerg Crit Care</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>413</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1476-4431.2010.00551.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20731807</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinkle</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Center</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Randolph</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erb</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of prognostic factors, survival rates, and treatment protocols for immune-mediated hemolytic anemia in dogs: 151 cases (1993&#8211;2002)</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>226</volume>:<fpage>1869</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/javma.2005.226.1869</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15934255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reimer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Troy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warnick</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Immune-mediated hemolytic anemia: 70 cases (1988-1996)</article-title>. <source>J Am Anim Hosp Assoc</source>. (<year>1999</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>384</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5326/15473317-35-5-384</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10493413</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panciera</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prognostic factors for mortality and thromboembolism in canine immune-mediated hemolytic Anemia: a retrospective study of 72 dogs</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>504</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1892/0891-6640(2002)016&amp;#x0003c;0504:pffmat&amp;#x0003e;2.3.co;2</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12322697</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ridyard</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Urinary 11-dehydrothromboxane B concentrations in 20 dogs with primary immune-mediated hemolytic anemia</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>86</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>96</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.16322</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34859495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8783321</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duclos</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bail&#233;n</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Boedec</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuq</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical presentation, outcome and prognostic factors in dogs with immune-mediated haemolytic anaemia: a retrospective single-Centre study of 104 cases in Ireland (2002&#8211;2020)</article-title>. <source>Ir Vet J</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13620-024-00277-w</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39054564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11270767</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agnoli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tumbarello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasylyeva</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selva Codd&#232;</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monari</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gruarin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Methylprednisolone alone or combined with cyclosporine or mycophenolate mofetil for the treatment of immune-mediated hemolytic anemia in dogs, a prospective study</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>2480</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.17122</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38961558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11423485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Creevy</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Treatment of canine idiopathic immune-mediated haemolytic anaemia with mycophenolate mofetil and glucocorticoids: 30 cases (2007 to 2011)</article-title>. <source>J Small Anim Pract</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>399</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>404</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsap.12107</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23879827</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McAlees</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Immune-mediated haemolytic anaemia in 110 dogs in Victoria, Australia</article-title>. <source>Aust Vet J</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1751-0813.2009.00537.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20148823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zoia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerou-Ferriani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drigo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caldin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Case-control study of plasma mean platelet component concentration and survival analysis for dogs with immune-mediated hemolytic anemia</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>252</volume>:<fpage>1384</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/javma.252.11.1384</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29772969</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mix</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wills</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mackin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Retrospective analysis of immunosuppressive and anti-thrombotic protocols in nonassociative immune mediated hemolytic anemia in dogs</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>528</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.16652</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36809664</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10061171</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Piek</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Junius</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schrauwen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slappendel</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teske</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Idiopathic immune-mediated hemolytic Anemia: treatment outcome and prognostic factors in 149 dogs</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>366</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-1676.2008.0060.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18346140</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thielemann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). Primary immune-mediated hemolytic anemia in dogs, a retrospective study (January 2003 - December 2011). Available online at: . (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.cabdirect.org/cabdirect/abstract/20163153297?q=((immune)+AND+(mediated)+AND+(hemolytic)+AND+(anemia)+AND+(hypokalemia))" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cabdirect.org/cabdirect/abstract/20163153297?q=((immune)+AND+(mediated)+AND+(hemolytic)+AND+(anemia)+AND+(hypokalemia))</ext-link>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weingart</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thielemann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kohn</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Primary immune-mediated haemolytic anaemia: a retrospective long-term study in 61 dogs</article-title>. <source>Aust Vet J</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>97</volume>:<fpage>483</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/avj.12875</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31454853</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brabrand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vinholt</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lassen</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hypokalemia in acute medical patients: risk factors and prognosis</article-title>. <source>Am J Med</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>128</volume>:<fpage>60</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>67.e1</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjmed.2014.07.022</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25107385</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouadma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mankikian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Darmon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of dyskalemia at admission and early dyskalemia correction on survival and cardiac events of critically ill patients</article-title>. <source>Crit Care</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>415</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13054-019-2679-z</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31856891</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6921444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoehne</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hopper</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Retrospective evaluation of the severity of and prognosis associated with potassium abnormalities in dogs and cats presenting to an emergency room (January 2014&#8211;august 2015): 2441 cases</article-title>. <source>J Vet Emerg Crit Care</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>653</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vec.12889</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31482659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Post</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Clinical physiology of Acid-Base and electrolyte disorders</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill Education</publisher-name> (<year>2001</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DiBartola</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Autran De Morais</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Disorders of potassium: hypokalemia and hyperkalemia</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>DiBartola</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group>, editor. <source>Fluid, electrolyte, and Acid-Base disorders in small animal practice</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>W.B. Saunders</publisher-name> (<year>2012</year>). <fpage>92</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>119</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shearer</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boudreau</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holowaychuk</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Distal renal tubular acidosis and immune-mediated hemolytic Anemia in 3 dogs</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>1284</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-1676.2009.0406.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19909430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halperin</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hypokalemia: a practical approach to diagnosis and its genetic basis</article-title>. <source>Curr Med Chem</source>. <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1551</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/092986707780831050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17584063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hopper</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haskins</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A case-based review of a simplified quantitative approach to acid-base analysis</article-title>. <source>J Vet Emerg Crit Care</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>467</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>76</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1476-4431.2008.00344.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garden</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mexas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeffery</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blois</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>ACVIM consensus statement on the diagnosis of immune-mediated hemolytic anemia in dogs and cats</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>313</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.15441</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30806491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6430921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hopper</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kass</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mellema</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of acid&#8211;base disorders in dogs and cats presenting to an emergency room. Part 1: comparison of three methods of acid&#8211;base analysis</article-title>. <source>J Vet Emerg Crit Care</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>493</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>501</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vec.12215</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25186080</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanova-Uhrikova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rauserova-Lexmaulova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehakova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scheer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doubek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Determination of reference intervals of acid-base parameters in clinically healthy dogs</article-title>. <source>J Vet Emerg Crit Care</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>325</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vec.12589</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28420042</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dionne</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishak</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cochran</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Point-of-care global coagulation assay parameters in normal dogs and dogs with primary immune-mediated hemolytic anemia</article-title>. <source>J Vet Emerg Crit Care</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vec.13262</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36453474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuq</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blois</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>B&#233;dard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrams-Ogg</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beauchamp</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Serum interleukin 17 concentrations in dogs with immune-mediated hemolytic anemia</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>217</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>25</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.15977</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33219716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7848375</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mektrirat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chongrattanameteekul</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pureeroj</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duangboon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loythong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiset</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Preliminary study on treatment outcomes and prednisolone tapering after marine lipid extract EAB-277 supplementation in dogs with immune-mediated hemolytic Anemia</article-title>. <source>Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>425</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vetsci10070425</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37505830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10386409</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suga</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raleigh</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vio</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Hypokalemia induces renal injury and alterations in vasoactive mediators that favor salt sensitivity</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Renal Physiol</source>. (<year>2001</year>) <volume>281</volume>:<fpage>F620</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajprenal.2001.281.4.F620</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11553508</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brace</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haddy</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The mechanism of the vasodilator action of potassium</article-title>. <source>Proc Soc Exp Biol Med</source>. (<year>1972</year>) <volume>140</volume>:<fpage>820</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3181/00379727-140-36560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4261065</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haddy</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vanhoutte</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feletou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Role of potassium in regulating blood flow and blood pressure</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>290</volume>:<fpage>R546</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpregu.00491.2005</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16467502</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reungjui</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roncal</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glushakova</surname><given-names>OY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Croker</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suga</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Hypokalemic nephropathy is associated with impaired angiogenesis</article-title>. <source>J Am Soc Nephrol</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>125</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1681/ASN.2007030261</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18178802</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2391040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pooler</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Regulation of potassium balance</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>John</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>, editor. <source>Vander&#8217;s renal physiology</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>McGraw Hill</publisher-name> (<year>2023</year>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kogika</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Morais</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A quick reference on hypokalemia</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin North Am Small Anim Pract</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>229</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cvsm.2016.10.010</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27939864</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kamel</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halperin</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Use of urine electrolytes and urine osmolality in the clinical diagnosis of fluid, electrolytes, and Acid-Base disorders</article-title>. <source>Kidney Int Rep</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1211</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ekir.2021.02.003</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34013099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8116912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhupa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Proulx</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hypocalcemia and Hypomagnesemia</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin North Am Small Anim Pract</source>. (<year>1998</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>587</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>608</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0195-5616(98)50057-5</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9597716</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matteson</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wingfield</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Pelt</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hackett</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Abnormalities of serum magnesium in critically III dogs: incidence and implications</article-title>. <source>J Vet Emerg Crit Care</source>. (<year>1994</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1476-4431.1994.tb00111.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirby</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudloff</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Magnesium physiology and clinical therapy in veterinary critical care</article-title>. <source>J Vet Emerg Crit Care</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>210</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>25</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vec.12253</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25427407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torrente</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silvestrini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz de Gopegui</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Severe life-threatening hypokalemia in a cat with suspected distal renal tubular acidosis</article-title>. <source>J Vet Emerg Crit Care</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>250</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1476-4431.2009.00490.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20487254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Achanti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szerlip</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Acid-Base disorders in the critically ill patient</article-title>. <source>Clin J Am Soc Nephrol</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>102</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2215/CJN.04500422</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35998977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10101555</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shmukler</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kedar</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madkaikar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Hemolytic anemia and distal renal tubular acidosis in two Indian patients homozygous for SLC4A1/AE1 mutation A858D</article-title>. <source>Am J Hematol</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>85</volume>:<fpage>824</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajh.21836</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20799361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3517738</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ungureanu</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Distal renal tubular acidosis in patients with autoimmune diseases&#8212;an update on pathogenesis, clinical presentation and therapeutic strategies</article-title>. <source>Biomedicines</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>2131</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biomedicines10092131</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36140232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9496140</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DiBartola</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chapter 10 - metabolic Acid-Base disorders</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>DiBartola</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group>, editor. <source>Fluid, electrolyte, and Acid-Base disorders in small animal practice</source>. <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>W.B. Saunders</publisher-name> (<year>2012</year>). <fpage>253</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barathidasan</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krishnamurthy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karunakar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajendran</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhandapany</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Systemic lupus erythematosus complicated by a Gitelman-like syndrome in an 8-year-old girl</article-title>. <source>CEN Case Rep</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13730-019-00440-1</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31853802</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7148407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunchur</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mauch</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parkanzky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahilly</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A review of renal tubular acidosis</article-title>. <source>J Vet Emerg Crit Care</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>325</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vec.13407</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39023331</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burnell</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teubner</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Metabolic acidosis accompanying potassium deprivation</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys</source>. (<year>1974</year>) <volume>227</volume>:<fpage>329</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajplegacy.1974.227.2.329</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4853167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hulter</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sebastian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sigala</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Licht</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glynn</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schambelan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pathogenesis of renal hyperchloremic acidosis resulting from dietary potassium restriction in the dog: role of aldosterone</article-title>. <source>Am J Phys</source>. (<year>1980</year>) <volume>238</volume>:<fpage>F79</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajprenal.1980.238.2.F79</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7361893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gabow</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaehny</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fennessey</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schrier</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Diagnostic importance of an increased serum anion gap</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>. (<year>1980</year>) <volume>303</volume>:<fpage>854</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM198010093031505</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6774247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orbegozo Cort&#233;s</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rayo Bonor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Isotonic crystalloid solutions: a structured review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Br J Anaesth</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>112</volume>:<fpage>968</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bja/aeu047</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24736393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>