<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vet Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Vet Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2350</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jvms</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JVMS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Veterinary Medical Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0916-7250</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1347-7439</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12150886</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12150886.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12150886</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12150886</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40128979</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.24-0428</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">24-0428</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Surgery</subject><subj-group><subject>Full Paper</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A retrospective study of the correlation of intraocular pressure and ultrasound biomicroscopy parameters with cataract maturity in small breed dogs</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>JANG</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yeajin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>KANG</surname><given-names initials="S">Seonmi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>SEO</surname><given-names initials="K">Kangmoon</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1)</label>Department of Veterinary Clinical Sciences, College of Veterinary Medicine and Research Institute for Veterinary Science, Seoul National University, Seoul,
Republic of Korea</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Seo K: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="kmseo@snu.ac.kr">kmseo@snu.ac.kr</email>, Department of Veterinary Clinical Sciences, College of Veterinary
Medicine and Research Institute for Veterinary Science, Seoul National University, 1 Gwanak-ro, Gwanak-gu, Seoul 08826, Republic of Korea</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>5</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>87</volume><issue>5</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">490303</issue-id><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>508</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>11</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-06-11 10:25:47.680"><day>11</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169;2025 The Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License. (CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"> https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>)</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jvms-87-5-503.pdf"/><abstract><p>There is a clinical challenge in decision-making regarding prophylactic glaucoma treatment based solely on intraocular pressure (IOP) trends for long-term cataract management or before
phacoemulsification surgery in canines. This study aimed to compare IOP and ultrasound biomicroscopy (UBM) parameters with cataract maturity in small dog breeds. We conducted a retrospective
review of medical records pertaining to ophthalmic examinations and UBM assessments of small breed dogs diagnosed with cataracts at the Veterinary Medical Teaching Hospital of Seoul National
University from January 2020 to August 2024. UBM images obtained under topical anesthesia were analyzed to quantify various parameters. Subsequently, the 47 eyes examined were classified
into four groups according to cataract maturity. The ciliary cleft area (CCA), ciliary cleft length (CCL) and width (CCW), and iridocorneal angle (ICA) were measured. The measured values
were compared to determine their degree of correlation with cataract maturity. Statistical analyses of patient demographics were also performed. Both CCA (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.0024) and CCL
(<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.0004) decreased significantly with increasing cataract maturity. However, IOP, CCW, and ICA were not significantly associated with cataract maturity. Age and sex did
not have significant effects on any dependent variable. Among the UBM parameters, CCA and CCL demonstrated a significant correlation with cataract maturity, indicating structural alterations
in the ICA might develop in association with cataracts, independent of direct IOP effects. These findings underscore the importance of considering prophylactic glaucoma management in
patients with advanced cataracts to mitigate potential complications.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>cataract</kwd><kwd>ciliary cleft</kwd><kwd>intraocular pressure</kwd><kwd>trabecular meshwork</kwd><kwd>ultrasound biomicroscopy</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Cataracts are a collective term for various lens-related disorders characterized by loss of transparency in the lens nucleus, cortex, or capsule. This condition may arise from genetic factors
or other systemic or ocular health issues [<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Lens-induced uveitis stemming from cataracts may influence intraocular pressure (IOP). Furthermore,
glaucoma is a prevalent postoperative complication after phacoemulsification, the primary surgical procedure for the treatment of canine cataracts [<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].</p><p>In dogs, disruption of the blood-aqueous barrier has been reported to occur in all cataract-affected eyes regardless of maturity level [<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The lower IOP in eyes with mature to hypermature cataracts indicated a possible relationship between cataract
severity and reduced IOP due to inflammatory processes [<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. However, the relationship between IOP and cataract development remains unclear.</p><p>Secondary glaucoma can result from iridocorneal angle (ICA) blockage due to uveitis, lens displacement, neoplastic cells, or other obstructions, including preiridal fibrovascular membranes
[<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Phacolytic open-angle glaucoma in dogs may also arise from
lens-induced uveitis caused by the resorption of hypermature cataracts [<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In humans, when phacolytic glaucoma progresses, it presents with classic
symptoms such as clouding of the anterior chamber, corneal opacity, and increased IOP [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p>Ultrasound biomicroscopy (UBM) has been instrumental in identify structural changes associated with cataract progression. In a human case, several key features of phacolytic glaucoma were
identified, highlighting the diagnostic potential of UBM in identifying structural changes associated with cataract progression and complications [<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].
In canines, UBM studies have documented parameter shifts following mydriasis and phacoemulsification [<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Kim
<italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> also demonstrated increases in ciliary cleft area, width, and length in dogs with immature and mature cataracts compared to those with normal eyes or incipient
cataracts [<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Although cataracts are known to increase the glaucoma risk, no study to date has directly investigated structural changes in the
iridocorneal angle across four stages of cataracts in dogs or their relationship to IOP. This study aimed to analyze how IOP and UBM parameters change across different cataract maturities to
guide glaucoma drug prescription decisions.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Selection of the animals</title><p>Forty-seven dogs were selected from a retrospective review of medical records from the Seoul National University Veterinary Medical Teaching Hospital Ophthalmology Service between January
2020 and August 2024. These dogs were diagnosed with cataracts without other intraocular diseases, as confirmed by a thorough ophthalmological examination. Eyes with a history of clinically
significant inflammation or diseases that could induce such inflammation were excluded from the study. Furthermore, any signs of previous inflammation, such as synechia or pigmentation, were
routinely reviewed in electronic medical records, and no such records were found for the eyes included in this study. The examinations were carried out in the same room with consistent
ambient light intensity and no injectable sedatives or topical ophthalmic drugs were used. It included basic neuro-ophthalmic evaluations, Schirmer Tear Test-1 (STT-1), IOP measurement using
the rebound tonometry device (Tonovet<sup>&#174;</sup>, iCare, Vantaa, Finland), fluorescein staining, slit-lamp biomicroscopy, and indirect ophthalmoscopy (Pan Retinal<sup>&#174;</sup> 2.2, VOLK,
Mentor, OH, USA). Examinations were carried out by trained ophthalmologists under the supervision of two veterinary ophthalmologists (S Kang and K Seo). This study was approved by the
Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Seoul National University (SNU-240603-8). The subjects were dogs of any breed, aged 0&#8211;16 years, of any sex, and without a history of underlying
systemic conditions or intraocular surgery. Cataract maturity was classified as incipient, immature, mature, or hypermature. Of the 47 eyes included in this study, body weight information
was available for 38 eyes. The mean, median, and range of body weight were 5.27 kg, 4.5 kg, and 1.88&#8211;11.7 kg, respectively. For the 9 eyes without body weight information, the breeds
included Maltese (n=4), Toy/Miniature Poodles (n=3), Bichon Frise (n=1), and Boston Terrier (n=1). This study focused on small-breed dogs, as body size (and eyeball size) may influence UBM
parameters.</p></sec><sec><title>UBM measurements</title><p>UBM examinations were performed after a thorough ophthalmic assessment. The instrument used for this study consisted of a 50 MHz probe (MD-320W<sup>&#174;</sup>, MEDA, Tianjin, China). Before
the examination, the canine subject was administered 0.5% proparacaine (Alcaine<sup>&#174;</sup>, Alcon Laboratories Inc., Fort Worth, TX, USA) and placed in the sternal recumbency with gentle
manual restraint, abstaining from sedation. The procedures were carried out in a standardized environment with consistent and uniformly dim yellow lighting. The aqueous outflow pathways in
the dorsal quadrant were assessed. The transducer was placed perpendicular to the corneoscleral limbus at the 9&#8211;12 o&#8217;clock position. Serial images were captured from each live video sequence
and selected for analysis by another examiner (Jang). The image was chosen to effectively show the drainage structures encompassing the corneoscleral limbus, iris root, ICA, and ciliary
cleft (CC).</p><p>The following four parameters were measured for each eye: (a) the geometric ICA defined by the iris root and the posterior corneoscleral limbus, (b) the width of the entrance to the CC as
the distance from the corneoscleral limbus to the iris root (CCW: ciliary cleft width), (c) the length of the CC measured from the pectinate ligament (or the most anterior visible part of
the uveal trabecular meshwork) to the front edge of the ciliary body (CCL: ciliary cleft length), and (d) the cross-sectional area of the CC measured as hypoechoic to anechoic area outlined
by CCW, CCL, and anterior surface of the iris root (CCA: ciliary cleft area) (<xref rid="fig_001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig_001" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Illustrative representation of the ciliary cleft parameterization using ultrasound biomicroscopy. <italic toggle="yes">Arrowhead</italic> indicates the iris root. <italic toggle="yes">Arrow</italic> marks the
margin of Schwalbe&#8217;s line. <italic toggle="yes">Solid line</italic> illustrates the iridocorneal angle (ICA), established by a line drawn tangential to the sclera from the iris root (arrowhead) and
extending to the margin of Schwalbe&#8217;s line (arrow), forming the angle. <italic toggle="yes">Dashed line</italic> represents the perpendicular distance from the iris root (arrowhead) to the
extension of the ICA, intersecting the sclera to define the ciliary cleft width (CCW). <italic toggle="yes">Dotted line</italic> highlights the hyperechoic area within the ciliary cleft, indicating
the ciliary cleft area (CCA), bounded by the inner and outer edges of the cleft. <italic toggle="yes">Bi-arrow line</italic> represents the length of the ciliary cleft (CCL), measured from its
beginning near the hyperechoic area to its deepest point.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jvms-87-5-503-g001.jpg"/></fig>). All measurements were performed using separate software (ImageJ<sup>&#174;</sup>, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All statistical analyses were performed with SPSS Statistics 26 software (IBM SPSS STATISTICS<sup>&#174;</sup>, IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA). A one-way analysis of variance was used to compare
age, IOP, and UBM parameters across the four stages of cataract. The eyes were grouped according to the patient&#8217;s age at the time of examination. Patients aged &#8804;8 years were classified as
&#8220;young patients (YP),&#8221; and those aged &gt;9 years were classified as &#8220;senior patients (SP).&#8221; The same dataset for the YP and SP groups was analyzed using a two-sample
<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test. The same statistical model was used for sex difference analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>RESULTS</title><p>The mean &#177; standard deviation (SD) age of the 47 dogs included in this study was 8.9 &#177; 3.2, ranging from 0 to 16 years old. Eight different breeds were represented, with poodles (n=25),
Bichon Frises (n=9), and Shih Tzu (n=6) being the most common. The remaining dogs included two Boston Terriers, two Maltese, and one each of the Cocker Spaniel, French Bulldog, and Maltipoo.
The study sample consisted of 5 intact females, 19 spayed females, 2 intact males, and 21 neutered males. The number of cases diagnosed with incipient cataract, immature cataract, mature
cataract, and hypermature cataract were 15, 13, 9, and 10, respectively.</p><p>The measurements of the dogs at each stage of cataract are shown in <xref rid="fig_002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig_002" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Representative images of CCL (yellow) and CCA (red) measurements from different cataract stages on ultrasound biomicroscopy. (A) Patient with incipient cataract, (B) patient with
immature cataract, (C) patient with mature cataract, (D) patient with hypermature cataract.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jvms-87-5-503-g002.jpg"/></fig>. A linear correlation was found between the progression of the cataract stage and CCA (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.024), showing that CCA decreased by approximately 0.073 mm<sup>2</sup> for
each 1 unit increase in cataract maturity. Furthermore, the CCL was significantly shortened with increasing cataract stage, decreasing by approximately 0.295 mm for each 1 unit increase in
cataract maturity (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.004). The mean &#177; SD value of CCA was 0.613 mm<sup>2</sup> &#177; 0.247 mm<sup>2</sup>, 0.467 mm<sup>2</sup> &#177; 0.277 mm<sup>2</sup>, 0.459 mm<sup>2</sup> &#177;
0.277 mm<sup>2</sup>, and 0.382 mm<sup>2</sup> &#177; 0.283 mm<sup>2</sup> in the incipient, immature, mature, and hypermature groups, respectively. Similarly, the mean &#177; SD value of CCL was 2.596
mm &#177; 0.962 mm, 2.172 mm &#177; 0.437 mm, 2.124 mm &#177; 0.825 mm, and 1.637 &#177; 0.697 in the incipient, immature, mature, and hypermature groups, respectively (<xref rid="fig_002" ref-type="fig">Fig.
2</xref>, <xref rid="tbl_001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl_001" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Values of intraocular pressure and anterior segment parameters by cataract maturity stage</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cataract stage</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IOP (mmHg)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICA (&#176;)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCW (mm)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCL (mm)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCA (mm<sup>2</sup>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incipient (n=15)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4 &#177; 3.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.768 &#177; 3.341</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.351 &#177; 0.099</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.596 &#177; 0.962***</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.613 &#177; 0.247**</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immature (n=13)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3 &#177; 4.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.225 &#177; 4.736</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.293 &#177; 0.121</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.172 &#177; 0.437***</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.467 &#177; 0.277**</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mature (n=9)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.2 &#177; 3.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.387 &#177; 4.433</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.315 &#177; 0.166</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.124 &#177; 0.825***</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.459 &#177; 0.277**</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypermature (n=10)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1 &#177; 4.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.470 &#177; 5.259</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.352 &#177; 0.117</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.637 &#177; 0.697***</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.382 &#177; 0.283**</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Statistical significance was observed in the linear regression model evaluating the correlation between cataract stage and ciliary cleft parameters (***<italic toggle="yes">P=</italic>0.004,
**<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.024). Mean &#177; SD values are shown. IOP, intraocular pressure; ICA, iridocorneal angle; CCW, width of the ciliary cleft; CCL, length of the ciliary cleft. CCA,
area of the ciliary cleft.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>).</p><p>The following results were observed for parameters that did not show statistically significant changes at different stages of cataract. The mean &#177; SD value of IOP was 13.4 mmHg &#177; 3.0 mmHg,
13.3 mmHg &#177; 4.1 mmHg, 12.2 mmHg &#177; 3.2 mmHg, and 13.1 mmHg &#177; 4.0 mmHg in the incipient, immature, mature, and hypermature groups, respectively (<xref rid="tbl_001" ref-type="table">Table
1</xref>).</p><p>Similarly, the mean &#177; SD value of ICA was 14.768&#176; &#177; 3.341&#176;, 13.225&#176; &#177; 4.736&#176;, 14.387&#176; &#177; 4.433&#176;, and 16.470&#176; &#177; 8.362&#176; in the incipient, immature, mature, and hypermature groups, respectively.
For CCW, the mean &#177; SD was 0.351&#176; &#177; 0.099&#176;, 0.293&#176; &#177; 0.121&#176;, 0.315&#176; &#177; 0.166&#176;, and 0.352&#176; &#177; 0.117&#176; in the incipient, immature, mature, and hypermature groups, respectively (<xref rid="tbl_001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>The mean &#177; SD value of age was 8.3 &#177; 3.1 years, 8.2 &#177; 3.5 years, 9.6 &#177; 2.8 years, and 10.2 &#177; 3.3 years in the incipient, immature, mature, and hypermature groups, respectively. The overall
mean &#177; SD value of age in all groups was 8.9 &#177; 3.2 years (<xref rid="fig_003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig_003" orientation="portrait"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Box plot showing the age distribution in different stages of cataracts: incipient, immature, mature, and hypermature. The isolated dot was an outlier.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jvms-87-5-503-g003.jpg"/></fig>).</p><p>In the analysis of demographic data from the patient, none of the variables showed significant differences between the eyes in the YP and SP groups (<xref rid="tbl_002" ref-type="table">Table
2</xref><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl_002" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Values of intraocular pressure and anterior segment parameters by age group</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age groups</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IOP (mmHg)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICA (&#176;)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCW (mm)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCL (mm)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCA (mm<sup>2</sup>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Young patients (&#8804;8 years)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3 &#177; 3.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.890 &#177; 4.594</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.312 &#177; 0.111</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.028 &#177; 0.704</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.474 &#177; 0.241</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Old patients (&#8805;9 years)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8 &#177; 3.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.402 &#177; 5.877</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.346 &#177; 0.133</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.349 &#177; 0.905</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.514 &#177; 0.265</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>No statistical significance was observed. Mean &#177; SD values are shown. IOP, intraocular pressure; ICA, iridocorneal angle; CCW, width of the ciliary cleft; CCL, length of the ciliary
cleft. CCA, area of the ciliary cleft.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>). We also performed the sex difference analysis, which did not show significant differences (<xref rid="tbl_003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl_003" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>Values of intraocular pressure and anterior segment parameters by sex</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IOP (mmHg)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICA (&#176;)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCW (mm)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCL (mm)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCA (mm<sup>2</sup>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1 &#177; 3.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.974 &#177; 6.041</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.337 &#177; 0.121</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.336 &#177; 0.709</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.557 &#177; 0.271</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.0 &#177; 3.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.300 &#177; 4.491</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.320 &#177; 0.125</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.039 &#177; 0.898</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.434 &#177; 0.218</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>No statistical significance was observed. Mean &#177; SD values are shown. IOP, intraocular pressure; ICA, iridocorneal angle; CCW, width of the ciliary cleft; CCL, length of the ciliary
cleft; CCA, area of the ciliary cleft.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>This study showed that the UBM parameters were associated with a narrower CCA and shorter CCL with cataract maturity. In contrast, the ICA, IOP, and CCW were not significantly correlated with
cataract maturity. The UBM measurements were independent of age and sex.</p><p>In this study, a significant narrowing of the CCA was observed with increasing cataract maturity, while no significant association was observed between IOP and cataract maturity. Within the
CC is the uveal trabecular meshwork, a spongiform cobweb-like tissue composed of irregular trabecular beams, and the spaces between these beams (Fontana&#8217;s spaces), which play an important role
in the drainage of aqueous humor and IOP [<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The CCA, as observed in the UBM, encompasses this area. It has previously been reported that there is a
negative correlation between CCA and IOP, which differs from the findings of this study [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. This study indicates that cataract progression may be associated with structural changes in the iridocorneal angle, although no significant differences in intraocular
pressure (IOP) were observed across the stages. In humans, neovascular glaucoma occurs when pro-angiogenic factors such as vascular endothelial growth factor is activated in the presence of
chronic uveitis, resulting in neovascularization of the iris. and iridocorneal angle, blocking the aqueous outflow pathway [<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Increased angiogenic
factors may contribute to the formation of fibrinous vascular material and the progression of CC narrowing, which may have led to an increase in IOP, although this increase was not significant
in this study.</p><p>Cataracts can change the mechanical characteristics of the lenses. In humans, the position of the lens changes with age and cataracts [<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. It has been
shown that mature cataract lenses thicken, although to a lesser extent than intumescent cataracts, while immature cataract lenses show thinning due to loss of lens protein in humans [<xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. The change in the physical morphometry of the lens itself could explain the variation in CCA in this study. In contrast, another study compared the UBM
parameters in dogs divided into two groups: a phacoemulsification surgery non-candidate group (including no-to-incipient cataracts) and a phacoemulsification surgery candidate group (including
immature to mature cataracts). The study showed that CCA and CCW were significantly greater in the cataract surgery candidate group. The increased weight of the lens and relaxed ciliary muscle
have been suggested to weaken the force that compresses the CC, leading to a larger CCA and CCW [<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The
difference in results between the aforementioned study and this study can be attributed to differences in the subjects studied. The previous study did not include patients with hypermature
cataracts, which could have reduced the volume of the lens due to resorption of the lens material, thus reducing the force on the CC. Furthermore, the accumulation of inflammatory substances
in chronic LIU may have been more pronounced during the progression of hypermature cataracts in the subjects included in this study.</p><p>To date, few studies have evaluated changes in the CCL. In one of such studies, tafluprost, a prostaglandin analog known to reduce IOP, significantly restricted the pupil, decreased ICA, and
increased CCW on UBM images [<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. However, it did not produce a significant change in the CCL. The disparity between their findings and those of this
study is probably due to differences in study objectives. This study did not aim to assess the impact of miotic drugs on ICA structure. However, the narrowing of the CCA mentioned above could
also explain the observed decrease in CCL as cataract maturity progressed (<xref rid="tbl_001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Furthermore, the study mentioned above reported that although
its results on CCA and CCL differed, its findings on CCW were similar to our study [<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. They confirmed that CCW increased as cataracts progressed from
the immature to mature stages, which was part of their inclusion criteria and was consistent with the findings of this study [<xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>Although not statistically significant, the IOP decreased from the incipient to the mature group and then increased again in the hypermature group. This observation was intriguing because
cataract maturation was associated with decreased CCA and CCL, which are critical for regulating aqueous outflow. The reductions in CCA and CCL may have resulted from the accumulation of
lens-induced uveitis-related inflammatory substances. This subclinical inflammation may explain the lower IOP observed during cataract progression [<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] to the mature stage. However, the increase in IOP in the
hypermature group may indicate the point at which the effects of inflammation, which initially improve uveoscleral flow, begin to hinder aqueous outflow, leading to elevated IOP [<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].</p><p>Differences in patient demographics, including age and sex, were not statistically significant for differences in IOP and UBM parameters in this study. In previous studies, 25 healthy male
and female Beagles with no history of goniodysgenesis were evaluated using high-resolution ultrasound to measure angle opening distance (AOD) and angle recess area (ARA) [<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The results showed that females had a significantly smaller AOD than males, which could explain their higher susceptibility to primary angle-closure glaucoma. Unlike a
previous study that focused on AOD and ARA in relation to primary angle-closure glaucoma, which was located anteriorly in ICA, this study emphasized metrics related to posterior part of the
CC. Additionally, while the previous study used healthy breed- and age-matched beagles (9&#8211;10 months old, 6&#8211;13 kg), the present study did not control for these factors, which may have
introduced some variability.</p><p>Age was also found to be insignificant in relation to IOP and UBM parameters. However, the age distribution of the patients increased slightly as cataract maturity progressed, which should be
considered in conjunction with previous discussions about IOP.</p><p>Kawata<italic toggle="yes"> et al.</italic> emphasized that it may also be necessary to adjust the measurement values based on the size of each patient [<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
Focusing on the eyes of small breed dogs within the same ophthalmic examination setting, we assumed that the UBM parameter values for the ICA structures would require minimal adjustment.
However, this study did not address potential breed-specific susceptibility. Furthermore, the findings of this study may only be universally applicable to some of the circumferences of the ICA
because the examination was limited to the dorsolateral quadrant. It would be valuable to perform the same UBM parameter assessments in multiple quadrants of a single eye.</p><p>This study has a recruitment bias. The UBM imaging was performed primarily during preoperative evaluations, in cases of increased IOP compared to previous levels, or when there were concerns
about possible development of glaucoma. The influence of iris configuration on the anterior segment structural parameters has been well documented in several studies [<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Controlling these effects requires optimization of the experimental conditions. However, this is a retrospective study. It was
also limited to UBM data obtained without the administration of topical mydriatics. In addition, the relatively small sample size may have limited the identification of significant age- and
sex-related effects. This study primarily included small-breed dogs predisposed to cataracts and glaucoma, such as Poodles, Bichon Frises, and Shih Tzus. Although we carefully eliminated eyes
where primary angle-closure glaucoma (PACG) appeared to have affected the opposite eye based on medical records, the potential influence of breed-related glaucoma predisposition cannot be
entirely excluded. Additionally, breed-specific statistical analysis was not conducted due to the sample size, which may limit the generalizability of findings to other breeds or
populations.</p><p>Unlike previous studies that examined UBM parameters and IOP after changes in iris morphology, such as miosis or mydriasis and after phacoemulsification surgery, this study aimed to minimize
the influence of the iris. It specifically identifies changes in UBM images that are likely caused by cataract maturation. These findings suggest that these changes are related to cataract
progression or age-related factors. Future research should explore histological changes in the posterior part of the CC of normotensive cataract eyes. In conclusion, using UBM to evaluate the
posterior part of the CC in cataractous eyes may be beneficial to assess glaucoma risk and consider prophylactic treatment when cataracts should be managed without surgery and before
performing phacoemulsification surgery for mature to hypermature cataracts.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s5"><title>CONFLICT OF INTEREST</title><p>The authors declare no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>This study was supported by the <funding-source>Research Institute for Veterinary Science (RIVS), College of Veterinary Medicine, Seoul National University</funding-source>. In addition, this research was supported by the
Basic Science Research Program through the <funding-source>National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF)</funding-source> funded by the Ministry of Education (2021R1I1A1A01058695).</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Boillot</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosolen</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dulaurent</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goulle</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isard</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azoulay</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lafarge-Beurlet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavillegrand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivkovic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neveux</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahel</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Picaud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Froger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2014</year>. <article-title>Determination of morphological, biometric and biochemical susceptibilities in healthy Eurasier dogs with suspected inherited
glaucoma</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source><volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e111873</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0111873</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25380252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4224419</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2019</year>. <article-title>Ultrasound biomicroscopy studies to evaluate ciliary cleft parameters in healthy eyes of American Cocker Spaniels</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Pak Vet J</italic></source><volume>39</volume>: <fpage>66</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.29261/pakvetj/2019.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Crumley</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gionfriddo</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Radecki</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2009</year>. <article-title>Relationship of the iridocorneal angle, as measured using ultrasound biomicroscopy, with post-operative increases in intraocular pressure
post-phacoemulsification in dogs</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet Ophthalmol</italic></source><volume>12</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1463-5224.2009.00669.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19152594</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhingra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grover</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapatia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandav</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaushik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2020</year>. <article-title>Phacolytic glaucoma: a nearly forgotten entity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Ophthalmol</italic></source><volume>30</volume>:
<fpage>NP32</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>NP35</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1120672119841972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30950286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dulaurent</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goulle</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dulaurent</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mentek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peiffer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isard</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2012</year>. <article-title>Effect of mydriasis induced by topical instillations of 0.5% tropicamide on the anterior segment in normotensive dogs using ultrasound
biomicroscopy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet Ophthalmol</italic></source><volume>15</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue>: <fpage>8</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1463-5224.2011.00898.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22050918</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Dziezyc</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Millichamp</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1997</year>. <article-title>Fluorescein concentrations in the aqueous of dogs with cataracts</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet Comp
Ophthalmol</italic></source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>267</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>270</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Escanilla</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leiva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monreal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>R&#237;os</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pe&#241;a</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2013</year>. <article-title>Aqueous humor fibrinolytic activity in dogs with cataracts</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet
Ophthalmol</italic></source><volume>16</volume>: <fpage>409</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>415</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vop.12013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23240635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Gelatt</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacKay</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2004</year>. <article-title>Secondary glaucomas in the dog in North America</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet Ophthalmol</italic></source><volume>7</volume>:
<fpage>245</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>259</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1463-5224.2004.04034.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15200621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Grozdanic</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kecova</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nilaweera</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuehn</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kardon</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>Functional and structural changes in a canine model of hereditary primary angle-closure glaucoma</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Invest
Ophthalmol Vis Sci</italic></source><volume>51</volume>: <fpage>255</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>263</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1167/iovs.09-4081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19661222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3258664</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ota</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2016</year>. <article-title>Ultrasound biomicroscopic findings of the iridocorneal angle in live healthy and glaucomatous dogs</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Vet
Med Sci</italic></source><volume>77</volume>: <fpage>1625</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1631</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.15-0311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26212256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4710719</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jonas</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iribarren</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nangia</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pardhi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panda-Jonas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2015</year>. <article-title>Lens position and age: the central india eye and medical study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Invest Ophthalmol Vis
Sci</italic></source><volume>56</volume>: <fpage>5309</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5314</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1167/iovs.15-16796</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26258615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsukizawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2010</year>. <article-title>Rectification of width and area of the ciliary cleft in dogs</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Vet Med
Sci</italic></source><volume>72</volume>: <fpage>533</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>537</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.09-0507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20009426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goh</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2023</year>. <article-title>Evaluation of ciliary cleft changes after phacoemulsification using ultrasound biomicroscopy in dogs with cataracts</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Front Vet Sci</italic></source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1247127</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1247127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38033645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10684783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2024</year>. <article-title>Ultrasound biomicroscopy analysis of ciliary muscle dynamics and its relation to intra-ocular pressure after phacoemulsification in
dogs</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Front Vet Sci</italic></source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>1366997</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2024.1366997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38784657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11111888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Karmiris</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Papakonstantinou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsiripidis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stavrakas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giannakis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chalkiadaki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2024</year>. <article-title>Atypical phacolytic glaucoma diagnosed by biometry and anterior segment optical coherence tomography (OCT) in a patient with CMV anterior
uveitis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Ophthalmol</italic></source><volume>34</volume>: <fpage>NP29</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>NP32</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/11206721241246816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38602030</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2017</year>. <article-title>Effect of preservative-free tafluprost on intraocular pressure, pupil diameter, and anterior segment structures in normal canine
eyes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet Ophthalmol</italic></source><volume>20</volume>: <fpage>34</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>39</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vop.12341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26728904</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Leasure</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gelatt</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacKay</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2001</year>. <article-title>The relationship of cataract maturity to intraocular pressure in dogs</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet
Ophthalmol</italic></source><volume>4</volume>: <fpage>273</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>276</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1463-5216.2001.00199.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11906663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Leiva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pe&#241;a</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2021</year>. Diseases of the lens and cataract formation. pp. 1317&#8211;1370. In: Veterinary Ophthalmology (Gelatt KN ed.), 6th ed., Wiley Blackwell.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <article-title>The effect of cataract extraction on the contractility of ciliary muscle</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J
Ophthalmol</italic></source><volume>146</volume>: <fpage>8</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>14</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajo.2008.02.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18439565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Peiffer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilcock</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1990</year>. <article-title>The pathogenesis and significance of pre-iridal fibrovascular membrane in domestic animals</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet
Pathol</italic></source><volume>27</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/030098589002700106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2309380</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pizzirani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2015</year>. <article-title>Functional anatomy of the outflow facilities</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet Clin North Am Small Anim
Pract</italic></source><volume>45</volume>: <fpage>1101</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1126, v</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cvsm.2015.06.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26337760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4787989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Renzo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortencio</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barros Sobrinho</surname><given-names>AAF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mineo</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laus</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2014</year>. <article-title>Intraocular pressure, specular microscopy, and prostaglandin E2 concentration in dogs with mature and hypermature cataract</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Vet Ophthalmol</italic></source><volume>17</volume>: <fpage>280</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>285</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vop.12144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24450881</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zangalli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sodre</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donini</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leite</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torigoe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diniz-Filho</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Almeida</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2016</year>. <article-title>Neovascular glaucoma: a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Retina Vitreous</italic></source><volume>2</volume>:
<fpage>26</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40942-016-0051-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27895936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5116372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattoon</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gemensky-Metzler</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkie</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajala-Schultz</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2008</year>. <article-title>Ultrasound biomicroscopy of the iridocorneal angle of the eye before and after phacoemulsification and intraocular lens implantation in
dogs</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Vet Res</italic></source><volume>69</volume>: <fpage>279</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>288</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/ajvr.69.2.279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18241027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaese</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2021</year>. <article-title>Association between preoperative gonioscopic status and postoperative glaucoma after phacoemulsification in dogs: a retrospective cohort
study of 505 eyes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet Ophthalmol</italic></source><volume>24</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue>: <fpage>39</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>49</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vop.12818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32946201</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RIE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peiffer</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilcock</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>1993</year>. <article-title>Some aspects of the pathology of canine glaucoma</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Prog Vet Comp
Ophthalmol</italic></source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>16</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vangyi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiese</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Almazan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conforti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2012</year>. <article-title>Gender differences in iridocorneal angle morphology: a potential explanation for the female predisposition to primary angle closure
glaucoma in dogs</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet Ophthalmol</italic></source><volume>15</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue>: <fpage>60</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1463-5224.2011.00956.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22050644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>. <year>2004</year>. <article-title>Lens morphometry determined by B-mode ultrasonography of the normal and cataractous canine lens</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet
Ophthalmol</italic></source><volume>7</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1463-5224.2004.04005.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14982588</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>