<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10472939</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10472939.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10472939</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10472939</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37662995</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1232570</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> anthelmintic efficacy of peppermint (<italic toggle="yes">Mentha x piperita</italic> L.) essential oil against gastrointestinal nematodes of sheep</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>&#352;trbac</surname><given-names initials="F">Filip</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2165365/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krnjaji&#263;</surname><given-names initials="S">Slobodan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stojanovi&#263;</surname><given-names initials="D">Dragica</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ratajac</surname><given-names initials="R">Radomir</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2185754/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simin</surname><given-names initials="N">Nata&#353;a</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1389992/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Or&#269;i&#263;</surname><given-names initials="D">Dejan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rinaldi</surname><given-names initials="L">Laura</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/379209/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciccone</surname><given-names initials="E">Elena</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maurelli</surname><given-names initials="MP">Maria Paola</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/795423/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cringoli</surname><given-names initials="G">Giuseppe</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names initials="A">Antonio</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c002" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Institute for Multidisciplinary Research, University of Belgrade</institution>, <addr-line>Belgrade</addr-line>, <country>Serbia</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Veterinary Medicine, Faculty of Agriculture, University of Novi Sad</institution>, <addr-line>Novi Sad</addr-line>, <country>Serbia</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Scientific Veterinary Institute Novi Sad</institution>, <addr-line>Novi Sad</addr-line>, <country>Serbia</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Department of Chemistry, Biochemistry and Environmental Protection, Faculty of Sciences, University of Novi Sad</institution>, <addr-line>Novi Sad</addr-line>, <country>Serbia</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Department of Veterinary Medicine and Animal Production, University of Naples Federico II, CREMOPAR</institution>, <addr-line>Naples</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0001"><p>Edited by: Marianna Pauletto, University of Padua, Italy</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0002"><p>Reviewed by: Ian Sutherland, AgResearch Ltd., New Zealand; Giulia Simonato, University of Padua, Italy</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Filip &#352;trbac, <email>filip.strbac@imsi.bg.ac.rs</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Antonio Bosco, <email>antonio.bosco@unina.it</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">427755</issue-id><elocation-id>1232570</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>02</day><month>09</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-07-22 21:25:13.530"><day>22</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 &#352;trbac, Krnjaji&#263;, Stojanovi&#263;, Ratajac, Simin, Or&#269;i&#263;, Rinaldi, Ciccone, Maurelli, Cringoli and Bosco.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>&#352;trbac, Krnjaji&#263;, Stojanovi&#263;, Ratajac, Simin, Or&#269;i&#263;, Rinaldi, Ciccone, Maurelli, Cringoli and Bosco</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-10-1232570.pdf"/><abstract><p>Nowadays, the exclusive use of commercial anthelmintics for the treatment of gastrointestinal nematode infections in ruminants is less sustainable due to anthelmintic resistance, as well as the problem of drug residues in animal products and the environment. Therefore, an integrated therapeutic approach is needed, including the search for alternatives to synthetic anthelmintic drugs. The aim of this study was to evaluate the possibility of using the essential oil of peppermint (<italic toggle="yes">Mentha x piperita</italic> L.) in the control of gastrointestinal nematodes in sheep. For this purpose, the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> anthelmintic efficacy of this oil and the toxic effects on the hosts were examined. In the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> egg hatch test, ovicidal activity varied from 21.0&#8211;90.3% depending on the concentration of essential oil used (0.0125, 0.025, 0.049, 0.195, 0.781, 3.125, 12.5, and 50&#8201;mg/mL). To some extent, anthelmintic efficacy was confirmed in the <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> fecal egg count reduction test at a mean dose of 150&#8201;mg/kg, with an average reduction of nematode eggs of 26.9 and 46.0% at Days 7 and 14 after treatment, respectively. Furthermore, no toxic effects of applied oil were observed on sheep behavior, kidney, or liver function. The main compounds identified by gas chromatography&#8211;mass spectrometry analyzes were menthol (32.6%), menthone (22.0%), menthyl-acetate (10.0%), and isomenthone (9.39%). Due to their complex chemical compositions, numerous bioactive ingredients, and natural origin, herbal formulations represent a potentially valuable alternative for the control of gastrointestinal nematodes in sheep. In this context, the results of the present study showed that peppermint essential oil is one of the promising candidates. Further studies should be performed to collect more data on the safety profile of <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO in treated animals to find the most appropriate formulation for use in field conditions and to test it against resistant gastrointestinal nematode populations.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Mentha x piperita</italic></kwd><kwd>essential oil</kwd><kwd>gastrointestinal nematodes</kwd><kwd>sheep</kwd><kwd>anthelmintic efficacy</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="6"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="73"/><page-count count="11"/><word-count count="9131"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Veterinary Pharmacology and Toxicology</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><label>1.</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Gastrointestinal nematodes (GINs) are one of the most important endoparasites in grazing animals, especially ruminants (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). In sheep, these parasites may cause various negative effects including subclinical disease with weight loss and reduced animal production, or clinically manifested disease with signs of anemia, diarrhea, protein loss, anorexia, decreased immunity, and fertility (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). In the case of a high worm burden, a possibly fatal outcome may occur (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Therefore, due to decreased productivity, high treatment costs, and possible death of the animals, GIN parasitism can have a huge economic impact (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Commercially available anthelmintics have been used successfully for decades to control these parasites (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). However, as a result of their irrational use, anthelmintic resistance (AR) has developed, whereby the following are considered high-risk factors: underdosing, overfrequent treatments, mass treatment, and single-drug regimens (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p><p>Thus, increasing resistance of nematodes to the well-known group of anthelmintics such as benzimidazoles, macrocyclic lactones, and imidazothiazoles has been reported, sometimes simultaneously to several different classes (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). The problem is also present in novel anthelmintic groups such as monepantel, an amino-acetonitrile derivative (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Annual economic losses resulting from the development of AR are estimated at &#8364;38&#8201;million in Europe, with expected growth in the future (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Other problems associated with the use of commercial anthelmintics are residues present in animal products such as meat and milk or in the ecosystem and biodiversity. This represents a serious problem associated with many currently available chemotherapeutic drugs, along with the increasing price (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). All the above-mentioned issues suggest the urgent need for developing novel strategies for future treatments (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p><p>As a possible solution for achieving sustainable control of sheep GINs, an integrated approach has been proposed by many researchers (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). This refers to the rational use of commercial anthelmintics, along with the use of alternatives. On the one hand, the rational use of anthelmintics should be based on refugia strategies such as targeted treatments (TT) or targeted selective treatments (TST), which imply only the treatment of herds or animals that require it due to clinical or economic reasons (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Besides, the rational use of commercial drugs may refer to the combination or rotation of anthelmintics from different chemical classes in order to avoid the excessive use of only one drug (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). On the other hand, integrated control implies the incorporation of various alternative strategies into the practice, such as genetic selection of sheep naturally resistant to GINs, pasture management, dietary manipulation, vaccine development, biological control (direct&#8211;use of nematophagous fungi, bacteria, and predatory nematodes or indirect&#8211;use of earthworms or dung beetles), or the use of plant-based anthelmintics (condensed tannins, various extracts, or essential oils) (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>).</p><p>As aromatic, complex, and concentrated mixtures of volatile, nonpolar compounds, essential oils (EOs) belong to the group of plant secondary metabolites that are responsible for enabling plants to be competitive in their own environment (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Thus, these mixtures contain various compounds such as terpenes, terpenoids, and phenylpropanoids that can be used for various pharmacological purposes (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). EOs and their compounds can be obtained from plants by various extraction methods, and along with their extracts, they are increasingly being used in veterinary medicine in recent times. Among the others, indications for their application include the use as coccidiostats to boost immunity and improve the performance of poultry, to prevent diarrhea in piglets (due to their antimicrobial properties), as fish diet supplementation, to use against <italic toggle="yes">Varroa destructor</italic> in beekeeping or against <italic toggle="yes">Malassezia pachydermatis</italic> and ticks in pets, etc. (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). In ruminants, the possible benefits of EOs among the others include the improvement of ruminal fermentation and digestion and the reduction of methanogenesis and nitrogen excretion (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). In addition, various studies have demonstrated the efficacy of EOs against GINs in sheep. The list is wide and includes oregano, thyme, coriander, tea tree, and lavender as well as various species of lemongrass, eucalyptus, lippia, mint, etc. (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>).</p><p>Peppermint (<italic toggle="yes">Mentha x piperita</italic> L.) represents a well-known aromatic and medicinal herb derived from crossing between spearmint (<italic toggle="yes">Mentha spicata</italic> L.) and water mint (<italic toggle="yes">Mentha aquatica</italic> L.). It belongs to the Lamiaceae family and is native to the Mediterranean region but is now cultivated in various parts of the world (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Peppermint is one of the most important plant species in the pharmaceutical and cosmetic industries, whose EO is widely produced and used. Many pharmacological properties of peppermint have been previously demonstrated and include analgetic, antiviral, antibacterial, antifungal, and antiparasitic effects (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Moreover, the effect of <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO against sheep GINs was also demonstrated in various studies, whereby it showed promising results against different parasite stages (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). However, only the efficacy under laboratory conditions has been proven so far, which requires the confirmation of these results in field trials. Therefore, along with <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>, the aim of the present study was to examine the <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> effect of <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO against GINs of sheep, as well as to evaluate the safety of its use in the hosts.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><label>2.</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec3"><label>2.1.</label><title>Chemical analyzes</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Mentha piperita</italic> EO was obtained from the Institute of Field and Vegetable Crops, Novi Sad, Serbia, whereby the chemical composition (qualitative and semiquantitative characterization) of the tested EO was determined by gas chromatography&#8211;mass spectrometry (GC&#8211;MS) at the Department of Chemistry, Biochemistry, and Environmental Protection, Faculty of Sciences, University of Novi Sad, Serbia. The exact parameters regarding the technical conditions for the analysis are described in Kne&#382;evi&#263; et al. (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>) and &#352;trbac et al. (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>) as follows: injection volume of EO 1&#8201;&#956;L; injector temperature 250&#176;C; split ratio 1:10; carrier gas helium; flow rate: 1&#8201;mL/min; capillary column: HP-5 (30&#8201;m&#8201;&#215;&#8201;0.25&#8201;mm, 0.25&#8201;&#956;m); temperature program 50&#8211;270&#176;C; ion source temperature 230&#176;C; electron energy 70&#8201;eV; quadrupole temperature 150&#176;C. The compounds were identified by comparison of mass spectra with data libraries (Wiley Registry of Mass Spectral Data, 7th ed., and NIST/EPA/NIH Mass Spectral Library 05) and confirmed by comparison with arithmetic retention indices (AI) with literature data (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Diesel oil, containing C8&#8211; C28 n-alkanes, was used as a standard for the determination of retention indices. The relative amounts of the components, expressed in percentages, were calculated by the normalization procedure according to the peak area in the total ion chromatogram.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>2.2.</label><title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> test&#8211;egg hatch test</title><p>The remaining analyzes were performed at the Regional Center for Monitoring of Parasitosis (CREMOPAR) located in Eboli (SA), Italy, in 2021. For the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> examination of the anthelmintic potential of <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO, the egg hatch test (EHT) was chosen. GIN eggs were collected from fecal samples taken directly from the rectal ampulla of sheep (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;40) with natural-mixed infection, and processed within 2&#8201;h of collection by the recovery method (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). To separate the eggs from the feces, samples were first pooled, homogenized, and filtered under running water through meshes of different sizes (1&#8201;mm, 250&#8201;&#956;m, 212&#8201;&#956;m, and 38&#8201;&#956;m). GIN eggs that were retained on the smallest mesh were washed with distilled water and centrifuged at 1500&#8201;rpm for 3&#8201;min, after which the supernatant was discarded. Then, centrifugation was performed using a 40% sugar solution to float the eggs, which were then isolated into new tubes and mixed with distilled water. Finally, a few more centrifugations were performed to remove the pellets and obtain an aqueous solution containing GIN eggs.</p><p>Similar to our previous study (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>), EHT was performed at eight different concentrations (50, 12.5, 3.125, 0.781, 0.195, 0.049, 0.025, and 0.0125&#8201;mg/mL) of the tested EO obtained by the dilution. For this purpose, 24-well plates were used in which each concentration of EO was emulsified with 3% Tween 80. An aqueous solution (40&#8201;mL) containing approximately 150 GIN eggs was added to each well, which was then completed with distilled water to reach a final volume of 0.5&#8201;mL in the wells. The positive control was thiabendazole at the two lowest concentrations used for EO, and the negative controls were 3% Tween 80 at the amount used for the emulsion, as well as distilled water. After an incubation period of 48&#8201;h at 27&#176;C, the GIN eggs and the hatched first-stage (L<sub>1</sub>) larvae were counted under an inverted microscope, and the inhibition of hatchability was calculated. The experiment was performed in three replicates, and the obtained values were expressed as arithmetic mean&#8201;&#177;&#8201;standard deviation.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>2.3.</label><title><italic toggle="yes">In vivo</italic> test&#8211;fecal egg count reduction test</title><p>The <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> trial was conducted in two different farms in southern Italy (Campania region), where the prevalence of GINs is high (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). In Farm 1, the animals were free-range, and in Farm 2, the animals were kept in boxes during treatment. Sheep with natural-mixed infection and different worm burdens were used, mainly the Lacaune/Bagnolese mixed dairy breed, which was homogeneous in terms of age (2&#8201;years &#177;0.5) and grazing season, with an average body weight (b.w.) of 50&#8201;kg&#8201;&#177;&#8201;5. The tested animals were fed with pasture and forage (barley and maize grains), and the diet was not changed during the experiment. None of the commercial treatments were applied at least 6&#8201;months before the trial, and the animals fasted and remained fasting until 2&#8201;h after administration of EO. In both farms studied, sheep were divided into three different treatment groups:</p><p>G1: 150&#8201;mg/kg of <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12 animals/group/farm).</p><p>G2: 3.8&#8201;mg/kg of albendazole, positive control (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12 animals/group/farm).</p><p>G3: 50&#8201;mL of sunflower oil per animal, negative control (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;12 animals/group/farm).</p><p>The EO formulation was prepared by diluting <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO in sunflower oil (1,4.5) to avoid the effect of pure oil on the mucous membranes of the gastrointestinal tract. In an attempt to ensure the largest possible number of active ingredients from EO reaching the target sites (abomasum and intestine), the formulation (as well as the controls) was applied directly into the rumen of the animals. Individual fecal samples were collected rectally before treatment (D0) and 7 and 14&#8201;days after treatment (D7 and D14) and stored at 4&#176;C before processing. Collected samples were analyzed using the novel Mini-FLOTAC technique (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) with a detection limit of five eggs per gram (EPG) of feces, using a sodium chloride flotation solution (specific gravity&#8201;=&#8201;1.200). Percentages of EPG reduction were evaluated at D7 and D14 by calculating means within each group, whereby the final results for each group were presented as arithmetic means of the two farms examined.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><label>2.4.</label><title>Coproculture</title><p>The coproculture study was conducted according to the protocol developed by the UK Ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries, and Food (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>) in order to identify the GIN genera in the sampled farms and the changes in their population after treatment. Before storage at 4&#176;C, an equal amount of feces was collected from each sample to form a pool for each group formed for the <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> test (<italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO, albendazole, and sunflower oil) at different time points (D0, D7, and D14). The developed third-stage larvae (L<sub>3</sub>) were identified based on the morphological keys proposed by van Wyk and Mayhew (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). The identification and percentage of each nematode genus was performed on 100 L<sub>3</sub>, whereby all larvae were identified if a sample contained 100 or fewer L<sub>3</sub>. In this way, the percentage of each genus could be determined from the total number of larvae identified (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><label>2.5.</label><title>Toxicity studies</title><p>All treated animals were observed clinically for the presence of potential adverse effects, with particular attention to their feeding, defecation, and behavior. In addition, blood samples were collected from the jugular vein at D0 and D14 to evaluate the effects of the used EO on blood parameters. For hematological parameters, blood samples were collected in vacuum tubes containing EDTA and processed shortly thereafter (within 2&#8211;4&#8201;h), whereas, for the biochemical parameters, blood was collected in vacuum tubes without coagulant and subsequently analyzed. For the latter, special attention was paid to urea, creatinine, and AST and GGT, which represent parameters of renal and hepatic function, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><label>2.6.</label><title>Statistical analyzes</title><p>Inhibition of Hatchability (IH) in the EHT was calculated using the following formula proposed by Coles et al. (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>) and Pinto et al. (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>):</p><p>IH (%)&#8201;=&#8201;number of eggs/(number of eggs + number of L1 larvae)&#8201;&#215;&#8201;100.</p><p>For the mutual comparison of the ovicidal effect of different concentrations as well as with controls, one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with <italic toggle="yes">post hoc</italic> Tukey&#8217;s test was performed with a value of p threshold of 0.05. Nonlinear regression/logarithmic distribution was used to assess the presence of a dose-dependent effect and calculate the half-maximal inhibitory concentration (IC<sub>50</sub>) (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>).</p><p>On the FECRT, the reduction in mean EPG in each treatment group at each time point was calculated using the following formula (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>):</p><p>FECR (%)&#8201;=&#8201;(1&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;(T<sub>2</sub>/T<sub>1</sub>&#8201;&#215;&#8201;C<sub>1</sub>/C<sub>2</sub>))&#8201;&#215;&#8201;100.</p><p>In this formula, T<sub>2</sub> represents the EPG after treatment (D7 or D14); T<sub>1</sub> represents the EPG before treatment (D0), C<sub>1</sub> represents the EPG before treatment in the negative control group and C<sub>2</sub> represents the EPG after treatment (D7 or D14) in the negative control group. The values obtained were compared using the two-way ANOVA followed by Tukey&#8217;s test in order to evaluate the differences in effect within a group and location for different days, as well as within the same day and location for different groups (value of p threshold of 0.05).</p><p>Finally, for the analysis of the results of the hematological and biochemical blood analyzes, a two-way ANOVA was also performed. For the comparison of values in the same group at D0 and D14 after treatment, the <italic toggle="yes">post hoc</italic> Sidak&#8217;s test (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) was used, while for the comparison of values obtained for different groups on the same day, <italic toggle="yes">post hoc</italic> Tukey&#8217;s test (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) was used.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec9"><label>3.</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec10"><label>3.1.</label><title>Chemical analyzes</title><p>Chemical analyzes revealed a complex composition of <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO with a total of 31 different compounds, of which 27 were identified (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Graph 1</xref>; <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The compounds belong to different chemical classes, where monoterpenes - alcohol (menthol, 32.6%), ketones (menthone, 22.0%; isomenthone, 9.39%), ester (menthyl acetate, 10.0%), and ether (eucalyptol, 5.22%) were predominant (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Graph 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Chemical composition (% of total peak area) of the <italic toggle="yes">Mentha x piperita</italic> L. essential oil determined by gas chromatography&#8211;mass spectrometry analyzes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AI*</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compound</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% of total peak area</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">925</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#945;-Thujene</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">932</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#945;-Pinene</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">946</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Camphene</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">971</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sabinene</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">976</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#946;-Pinene</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">990</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myrcene</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,016</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#945;-Terpinene</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,023</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-Cymene</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,027</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limonene</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,029</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,8-Cineole</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,035</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cis-Ocimene</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,057</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#947;-Terpinene</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,065</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.i.</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,087</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpinolene</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,100</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">trans-Sabinene hydrate</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,107</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.i.</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,152</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Menthone</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,163</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isomenthone</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,172</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Menthol</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,176</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpinen-4-ol</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,182</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">iso-Menthol</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,190</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#945;-Terpineol</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,238</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pulegone</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,274</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">neo-Menthyl acetate</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,293</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Menthyl acetate</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,307</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">iso-Menthyl acetate</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,383</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#946;-Bourbonene</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,391</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.i.</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,417</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#946;-Caryophyllene</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,480</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germacrene D</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,495</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.i.</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total % of identified compounds</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*AI&#8211;arithmetic retention index.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Graph 1</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">Mentha x piperita</italic> L. essential oil by gas chromatography&#8211;mass spectrometry analyzes.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1232570-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec11"><label>3.2.</label><title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> test&#8211;egg hatch test</title><p>In the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> test, <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO showed ovicidal activity with inhibition of hatchability ranging from 20.0 to 90.3% depending on the concentration used (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The highest concentration showed similar activity with thiabendazole at both concentrations tested (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05), whereas all tested EO concentrations showed significantly higher activity than negative controls (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The calculated <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sup>2</sup> value was 0.96, suggesting a dose-dependent activity with a determined IC<sub>50</sub> value of 0.43&#8201;mg/mL (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Graph 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Ovicidal activity of <italic toggle="yes">Mentha x piperita</italic> L. essential oil against gastrointestinal nematodes eggs (<italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>&#8211;egg hatch test).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Concentration (mg/mL)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inhibition of hatchability (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.3 &#177; 2.08<sup>A</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.0 &#177; 2.00<sup>B</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.125</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.0 &#177; 2.65<sup>C</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.781</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.3 &#177; 2.52<sup>CD</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.195</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.7 &#177; 1.53<sup>D</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.7 &#177; 2.52<sup>E</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0 &#177; 1.00<sup>EF</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0125</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.0 &#177; 1.00<sup>E</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control (+)<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.3 &#177; 1.53<sup>A</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control (+)<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.0 &#177; 1.00<sup>A</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control (&#8722;)<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.2 &#177; 3.34<sup>F</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control (&#8722;)<sup>d</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.60 &#177; 1.92<sup>G</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Uppercase compares means between different concentrations as well as controls. Different letters indicate significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Control (+)<sup>a</sup> - thiabendazole, 0.025&#8201;mg/mL; control (+)<sup>b</sup> - thiabendazole, 0.0125&#8201;mg/mL; control (&#8722;)<sup>c</sup> - 3% Tween 80, v/v; control (&#8722;)<sup>d</sup> - distilled water.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Graph 2</label><caption><p>Inhibition of egg hatchability at different concentrations of <italic toggle="yes">Mentha x piperita</italic> L. essential oil.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1232570-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec12"><label>3.3.</label><title><italic toggle="yes">In vivo</italic> test<italic toggle="yes">&#8211;</italic>fecal egg count reduction test</title><p>The results of <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> trial also showed the anthelmintic potential of <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO with a mean efficacy of 26.86% (Day 7) and 46.04% (Day 14) (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Applied oil significantly reduced the number of EPG in comparison with a value obtained before the treatment (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) in Farm 2, as well as in total. In general, the effect of EO was better on Farm 2 (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Graph 3</xref>) and reached an efficacy of 33.63 and 63.35% on Days 7 and 14, respectively. However, EPG values in two different farms were not significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05) in the <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> group, in contrast to the control groups where EPGs were significantly higher in Farm 1 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Eggs per gram (mean&#8201;&#177;&#8201;standard deviation) values and efficacy (%) of <italic toggle="yes">Mentha x piperita</italic> L. essential oil against gastrointestinal nematodes of sheep (<italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>&#8211;fecal egg count reduction test).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Treatment</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO, 150&#8201;mg/kg</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Albendazole, 3.8&#8201;mg/kg (control +)</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Sunflower oil, 50&#8201;mL (control -)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Location/Time point</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EPG</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reduction</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EPG</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reduction</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EPG</th><th align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reduction</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Farm 1</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 0</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">974.6 &#177; 709.2<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">983.3 &#177; 1160.1<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1279.6 &#177; 1092.3<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 7</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">767.5 &#177; 637.9<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.08%</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9 &#177; 20.7<sup>Bb</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.16%</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1260.9 &#177; 1052.6<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 14</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">598.3 &#177; 707.5<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.73%</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.7 &#177; 70.8<sup>Ba</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.17%</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1102.3 &#177; 841.8<sup>Ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Farm 2</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 0</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">783.8 &#177; 770.0<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">377.9 &#177; 311.0<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">548.3 &#177; 551.5<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 7</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">538.8 &#177; 505.6<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.63%</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 &#177; 2.89<sup>Bb</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.79%</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">567.9 &#177; 517.0<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 14</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261.3 &#177; 295.8<sup>Ba</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.35%</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.08 &#177; 12.5<sup>Bb</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.94%</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">498.8 &#177; 518.8<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 0</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">879.2 &#177; 739.6<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">680.6 &#177; 735.6<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">914.0 &#177; 821.9<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 7</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">653.2 &#177; 572.0<sup>Ba</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.86%</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.39 &#177; 11.8<sup>Bb</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.98%</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">914.4 &#177; 784.8<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 14</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">492.8 &#177; 501.7<sup>Ba</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.04%</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.9 &#177; 41.7<sup>Cb</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.06%</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">800.6 &#177; 680.3<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Uppercase compares means between different time points within one treatment group and location (Farm 1, Farm 2, or in total); lowercase compares means between different treatment groups at one time point and one location. Different letters indicate significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). EO, essential oil; EPG, eggs per gram.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Graph 3</label><caption><p>The mean number of eggs per gram at different time points in <italic toggle="yes">Mentha x piperita</italic> L. essential oil treatment groups. Uppercase compares means between different time points within one location and lowercase between two farms at the same time point. Different letters indicate significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1232570-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec13"><label>3.4.</label><title>Toxicity studies</title><p>No side effects were noticed during clinical observation of the tested animals on Days 7 and 14 after the treatment. Similarly, values of hematological parameters did not change significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05) after EO administration (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). In the biochemical blood analyzes, the values of urea and creatinine were also similar on Day 14 compared to Day 0, whereas liver enzymes showed a significantly lower activity after treatment with <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO and albendazole (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>The effect of <italic toggle="yes">Mentha x piperita</italic> (L.) essential oil on serological parameters evaluating kidney and liver function in treated animals&#8211;in total from both examined farms.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urea (mg/dl)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Creatinine (mg/dl)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST (UI/l)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGT (UI/l)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Mentha piperita</italic> (L.) EO</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.3 &#177; 7.24<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9 &#177; 3.48<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225.2 &#177; 47.47<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.8 &#177; 8.01<sup>Aa</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.3 &#177; 3.93<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.5 &#177; 2.91<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156.8 &#177; 49.99<sup>Ba</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.0 &#177; 6.09<sup>Ba</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Albendazol (control +)</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.6 &#177; 9.45<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4 &#177; 2.75<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">173.3 &#177; 82.72<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.0 &#177; 8.86<sup>Aa</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.4 &#177; 6.07<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4 &#177; 3.68<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163.0 &#177; 50.72<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.5 &#177; 5.54<sup>Ba</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sunflower oil (control &#8211;)</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.8 &#177; 7.87<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4 &#177; 2.84<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189.7 &#177; 72.63<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.5 &#177; 7.82<sup>Aa</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.3 &#177; 4.91<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8 &#177; 3.04<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206.9 &#177; 56.32<sup>Aa</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.7 &#177; 5.30<sup>Aa</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Uppercase compares means between values at different time points within one treatment group and lowercase values at the same time points between different treatment groups. Different letters indicate significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05); AST, aspartate aminotransferase; GGT, gamma-glutamyltransferase; EO, essential oil.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec14"><label>3.5.</label><title>Coproculture</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="tab5" ref-type="table">Tables 5</xref>, <xref rid="tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>, four sheep GIN genera were identified in varying proportions on the two farms examined: <italic toggle="yes">Trichostrongylus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Teladorsagia</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Haemonchus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Chabertia</italic>. In total, their representation before treatment was 43.67, 39, 11, and 6.33% in Farm 1 and 44.33, 43.67, 10, and 2% in Farm 2. These percentages did not change significantly after treatment in any of the tested groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Percentage of sheep nematode third-stage larvae (L<sub>3</sub>) for each treatment group at D0, D7, and D14&#8211;Farm 1.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Trichostrongylus</italic> (%)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Teladorsagia</italic> (%)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Haemonchu</italic>s (%)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Chabertia</italic> (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D0</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D14</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Albendazole (control +)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D0</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D14</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Sunflower oil (control +)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D0</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D14</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>No statistically significant differences were found when comparing values in different time points within groups, nor when comparing values for different groups on the same day in any of the groups tested (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05); EO, essential oil.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Percentage of sheep nematode third-stage larvae (L<sub>3</sub>) for each treatment group at D0, D7, and D14&#8211;Farm 2.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Trichostrongylus</italic> (%)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Teladorsagia</italic> (%)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Haemonchu</italic>s (%)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Chabertia</italic> (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D0</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D14</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Albendazole (control +)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D0</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D14</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Sunflower oil (control +)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D0</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D7</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D14</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>No statistically significant differences were found when comparing values in different time points within groups, nor when comparing values for different groups on the same day in any of the groups tested (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05); EO, essential oil.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussions" id="sec15"><label>4.</label><title>Discussion</title><p>The urgent problem associated with the development and spread of AR in sheep GINs requires actively searching for alternative strategies, whereby botanical anthelmintics are considered one of the most promising options (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). However, finding the most suitable plant formulation among the wide number of species, both from an efficacy and safety point of view, as well as from the aspect of price, is a challenging task. Thus, EOs and extracts from a wide number of plants have been tested so far on the efficacy against sheep GINs, as discussed earlier (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). As can be noticed, most of these studies refer to <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> testing. Although these tests are appropriate for the initial evaluation of anthelmintic potential due to their speed, reproducibility, easy application, absence of animals, and price (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> tests and evaluation of safety are also crucial parts of the process of developing a new anthelmintic drug and are needed before the formulation is introduced into practice (<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). The choice of assays is also important, with the EHT and FECRT being recommended due to their accuracy and reliability. In fact, these tests are most commonly used for such studies (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>).</p><p>Considering the number of studies conducted so far and their results, the EO of <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> can be considered one of the potential candidates for the development of a new anthelmintic agent. Thus, in a study by Katiki et al. (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>), it showed significant activity against <italic toggle="yes">Haemonchus contortus</italic> on the EHT with an obtained IC<sub>50</sub> value of 0.26&#8201;mg/mL. Along with the ovicidal activity, EO also exhibited an effect on larval development and feeding with IC<sub>50</sub> values of 0.26 and 0.07&#8201;mg/mL, respectively. Next, a study by Chagas et al. (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>) has demonstrated moderate ovicidal (IC<sub>50</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;1.44&#8201;mg/mL) but high larvicidal (IC<sub>50</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;0.10&#8201;mg/mL) activity of the aforementioned EO, also against <italic toggle="yes">H. contortus</italic>. In our last study (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO showed a strong, dose-dependent (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#8201;=&#8201;0.98) activity against a mixture of sheep GIN genera (<italic toggle="yes">Hemonchus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Trichostrongylus</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Teladorsagia,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Chabertia</italic>) with an inhibition of egg hatchability varying from 72.5&#8211;99.8% (IC<sub>50</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;0.28&#8201;mg/mL) in the concentration range of 0.049&#8211;50&#8201;mg/mL. From that perspective, the results of the EHT in the present study showed a lower ovicidal effect of <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO, which may be attributed to the use of different EO samples in comparison with that study. In addition, in the present study, we used a different method to obtain concentrations (dilution method in comparison with micropipettes in the last study).</p><p>In the FECRT, the tested formulation (EO diluted in sunflower oil) exhibited an anthelmintic activity of 46.04% in total on Day 14 at the tested dose of 150&#8201;mg/kg (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). As in our study performed with oregano EO (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>), the efficacy was better in Farm 2 compared with Farm 1 (63.35 and 28.73%, respectively, on D14) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Graph 3</xref>), which can be explained by the differences in animal husbandry. That is, on the second farm, sheep were kept in boxes during the treatment, which facilitated the manipulation of animals and the application of formulations. In contrast, in the first farm, sheep were completely kept free-range. Other factors such as differences in feed (due to differences in animal husbandry), and consequently composition and volume of rumen content, may also affect the results. On the other hand, albendazole showed a high effect (&gt;95%) on both farms on Days 7 and 14, indicating that anthelmintic resistance did not develop in the tested farms. The lower efficacy of the tested sample compared with the positive control can be explained by interactions of phytochemicals along the gastrointestinal tract and thus their partial inactivation and consecutive limited bioavailability (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Next, the high standard deviation values of EPGs in both farms in all treatment groups suggest a large variation in the degree of parasite burden of individual animals. This is usually a characteristic of GINs, where the largest number of parasites accumulates in a smaller number of animals in certain herd (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). On the other hand, this suggests the importance of TST strategies during the treatments (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>).</p><p>According to the GC&#8211;MS analyzes, menthol and menthone were most responsible for the anthelmintic effect shown, as their percentage representations were 32.6 and 22.0%, respectively. Indeed, these two compounds are considered the most important for various pharmacological properties of <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO and its wide use (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). However, pure menthol failed to reduce the EPG of <italic toggle="yes">H. contortus</italic> during <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> testing. In contrast, the whole EO of <italic toggle="yes">M. arvensis</italic>, whose main component was menthol (86.7%), showed an efficacy of approximately 50% on Days 1, 14, and 21 (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). In other similar studies, whole EOs were also usually more effective than their isolated major components, as shown for <italic toggle="yes">Croton Zehtneri</italic> - anethole (<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>) and <italic toggle="yes">Thymus vulgaris</italic>&#8211;thymol (<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). This suggests the importance of all EO compounds for their activity, potentially due to their synergistic effect. The absence of an effect of pure menthol in mentioned research was explained by its limited bioavailability and by the fact that menthol is excreted in the form of glucuronides via urine (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>).</p><p>In comparison with the composition of <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO in our previous study (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), differences in the present compounds and their percentages may be observed. That is, the main compounds of that sample were piperitone (25.4%) and trans-dihidrocarvone (14.6%). In other mentioned studies, the chemical composition of <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO corresponds more to the sample of the present study. Thus, menthol (42.5%) followed by menthone (27.4%) were the main compounds of the sample in a study by Katiki et al. (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>), and menthol (30.5%) was also the main compound of the sample in a study by Chagas et al. (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). This suggests that the composition of EO may vary considerably, even among those obtained from the same plant species. From that aspect, various factors such as the age and part of the plant, geographical origin, precipitation, light, and soil properties that refer to pH, structure, and salinity, as well as the presence of various organisms and microorganisms in a plant environment may be involved. In addition, the methods used for the extraction of oils, the producers from whom the oils are sourced, and the way they were stored prior to their use may also affect chemical composition (<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). Consequently, these factors may also lead to smaller or larger differences in efficacies, as can be noticed if the results of the mentioned studies, including the present one, are compared. The question that arises is to what extent these variations may hinder the development of commercial preparation, and whether ways to standardize the composition of certain EOs should be a topic of further studies.</p><p>Despite their increasing popularity, one of the main problems associated with the wider use of EOs in practice appears to be the lack of toxicity studies (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Potential toxic and side effects of EOs and their constituents are usually tested in experimental animals such as rodents, whereas acute toxicity tests conducted so far in rats showed that most EOs have an LD<sub>50</sub> of 1&#8211;20&#8201;g/kg, indicating their low toxicity (<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). However, studies evaluating the effects on the host are rarely conducted. In the present study, the results of the preliminary toxicity tests showed the absence of side and toxic effects of <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO on sheep, i.e., their behavior, hematological parameters, as well as kidney and liver functions. This suggests the safety of the use of the applied formulation in sheep, at least when it comes to short-term effects. The same results were obtained for EO of lemongrass (<italic toggle="yes">Cymbopogon schoenanthus</italic> L.) applied to sheep (180 and 360&#8201;mg/kg, p.o.), and for the encapsulated combination of anethole and carvone applied to lambs (20 and 50&#8201;mg/kg, p.o.), with the absence of toxic effects on animal behavior, as well as liver and kidney functions, suggesting their safety (<xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>).</p><p>In a study by Chagas et al. (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>), no toxicity symptoms were observed in sheep treated with <italic toggle="yes">M. arvensis</italic> EO. This and the results of the present study may be considered to be expected since the main compound of both of these EOs, menthol, has very low acute oral toxicity (LD<sub>50</sub>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;2000&#8201;mg/kg b.w.) and is therefore generally recognized as safe by the FDA (U.S. Food and Drug Administration). Moreover, the FDA has approved the use of menthol in food (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="ref60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). According to the Assessment Report on <italic toggle="yes">Mentha x piperita</italic> L., <italic toggle="yes">folium</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">aetheroleum</italic> (<xref rid="ref61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>) can be safely used in humans at the recommended doses (oral, cutaneous, and inhalation) for the treatment of various gastrointestinal disorders or the symptomatic relief of mild tension-type headaches. However, although <italic toggle="yes">Mentha</italic> species are considered safe, special attention should be paid to the content of pulegone and menthofuran in the formulation due to their reported hepato-toxicity (<xref rid="ref62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="ref63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). Thus, according to the Public Statement on the use of herbal medicinal products containing pulegone and menthofuran (<xref rid="ref64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>), the intake of their combination in 37.5&#8201;mg/person/day in humans is considered acceptable for herbal-medicinal products, which is set up as a limit for a life-long exposure. Such studies should be provided for animals including sheep.</p><p>The results of the coproculture examination showed the presence of four GIN genera before the treatment on the tested farms: <italic toggle="yes">Trichostrongylus</italic> (44%), <italic toggle="yes">Teladorsagia</italic> (41.33%), <italic toggle="yes">Haemonchus</italic> (10.5%), and <italic toggle="yes">Chabertia</italic> (4.17%). Since their percentage representation did not change significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05) after the treatment, it can be concluded that the treatment with <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO is not specific for only a single genus. However, the results of some other studies showed higher activity of EOs against <italic toggle="yes">H. contortus</italic> in comparison with <italic toggle="yes">Trichostrongylus</italic> spp. after per-oral administration of the formulations (<xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>), suggesting that there may be differences in sensitivity on EOs within the GIN genera (e.g., due to their position in the gastrointestinal tract). Anyhow, the mechanism of nematicidal activity of <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO compounds is still not fully elucidated. In a study by Choudhary et al. (<xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>), menthol was shown to potentiate acetylcholine and levamisole responses in the receptor sensitive to levamisol but not to nicotine. The same study also showed that menthol can significantly potentiate the contraction of <italic toggle="yes">Ascaris suum</italic> somatic muscle strips at each concentration of acetylcholine. A study by Khan et al. (<xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>) showed that methanol and the extract of <italic toggle="yes">M. arvensis</italic> cause high apoptotic effect in the muscles, gonads, and uterus (eggs) of the free-living nematode <italic toggle="yes">Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>, which was used as a model organism. The results also showed that stress genes (gst-4 and hsp-16.2) were highly expressed in the affected nematodes compared to normal <italic toggle="yes">C. elegans</italic>.</p><p>Although the applied oil significantly reduced the number of EPG after the treatment, with the achieved <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> efficacy being one of the highest obtained for EOs against GINs (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), it is still insufficient for its independent use. However, studies conducted so far showed that none of the aforementioned possible control methods appears to be sustainable when applied alone (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Thus, as discussed earlier, it is generally agreed that a combination of different strategies in the form of integrated parasite management is the only sustainable solution for long-term parasite control (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="ref70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>). An example is the results obtained in a mentioned study by Choudhary et al. (<xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>), where the positive allosteric modulatory properties of menthol were proven, which could be used in combination therapy with cholinergic anthelmintics.</p><p>From all the above, results obtained in the present study suggest that <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO can play a valuable role in an integrated approach to control parasites. In general, the use of botanical anthelmintics offers many advantages, such as their rich chemical composition with a lot of compounds belonging to different chemical groups (lower susceptibility to the development of resistance), their natural origin (lower amount of residues in animal products and the environment), suitable price, etc. (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). Moreover, <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> efficacy of <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO could be further improved with the use of an encapsulation technique that can protect its active ingredients from degradation, and thus enable their higher bioavailability (<xref rid="ref71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>, <xref rid="ref72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>). On the other hand, better results can also be achieved by increasing the dose or using multiple applications over several consecutive days instead of single administration although the use of a higher dose or multiple administration should also be evaluated from the toxic point of view. Efficacy can also be improved, as well as control release enabled by other ways of applications such as lick blocks that contain plant-based compounds, and may provide long-term use (<xref rid="ref73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec16"><label>5.</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>The development and spread of anthelmintic resistance in nematodes require an urgent search for alternatives. The results of the present study suggest that <italic toggle="yes">M. piperita</italic> EO is suitable for use against GINs in sheep based on the efficacy and preliminary toxicity tests performed. Therefore, in combination with other strategies (rational use of anthelmintics or other alternatives), the tested formulation could play a valuable role in an integrated, environmentally friendly control of these parasites. Further studies should be performed to confirm the safety after long-term use of peppermint oil in practice to achieve even higher efficacy in field trials, as well as to test its efficacy against GINs resistant to commercial drugs.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec17"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref>, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding authors.</p></sec><sec id="sec18"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The study was conducted according to the guidelines of the Declaration of Helsinki and approved by the Ethics Committee of the University of Naples (PG/2021/0130480, 16 December 2021). The studies were conducted in accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements. Written informed consent was obtained from the owners for the participation of their animals in this study.</p></sec><sec id="sec19"><title>Author contributions</title><p>F&#352;: conceptualization, methodology, formal analysis, investigation, data curation, and writing original draft preparation. SK: conceptualization, resources, and writing review and editing. DS: conceptualization, validation, and supervision. RR: conceptualization, methodology, and resources. NS: investigation, resources, and writing review and editing. DO: investigation and resources. LR: methodology, validation, writing review and editing, and supervision. EC: methodology and investigation. MM: methodology and validation. GC: validation and supervision. AB: conceptualization, methodology, investigation, data curation, and writing review and editing. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="sec20"><title>Funding</title><p>This research was cofounded by the Ministry of Education, Science, and Technological Development of the Republic of Serbia, rescript No. 451&#8211;03-1183/2021&#8211;14.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec21"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec100"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We deeply thank Mario Parrilla from CREMOPAR, Eboli (SA), Italy, for the technical support in the laboratory, as well as Katarina Ho&#269;evar from the Institute for Biological Research, Sini&#353;a Stankovi&#263;, University of Belgrade, Serbia, for the technical support during the production of the manuscript.</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec22"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2023.1232570/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2023.1232570/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_1.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Redman</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morosetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kulle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morden</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Seasonal epidemiology of gastrointestinal nematodes of cattle in the northern continental climate zone of western Canada as revealed by internal transcribed spacer-2 ribosomal DNA nemabiome barcoding</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>604</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-021-05101-w</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34895334</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8665551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abebe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yobsan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Debela</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of major gastrointestinal nematode and degree of parasite infestation in sheep of Bako agricultural research center community based breeding program project small holder farms at Horro district</article-title>. <source>Dairy Vet Sci J</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>555740</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.19080/JDVS.2018.08.555740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kie&#223;ler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amadesi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varady</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinney</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ianniello</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The threat of reduced efficacy of anthelmintics against gastrointestinal nematodes in sheep from an area considered anthelmintic resistance-free</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>457</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-020-04329-2</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32907633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7487796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castagna</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bava</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Musolino</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piras</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cardamone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carresi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Potential new therapeutic approaches based on <italic toggle="yes">Punica granatum</italic> fruits compared to synthetic anthelmintics for the sustainable control of gastrointestinal nematodes in sheep</article-title>. <source>Animals</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>2883</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani12202883</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36290268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9598348</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beleck&#279;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kup&#269;inskas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stadalien&#279;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#246;glund</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thamsborg</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stuen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anthelmintic resistance in small ruminants in the Nordic-Baltic region</article-title>. <source>Acta Vet Scand</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13028-021-00583-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33906690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8085717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szewc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Waal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zintl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Biological methods for the control of gastrointestinal nematodes</article-title>. <source>Vet J</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>268</volume>:<fpage>105602</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tvjl.2020.105602</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33468301</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Biology, epidemiology, diagnosis and management of anthelmintic resistance in gastrointestinal nematodes of livestock</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin N Am Food Anim Pract</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cvfa.2019.12.001</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32029182</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shalaby</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anthelmintic resistance; how to overcome it?</article-title><source>Iran J Parasitol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23682256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3655236</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Denwood</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thamsborg</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torgerson</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilleard</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>World Association for the Advancement of veterinary parasitology (W.a.a.V.P.) guideline for diagnosing anthelmintic resistance using the faecal egg count reduction test in ruminants, horses and swine</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>318</volume>:<fpage>109936</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2023.109936</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37121092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vinner</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hertzberg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartley</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charlier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Increasing importance of anthelmintic resistance in European livestock: creation and meta-analysis of an open database</article-title>. <source>Parasite</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5167/uzh-193329</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33277891</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7718593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fissiha</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kinde</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anthelmintic resistance and its mechanism: a review</article-title>. <source>Infect Drug Resist</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>5403</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S332378</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34938088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8687516</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mederos</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Banchero</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>First report of monepantel <italic toggle="yes">Haemonchus contortus</italic> resistance on sheep farms in Uruguay</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>598</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/PREACCEPT-1982759817140038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25515711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4305228</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Veerakumari</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Botanical anthelmintics</article-title>. <source>Asian J Scie Technol</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1881</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prakash</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pundir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prakash</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Documentation of commonly used ethnoveterinary medicines from wild plants of the high mountains in Shimla district, Himachal Pradesh</article-title>. <source>India Horticulturae</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>351</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/horticulturae7100351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Werne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isensee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maurer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drewek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heckendorn</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Integrated control of gastrointestinal nematodes in lambs using a bioactive feed &#215; breed approach</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>198</volume>:<fpage>298</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>304</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2013.09.021</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24183648</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maqbool</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wani</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahardar</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allaie</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Integrated parasite management with special reference to gastrointestinal nematodes</article-title>. <source>J Parasit Dis</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12639-016-0765-6</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28316380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5339188</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Velde</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charlier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Claerebout</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Farmer behavior and gastrointestinal nematodes in ruminant livestock - uptake of sustainable control approaches</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>255</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2018.00255</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30386785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6198092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bricarello</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Longo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Rocha</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#246;tzel</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Understanding animal-plant-parasite interactions to improve the management of gastrointestinal nematodes in grazing ruminants</article-title>. <source>Pahogens</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>531</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/pathogens12040531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10145647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37111417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maurizio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perrucci</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamponi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rinaldi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Control of gastrointestinal helminths in small ruminants to prevent anthelmintic resistance: the Italian experience</article-title>. <source>Parasitology</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>2023</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>14</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182023000343</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37039466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10801368</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hodgkinson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kenyon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Refugia and anthelmintic resistance: concepts and challenges</article-title>. <source>Int J Parasitol Drugs Drug Resist</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpddr.2019.05.001</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31125837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6531808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Calvete</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrer</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacasta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of targeted selective treatment criteria to control subclinical gastrointestinal nematode infections on sheep farms</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>277</volume>:<fpage>109018</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2019.109018</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31896020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Castro</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azambuja</surname><given-names>RHM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Capella</surname><given-names>GDA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Moura</surname><given-names>MQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Terto</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Ovicidal and larvicidal potential of <italic toggle="yes">Rosmarinus officinalis</italic> to control gastrointestinal nematodes of sheep</article-title>. <source>Rev Bras Parasitol Vet</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>807</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1984-29612019060</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31483032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castagna</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piras</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Musolino</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lupia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Green veterinary pharmacology applied to parasite control: evaluation of <italic toggle="yes">Punica granatum</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Artemisia campestris</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Salix caprea</italic> aqueous macerates against gastrointestinal nematodes of sheep</article-title>. <source>Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>237</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vetsci8100237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34679067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8539373</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teoh</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Secondary metabolites of plants</article-title>. <source>Med Orchids Asia</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>59</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-24274-3_5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>&#352;trbac</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krnjaji&#263;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stojanovi&#263;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Novakov</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Botanical control of parasites in veterinary medicine</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marcelino</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Younus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saeed</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group>, editors. <source>One health Triad</source>, vol. <volume>3</volume>. <publisher-loc>Faisalabad, Pakistan</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Unique Scientific Publishers</publisher-name> (<year>2023</year>). <fpage>215</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castagna</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cringoli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nistic&#242;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caligiuri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Use of complementary natural feed for gastrointestinal nematodes control in sheep: effectiveness and benefits for animals</article-title>. <source>Animals</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1037</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani9121037</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31783538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6941046</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhatti</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kayani</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Plant secondary metabolites: therapeutic potential and pharmacological properties</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vijayakumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raja</surname><given-names>SSS</given-names></name></person-group>, editors. <source>Secundary metabolites</source>. <publisher-loc>United Kingdom</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Intechopen</publisher-name> (<year>2022</year>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mutinelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Veterinary medicinal products to control <italic toggle="yes">Varroa destructor</italic> in honey bee colonies (<italic toggle="yes">Apis mellifera</italic>) and related EU legislation &#8211; an update</article-title>. <source>J Apic Res</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>78</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00218839.2016.1172694</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mucha</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Witkowska</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The applicability of essential oils in different stages of production of animal-based foods</article-title>. <source>Molecules</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>3798</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules26133798</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34206449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8270267</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>&#352;trbac</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrovi&#263;</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stojanovi&#263;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ratajac</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Possibilities and limitations of the use of essential oils in dogs and cats</article-title>. <source>Vet J Rep Srp</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>238</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7251/VETJEN2101238S31</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bava</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castagna</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Musolino</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carresi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cardamone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phytochemical profile of <italic toggle="yes">Foeniculum vulgare</italic> subsp. piperitum essential oils and evaluation of acaricidal efficacy against <italic toggle="yes">Varroa destructor</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">Apis mellifera</italic> by <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and semi-field fumigation tests</article-title>. <source>Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>684</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vetsci9120684</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36548845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9784571</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andr&#233;</surname><given-names>WPP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>WLC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>LMB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macedo</surname><given-names>ITF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rondon</surname><given-names>FCR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bevilaqua</surname><given-names>CML</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Essential oils and their bioactive compounds in the control of gastrointestinal nematodes of small ruminants</article-title>. <source>Acta Sci Vet</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>14</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22456/1679-9216.81804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>&#352;trbac</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pu&#353;i&#263;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stojanovi&#263;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cringoli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The use of essential oils against sheep gastrointestinal nematodes</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saleemi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group>, editors. <source>Animal health perspectives. Volume I</source>. <publisher-loc>Faisalabad, Pakistan</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Unique Scientific Publishers</publisher-name> (<year>2022</year>). <fpage>86</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shabih</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajdari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mustafa</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quave</surname><given-names>QL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Medicinal plants in the Balkans with antimicrobial properties</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chassagne</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>, editor. <source>Medicinal plants as anti-Infectives</source>. <publisher-loc>United States</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name> (<year>2022</year>). <fpage>103</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaia</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cagnazzo</surname><given-names>TDO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feitosa</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faccioli</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allegretti</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anti-inflammatory properties of menthol and menthone in <italic toggle="yes">Schistosoma mansoni</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>Front Pharmacol</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>170</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphar.2016.00170</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27378927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4911957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ostadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Javanmard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Machiani</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morshedloo</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nouraein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasouli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of different fertilizer sources and harvesting time on the growth characteristics, nutrient uptakes, essential oil productivity and composition of <italic toggle="yes">Mentha x piperita</italic> L</article-title>. <source>Ind Crop Prod</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>148</volume>:<fpage>112290</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.indcrop.2020.112290</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katiki</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bizzo</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>JFS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amarantee</surname><given-names>AFT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anthelmintic activity of <italic toggle="yes">Cymbopogon martinii</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Cymbopogon schoenanthus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Mentha piperita</italic> essential oils evaluated in four different in vitro tests</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>183</volume>:<fpage>103</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2011.07.001</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21820807</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chagas</surname><given-names>ACC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Figueiredo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Politi</surname><given-names>FAS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moro</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esteves</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bizzo</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of essential oils from plants cultivated in the Amazonian biome against gastrointestinal nematodes in sheep</article-title>. <source>J Parasit Dis</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>357</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12639-018-1007-x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30166782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6104224</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>&#352;trbac</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maurelli</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ratajac</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stojanovi&#263;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Anthelmintic properties of essential oils to control gastrointestinal nematodes in sheep&#8212;in vitro and in vivo studies</article-title>. <source>Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani13010045</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35202346</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8880401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kne&#382;evi&#263;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aleksi&#263;</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Svir&#269;ev</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrovi&#263;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mimica-Duki&#263;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial activity of <italic toggle="yes">Eucalyptus camaldulensis</italic> essential oils and their interactions with conventional antimicrobial agents against multi-drug resistant <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></article-title>. <source>J Ethnopharmacol</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>178</volume>:<fpage>125</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jep.2015.12.008</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26671210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>&#352;trbac</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krnjaji&#263;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maurelli</surname><given-names>MPM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stojanovi&#263;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Or&#269;i&#263;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A potential anthelmintic phytopharmacological source of <italic toggle="yes">Origanum vulgare</italic> (L.) essential oil against gastrointestinal nematodes of sheep</article-title>. <source>Animals</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani13010045</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36611652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9817997</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Identification of essential oil components by gas chromatography/mass spectrometry</source>. <edition>4th</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Carol Stream, IL</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Allured Business Media</publisher-name> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maurelli</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ianniello</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgoglione</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amadesi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The recovery of added nematode eggs from horse and sheep faeces by three methods</article-title>. <source>BMC Vet Res</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12917-017-1326-7</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29304858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5756441</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cringoli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maurelli</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levecke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vercruysse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Utzinger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The Mini-FLOTAC technique for the diagnosis of helminth and protozoan infections in humans and animals</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1723</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2009.235</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28771238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll1">Ministry of Agriculture</collab></person-group>. <source>Fisheries and food (MAFF). Grande-Bretagne, manual of veterinary parasitological laboratory techniques</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>HM Stationery Off</publisher-name> (<year>1986</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Wyk</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayhew</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Morphological identification of parasitic nematode infective larvae of small ruminants and cattle: a practical lab guide</article-title>. <source>Onderstepoort J Vet Res</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>80</volume>:<fpage>539</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4102/ojvr.v80i1.539</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23718204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borgsteede</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geerts</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klei</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>World association for the advencement of veterinary parasitology (W.a.a.V.P.) methods for the detection of anthelmintic resistance in nematodes of veterinary importance</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source>. (<year>1992</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0304-4017(92)90141-U</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1441190</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benincasa</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fachin</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Contini</surname><given-names>SHT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fran&#231;a</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chagas</surname><given-names>ACS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Essential oils of <italic toggle="yes">Citrus aurantifola</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Anthemis nobile</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Lavandula officinalis</italic>: in vitro anthelmintic activities against Haemonchus contortus</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>269</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-018-2849-x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29695271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5918559</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sangster</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Besier</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodgate</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Geometric means provide a biased efficacy result when conducting a faecal egg count reduction test (FECRT)</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>161</volume>:<fpage>162</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2008.12.007</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19135802</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>DGL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>FDA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Plants and their medicinal potential for controling gastrointestinal nematodes in ruminants</article-title>. <source>Nematoda</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e92016</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4322/nematoda.00916</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soren</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of in vitro and in vivo anthelmintic efficacy of <italic toggle="yes">Cyperus compressus</italic> Linn., a traditionally used anthelmintic plant in parasite-animal models. Future</article-title>. <source>J Pharm Sci</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>126</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s43094-020-00148-552</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Panda</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daemen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahoo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luyten</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Essential oils as novel anthelmintic drug candidates</article-title>. <source>Molecules</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>8327</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules27238327</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36500419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9735941</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Camur&#231;a-Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>ALF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bevilaqua</surname><given-names>CML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morais</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maciel</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>CTC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macedo</surname><given-names>ITF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Anthelmintic activity of <italic toggle="yes">Croton zehtneri</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Lippia sidoides</italic> essential oils</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>148</volume>:<fpage>288</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2007.06.012</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17629623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benincasa</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fachin</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fran&#231;a</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Contini</surname><given-names>SSHT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chagas</surname><given-names>ACS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Thymus vulgaris</italic> L. essential oil and its main component thymol: anthelmintic effects against <italic toggle="yes">Haemonchus contortus</italic> from sheep</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>228</volume>:<fpage>70</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2016.08.011</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27692335</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Factors affecting chemical variability of essential oils: a review of recent developments</article-title>. <source>Nat Prod Commun</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>1147</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>54</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1934578X0900400827</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19769002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fokou</surname><given-names>JBH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dongmo</surname><given-names>PMJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyom</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Essential oil&#8217;s chemical composition and pharmacological properties</article-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Shemy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>, editor. <source>Essential Oils&#8211;Oils of Nature</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IntechOpen</publisher-name> (<year>2020</year>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vostinaru</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heghes</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Filip</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. &#8220;<article-title>Safety profile of essential oils</article-title>&#8221; In <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>MS</given-names><prefix>de</prefix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>WA</given-names><prefix>da</prefix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Essential oils - bioactive compounds, new perspectives and applications</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IntechOpen</publisher-name>. (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katiki</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chagas</surname><given-names>ACS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahira</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juliani</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>JFS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amarante</surname><given-names>AFT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of <italic toggle="yes">Cymbopogon schoenanthus</italic> essential oil in lambs experimentally infected with <italic toggle="yes">Haemonchus contortus</italic></article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>186</volume>:<fpage>312</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2011.12.003</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22206645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katiki</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Araujo</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ziegelmeyer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>ACP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gutmanis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of encapsulated anethole and carvone in lambs artificially- and naturally-infected with <italic toggle="yes">Haemonchus contortus</italic></article-title>. <source>Exp Parasitol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>197</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exppara.2019.01.002</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30633915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll2">FDA Food and Drug Administration</collab></person-group>. <italic toggle="yes">Food additive status list</italic>. (<year>2014</year>). <comment>Available at:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.fda.gov/Food/IngredientsPackagingLabeling/FoodAdditivesIngredients/ucm091048.htm" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.fda.gov/Food/IngredientsPackagingLabeling/FoodAdditivesIngredients/ucm091048.htm</ext-link>. (Accessed May 15, 2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll3">European Medicines Agency</collab></person-group>. <italic toggle="yes">Assessment report on Mentha x piperita L., folium and aetheroleum</italic>. (<year>2020</year>). <comment>Available at:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/documents/herbal-report/assessment-report-mentha-x-piperita-l-folium-aetheroleum-revision-1_en.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/documents/herbal-report/assessment-report-mentha-x-piperita-l-folium-aetheroleum-revision-1_en.pdf</ext-link> (Accessed May 15, 2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moorthy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madyastha</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madyastha</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hepatotoxicity of pulegone in rats: its effects on microsomal enzymes, in vivo</article-title>. <source>Toxicology</source>. (<year>1989</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>327</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>37</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0300-483X(89)90022-X</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2541521</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khojasteh</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oishi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The metabolism and toxicity of menthofuran in rat liver slices and in rats</article-title>. <source>Chem Res Toxicol</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>1824</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/tx100268g</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20945912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2981629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll4">European Medicines Agency</collab></person-group>. <italic toggle="yes">Public statement on the use of herbal medicinal products containing pulegone and menthofuran</italic>. (<year>2016</year>). <comment>Available at:</comment><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/documents/scientific-guideline/public-statement-use-herbal-medicinal-products-containing-pulegone-menthofuran-revision-1_en.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ema.europa.eu/en/documents/scientific-guideline/public-statement-use-herbal-medicinal-products-containing-pulegone-menthofuran-revision-1_en.pdf</ext-link> [Accessed May 15, 2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Camur&#231;a-Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>ALF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bevilaqua</surname><given-names>CML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morais</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maciel</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>CTC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macedo</surname><given-names>ITF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Anthelmintic activity of <italic toggle="yes">Lippia sidoides</italic> essential oil on sheep gastrointestinal nematodes</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>154</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2008.02.023</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18423877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andr&#233;</surname><given-names>WPP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>WLC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavalcante</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>JML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macedo</surname><given-names>ITF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Paula</surname><given-names>HCB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative efficacy and toxic effects of carvacryl acetate and carvacrol on sheep gastrointestinal nematodes and mice</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>218</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2016.01.001</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26872928</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Macedo</surname><given-names>ITF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>LMB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andre</surname><given-names>WBP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Filho</surname><given-names>JVA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>JML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rondon</surname><given-names>FCM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Anthelmintic effect of <italic toggle="yes">Cymbopogon citratus</italic> essential oil and its nanoemulsion on sheep gastrointestinal nematodes</article-title>. <source>Rev Bras Parasitol Vet</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>522</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1984-29612019065</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31483036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choudhary</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marijanovi&#263;</surname><given-names>&#272;S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abongwa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coats</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Menthol acts as a positive allosteric modulator on nematode levamisole sensitive nicotinic acetylcholine receptors</article-title>. <source>Int J Parasitol Drugs Drug Resist</source>. (<year>2019</year>):<fpage>44</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpddr.2018.12.005</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30682641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6352305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>NU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sajid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bibi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehman</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alanazi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdellatif</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nematicidal characterization of <italic toggle="yes">Solanum nigrum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Mentha arvensis</italic> leaf extracts using <italic toggle="yes">Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> as a model organism</article-title>. <source>ACS Omega</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>9454</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsomega.2c08124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36936282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10018721</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoste</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torres-Acosta</surname><given-names>JFJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Non chemical control of helminths in ruminants: adapting solutions for changing worms in a changing world</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>180</volume>:<fpage>144</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>54</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2011.05.035</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21705144</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mesquita</surname><given-names>MDA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>J&#250;nior</surname><given-names>JBES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panassol</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>ALCF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Paula</surname><given-names>HCB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Anthelmintic activity of <italic toggle="yes">Eucalyptus staigeriana</italic> encapsulated oil on sheep gastrointestinal nematodes</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>112</volume>:<fpage>3161</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-013-3492-2</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23783400</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouquillion</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fauconnier</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Encapsulation of essential oils for the development of biosourced pesticides with controlled release: a review</article-title>. <source>Molecules</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>2539</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules24142539</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31336803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6680563</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Junkuszew</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milerski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bojar</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szczepaniak</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Scouarnec</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomczuk</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of various antiparasitic treatments on lamb growth and mortality</article-title>. <source>Small Rumin Res</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>123</volume>:<fpage>306</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smallrumres.2014.11.019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>