<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12263357</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC12263357.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">12263357</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">12263357</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40671822</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2025.1561144</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Characterization of the vitrification parameters for oviduct aggregates in <italic toggle="yes">Camelus dromedarius</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Sokary</surname><given-names initials="MMM">Mohamed M. M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/736601/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/resources/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/visualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Albreiki</surname><given-names initials="HA">Hamad A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shehata</surname><given-names initials="SF">Seham F.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names initials="KGM">Karima Gh. M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1232518/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Theriogenology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Benha University</institution>, <addr-line>Benha</addr-line>, <country>Egypt</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Faculty of Health Sciences, Higher Colleges of Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Abu Dhabi</addr-line>, <country>United Arab Emirates</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Animal Wealth Development, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Benha University</institution>, <addr-line>Benha</addr-line>, <country>Egypt</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Department of Animal Reproduction and Artificial Insemination, Veterinary Research Institute, National Research Centre</institution>, <addr-line>Giza</addr-line>, <country>Egypt</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0001"><p>Edited by: Guangbin Zhou, Sichuan Agricultural University, China</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0002"><p>Reviewed by: Seham Samir Soliman, National Research Centre, Egypt</p><p>Davide Monaco, University of Bari Aldo Moro, Italy</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Mohamed M. M. El-Sokary, <email>Mohamed.alsokary@fvtm.bu.edu.eg</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>02</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">480746</issue-id><elocation-id>1561144</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>6</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>02</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>16</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-07-17 23:25:17.153"><day>17</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2025 El-Sokary, Albreiki, Shehata and Mahmoud.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><copyright-holder>El-Sokary, Albreiki, Shehata and Mahmoud</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-12-1561144.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Camel oviductal isthmus aggregates provide a novel and promising model for studying sperm attachment and longevity, offering a potential alternative for short-to mid-term sperm preservation and transport under non-cryogenic conditions. Effective cryopreservation of the aggregates for later use can contribute to addressing challenges associated with camel semen preservation by potentially extending sperm lifespan and facilitating semen transport to remote areas without cryogenic facilities. Challenges in preserving the structural integrity and viability of camel oviductal aggregates remain a key critical gap during cryopreservation. This study evaluated the efficiency of vitrification protocols for camel oviductal isthmus aggregates, focusing on the effects of aggregate size, cryoprotectants (CPA), cryodevices, post-thaw viability, and sperm-binding capacity.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Aggregates retrieved from the oviductal isthmus were classified into four size groups (50, 100, 150, and 200 &#956;m) and vitrified to determine the influence of size on post-thaw outcomes. CPA concentrations (3, 5, and 7 M) of DMSO and EG in a 1:1 ratio were tested for their impact on structural integrity and viability. The performance of cryodevices, including cryovials, 0.5 mL straws, and 0.25 mL straws, was also assessed.</p></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><p>The results indicated that aggregates sized 150 &#956;m and 200 &#956;m demonstrated superior post-thaw viability, with intactness rates of 78 &#177; 2.0% and 83 &#177; 2.8%, respectively. Among the tested CPA concentrations, 7 M showed the highest post-vitrification viability (69 &#177; 1.9%). Additionally, 0.25 mL straw cryodevice achieved significantly better post-thaw viability (67 &#177; 2.7%) compared to 0.5 mL straws (32 &#177; 2.1%) and cryovials (10 &#177; 1.1%). Regarding sperm-binding capacity post-thaw, aggregates treated with 5 M (69 sperm) and 7 M (74) CPAs showed the highest binding rates, with no significant difference between these concentrations. Further studies are required to optimize vitrification protocols to enhance the aggregate&#8217;s post-vitrification viability and structural integrity.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>isthmus</kwd><kwd>cryoprotectant</kwd><kwd>cryodevice</kwd><kwd>camel</kwd><kwd>reproductive biotechnology</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn1">Higher Colleges of Technology, Abu Dhabi</funding-source><award-id award-type="contract" rid="cn1">267779</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that financial support was received for the research and/or publication of this article. This study was funded by the Higher Colleges of Technology, Abu Dhabi, as part of an Applied Research Project (Grant Number 267779).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="32"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="6978"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Animal Reproduction - Theriogenology</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>The dromedary camel (<italic toggle="yes">Camelus dromedarius</italic>) holds significant cultural, economic, and recreational value in the Middle East, playing vital roles in milk and meat production, racing, and show competitions (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Reproductive performance in this species remains a significant challenge, with fertility issues affecting both males and females. Low conception rates and male infertility are widespread concerns, limiting overall reproductive efficiency (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). One of the major limitations in advancing camel reproductive management is the incomplete understanding of the physiological mechanisms underlying fertility, particularly in the context of gamete interaction and embryo development (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). These challenges are further complicated by the difficulty of preserving camel semen, which is an essential component of assisted reproductive technologies. Maintaining semen viability and fertilizing capacity during extended storage remains a major obstacle, hindering the broader implementation of artificial insemination programs (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Given these reproductive challenges, understanding the microenvironment where fertilization occurs is essential.</p><p>The oviduct, recognized as the site of fertilization, plays a critical role in ensuring reproductive success across various animal species. The oviduct exhibits a remarkable capacity to support sperm survival, particularly within the isthmus, or &#8220;sperm nest.&#8221; Sperm can be stored within the oviduct of swine and cattle for approximately 24 to 48&#8239;h, while in other vertebrate and invertebrate species, sperm storage may extend to several days or even months (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>).</p><p>Oviductal cell aggregates have been adopted as an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> model to closely mimic the oviduct&#8217;s physiological environment and allow investigation of sperm behavior under conditions that resemble those <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). These aggregates are highly comparable to the <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> oviduct in their three-dimensional architecture and microenvironmental features, including cell&#8211;cell interactions, secretory activity, and spatial organization. Such characteristics make them an ideal platform for exploring sperm attachment, motility, and survival (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Supporting this approach, Dutta et al. (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) demonstrated that co-incubation of bovine sperm with bovine oviductal cell aggregates <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> significantly extended sperm lifespan, emphasizing the potential of this model to preserve sperm viability.</p><p>However, despite these advances, a critical knowledge gap persists regarding the effective cryopreservation of camel oviductal isthmus aggregates, particularly how to preserve their structural integrity and biological functionality post-thaw to maintain their utility as a model for sperm preservation and fertility studies. To address this gap, the preservation of these cell aggregates has become an essential focus in cellular biology. Techniques adapted from stem cell and oncology research, such as the freezing of spheroids, have been employed to ensure the availability and readiness of these models for experimentation (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). By maintaining their three-dimensional structure and biological functionality post-preservation, these aggregates serve as a versatile and reliable tool for studying cellular behavior and advancing reproductive biology research.</p><p>In this context, the application and refinement of cryopreservation methodologies are essential to achieving successful preservation outcomes, particularly in the field of reproductive biotechnology. Cryopreservation is a cornerstone technique in reproductive and cellular biology, enabling the long-term storage and availability of biological materials such as cells, tissues, and aggregates for research and clinical applications (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Various methods, including conventional freezing, programmable slow freezing, and vitrification, have been developed to preserve cellular integrity and functionality. Vitrification has emerged as a superior technique due to its ability to achieve higher cell survival rates (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Among cryopreservation methods, vitrification has gained prominence due to its rapid cooling and improved cell survival. Given its advantages, vitrification represents a particularly promising approach for the cryopreservation of camel oviductal aggregates, providing a methodological basis for the current investigation on the success of cryopreservation.</p><p>Vitrification is an ultra-rapid cooling method that prevents ice crystal formation by solidifying cells into a glass-like state through direct exposure to liquid nitrogen and high concentrations of cryoprotectants (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Unlike slow freezing, vitrification maintains cellular integrity by avoiding intracellular ice, which is particularly damaging to the delicate structure of mammalian oocytes (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Its effectiveness is linked to the ability of high CPA concentrations to induce osmotic dehydration, minimizing cryo-injury during cooling and warming. Moreover, vitrification has become the method of choice in many species due to improved post-warming morphology and developmental potential.</p><p>The success of vitrification, however, depends on several critical factors that must be carefully optimized. These factors include the type, concentration, and permeability of the cryoprotectant agent (CPA) used, such as dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO), glycerol, ethylene glycol, and propylene glycol, as well as the type of cryodevice (cryovials, straws, and cryotop) employed during the process (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). In addition to these parameters, the size and structural integrity of the aggregates are critical factors influencing cryosurvival, with careful handling and gentle pipetting significantly enhancing post-thaw recovery (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Furthermore, the efficiency of a freezing protocol can be assessed through various methods, such as evaluating cell viability, membrane integrity, and mitochondrial function. Yet, beyond these immediate assessments, the ultimate measure of success lies in the ability of the frozen cells to resume their normal physiological capabilities after thawing, with minimal damage to their structure and function (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). These factors collectively determine the preservation of structural integrity and viability post-thaw.</p><p>Therefore, this study aimed to assess the efficacy of a vitrification protocol for camel oviductal isthmus aggregates by optimizing cryoprotectant concentration, evaluating the suitability of cryodevices, and determining the impact of aggregate size on post-thaw outcomes such as viability, structural integrity, and sperm-binding capacity, thereby supporting future research on sperm-oviduct interactions in camels.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec3"><label>2.1</label><title>Ethical considerations</title><p>This study was conducted in accordance with ethical guidelines and approved by the Research Ethics and Integrity Committee at the Higher Colleges of Technology, under Approval Number REIC2024-FAC35. All experimental procedures adhered to institutional and international standards for the ethical use of biological materials in research and animal welfare.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>2.2</label><title>Chemicals</title><p>All chemicals were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich unless otherwise stated.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>2.3</label><title>Animals and sample collection</title><p>The study was conducted from September to November 2024. The samples for this study were collected from a local slaughterhouse in the Al Ain region, Abu Dhabi. Testes and their attached epididymides were obtained from 23 mature dromedary camels, aged between 5 and 10&#8239;years, at a local slaughterhouse. A total of 46 testes were collected over eight separate collections. Only testes that appeared normal in size, color, and consistency, with no visible lesions or abnormalities, were included in the study. Immediately following slaughter, the samples were placed in phosphate-buffered saline containing antibiotics (penicillin and streptomycin) and transported to the laboratory in a temperature-controlled container maintained at 4&#176;C within 1 to 2&#8239;h.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><label>2.4</label><title>Experimental design</title><p>This study was composed of five sequential experiments designed to systematically optimize key parameters influencing the cryopreservation of camel oviduct explant aggregates. The effects of aggregate size, cryoprotectant concentration, and cryodevice type on post-thaw viability, structural integrity, and reproductive functionality were evaluated. Each experiment built upon the findings of the previous one to enable stepwise refinement of vitrification conditions. Experiment 1 evaluated the impact of aggregate size on viability; Experiments 2 and 3 assessed the effects of cryoprotectant concentration on structural integrity and viability, respectively; Experiment 4 compared different cryodevices; and Experiment 5 examined the sperm-binding ability of thawed aggregates.</p><sec id="sec7"><label>2.4.1</label><title>Experiment 1: effect of aggregate size on post-thaw viability</title><p>This experiment aimed to identify the most suitable aggregate size for successful cryopreservation, hypothesizing that aggregate size influences cryosurvival due to factors such as cryoprotectant penetration and ice formation. Aggregates were categorized into four size groups: 50&#8239;&#956;m, 100&#8239;&#956;m, 150&#8239;&#956;m, and 200&#8239;&#956;m in diameter. Vitrification was performed using 0.25&#8239;mL straws. Post-thaw viability was assessed using SYBR14/PI dual staining, allowing differentiation between live and dead cells.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><label>2.4.2</label><title>Experiment 2: effect of CPA concentration on structural integrity</title><p>This experiment was conducted after determining the optimal aggregate size, focusing on optimizing CPA concentration to minimize cryo-injury and preserve the three-dimensional structure critical for aggregate function. The objective of this experiment was to evaluate the impact of varying CPA concentrations on the structural preservation of vitrified aggregates. Aggregates were exposed to three CPA concentrations&#8212;3&#8239;M, 5&#8239;M, and 7&#8239;M&#8212;consisting of dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) and ethylene glycol (EG) in a 1:1 ratio. Post-thaw structural integrity was analyzed to identify the concentration that best maintained aggregate morphology and cohesion.</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><label>2.4.3</label><title>Experiment 3: effect of CPA concentration on post-thaw viability</title><p>This experiment aimed to establish the relationship between CPA concentration and cellular survival, determining the most suitable concentration for optimal viability. By evaluating viability alongside structural integrity, this step refined the CPA concentration choice to balance toxicity and cryoprotection. This experiment investigated the influence of CPA concentration (3&#8239;M, 5&#8239;M, and 7&#8239;M) on aggregate viability post-thaw. SYBR14/PI dual staining was performed to assess live and dead cell populations.</p></sec><sec id="sec10"><label>2.4.4</label><title>Experiment 4: influence of cryodevice type on post-thaw viability</title><p>The fourth experiment was designed to compare the performance of different cryodevices in maintaining post-thaw aggregate viability. Three cryodevice types&#8212;cryovials, 0.5&#8239;mL straws, and 0.25&#8239;mL straws&#8212;were tested under identical vitrification and warming conditions. Post-thaw viability was evaluated to determine which cryodevice offered the most effective cryopreservation outcomes.</p></sec><sec id="sec11"><label>2.4.5</label><title>Experiment 5: effect of CPA concentration on post-thaw sperm-binding ability</title><p>Based on the vitrification parameters identified in the previous experiments (the aggregate size, the CPA concentration, and the cryodevice), this experiment aimed to evaluate the impact of the CPA concentration on the capacity of oviduct aggregates to bind to sperm after thawing. Thawed aggregates were incubated with epididymal sperm, and the binding ability was assessed by quantifying the number of sperm bound to the aggregates. This experiment provided insights into how varying CPA concentrations influence the sperm-binding competence of vitrified aggregates post-thaw.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec12"><label>2.5</label><title>Retrieval of the epithelial cells from the oviduct</title><p>Oviducts were collected from apparently healthy pubertal female camels aged 4&#8211;8&#8239;years old (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;10) slaughtered at a local abattoir and transported on ice to the laboratory at Higher Colleges of Technology, Abu Dhabi. The oviduct epithelial cells were collected and prepared at the laboratory according to El-Sokary et al. (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Isolation of oviductal epithelial sheets from the isthmus involved gently squeezing them out with a glass slide angled at 45 degrees. The collected sheets were then transferred to a 15&#8239;mL conical tube and pelleted via centrifugation at 100 &#215; g for 30&#8239;s. The supernatant was decanted, and the pellet was resuspended in 1&#8239;mL of capacitating TALP medium. Disaggregation was initiated by aspirating and expelling the suspension 10 times through a 1&#8239;mL pipette tip. The partially separated cells were then washed with 5&#8239;mL of fresh TALP and re-centrifuged at 100 &#215; g for 1&#8239;min. After discarding the supernatant, the cells were re-suspended in an additional 1&#8239;mL of TALP. Complete disaggregation was achieved by passing the suspension through a 23-gauge needle 10 times. The total volume was then brought to 9&#8239;mL with TALP and equally aliquoted (3&#8239;mL each) into three 100-mm petri dishes and incubated at 39&#176;C for 90&#8239;min to allow cells to re-aggregate.</p></sec><sec id="sec13"><label>2.6</label><title>Aggregate selection and size measurement</title><p>After retrieval of oviduct tissue, aggregates were produced as described in the previous section. The resulting aggregates were washed three times by gentle pipetting in pre-warmed TALP medium to ensure their structural stability and viability during handling. Aggregates were then visually inspected under a stereo microscope (magnification: &#215;40&#8211;100) to identify and select those with clear, intact morphology (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Aggregates were categorized into four size groups: 50&#8239;&#956;m, 100&#8239;&#956;m, 150&#8239;&#956;m, and 200&#8239;&#956;m in diameter (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>). To ensure accurate size measurement, aggregates were imaged using a digital microscope with calibrated imaging software (ImageJ). Diameters were measured across the widest part of the aggregates, and only those within the defined size ranges were included in the experiments. A total of 30 aggregates per size group were selected for observation in each experimental replicate.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Effect of aggregate size on post-thaw viability of oviduct aggregates. <bold>(A)</bold> Column graph illustrating the post-thaw viability (%) of oviduct aggregates of varying sizes: 50&#8239;&#956;m, 100&#8239;&#956;m, 150&#8239;&#956;m, and 200&#8239;&#956;m. Columns with different letters denote statistically significant differences among the groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05). <bold>(B)</bold> Representative microscopic images of oviduct aggregates of different diameters (50&#8239;&#956;m, 100&#8239;&#956;m, 150&#8239;&#956;m, and 200&#8239;&#956;m). Scale bar&#8239;=&#8239;50&#8239;&#956;m.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1561144-g001.jpg"><alt-text content-type="machine-generated">Graph A shows post-thawing viability percentages for different aggregate sizes: 50 &#181;m (60%), 100 &#181;m (near 70%), 150 &#181;m, and 200 &#181;m (near 80% each). Images B display microscopic views of aggregates of sizes 200 &#181;m, 150 &#181;m, 100 &#181;m, and 50 &#181;m, outlined in red, showing their structures.</alt-text></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="sec14"><label>2.7</label><title>Vitrification and warming by straw and cryovial methods</title><p>Oviduct aggregates were exposed to two-step cryoprotectant treatments at varying concentrations as illustrated in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The holding medium used during vitrification contained TCM 199 supplemented with 2.5&#8239;mM HEPES and 20% fetal calf serum. For cryovial vitrification, oviduct aggregates (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#8239;=&#8239;5&#8211;10) were transferred into 1.5&#8239;mL cryovials (Nunc, Rochester, MN, United States) and directly plunged into liquid nitrogen (LN2) (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). In the case of straw vitrification, the aggregates were immediately loaded into 0.25&#8239;mL or 0.5&#8239;mL straws, placed in the middle column of VS2, and separated by air bubbles. The straws were sealed with straw plugs and pre-cooled by exposure to liquid nitrogen (LN2) vapor at approximately 4&#8239;cm above the LN2 surface for at least 60&#8239;s before being vertically immersed in LN2 for storage for 2&#8239;weeks. Straws were transferred rapidly in less than 5&#8239;s through the air to avoid structural damage (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) and then placed in a water bath at 35&#8211;37&#176;C for 20&#8239;s for warming. Following warming, the expelled oviduct aggregates were equilibrated for 5&#8239;min in a 0.5&#8239;M galactose solution (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) in TCM 199 to dilute and remove cryoprotectants. Oviduct aggregates were then washed 4&#8211;5 times in a fresh washing medium and cultured in a warm TCM medium for 2&#8239;h.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Two-step cryoprotectant treatments applied to oviduct aggregates at varying concentrations.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CPA concentration</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 1 (VS1)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exposure time</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 2 (VS2)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exposure time</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#8239;M</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75&#8239;M EG&#8239;+&#8239;0.75&#8239;M DMSO</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#8239;s</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5&#8239;M EG&#8239;+&#8239;1.5&#8239;M DMSO</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#8239;s</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#8239;M</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25&#8239;M EG&#8239;+&#8239;1.25&#8239;M DMSO</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#8239;s</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5&#8239;M EG&#8239;+&#8239;2.5&#8239;M DMSO</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#8239;s</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#8239;M</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75&#8239;M EG&#8239;+&#8239;1.75&#8239;M DMSO</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#8239;s</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5&#8239;M EG&#8239;+&#8239;3.5&#8239;M DMSO</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25&#8239;s</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec15"><label>2.8</label><title>Assessment of the structural integrity of aggregates following vitrification</title><p>The structural integrity of the aggregates was evaluated post-vitrification and warming using phase-contrast microscopy (&#215;100&#8211;200 magnification). Aggregates were assessed for compactness, shape, surface characteristics, and overall cohesion to determine their quality (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). The evaluation of the aggregates is categorized as shown in <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Morphological grading criteria for post-thaw oviductal cell aggregates.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade A (high quality)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aggregates in this category exhibited a compact and rigid structure with no loose cells in the surrounding medium, reflecting strong cell adhesion and cohesion. The surface was smooth and intact, indicating healthy cellular connections. Morphologically, they maintained a spherical and uniform shape with consistent size, presenting a well-defined three-dimensional (3D) architecture that closely mimicked natural cellular interactions (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figures 4II,A</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade B (moderate quality)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aggregates were generally compact and retained their spherical shape; however, minor surface irregularities and occasional deviations in size were observed. A few loose cells were present in the surrounding medium, indicating moderate cell cohesion and a slight reduction in overall quality (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figures 4II,B</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade C (low quality)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aggregates displayed noticeable looseness with partially detached cells and irregular, inconsistent shapes. Variability in size and a lack of surface uniformity were also noted, reflecting compromised cell cohesion and structural integrity (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figures 4II,C</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade D (poor quality)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aggregates exhibited severe structural disintegration, characterized by significant cell detachment and highly irregular, non-spherical shapes. The surface appeared rough and damaged, and the 3D architecture was severely disrupted, making them unsuitable for further analysis (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figures 4II,D</xref>)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec16"><label>2.9</label><title>Evaluation of viability in vitrified oviduct aggregates</title><p>To evaluate aggregate viability, SYBR-14 (1&#8239;&#956;M) was added to the aggregate suspension and incubated for 10&#8239;min in a dark room to allow sufficient staining of the viable cells. Following this incubation, propidium iodide (PI, 1&#8239;&#956;M) was introduced to the suspension and incubated for an additional 5&#8239;min. PI is a vital stain that can only penetrate the membranes of non-viable aggregates and emits a red fluorescence. In contrast, SYBR-14 stains the DNA of viable aggregates, producing a green fluorescence (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). The stained aggregates were then examined under a fluorescence microscope to visually differentiate between viable and non-viable aggregates based on the distinct green and red fluorescence patterns (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2C</xref>,<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">I&#8211;IV</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Impact of cryoprotectant (CPA) concentration and cryodevice type on post-thaw viability of oviduct aggregates. <bold>(A)</bold> Column graph illustrating the effect of CPA concentrations (3&#8239;M, 5&#8239;M, and 7&#8239;M) on post-thaw viability percentage of oviduct aggregates. Columns with different letters denote statistically significant differences among the groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;&#8239;0.05). <bold>(B)</bold> Column graph demonstrates the influence of cryodevice type (cryovials, midi-straws, and mini-straws) on post-thaw viability percentage. Columns with different letters denote statistically significant differences among the groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;&#8239;0.05). <bold>(C)</bold> Fluorescence microscopy images evaluating aggregate viability using SYBR-14 (green; live cells) and PI (red; dead cells) staining. <bold>(C,I)</bold> Control group. <bold>(C,II)</bold> 7&#8239;M CPA. <bold>(C,III)</bold> 5&#8239;M CPA. <bold>(C,IV)</bold> 3&#8239;M CPA. Scale bar&#8239;=&#8239;50&#8239;&#956;m.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1561144-g002.jpg"><alt-text content-type="machine-generated">Graph A shows post-thawing viability percentages in different CPAs concentrations: Control (100%), 3M (low), 5M (medium), 7M (high). Graph B displays viability in different cryodevices: Control (100%), cryovial (low), 0.5 ml straw (medium), 0.25 ml straw (high). Images C I-IV depict fluorescent microscopy of samples showing varying levels of green and red fluorescence, indicating different viability levels.</alt-text></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="sec17"><label>2.10</label><title>Epididymal sperm processing and preparation</title><p>Testes with epididymis were carefully separated and transported to the laboratory on chilled (approximately 4&#176;C) physiological saline solution (0.9% NaCl) to minimize potential damage during transport. Upon arrival at the laboratory, the testes and epididymis were meticulously separated using sterile dissection techniques. The epididymides were then thoroughly rinsed with a sterile 0.9% saline solution to remove any residual blood or debris. Subsequently, the epididymal tissue underwent a brief dip in 70% ethyl alcohol for surface disinfection. The epididymis was incised to allow for the collection of sperm, which was subsequently examined [modified from Rashad et al. (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>)]. The epididymal sperm was evaluated for motility and viability, and aliquoted for further use.</p></sec><sec id="sec18"><label>2.11</label><title>Assay of sperm binding to oviduct epithelial cells</title><p>The sperm-binding assay was carried out according to the methodology described by Winters et al. (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), with minor modifications as reported by El-Sokary et al. (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Briefly, 20 oviduct cell explants were combined with 20&#8239;&#956;L sperm droplets (1.6&#8239;&#215;&#8239;10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL) and the assay was performed in triplicate. Before incubation, sperm were stained with MitoTracker Green (1&#8239;&#956;M) and allowed to stand for 10&#8239;min at room temperature in the dark room to ensure optimal staining. The stained sperm were then incubated with thawed oviduct cell aggregates at 39&#176;C for 30&#8239;min. The experiment was independently replicated 3 times to ensure reproducibility. Each experimental condition utilized 30 oviductal aggregates, and following the incubation, unattached and loosely bound spermatozoa were carefully removed by washing with TALP medium. The number of spermatozoa bound to the periphery of each oviduct aggregate was subsequently quantified to estimate the binding capacity (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3B</xref>,<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">I,II</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Effect of cryoprotectant (CPA) concentrations on sperm binding to post-thaw aggregates. <bold>(A)</bold> Number of sperm bound to oviduct aggregates following post-thawing across CPA concentrations (3&#8239;M, 5&#8239;M, and 7&#8239;M). Columns with different letters denote statistically significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05). <bold>(B)</bold> Fluorescence microscopy images illustrating sperm binding to oviduct aggregates. <bold>(B,I)</bold> Viable and intact aggregate post-thawing with sperm stained using MitoTracker Green. Yellow arrows and &#8220;X&#8221; indicate attached sperm. <bold>(B,II)</bold> Disintegrated aggregate post-thawing, with most cells stained with PI (red; dead) while few cells were stained with SYBR-14 (green; live), indicating extensive post-thaw damage and the absence of sperm binding. Scale bar&#8239;=&#8239;50&#8239;&#956;m.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1561144-g003.jpg"><alt-text content-type="machine-generated">Chart A shows the number of bound sperm decreasing with increasing CPA concentration, marked A, B, and C. Image B features two panels: the left shows clustered orange-red structures, while the right displays a green structure with highlighted areas and arrows.</alt-text></graphic></fig></sec><sec id="sec19"><label>2.12</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Statistical analysis was performed separately for each experiment using one-way ANOVA to evaluate the effect of a single independent factor within each experiment (as in the experimental design). Tukey&#8217;s post-hoc test was used for multiple comparisons in each analysis, using IBM SPSS Statistics (version 22). A <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value of less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant. All experiments were independently repeated three times to confirm reproducibility. Data distribution was assessed for normality before analysis. Results are expressed as the mean &#177; standard error of the mean (SEM).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec20"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec21"><label>3.1</label><title>Experiment 1: effect of aggregate size on post-thaw viability</title><p>The post-thaw viability of oviduct cell aggregates was significantly influenced by aggregate size. Aggregates with a diameter of 50&#8239;&#956;m exhibited the lowest viability, with a mean value of 64.31&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.33%. In the 100&#8239;&#956;m group, viability increased to 70&#8239;&#177;&#8239;2.3% (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05). A further increase in aggregate size to 150&#8239;&#956;m resulted in a higher viability of 78&#8239;&#177;&#8239;2.0% (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05), while the 200&#8239;&#956;m group achieved the highest viability at 83&#8239;&#177;&#8239;2.8% (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05). No statistically significant difference was observed between the 150&#8239;&#956;m and 200&#8239;&#956;m groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&gt;&#8239;0.05), indicating a plateau in post-thaw viability at these larger sizes (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>). However, both the 150&#8239;&#956;m and 200&#8239;&#956;m groups demonstrated significantly higher viability compared to the 100&#8239;&#956;m group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05), which itself was significantly higher than the 50&#8239;&#956;m group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05).</p></sec><sec id="sec22"><label>3.2</label><title>Experiment 2: effect of CPA concentration on structural integrity</title><p>The results of Experiment 2 are presented in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4I</xref>. The concentration of cryoprotectant agents (CPA) significantly affected the post-thaw structural integrity of oviduct cell aggregates, as indicated by the distribution of Grades A, B, C, and D.</p><fig position="float" id="fig4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Effect of cryoprotectant (CPA) concentration on post-thaw structural integrity of oviduct aggregates. <bold>(I)</bold> Column graph showing the post-thaw soundness (%) of oviduct aggregates treated with CPA concentrations of 3&#8239;M, 5&#8239;M, and 7&#8239;M. Columns with asterisks denote statistically significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05). <bold>(II)</bold> Representative microscopic images illustrating different grades of aggregate structural integrity (Grades A to D). Scale bar&#8239;=&#8239;50&#8239;&#956;m.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-12-1561144-g004.jpg"><alt-text content-type="machine-generated">A bar chart labeled "Post thawing soundness %" shows the effects of different CPA concentrations (Control, 3 M, 5 M, 7 M) on grades A, B, C, and D. Grades are color-coded, with various levels of significance indicated by asterisks. Below the chart, four images labeled A, B, C, D depict microscopic views of cells under different CPA concentrations, showing variations in cell integrity and structure.</alt-text></graphic></fig><p>In the control group, Grade A aggregates were the most abundant (64&#8239;&#177;&#8239;2.1%), significantly higher than Grade B (20&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.3%), Grade C (6&#8239;&#177;&#8239;3.3%), and Grade D (10&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.8%) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05). Grade B was also significantly higher than Grade C and Grade D (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05). When exposed to 3&#8239;M CPA, Grade A aggregates dropped sharply to 1&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.13%, while Grade D aggregates increased substantially to 73&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.3%, becoming the most dominant. Grades B and C were 2&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.5% and 24&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.19%, respectively. Grade D was significantly higher than Grade C, and Grade C was significantly higher than Grades A and B (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05).</p><p>At 5&#8239;M CPA, Grade A aggregates increased slightly to 7&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.2%, while Grade D decreased to 58&#8239;&#177;&#8239;3.1%. Grades B and C were 13&#8239;&#177;&#8239;2.4% and 22&#8239;&#177;&#8239;2.6%, respectively. Grade D was significantly higher than all other grades. Grade C was significantly higher than Grade B, and Grade B was significantly higher than Grade A (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05). At 7&#8239;M CPA, Grade A increased further to 9&#8239;&#177;&#8239;0.57%, and Grade D decreased to 47&#8239;&#177;&#8239;4.1%. Grades C and B were 27&#8239;&#177;&#8239;2.7% and 17&#8239;&#177;&#8239;2.1%, respectively. Grade D remained significantly higher than all other grades. Grade C was significantly higher than Grade B, and Grade B was significantly higher than Grade A (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05).</p></sec><sec id="sec23"><label>3.3</label><title>Experiment 3: effect of CPA concentration on post-thaw viability</title><p>The results of Experiment 3 are presented in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>. The effect of CPA concentration on the post-thaw viability of oviduct cell aggregates was evaluated across four experimental groups: control, 3&#8239;M, 5&#8239;M, and 7&#8239;M. The 3&#8239;M group showed a dramatic reduction in viability to 20&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.5% (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05 compared to all other groups. Viability significantly improved in the 5&#8239;M group, with 60&#8239;&#177;&#8239;3.7% of aggregates retaining their viability post-thaw (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05) compared to 3&#8239;M) demonstrating a marked enhancement with an increased CPA concentration. The 7&#8239;M group exhibited further significant improvement, reaching 69&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.9% viability (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05) compared to 5&#8239;M.</p></sec><sec id="sec24"><label>3.4</label><title>Experiment 4: influence of cryodevice type on post-thaw viability</title><p>The results of Experiment 3 are shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>. Post-thaw viability of oviduct aggregates was significantly affected by the type of cryodevice used. In the control group, viability was high at 93&#8239;&#177;&#8239;4.3% (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05). Among the cryopreserved groups, aggregates frozen in cryovials had the lowest viability at 10&#8239;&#177;&#8239;1.1% (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05). Viability improved in the 0.5&#8239;mL straw group, reaching 32&#8239;&#177;&#8239;2.1%, which was significantly higher than in cryovials (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05). The highest viability among cryopreserved samples was observed in the 0.25&#8239;mL straw group, with 67&#8239;&#177;&#8239;2.7%, which was significantly greater than both the cryovial and 0.5&#8239;mL straw groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05).</p></sec><sec id="sec25"><label>3.5</label><title>Experiment 5: effect of CPA concentration on post-thawing sperm binding ability to oviduct aggregates</title><p>The effect of CPA concentration on post-thaw sperm-binding ability was evaluated across four experimental groups: control, 3&#8239;M, 5&#8239;M, and 7&#8239;M. In the control group, the number of sperm bound to the oviduct aggregates was highest, with an average of 92 bound sperm, significantly higher than all CPA-treated groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05). Among the CPA-treated groups, the 3&#8239;M concentration resulted in the lowest sperm-binding ability, with an average of 25&#8239;sperm bound per aggregate (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8239;&lt;&#8239;0.05). In contrast, the 5&#8239;M and 7&#8239;M concentrations demonstrated significantly higher sperm-binding abilities (compared to 3&#8239;M group), with averages of 69 and 74 bound sperm, respectively. However, no significant difference was observed between the 5&#8239;M and 7&#8239;M groups. Statistical analysis confirmed that both 5&#8239;M and 7&#8239;M concentrations were significantly higher than the 3&#8239;M group. These findings suggest that CPA concentration affects sperm-binding ability, with higher concentrations (5&#8239;M and 7&#8239;M) maintaining better binding efficiency compared to the 3&#8239;M group (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec26"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>This study evaluated the effects of aggregate size, cryoprotectant concentration, and cryodevice type on the structural integrity, post-thaw viability, and sperm-aggregate binding ability of oviduct aggregates, contributing to a better understanding of factors influencing cryopreservation outcomes. The results demonstrated a significant influence of aggregate size on post-thaw viability, with viability improving as aggregate size increased up to 150&#8239;&#956;m. However, the plateau observed between the 150&#8239;&#956;m and 200&#8239;&#956;m groups suggests that additional increases in size do not further enhance viability, potentially due to diffusion limitations of cryoprotectants or increased thermal gradients.</p><p>Furthermore, CPA concentration played a pivotal role in maintaining structural integrity post-thaw. As CPA concentration increased from 3&#8239;M to 7&#8239;M, a gradual improvement in the proportion of Grade A aggregates was observed. This indicates that higher CPA concentrations can mitigate osmotic and ice crystal damage by stabilizing cellular membranes and intracellular structures (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). However, the concurrent increase in Grade D aggregates across all CPA-treated groups highlights the potential cytotoxicity associated with cryoprotectants at suboptimal concentrations.</p><p>Cryoprotectants (CPAs), particularly at the high concentrations used in vitrification, can impact mammalian cells by affecting membrane integrity and cellular metabolism. Agents like dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) and ethylene glycol effectively prevent ice formation but may cause osmotic stress and oxidative damage if exposure is prolonged or not well controlled. Moreover, the evaluation of sperm-binding ability revealed a concentration-dependent effect of CPAs. The reduced binding observed at 3&#8239;M suggests compromised aggregate functionality. The improved viability observed at the 150&#8239;&#956;m aggregate size underscores its importance in cryosurvival. These findings align with previous studies emphasizing the role of aggregate structure in preserving cellular integrity during cryopreservation (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).</p><p>The observed increase in Grade A aggregates with higher CPA concentrations, despite some cytotoxic effects, supports previous insights into cryoprotectant dynamics. These results are consistent with earlier findings on the balance between cryoprotective efficacy and cytotoxic effects of CPAs (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Increasing CPA concentration from 3&#8239;M to 7&#8239;M improved post-thaw viability, reflecting better protection against ice crystallization and osmotic shock (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Although viability in the 7&#8239;M group was slightly lower than controls, this is likely due to mild residual CPA toxicity rather than substantial harm. This underscores the delicate balance between achieving cryoprotection and minimizing cytotoxicity, highlighting the importance of optimizing CPA concentration and exposure duration to maintain cell survival and function (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). In this study, the combination of EG and DMSO appeared beneficial in improving post-thaw outcomes. However, previous studies reported mixed findings. Yadav et al. (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) found no advantage in combining DMSO with EG, and (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) reported similar results when using either 20% EG or 20% DMSO individually.</p><p>The superior viability associated with the 0.25&#8239;mL straws highlights how cryodevice choice shapes post-thaw outcomes. The higher viability observed in 0.25&#8239;mL straws may be attributed to their ability to facilitate faster and more uniform cooling and warming rates, which are critical for minimizing intracellular ice formation and osmotic stress (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Conversely, the lower viability in cryovials (1.5&#8239;mL) is likely due to their larger volume and slower cooling rates, which can exacerbate cryo-induced damage (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). The findings emphasize the importance of cryodevice selection in cryopreservation protocols, particularly for sensitive biological materials like oviduct aggregates. However, vitrification in 0.25-ml straws causes a delay in heat loss from the solutions, possibly leading to devitrification, i.e., intracellular recrystallization during warming (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). This apparent contradiction may be due to differences in sample composition, cryoprotectant penetration, or technical variations in the handling and warming steps.</p><p>The CPA concentration-dependent improvement in sperm binding reinforces the link between structural integrity and functionality. This is consistent with Parnpai et al. (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), who reported that a strong indicator of cryopreservation success is the ability of thawed cells to restore normal physiological function with minimal structural damage. The reduced binding rate is likely due to structural and membrane damage or alterations in the surface receptors essential for sperm interaction. The improved binding at 5&#8239;M and 7&#8239;M highlights the protective effects of optimal CPA concentrations in preserving the structural integrity of oviduct aggregates. However, the lack of significant difference between these two concentrations indicates a plateau in functional recovery, which mirrors the trends observed in viability. These findings highlight the intricate balance between maintaining structural integrity and preserving functional capabilities during cryopreservation (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>).</p><p>Efficient vitrification and recovery of the aggregates may support the development of more refined <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> fertilization protocols, improve sperm selection strategies, and serve as biological carriers for oviductal secretions that influence fertilization (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). The successful vitrification protocol of the aggregates offers different practical applications, including but not limited to their importance as a promising tool for studying sperm-oviduct interactions under near-physiological conditions, particularly in species like camels, where <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> studies are limited.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec27"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, this study demonstrates that aggregate size, cryoprotectant concentration, and cryodevice type significantly affect post-thaw viability, structural integrity, and sperm-binding ability of oviduct cell aggregates. Specifically, increasing aggregate size up to 150&#8239;&#956;m improves viability, with no further benefit observed at 200&#8239;&#956;m. Cryoprotectant concentration exhibits a clear dose-dependent effect: low levels (3&#8239;M) result in poor viability and structural damage, whereas higher concentrations (7&#8239;M) substantially enhance viability and preserve sperm-binding function. Among the cryodevices tested, the 0.25&#8239;mL straw outperforms both cryovials and 0.5&#8239;mL straws, achieving the highest post-thaw viability. Based on our findings, we recommend cryopreserving oviduct cell aggregates approximately 150&#8239;&#956;m in diameter using a 7&#8239;M cryoprotectant concentration and 0.25&#8239;mL straw cryodevices to achieve optimal preservation outcomes. This optimized protocol offers a reliable model for the cryopreservation of oviduct aggregates, with promising applications in reproductive biology research and fertility preservation.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec28"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be made available by the authors, without undue reservation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="sec29"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The animal study was approved by Research Ethics and Integrity Committee under Approval Number REIC2024-FAC35. The study was conducted in accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="sec30"><title>Author contributions</title><p>ME-S: Conceptualization, Data curation, Investigation, Methodology, Project administration, Resources, Software, Supervision, Validation, Visualization, Writing &#8211; original draft, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. HA: Investigation, Methodology, Writing &#8211; original draft, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. SS: Data curation, Formal analysis, Methodology, Software, Writing &#8211; original draft, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing. KM: Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec32"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ai-statement" id="sec33"><title>Generative AI statement</title><p>The authors declare that no Gen AI was used in the creation of this manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec34"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kandeel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morsy</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd El-Lateef</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marzok</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Beltagi</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Khodair</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A century of &#8220;camel research&#8221;: a bibliometric analysis</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1157667</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1157667</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37323832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10267326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Derar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alsharari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alsharari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Almundarij</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Factors affecting reproductive performance in dromedary camel herds in Saudi Arabia</article-title>. <source>Trop Anim Health Prod</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>1155</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11250-018-1545-3</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29450815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tibary</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anouassi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sghiri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khatir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Current knowledge and future challenges in camelid reproduction</article-title>. <source>Soc Reprod Fertil Suppl</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>313</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5661/rdr-vi-297</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17491155</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Bulushi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manjunatha</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bathgate</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rickard</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Graaf</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Liquid storage of dromedary camel semen in different extenders</article-title>. <source>Anim Reprod Sci</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>207</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>106</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anireprosci.2019.06.008</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31208848</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>WV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fazeli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The oviduct as a complex mediator of mammalian sperm function and selection</article-title>. <source>Mol Reprod Dev</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>934</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mrd.21234</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20886635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Sokary</surname><given-names>MMM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shehata</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>KGM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Heparin and progesterone exert synergistic effects to improve the <italic toggle="yes">in-vitro</italic> fertilization rate of bovine sperm bound to oviduct cell aggregates from the isthmus</article-title>. <source>Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>372</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vetsci9070372</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35878389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9318521</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Sokary</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Naby</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sosa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nawito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>New insights into molecular aspects of sperm-oviductal binding in Egyptian buffaloes using an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> model: effects of oviductal segments and media</article-title>. <source>Andrologia</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>e13984</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/and.13984</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33565139</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doungkamchan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiemeyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bovin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sulfated Lewis A trisaccharide on oviduct membrane glycoproteins binds bovine sperm and lengthens sperm lifespan</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>294</volume>:<fpage>13445</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.RA119.007695</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31337705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6737213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehrhart</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katsen-Globa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shirley</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A comparative study of freezing single cells and spheroids: towards a new model system for optimizing freezing protocols for cryobanking of human tumours</article-title>. <source>Cryobiology</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>119</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cryobiol.2008.11.005</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19094979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shajib</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Futrega</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>RAG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenna</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guillesser</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A tumour-spheroid manufacturing and cryopreservation process that yields a highly reproducible product ready for direct use in drug screening assays</article-title>. <source>J R Soc Interface</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>20230468</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsif.2023.0468</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37817581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10565407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Igor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Vitrification for cryopreservation of 2D and 3D stem cells culture using high concentration of cryoprotective agents</article-title>. <source>BMC Biotechnol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12896-020-00636-9</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32843026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7449025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fahy</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Vitrification: a new approach to organ cryopreservation</article-title>. <source>Prog Clin Biol Res</source>. (<year>1986</year>) <volume>224</volume>:<fpage>305</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3540994</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Purohit</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Survival of vitrified water buffalo cumulus oocyte complexes and their subsequent development <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic></article-title>. <source>Bulg J Vet Med</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>KGM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Sokary</surname><given-names>MMM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scholkamy</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abou El-Roos</surname><given-names>MEA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sosa</surname><given-names>GAM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nawito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of cryodevice and cryoprotectant concentration on buffalo oocytes vitrified at MII stage</article-title>. <source>Anim Reprod</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>689</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>96</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Uhrig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ezquer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ezquer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Improving cell recovery: freezing and thawing optimization of induced pluripotent stem cells</article-title>. <source>Cells</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>799</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cells11050799</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35269421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8909336</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parnpai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ketudat-Cairns</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Somfai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Vitrification of buffalo oocytes and embryos</article-title>. <source>Theriogenology</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>214</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2016.04.034</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27160442</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winters</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nettenstrom</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willenburg</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vishwanath</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bovin</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of sorting boar spermatozoa by sex chromosomes on oviduct cell binding</article-title>. <source>Theriogenology</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>108</volume>:<fpage>22</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2017.11.010</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29182943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Subramaniam</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Devarajan</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohanan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Incidence and avoidance of zona fracture in cryopreserved bovine ova and embryos</article-title>. <source>N Z Vet J</source>. (<year>1990</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>156</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00480169.1990.35643</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16031603</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seidel</surname><given-names>GE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>. <article-title>Vitrification of bovine oocytes after treatment with cholesterol-loaded methyl-beta-cyclodextrin</article-title>. <source>Theriogenology</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>1026</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2006.03.004</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16620935</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bissoyi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tom&#225;s</surname><given-names>RMF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cryopreservation of liver-cell spheroids with macromolecular cryoprotectants</article-title>. <source>ACS Appl Mater Interfaces</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>2630</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsami.2c18288</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36621888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9869333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garner</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Viability assessment of mammalian sperm using SYBR-14 and propidium iodide</article-title>. <source>Biol Reprod</source>. (<year>1995</year>) <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>276</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1095/biolreprod53.2.276</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7492679</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rashad</surname><given-names>DEM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Sokary</surname><given-names>MMM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>KGM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abou El-Roos</surname><given-names>MEA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sosa</surname><given-names>GAM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Abundance of selected genes implicated in testicular functions in <italic toggle="yes">Camelus dromedarius</italic> with high and low epididymal semen quality</article-title>. <source>Biol Reprod</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>110</volume>:<fpage>501</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/biolre/ioad177</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38145478</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brockbank</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Vitrification: preservation of cellular implants</article-title> In: <source>Encyclopedia of biomaterials and biomedical engineering</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Marcel Dekker</publisher-name> (<year>2003</year>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blomsma</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Midwoud</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fahy</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Groothuis</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Graaf</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of cryoprotectant addition and washout methods on the viability of precision-cut liver slices</article-title>. <source>Cryobiology</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>179</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>87</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cryobiol.2012.05.011</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22722061</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuwayama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vajta</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leibo</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Highly efficient vitrification method for cryopreservation of human oocytes</article-title>. <source>Reprod Biomed Online</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>300</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s1472-6483(10)60837-1</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16176668</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scholkamy</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seidel</surname><given-names>GE</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nawito</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of different combinations of cryoprotectants on <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> maturation of immature buffalo (<italic toggle="yes">Bubalus bubalis</italic>) oocytes vitrified by straw and open-pulled straw methods</article-title>. <source>Reprod Domest Anim</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>565</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1439-0531.2008.01293.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19090828</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Albarrac&#237;n</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morat&#243;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rojas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mogas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of vitrification in open pulled straws on the cytology of <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> matured prepubertal and adult bovine oocytes</article-title>. <source>Theriogenology</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>890</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>901</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2004.05.010</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15629805</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wani</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maurya</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lakhchaura</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of cryoprotectants and their concentration on <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> development of vitrified-warmed immature oocytes in buffalo (<italic toggle="yes">Bubalus bubalis</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Theriogenology</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>831</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2003.06.002</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14757469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gasparrini</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Attanasio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Rosa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monaco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Palo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campanile</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cryopreservation of <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> matured buffalo (<italic toggle="yes">Bubalus bubalis</italic>) oocytes by minimum volumes vitrification methods</article-title>. <source>Anim Reprod Sci</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>335</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anireprosci.2006.04.046</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16698202</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morat&#243;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Izquierdo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paramio</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mogas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cryotops versus open-pulled straws (OPS) as carriers for the cryopreservation of bovine oocytes: effects on spindle and chromosome configuration and embryo development</article-title>. <source>Cryobiology</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cryobiol.2008.07.003</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18680737</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meneghel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kilbride</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cryopreservation as a key element in the successful delivery of cell-based therapies&#8212;a review</article-title>. <source>Front Med</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>592242</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2020.592242</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33324662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7727450</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mah&#233;</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laffont</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pranomphon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmaltz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynaud</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mermillod</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of sperm binding capacity in the reservoir using an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> model of oviduct epithelial spheroids in cattle</article-title> In: <source>Spermatology: methods in molecular biology</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Humana</publisher-name> (<year>2025</year>). <fpage>687</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>98</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1007/978-1-0716-4406-5_47</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40202670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>