<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="brief-report" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10318142</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10318142.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10318142</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10318142</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37408832</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1170499</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Brief Research Report</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Emergence of novel porcine circovirus 2d strains in Thailand, 2019&#8211;2020</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sirisereewan</surname><given-names initials="C">Chaitawat</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2333390/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names initials="TC">Thanh Che</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2217999/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Janetanakit</surname><given-names initials="T">Taveesak</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kedkovid</surname><given-names initials="R">Roongtham</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2216347/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thanawongnuwech</surname><given-names initials="R">Roongroje</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c002" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/702078/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Veterinary Pathology, Faculty of Veterinary Science, Chulalongkorn University</institution>, <addr-line>Bangkok</addr-line>, <country>Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>The International Graduate Program of Veterinary Science and Technology, Faculty of Veterinary Science, Chulalongkorn University</institution>, <addr-line>Bangkok</addr-line>, <country>Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Center of Excellence for Emerging and Re-emerging Infectious Diseases in Animals and One Health Research Cluster, Faculty of Veterinary Science, Chulalongkorn University</institution>, <addr-line>Bangkok</addr-line>, <country>Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Department of Veterinary Medicine, Faculty of Veterinary Science, Chulalongkorn University</institution>, <addr-line>Bangkok</addr-line>, <country>Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Center of Excellence in Swine Reproduction, Chulalongkorn University</institution>, <addr-line>Bangkok</addr-line>, <country>Thailand</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Qi Wang, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, China</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Eunice M. Machuka, International Livestock Research Institute (ILRI), Kenya; Anbu K. Karuppannan, Tamil Nadu Veterinary and Animal Sciences University, India</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Roongtham Kedkovid <email>roongtham.k@chula.ac.th</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Roongroje Thanawongnuwech <email>roongroje.t@chula.ac.th</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">427755</issue-id><elocation-id>1170499</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>05</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>05</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-07-06 11:25:09.980"><day>06</day><month>07</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 Sirisereewan, Nguyen, Janetanakit, Kedkovid and Thanawongnuwech.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sirisereewan, Nguyen, Janetanakit, Kedkovid and Thanawongnuwech</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-10-1170499.pdf"/><abstract><p>Porcine circovirus 2 (PCV2) has been recognized as a causative agent of porcine circovirus diseases (PCVDs) affecting the global swine industry. In this study, the genetic diversity of PCV2 strains circulating in Thailand between 2019 and 2020 was investigated using 742 swine clinical samples from 145 farms. The results showed PCV2-positive rates of 54.2% (402/742) and 81.4% (118/145) at the sample and farm levels, respectively. Genetic analysis of 51 Thai PCV2 genomic sequences showed that 84.3% (43/51) was PCV2d, 13.7% (7/51) was PCV2b and 1.9% (1/51) was PCV2b/2d recombinant virus. Surprisingly, the majority of the Thai PCV2d sequences from this study (69.77%, 30/43) formed a novel cluster on a phylogenetic tree and contained a unique <sup>133</sup>HDAM<sup>136</sup> on the ORF2 deduced amino acid sequence, which is in one of the previously identified immunoreactive domains strongly involved in virus neutralization. The PCV2b/2d recombinant virus also carried <sup>133</sup>HDAM<sup>136</sup>. The emergence of the novel PCV2d strains predominating in Thailand was discussed. This study highlights the need for further investigations on the spreading of these PCV2d strains in other regions and the efficacy of current commercial vaccines.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>porcine circovirus 2</kwd><kwd>PCV2d</kwd><kwd>mutation</kwd><kwd>recombination</kwd><kwd>pigs</kwd><kwd>Thailand</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>This project was supported by the National Research Council of Thailand (NRCT): RT NRCT Senior scholar 2022 #N42A650553.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="27"/><page-count count="7"/><word-count count="4498"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Veterinary Infectious Diseases</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Porcine circovirus (PCV) 2, the causative agent of porcine circovirus diseases (PCVDs) affecting the global swine industry, is a non-enveloped single-stranded DNA virus containing a circular genome of 1766&#8211;1768 nucleotides (nt) (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>) containing three main open reading frames (ORFs). Replicase protein encoded by ORF1 (<italic toggle="yes">Rep</italic> gene) is essential for viral replication (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Capsid protein encoded by ORF2 (<italic toggle="yes">Cap</italic> gene) is a viral structural protein playing a significant role in the immunogenicity, virulence, and characteristics of the virus genotypes (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Finally, an ORF3 protein could induce apoptosis (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Since its discovery, PCV2 has been recognized as a viral pathogen with a significant economic impact on the pig industry in various regions, particularly in North America, Europe, and Asia (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>).</p><p>To date, PCV2 is classified into eight genotypes, PCV2a&#8211;h, based on the ORF2 nucleotide sequence (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). PCV2d is currently the predominant genotype worldwide (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), possibly due to selection pressure from the global PCV2 vaccination or the previously circulating PCV2 strains. In general, mutation at neutralizing epitopes might render the mutant virus less susceptible to the pre-existing antibodies (from vaccination or previously circulating viruses) (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Hence, a further genetic shift from the current PCV2d strains was not unexpected. In this study, novel variants of PCV2d with a unique mutation at a previously recognized immunoreactive domain on the ORF2 were identified and found to rapidly dominate in Thailand. This finding may raise awareness for further investigations on the spreading of these viruses in other regions and the cross-protection with current commercial vaccines.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>2. Materials and methods</title><sec><title>2.1. Clinical samples</title><p>A set of 742 swine clinical samples, each collected from a different pig, were retrieved from the sample repository of Chulalongkorn University, Veterinary Diagnostic Laboratory (CU-VDL) and Diagnostic Laboratory of Large Animal Hospital and Students Training Center (DLSTC). The samples were originally submitted to CU-VDL and DLSTC as part of routine diagnosis from January 2019 to December 2020. These samples were obtained from 145 swine farms located in 18 provinces across different geographical regions of Thailand, primarily in the high pig-density areas in the Western, Central, and Eastern parts (<xref rid="SM5" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>). The corresponding data of these samples were also obtained, including sample types, sample collection dates, age groups or statuses of the pigs, clinical signs, and farm locations.</p></sec><sec><title>2.2. PCV2 detection and DNA sequencing</title><p>Viral DNA was extracted from the clinical samples by using the IndiMag Pathogen kit of viral RNA/DNA (Indical Bioscience, Germany) on the automated extraction platform. The obtained DNA was stored at &#8722;80&#176;C until used.</p><p>For PCV2 detection, a real-time PCR assay was done using Luna<sup>&#174;</sup> Universal Probe qPCR master mix (NEB, MA, USA) with previously described protocol (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). The PCV2-PCR positive samples were further systematically selected for genetic characterization.</p><p>The sample selection process aimed to fulfill three criteria; (1) obtaining at least one PCV2 sequence from each of the six geographical regions of Thailand (the Northern, Northeastern, Central, Western, Eastern, and Southern regions), (2) including PCV2 sequences from both 2019 and 2020, and (3) acquiring a maximum of one PCV2 sequence from each individual pig. Whenever possible, samples with ct values lower than 30 during the PCV2 detection process were selected, to increase the likelihood of successful whole genome sequencing.</p><p>For genome sequencing, PCR amplicons were prepared and then submitted to the third-party sequencing company. The PCR assay was performed as previously described (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). The PCR reactions were done using Onetaq<sup>&#174;</sup> 2x Master Mix (NEB, MA, USA). The PCR products were examined by 1% agarose gels and purified using NucleoSpin&#8482; Gel and PCR Clean<italic toggle="yes">-</italic>up <italic toggle="yes">(</italic>MACHEREY-NAGEL, Germany<italic toggle="yes">)</italic>. The PCR products were then submitted to Celemics, Inc. (Seoul, Korea) for barcode-tagged sequencing. The obtained nucleotide sequences were assembled and validated with SeqMan and EditSeq software v.5.03 (DNASTAR Inc., Madison, Wisconsin, USA) and submitted to GenBank.</p></sec><sec><title>2.3. Sequence analysis</title><p>Classification of the Thai PCV2 sequences was done using a previously proposed phylogeny-based method (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). The Thai PCV2 sequences (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 51) were aligned with a set of PCV2a-h reference sequences (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 266, <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 1</xref>) (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). In total, 317 sequences were used for phylogenetic analysis. Phylogenetic trees were constructed based on the Neighbor-Joining (NJ) algorithm using p-distance data. The classification was separately done using the complete sequences of genomic, ORF1, and ORF2 data. The tree was also reconstructed using the Maximum Likelihood method with a sequence of PCV1 (GenBank accession number: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="KJ408798">KJ408798</ext-link>) as an outgroup to confirm the topology.</p><p>For the initial PCV2d sequence analysis, a phylogenetic tree of complete ORF2 sequences of Thai PCV2d from 2010 to 2020 was built (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 124). The data from 2010 to 2015 were retrieved from GenBank (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 73, <xref rid="SM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 2</xref>) and the data from 2019 to 2020 (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 51) were from this study. Nucleotide sequences were aligned and the phylogenetic tree was then constructed based on the NJ algorithm with the Maximum Composite Likelihood model (NJ-MCL method).</p><p>NCBI BLAST function (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov" ext-link-type="uri">https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link>) was performed using 19RBR58 ORF2 as a query sequence (6<sup>th</sup> February 2023) to retrieve sequences with high similarity from GenBank database for further PCV2d ORF2 analysis. The dataset was named 19RBR58/BLAST (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 440, <xref rid="SM3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 3</xref>). The non-redundant version of 19RBR58/BLAST (19RBR58/BLAST/NR, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 158) was used in phylogenetic analysis. A phylogenetic tree was constructed using NJ-MCL method.</p><p>Otherwise stated, all sequence alignment was done using the Clustal W algorithm (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) of BioEdit 7.2.5 (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Phylogenetic tree construction was done using MEGA version 10.2.6 (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) with bootstrap analysis of 1,000 replications.</p><p>Recombination analysis was carried out using Recombination Detection Program (RDP, version 4.22) (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Seven recombination detection methods were used; i.e., RDP, GENECOV, Bootscan, MaxChi, Chimera, SiScan, and 3Seq. A recombination event was accepted when it was detected by at least five methods with the <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01. Bonferroni correction was applied. In the final step, the identified recombinant virus was re-analyzed with SIMPLOT software v. 3.5 by Bootscan methods (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) and a direct PCR sequencing covering the recombination breakpoint.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>3. Results</title><sec><title>3.1. PCV2d is the major genotype in Thailand</title><p>PCV2 screening by real-time PCR was done on 742 pigs from 145 farms. The results are shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Overall, animal-level and farm-level positivity were 54.2% (402/742) and 81.4% (118/145), respectively. Fifty-one PCV2-positive samples (from 51 pigs) from 48 farms were genetically characterized. The nucleotide sequences were deposited in the NCBI GenBank database under accession no. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide-range" xlink:href="OL677572:OL677622">OL677572&#8211;OL677622</ext-link> (<xref rid="SM4" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 4</xref>). Phylogeny-based genotyping of the ORF2 data showed that the Thai strains were PCV2b and PCV2d (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>), found at 13.73% (7/51) and 84.31% (43/51), respectively (similar results were observed when ORF1 or genome data were used). However, one strain, 19NPT29, was not grouped within any genotype clusters. At the farm level, PCV2b and PCV2d were found at 14.58% (7/48) and 87.50% (42/48), respectively.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The prevalence of PCV2 in all tested samples during 2019&#8211;2020.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#8f9496"><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>Types of samples</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Prevalence at sample level</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Prevalence at farm level</bold>
</th></tr><tr style="background-color:#8f9496"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Periods</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Group of pigs<sup>&#8224;</sup></bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Pooled tissues</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Serum</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Feces</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Semen</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Oral fluids</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Colostrum</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Umbilical cords</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Positive rate</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Positive rate</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jan-Dec 2019</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suckling</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/21</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">194/373 (52.0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62/81 (76.5%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nursery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66/75</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24/98</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growers</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28/28</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/38</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breeders</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14/48</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fetuses</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23/34</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jan-Dec 2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suckling</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/13</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208/369 (56.4%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66/74 (89.2%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nursery</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38/43</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23/53</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growers</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14/15</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90/132</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breeders</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/38</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fetuses</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22/42</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Jan 2019-Dec 2020</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212/272 (77.9%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178/427 (41.7%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/15 (40.0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/22 (9.1%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/2 (0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/2 (100%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/2 (100%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">402/742 (54.2%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118/145 (81.4%)<sup>&#8225;</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><p><sup>&#8224;</sup>Suckling: &lt; 4 weeks; Nursery: 5&#8211;8 weeks; Growers: 9&#8211;20 weeks; Breeders: boars, gilts, and sows.</p></fn><fn id="TN2"><p><sup>&#8225;</sup>The PCV2 positive farms were calculated from Jan 2019 to Dec 2020.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic tree of PCV2 ORF2 sequences from Thailand. The 317 complete ORF2 sequences were Thai PCV2 sequences (2019&#8211;2020) in this study and reference sequences from an available database (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). The tree was constructed using the Neighbor-Joining method with a p-distance model and bootstrapping at 1,000 replicates. Node labels indicate bootstrap values. The taxon position markers were adjusted to enhance readability.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1170499-g0001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.2. Novel PCV2d variants were identified and dominated among the PCV2d strains</title><p>Due to the high detection rate of PCV2d in this study, a phylogenetic tree was constructed to examine the genetic relationship between the current Thai PCV2d sequences (2019&#8211;2020) and the previously identified Thai PCV2d sequences (2010&#8211;2015). A cluster of PCV2d strains exclusively from 2019 to 2020 with a high bootstrap support was identified (data not shown). This cluster was named 19RBR58-like cluster, which accounted for 69.77% (30/43) of the PCV2d strains or 58.82% (30/51) of the PCV2 in this study. Percent nucleotide sequence identity of the 19RBR58-like cluster were as follows; genomic: 99.60&#8211;100, ORF2: 99.29&#8211;100, and ORF1: 99.58&#8211;100. Amino acid sequence identity was as follows; capsid: 99.15&#8211;100, and replicase: 99.36&#8211;100.</p><p>ORF2 nucleotide and amino acid sequence alignment were examined to identify a distinctive genetic characteristic of the 19RBR58-like cluster. A unique <sup>133</sup>HDAM<sup>136</sup> and <sup>232</sup>K were found in all amino acid sequences from the 19RBR58-like cluster. Other Thai PCV2 sequences (PCV2a, b, d, and h) were <sup>133</sup>ANAL<sup>136</sup> or <sup>133</sup>ATAL<sup>136</sup>. To our knowledge, PCV2 strains with <sup>133</sup>HDAM<sup>136</sup> have not been reported previously.</p><p>NCBI BLAST function using 19RBR58 ORF2 (6<sup>th</sup> February 2023) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov" ext-link-type="uri">https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link>) was used to retrieve sequences with high similarity from GenBank database for further analysis (<xref rid="SM3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 3</xref>). From the dataset, PCV2d strains with <sup>133</sup>HDAM<sup>136</sup> from Japan and Taiwan during the period of 2018&#8211;2020 were found. However, those sequences were direct submissions. Moreover, PCV2d with amino acid sequences other than HDAM, ANAL, and ATAL at the position 133&#8211;136 were also identified (<xref rid="SM3" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 3</xref>) such as HAAM and HNAM. Clustering of the 19RBR58-like viruses was shown in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic tree of PCV2d ORF2 sequences from Thailand. The 158 complete ORF2 sequences were Thai PCV2d sequences in this study and the related PCV2d sequences from NCBI BLAST. A sequence of Thai PCV2b was used as an outgroup. The tree was constructed using the Neighbor-Joining method with the Maximum Composite Likelihood model and bootstrapping at 1,000 replicates. Node labels indicate bootstrap values. Specific branches were shortened, and the taxon position markers were adjusted to improve readability. A tree with each taxon label indicating the country of origin and the year of sample collection is available as <xref rid="SM6" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1170499-g0002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>3.3. The novel PCV2d variants was a parental strain of a PCV2b/2d recombinant virus</title><p>Recombination analysis using seven different methods provided strong statistical support (average <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 3.84 &#215; 10<sup>&#8722;9</sup>) confirming that 19NPT29 is an intergenotypic recombinant virus of PCV2b and PCV2d. The analysis indicated that PCV2b strains (such as South Korea/2016/KU-1605-like viruses) and PCV2d strains (such as Thailand/2019/19RBR10-like viruses) were the potential parental strains involved in the recombination event. Notably, the parental PCV2d strain was also found within the 19RBR58-like cluster, and the presence of <sup>133</sup>HDAM<sup>136</sup> and <sup>232</sup>K in the capsid protein was observed in 19NPT29. The putative recombination breakpoints were identified at nucleotide positions 508 (ORF1) and 1356 (ORF2) (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). The detection rate of the recombinant strain at the animal and farm levels was found to be 1.96% (1/51) and 2.08% (1/48), respectively.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Recombination analysis of 19NPT29. Recombination analysis was done using RDP software. Recombination breakpoints were identified in ORF1 and ORF2 regions of the 19NPT29 genome, resulting in recombinant region 1 (purple shaded) and 2 (dark green shaded) <bold>(A)</bold>. Bootscanning analysis shows KU-1605 (South Korea) and 19RBR10 (Thailand, in this study) as parental strains <bold>(B)</bold>. The phylogenetic trees were constructed based on recombinant region 1 <bold>(C)</bold> and 2 <bold>(D)</bold> to confirm recombination event.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1170499-g0003.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>4. Discussion</title><p>PCV2 is a major swine virus causing economic losses. Although vaccines have been widely used, vaccine failures and immune escaping mutation of PCV2 has been proposed (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). In this study, novel variants of PCV2d were identified providing a clue on the PCV2 evolution and epidemiology.</p><p>The prevalence of PCV2 in Thailand remained consistently high during the period of 2019&#8211;2020 compared to the period of 2009&#8211;2015. The prevalence at the animal level from 2009 to 2015 was 44.09% (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). In the current study, the prevalence increased to 54.2%. At the farm level, the prevalence from 2009 to 2015 was 80% (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), and in 2019&#8211;2020, it reached 81.4%. These findings suggests that PCV2 was still circulating, despite the implementation of PCV2 vaccines in Thailand. Unfortunately, the PCV2 vaccination status of each farm was not available in this study. Therefore, no conclusion can be made regarding the effect of the PCV2 vaccination and the overall PCV2 prevalence in Thailand.</p><p>In recent years, a genotype shift toward PCV2d can be observed in various countries, particularly in Asia. These countries include China (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), South Korea (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), Vietnam (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>), Malaysia (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), and Thailand (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). In Thailand, the prevalence of PCV2d has been increasing since 2010, with only PCV2d detected by 2015 (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). However, in this study, a novel strain of PCV2d, which accounted for 69.77% of all the current Thai PCV2d, was identified. Therefore, this novel strain of PCV2d plays a crucial role in the prevailing PCV2d strain in Thailand during 2019&#8211;2020. Moreover, this finding suggests that it may serve as the starting point for the next genetic shift within PCV2d.</p><p>This study identified the dominance of novel PCV2d strains, the 19RBR58-like cluster, over the previously circulating PCV2 strains in Thailand. At position 133&#8211;136 of the capsid protein, the 19RBR58-like cluster was <sup>133</sup>HDAM<sup>136</sup> while other Thai PCV2 strains were <sup>133</sup>ANAL<sup>136</sup> or <sup>133</sup>ATAL<sup>136</sup>. Notably, this region of amino acids resides in one of the antibody recognition domains (domain B) previously described (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>), i.e., domain A (aa 51&#8211;84), B (aa 113&#8211;139), C (aa 161&#8211;207), and D (aa 228&#8211;233). A single mutation at position 134, 135 or 136 has been shown to strongly reduce the neutralization activity (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Therefore, the capsid protein with <sup>133</sup>HDAM<sup>136</sup> might render the 19RBR58-like cluster less susceptible to the antibodies from the previously circulating strains and the vaccines. In fact, PCV2 vaccination is widely implemented in Thailand (personal communication). The observed immune escaping mechanism is further supported by the rapid increase of the 19RBR58-like cluster. Prior to 2015, the 19RBR58-like cluster was not detected in Thailand, and there is a lack of sequence data from 2016 to 2018. Thus, it is possible that the emergence of the 19RBR58-like cluster occurred during the period of 2016&#8211;2018.</p><p>In addition to Thailand, this study also identified PCV2d sequences with <sup>133</sup>HDAM<sup>136</sup> from Japan and Taiwan (direct submission in GenBank). Interestingly, the strains carrying <sup>133</sup>HDAM<sup>136</sup> from each region formed a distinct cluster on the phylogenetic tree. This suggests that the current situation of these viruses may not be attributed to recent spreading between regions. Phylogenetic analysis further revealed that all the clusters harboring <sup>133</sup>HDAM<sup>136</sup> (Thailand, Japan, and Taiwan) likely share a common ancestor with PCV2d strains from Malaysia. At present, the prevalence of the <sup>133</sup>HDAM<sup>136</sup> PCV2d variants in Japan and Taiwan is unknown. Further investigations are needed to determine whether the prevalence of these PCV2d variants is high, similar to that observed in Thailand.</p><p>Recombinant viruses derived from PCV2d strains have been reported in various countries, including China, India, and South Korea (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). In this study, a recombinant PCV2d/PCV2b strain, named 19NPT29, was identified. Interestingly, <sup>133</sup>HDAM<sup>136</sup> was also found in the capsid protein of 19NPT29. It would be valuable to conduct further studies to investigate whether the presence of <sup>133</sup>HDAM<sup>136</sup> provides any advantages to the recombinant PCV2 strain, particularly in the case of inter-genotypic recombinants. Unfortunately, conducting further epidemiological studies on the 19NPT29-like viruses from the source farm is not possible as the farm is no longer operational.</p><p>The main limitation of this study was the absence of information regarding the vaccination status of the farms, along with the passive surveillance nature of the study. The observed mutation in the antibody recognition domain of the capsid protein within the 19RBR58-like cluster is suspected to have played a role in its emergence. Therefore, the information regarding the vaccination status would have been invaluable for interpreting the data and generating hypotheses for further studies on cross-protection. Furthermore, it is important to note that the samples used in this study were obtained from two diagnostic laboratories (CU-VDL and DLSTC), which may have led to potential underrepresentation of certain geographical regions. However, it is worth mentioning that this study managed to collect samples from all the high-pig-density regions in the country. Conducting active surveillance in the future may provide a more precise assessment of the prevalence of PCV2 and the PCV2d status.</p><p>In conclusion, this study reveals the presence of a novel PCV2d strain with <sup>133</sup>HDAM<sup>136</sup> in the capsid protein as the predominant PCV2 strain in Thailand. Additionally, a recombinant virus between PCV2b and the novel PCV2d was identified. The emergence of these novel PCV2d strains might have been influenced by both vaccination and the previously circulating viruses. Conducting active surveillance can provide a comprehensive understanding of PCV2 evolution and facilitate the implementation of early interventions against the emergence of novel strains.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s5"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The datasets presented in this study can be found in online repositories. The names of the repository/repositories and accession number(s) can be found in the article/ <xref rid="s9" ref-type="sec">Supplementary material</xref>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s6"><title>Author contributions</title><p>CS, TN, and TJ collected the samples and did the PCR and sequencing. CS, RK, and RT analyzed the data and interpreted the results and prepared the manuscript. All authors helped in designing the research and contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>CS would like to thank the Second Century Fund (C2F), Chulalongkorn University, for providing the scholarship. In addition, we thank the staff of Veterinary Diagnostic Laboratories, Faculty of Veterinary Science, Chulalongkorn University for their technical assistance. We would like to thank Chulalongkorn University for supporting the Center of Excellence for Emerging and Re-emerging Infectious Disease in Animals (CUEIDAs) (GCE6403031002-1) and the One Health Research Cluster (CU-764002-HE02).</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s8"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s9"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2023.1170499/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2023.1170499/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_1.XLSX" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM2" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_2.XLSX" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM3" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_3.XLSX" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM4" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_4.XLSX" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM5" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Image_1.JPEG" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM6" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Image_2.JPEG" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Porcine circovirus type 2 (Pcv2): genetic variation and newly emerging genotypes in China</article-title>. <source>Virol J.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>273</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1743-422X-7-273</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20955622</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2967541</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mankertz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buhk</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blaess</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mankertz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Transcription analysis of porcine circovirus (Pcv)</article-title>. <source>Virus Genes.</source> (<year>1998</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>267</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1008022521329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9654680</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nawagitgul</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morozov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolin</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harms</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sorden</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Open reading frame 2 of porcine circovirus type 2 encodes a major capsid protein</article-title>. <source>J Gen Virol.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>81</volume>:<fpage>2281</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/0022-1317-81-9-2281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10950986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olvera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cortey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Segales</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular evolution of porcine circovirus type 2 genomes: phylogeny and clonality</article-title>. <source>Virology.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>357</volume>:<fpage>175</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2006.07.047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16963096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grau-Roma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraile</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Segales</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Recent advances in the epidemiology, diagnosis and control of diseases caused by porcine circovirus type 2</article-title>. <source>Vet J.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>187</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tvjl.2010.01.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20211570</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franzo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Segales</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Porcine circovirus 2 (Pcv-2) genotype update and proposal of a new genotyping methodology</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>e0208585</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0208585</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30521609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6283538</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Afolabi</surname><given-names>KO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iweriebor</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okoh</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Obi</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Global status of porcine circovirus type 2 and its associated diseases in Sub-Saharan Africa</article-title>. <source>Adv Virol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>2017</volume>:<fpage>6807964</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2017/6807964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28386278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5366187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halbur</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Opriessnig</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Global molecular genetic analysis of porcine circovirus type 2 (Pcv2) sequences confirms the presence of four main Pcv2 genotypes and reveals a rapid increase of Pcv2d</article-title>. <source>J Gen Virol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>1830</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/vir.0.000100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25711965</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Neutralization mechanism of a monoclonal antibody targeting a porcine circovirus type 2 cap protein conformational epitope</article-title>. <source>J Virol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>e01836</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>19</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.01836-19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32075932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7163150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noll</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A multiplex real-time pcr assay for the detection and differentiation of the newly emerged porcine circovirus type 3 and continuously evolving type 2 strains in the United States</article-title>. <source>J Virol Methods.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>269</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jviromet.2019.03.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30904590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7113677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fenaux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halbur</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toth</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic characterization of type 2 porcine circovirus (Pcv-2) from pigs with postweaning multisystemic wasting syndrome in different geographic regions of North America and development of a differential Pcr-restriction fragment length polymorphism assay to detect and differentiate between infections with Pcv-1 and Pcv-2</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>2494</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>503</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.38.7.2494-2503.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10878032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC86951</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roh</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Phylogenetic characterization of porcine circovirus type 2 in Pmws and Pdns Korean pigs between 1999 and 2006</article-title>. <source>Virus Res.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>129</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2007.06.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17706315</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Clustal W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source> (<year>1994</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>4673</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/22.22.4673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7984417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC308517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bioedit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for windows 95/98/Nt</article-title>. <source>Nucl Acids Symp Ser.</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Filipski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mega6: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 60</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>2725</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mst197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24132122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3840312</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moulton</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lefeuvre</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>RDP3: a flexible and fast computer program for analyzing recombination</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>2462</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq467</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20798170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2944210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lole</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bollinger</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paranjape</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gadkari</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Full-length human immunodeficiency virus type 1 genomes from subtype C-infected seroconverters in India, with evidence of intersubtype recombination</article-title>. <source>J Virol.</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>73</volume>:<fpage>152</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.73.1.152-160.1999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9847317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC103818</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thangthamniyom</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sangthong</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poolperm</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thanantong</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boonsoongnern</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansoongnern</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic diversity of porcine circovirus type 2 (Pcv2) in Thailand during 2009&#8211;2015</article-title>. <source>Vet Microbiol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>208</volume>:<fpage>239</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2017.08.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28888644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and genetic diversity of porcine circovirus type 2 in Northern Guangdong Province during 2016&#8211;2021</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>932612</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.932612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36032297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9399655</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Je</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyoo</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Genotypic diversity of porcine circovirus type 2 (Pcv2) and genotype shift to Pcv2d in Korean pig population</article-title>. <source>Virus Res.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>228</volume>:<fpage>24</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2016.11.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27867029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doan</surname><given-names>HTT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Do</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thao</surname><given-names>PTP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le</surname><given-names>XTK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hien</surname><given-names>NTT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular genotypic analysis of porcine circovirus type 2 reveals the predominance of Pcv2d in Vietnam (2018-2020) and the association between Pcv2h, the recombinant forms, and vietnamese vaccines</article-title>. <source>Arch Virol.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>167</volume>:<fpage>2011</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00705-022-05517-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35794492</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thanawongnuwech</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arshad</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>MWC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ooi</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Genotype shift of malaysian porcine circovirus 2 (Pcv2) from Pcv2b to Pcv2d within a Decade</article-title>. <source>Animals.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1849</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani12141849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35883396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9311952</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Truong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnauld</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Cann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cariolet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Differential recognition of Orf2 protein from type 1 and type 2 porcine circoviruses and identification of immunorelevant epitopes</article-title>. <source>J Gen Virol.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>81</volume>:<fpage>1815</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/0022-1317-81-7-1815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10859388</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lekcharoensuk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morozov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thangthumniyom</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wajjawalku</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epitope mapping of the major capsid protein of type 2 porcine circovirus (Pcv2) by using chimeric Pcv1 and Pcv2</article-title>. <source>J Virol.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>78</volume>:<fpage>8135</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.78.15.8135-8145.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15254185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC446101</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Emergence of a novel recombinant porcine circovirus type 2 in China: Pcv2c and Pcv2d recombinant</article-title>. <source>Transbound Emerg Dis.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>2496</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>506</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tbed.13307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31342637</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic and phylogenetic analysis of porcine circovirus type 2 on Jeju Island, South Korea, 2019&#8211;2020: evidence of a novel intergenotypic recombinant</article-title>. <source>Arch Virol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>166</volume>:<fpage>1093</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>102</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00705-020-04948-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33570666</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parthiban</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramesh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karuppannan</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dhinakar</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hemalatha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Emergence of novel porcine circovirus 2 genotypes in Southern India</article-title>. <source>Transbound Emerg Dis.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>1804</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tbed.14158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34008351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>