<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="systematic-review" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11216035</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11216035.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11216035</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11216035</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38952801</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2024.1418979</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Systematic Review</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The prevalence and infection rates of amphistome species in intermediate snail hosts: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyagura</surname><given-names initials="I">Ignore</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1846264/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malatji</surname><given-names initials="MP">Mokgadi Pulane</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukaratirwa</surname><given-names initials="S">Samson</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1085786/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>School of Life Sciences, College of Agriculture, Engineering and Science, University of KwaZulu-Natal, Westville Campus</institution>, <addr-line>Durban</addr-line>, <country>South Africa</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>One Health Centre for Zoonoses and Tropical Veterinary Medicine, Ross University School of Veterinary Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Basseterre</addr-line>, <country>Saint Kitts and Nevis</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0002"><p>Edited by: Calin Mircea Gherman, University of Agricultural Sciences and Veterinary Medicine of Cluj-Napoca, Romania</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0003"><p>Reviewed by: Angela Monica Ionica, Clinical Hospital of Infectious Diseases, Romania</p><p>Saw Bawm, University of Veterinary Science, Myanmar</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Ignore Nyagura, <email>nyaguraigy@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>6</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2024</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">454084</issue-id><elocation-id>1418979</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>4</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2024</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-07-02 17:25:17.400"><day>02</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2024 Nyagura, Malatji and Mukaratirwa.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2024</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Nyagura, Malatji and Mukaratirwa</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-11-1418979.pdf"/><abstract><p>The systematic review and meta-analysis were conducted to determine the estimates of the prevalence and infection rates of natural and experimental infections of amphistome species in intermediate host snails (IHs) across different continents. A search of peer-reviewed literature on natural and experimental infections of freshwater snails with amphistome species was conducted from four electronic databases from 1984 to 2023. The estimates of the prevalence and/or infection rates were based on 36 eligible peer-reviewed articles, which met the inclusion criteria and reported on natural and experimental infections of amphistome species in freshwater snails. The results showed that a total of 1,67,081 snail species from the peer-reviewed articles were examined for natural infections and 7,659 snail species for experimental infections. The overall pooled prevalence of amphistome infections from naturally infected snails was 2% (95% CI: 0&#8211;4), while the overall pooled prevalence of amphistome infections from infections was 40% (95% CI: 18&#8211;64). The highest pooled prevalence of natural infection was 3%, which was recorded in Europe (95% CI: 1&#8211;7%). The highest overall prevalence of naturally infected amphistome was 6% (95% CI: 0&#8211;20%) for <italic toggle="yes">Paramphistomum epiclitum</italic>. The Americas had the highest pooled prevalence of experimental amphistome infection among freshwater snails (66%; 95% CI: 26&#8211;96%). The highest pooled infection rate of 65% (95% CI: 12&#8211;100%) was recorded for <italic toggle="yes">Paramphistomum cervi</italic> in experimental infections. <italic toggle="yes">Galba truncatula</italic> was the only snail that qualified for meta-analysis for natural infection with <italic toggle="yes">Calicophoron daubneyi,</italic> with a pooled prevalence of 3% (95% CI: 1&#8211;8%). <italic toggle="yes">Galba truncatula</italic> infected with <italic toggle="yes">C. daubneyi and P. cervi,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bulinus tropicus</italic> infected with <italic toggle="yes">Calicophoron microbothrium</italic> in the experimental infection qualified for the meta-analysis, with an overall infection rate of 66% (95% CI: 34&#8211;92%) and 30% (95% CI: 0&#8211;74%), respectively. The pooled prevalence of amphistome species infection in the intermediate host (IH) snails based on detection techniques was higher with PCR compared to the dissection and shedding of cercariae. The results from the quality effects model revealed a high heterogeneity and publication bias between studies. This meta-analysis provided valuable insights into the prevalence and infection rates of amphistome species in snail IHs across different geographical regions.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>amphistomes</kwd><kwd>intermediate host snails</kwd><kwd>meta-analysis</kwd><kwd>prevalence</kwd><kwd>natural infection</kwd><kwd>experimental infection</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn1">SM&#8217;s Research Productivity funds</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that financial support was received for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. The study received financial assistance from SM&#8217;s Research Productivity funds (UKZN).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="6"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="68"/><page-count count="14"/><word-count count="8609"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Parasitology</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Intestinal amphistomosis, otherwise known as amphistomiasis (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), paramphistomiasis (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), or paramphistomosis (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), is a neglected trematode disease of domestic and wild ruminants (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). The disease is caused by a heavy infection with immature flukes, resulting in acute gastroenteritis with significant morbidity and mortality, particularly in young animals (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). In domestic ruminants, amphistomosis can cause major economic losses due to decreased milk and meat production, poor nutrient conversion, weight loss, and reduced fertility (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>).</p><p>The disease is spread worldwide, with the highest infection rates reported in the tropical and subtropical regions of Asia (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), Africa (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), Australia (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), Europe (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), and Russia (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). The causative amphistome species are commonly known as rumen flukes or conical flukes, belonging to the class Trematoda under the superfamily Paramphistomoidea Fischoeder, 1901 (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). This superfamily is composed of 100&#8201;s of species belonging to 10 families: Balanorchiidae Stunkard, 1925; Cladorchiidae Fischoeder, 1901; Diplodiscidae Cohn, 1904; Gastrothylacidae Stiles and Goldberger, 1910; Gastrodiscidae Monticelli, 1892; Olveriidae Yamaguti, 1958; Paramphistomidae Fischoeder, 1901; Stephanopharyngidae Stiles and Goldberger, 1910; Zonocotylidae Yamaguti, 1963; and Zygocotylidae Yamaguti, 1963. The group of trematodes is characterized by the absence of an oral sucker and the position of the acetabulum at or close to the posterior end of the body in both adults and cercariae (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p><p>Amphistomes have a complex heteroxenous life cycle that involves a variety of species of intermediate host snails (IHs), where development and asexual replication occur, giving rise to multiple cercariae that escape the snail and encyst on the water surface, plants immersed in water or herbage to form metacercariae. Domesticated and wild ruminants are definitive hosts that become infected through drinking water or grazing on pasture contaminated with metacercariae (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Within the definitive hosts, the prepatent period ranges between 56 and 89&#8201;days (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Adult flukes located in the rumen and reticulum produce eggs, which are then passed through feces (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). The eggs that need an aquatic environment hatch into miracidia, which is the infective stage for the intermediate hosts, and the miracidia will infect various intermediate host snails (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>).</p><p>To date, there are more than 70 amphistome species reported in both domestic and wild ruminants worldwide (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). The IHs belonging to the taxa Caenogastropoda Cox, 1960; Stylommatophora Schmidt, 1855; and Basommatophora Keferstein, 1864, involving many genera and species within the families Planorbidae Rafinesque, 1815, and Lymnaeidae Rafinesque, 1815 (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) have been implicated in the transmission of various amphistome species. These snails play a vital role as obligatory intermediate hosts in the transmission of trematodes to their final hosts (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14&#8211;20</xref>).</p><p>The prevalence of amphistome infections or any snail-borne trematode is influenced by the abundance of susceptible IHs and vertebrate definitive hosts (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Thus, the availability of the IHs in the grazing habits of the infected vertebrate definitive hosts largely determines the epidemiology and seasonal patterns of amphistome infection (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Furthermore, knowledge of the IHs for various amphistome species is essential in developing sustainable strategies for the prevention and control of amphistome infections in domestic and wild ruminants, especially in areas where mixed livestock and game farming are being practiced. Therefore, this study systematically reviewed and analyzed quantitative data extracted from peer-reviewed articles on the prevalence and infection rates of natural and experimental infections of amphistome species in various snail host species from 1984 to 2023.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec3"><title>Search strategy</title><p>A systematic literature search was conducted on Google Scholar, PubMed, Scopus, and Web of Science Core Collection databases to retrieve studies from 1984 to 2023 using Boolean Operators (AND, OR) and a combination of keywords such as amphistome OR paramphistome AND intermediate host snail OR freshwater snail OR gastropods AND natural infections AND prevalence, amphistome OR paramphistome AND intermediate host snail OR freshwater snail OR gastropods AND experimental infections OR infectivity OR susceptibility AND prevalence. Additional relevant studies were identified by cross-referencing or screening through bibliographies (snowballing) of selected articles. EndNote reference management version X8 (Clarivate Analytics, Philadelphia, PA, USA) was used to retrieve and manage full-text articles.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Inclusion and exclusion criteria</title><p>Five inclusion criteria were used to select articles for the systematic review and meta-analysis from 1984 to 2023, which are listed as follows: (i) studies reporting the number of screened and infected snails with amphistome species, (ii) studies reporting intermediate host snails to species level, (iii) studies reporting data on amphistome infections to species level, (iv) studies that reported prevalence and/or infection rates based on natural and/or experimental infections, and (v) studies that mentioned the detection method(s) of amphistome infection in snails.</p><p>All studies reporting on other trematode species including amphistome infections, but did not identify amphistomes and/or the intermediate hosts up to species level or reporting on amphistome infections in definitive hosts were excluded. Furthermore, articles published in other languages besides English or outside the period of study were excluded.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Data extraction</title><p>Following the study design, the title and abstract of the articles were assessed independently by two reviewers (IN and MPM), and relevant articles were retrieved. The retrieved articles were thoroughly rechecked, and duplicates and articles that did not fulfill the inclusion criteria were removed. For meta-analysis, data were extracted from text, tables, and figures and processed in MS Excel. Variables that were considered for each article are as follows: author names, year of publication, year of study and duration, country of study, snail species, amphistome species, detection method(s), number of snail samples screened, number of positives, and prevalence rate.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Quality assessment of the articles</title><p>The Grading of Recommendations Assessment, Development, and Evaluation (GRADE) approach was used to assess the overall quality of articles for meta-analysis (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Articles that met each given inclusion criteria received one point, and as a result, each study was assigned a score ranging from 0 to 5. Publications with a total score of 5 points were deemed as good quality, 4 as moderate quality, and&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;3 as low quality and were excluded (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). The standardized quality index score (ranging from 0 to 1) was then computed (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Frequency of snail species naturally infected with amphistomes from 1984 to 2023.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Snail species</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of studies</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No examined</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No infected</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prevalence (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Biomphalaria (Bio.) peregrina</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,424</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bio. tenagophila</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,448</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bithynia (Bi.) tentaculata</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,180</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bulinus (B.) tropicus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">406</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.69</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Ferrissia (F.) fragilis</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">243</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Galba (G.) truncatula</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95,839</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,644</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Gyraulus (Gy.) convexiusculus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,677</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Helicorbis (H.) coenosus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">474</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Helisoma (He.) anceps</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Indoplanorbis (I.) exustus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,232</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">434</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Lymnaea (L.) acuminata</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">699</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">L. luteola</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,064</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">L. ovata</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.63</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Melanoides (M.) tuberculata</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32,026</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Menetus (Me.) dilatatus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">494</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Omphiscola (O.) glabra</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,963</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">270</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.71</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Physa (Ph.) acuta</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">430</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Planorbis (P.) leucostoma</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1841</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P. planorbis</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Pseudosuccinea (Ps.) columella</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">971</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Vivipara (V.) bengalensis</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">279</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">167,081</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,721</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>Study quality assessment, data preparation, and analysis</title><p>Prevalence data were transformed using the double arcsine method to avoid overestimating the weight of individual studies (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). The double arcsine approach uses the arcsine transformation twice to measure the prevalence of the meta-analysis and to take into account the heterogeneity caused by studies with small sample sizes and extreme proportions (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). The MetaXL add-in for Microsoft Excel<xref rid="fn0001" ref-type="fn"><sup>1</sup></xref> was used to compute a quality effects model to account for the heterogeneity. The heterogeneity between estimates was quantified using the inverse variance statistic (<italic toggle="yes">I<sup>2</sup></italic> index), and its significance was assessed using the Cochrane&#8217;s Q test. Following the protocol of Higgins et al. (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>), the <italic toggle="yes">I<sup>2</sup></italic> score of 25, 50%, or 75% was interpreted as low, moderate, or high heterogeneity, respectively. Forest plots were used to graphically demonstrate the estimated prevalence and the 95% confidence interval of the amphistome species among the intermediate host snails. A subgroup analysis was conducted to evaluate the estimates of the prevalence for the major subgroups, including geography (continent), snail species, amphistome species, detection method, and years. Funnel plots were used to evaluate the publication bias.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec8"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec9"><title>Search results</title><p>A total of 1,146 records, from which 36 were found to be eligible articles, were identified through database searching and snowballing, as summarized in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. Preliminary screening of duplicates, titles, and abstracts deemed 1,088 articles irrelevant and were excluded. Full-texts of 58 articles were assessed for eligibility, and 22 articles were excluded as they did not meet the inclusion criteria. The remaining 36 articles distributed across 5 continents met the inclusion criteria and quality assessment. In total, 20 articles (55.6%) were field-based studies, and 16 (44.4%) were experimental studies. Of the field studies conducted, twelve (60%) were from Europe, four (20%) were from Asia, two (10%) were from Africa, and one (5%) each from North America and South America. The geographical distribution and contributions of the experimental studies were as follows: Europe (43.8%), Africa (25%), North America (12.5%), South America (12.5%), and a combination of Africa and Europe (6.3%). The total quality of all primary studies was five, indicating that the quality of the included studies was high.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>PRISMA flow diagram.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-11-1418979-g001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec10"><title>Natural infections of amphistomes in freshwater snails</title><p>The prevalence of amphistome cercaria in field-collected snails from the studies ranged from 0 to 22.54% (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). A total of 167,081 freshwater snails represented by 21 different snail species were collected and identified (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Out of these snails, 5,721 were infected with different amphistome species. The results from the natural infection showed that 16 species of IHs were implicated in the transmission of 10 amphistome species (<italic toggle="yes">Calicophoron [C.] daubneyi, C. microbothrium, Explanatum [E.] explanatum, Fischoederius [F.] elongatus, Gastrothylax [G.] crumenifer, Orthocoelium [O.] scoliocoelium, Paramphistomum [P.] epiclitum, Pisciamphistoma [Pi.] stunkardi, Stichorchis [S.] subtriquetrus,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Zygocotyle [Z.] lunata</italic>) (<xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Documented snail species naturally infected with various amphistome species from 1984 to 2023.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Snail species</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="10" rowspan="1">Number of snails naturally infected with various amphistome species</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Z. lunata</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">G. crumenifer</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">O. scoliocoelium</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">C. daubneyi</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">C. microbothrium</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">S. subtriquetrus</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. explanatum</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">F. elongatus</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P. epiclitum</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Pi. stunkardi</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bio. peregrina</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,424</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bio. tenagophila</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,448</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bi. tentaculata</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,180</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">B. tropicus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">406</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">F. fragilis</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">243</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">G. truncatula</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95,839</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,644</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Gy. convexiusculus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,677</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,613</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">H. coenosus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">474</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">He. anceps</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">I. exustus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,232</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">434</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">L. acuminata</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">699</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">L. luteola</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,064</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">L. ovata</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculata</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32,026</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Men. dilatatus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">494</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">O. glabra</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,863</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">270</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Ph. acuta</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">430</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P. leucostoma</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1841</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P. planorbis</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Ps. columella</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">971</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">V. bengalensis</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">279</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="sec11"><title>The overall prevalence of natural infections of amphistome species in freshwater snails</title><p>The results from the quality effects model revealed high heterogeneity (<italic toggle="yes">Q</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;9639.15, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001), and the <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> index was 99% (<xref rid="SM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>). The overall pooled prevalence of amphistome infection from naturally infected snails was 2% (95% CI: 0&#8211;4) (<xref rid="SM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>), and <italic toggle="yes">C. daubneyi</italic> was the most frequently reported infection in <italic toggle="yes">Galba (G.) truncatula</italic> and was found predominantly in Europe.</p></sec><sec id="sec12"><title>The prevalence of natural infection of amphistomes in freshwater snails by continent</title><p>The pooled prevalence of amphistome species among freshwater snails varied from continent to continent. The pooled prevalence of amphistome species infection among freshwater snails was low in Asia (95% CI: 0&#8211;3%, <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>) and in the Americas (95% CI: 0&#8211;1%, <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>) and high in Europe (3, 95% CI: 1&#8211;7%, <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C</xref>). Data from North and South America were combined as Americas for meta-analysis due to their proximity, and Africa as a continent did not have sufficient data for meta-analysis, as only two studies were published, each demonstrating the infection of <italic toggle="yes">C. microbothrium</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">Bulinus (B.) tropicus</italic> with the prevalence of 16.36 and 21.37%, respectively.</p><fig position="float" id="fig2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Forest plots of the prevalence of amphistome species in intermediate host snails from natural infection from <bold>(A)</bold> Asia, <bold>(B)</bold> America, and <bold>(C)</bold> Europe recorded from 1984 to 2023.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-11-1418979-g002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec13"><title>The prevalence of natural infection of amphistomes in freshwater snails by amphistome species</title><p>The pooled prevalence of individual amphistome species in snail intermediate host species was computed (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>), with <italic toggle="yes">C. daubneyi</italic> prevalence estimated at 3% (95% CI: 1&#8211;6%). <italic toggle="yes">Calicophoron daubneyi</italic> was the most prevalent amphistome species in snails from Europe and in a single study in Asia. The highest overall prevalence estimated from snails in Asia was for <italic toggle="yes">P. epiclitum</italic> at 6% (95% CI: 0&#8211;20%), and the prevalence was substantially low for <italic toggle="yes">O. scoliocoelium</italic> (95% CI: 0&#8211;1%), <italic toggle="yes">G. crumenifer</italic> (95% CI: 0&#8211;2%), and <italic toggle="yes">F. elongatus</italic> (95% CI: 0&#8211;2%). Only <italic toggle="yes">S. subtriquetrus,</italic> with an overall prevalence of 6% (95% CI: 0&#8211;20%) in North America, qualified for meta-analysis. Three studies from Africa and one study from Asia reported on the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">C. microbothrium</italic> from <italic toggle="yes">Bulinus</italic> species, and the estimated prevalence was 5% (95% CI: 0&#8211;15%). The results from the quality effects model revealed a high heterogeneity between studies on amphistomes with <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;75 except for <italic toggle="yes">E. explanatum</italic> with <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#8201;=&#8201;19% and <italic toggle="yes">O. scoliocoelium</italic> with <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#8201;=&#8201;60. It was not possible to conduct a meta-analysis for amphistome species, such as <italic toggle="yes">Pi. Stunkardi</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Z. lunata,</italic> since they were surveyed in a limited number of studies and host species.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Pooled prevalences (PPs) of amphistome species in snail species from natural infections across different continents (1984&#8211;2023).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amphistome species</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Continent</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No of studies</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No of snail hosts</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PP (PP) (95% CI)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. explanatum</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asia</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3% (95% CI: 2&#8211;3%).</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">C. daubneyi</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Europe and Asia</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3% (95% CI: 1&#8211;6%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">C. microbothrium</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Africa and Asia</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5% (95% CI: 0&#8211;15%).</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">F. elongatus</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asia</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (95% CI: 0&#8211;2%).</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">G. crumenifer</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asia</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (95% CI: 0&#8211;2%),</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">O. scoliocoelium</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asia</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0% (95% CI: 0&#8211;1%),</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P. epiclitum</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asia</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6% (95% CI: 0&#8211;20%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Pi. stunkardi</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North America</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">S. subtriquetrus</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North America</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6% (95% CI: 0&#8211;20%)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Z. lunata</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South America</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec14"><title>The prevalence of natural infection of amphistomes in snail species</title><p>The frequency of infected snail species with different amphistome species is presented in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The snail species that qualified for meta-analysis was <italic toggle="yes">G. truncatula</italic> infected with <italic toggle="yes">C. daubneyi</italic> with a pooled prevalence of 3% (95% CI: 1&#8211;8%), and a high level of heterogeneity was observed (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> =&#8201;99%). Other infected snails were investigated for a few amphistome species and only in a few studies; thus, it was not possible to carry out a meta-analysis.</p></sec><sec id="sec15"><title>The prevalence of natural infection of amphistomes in freshwater snails by time in years</title><p>To evaluate the changes in amphistome infection rates in intermediate host snails between the eras, articles were divided into four groups based on decade: 1984&#8211;1993, 1994&#8211;2003, 2004&#8211;2013, and 2014&#8211;2023. Most studies were conducted between 1994 and 2003, and studies between 1984 and 1993 were not eligible for meta-analysis. The pooled prevalence of amphistome species among freshwater snails was higher in years 2004&#8211;2013 (4%; 95% CI: 0&#8211;14%), followed by 1994&#8211;2003 (2%; 95% CI: 1&#8211;4%) and 2014&#8211;2023 (1%; 95% CI: 0&#8211;3%) (<xref rid="SM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figures S2A&#8211;C</xref>). The results from the quality effects model revealed a high heterogeneity between studies on each given period, 1994 to 2003 (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> =&#8201;98%), 2004 to 2013 (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> =&#8201;100%), and 2014 to 2023 (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> =&#8201;99%) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3A</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">C</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Forest plots of experimental infection rate of amphistome species in intermediate host snails from <bold>(A)</bold> Africa, <bold>(B)</bold> America, and <bold>(C)</bold> Europe recorded from 1984 to 2023.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-11-1418979-g003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec16"><title>The prevalence of natural infection of amphistomes in freshwater snails by detection techniques</title><p>To detect natural infections in the intermediate host snails, 12 studies used dissection, 8 studies used cercarial shedding, 2 studies used molecular (PCR) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figures 4A</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">C</xref>), and one study involved both dissection and molecular. The pooled prevalence of natural infections of amphistomes in the intermediate host (IH) snails based on techniques was higher with PCR (6, 95% CI: 1&#8211;15%) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4C</xref>), followed by dissection with 3% (1&#8211;5%) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>) and cercarial shedding with (95% CI: 0&#8211;3%) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B</xref>). The results revealed a high heterogeneity between studies involving dissection (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> =&#8201;99%), shedding (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> =&#8201;99%), and PCR (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> =&#8201;90%) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figures 4A</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">C</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Forest plots of the prevalence of natural infections of amphistome species in intermediate host snails as determined by <bold>(A)</bold> dissection, <bold>(B)</bold> shedding, and <bold>(C)</bold> molecular methods.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-11-1418979-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec17"><title>Publication bias of studies reporting on natural infections of amphistomes in intermediate host snails</title><p>The visual inspection of the funnel plots revealed an asymmetric funnel shape, demonstrating the presence of publication bias (<xref rid="SM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>), which may be due to a small sample size bias or publication bias in the articles.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec18"><title>Experimental infection rates of amphistomes in freshwater snails</title><p>The infection rate of amphistome cercaria in experimentally infected snails from individual studies ranged from 0 to 100% (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). A total of 7,659 snails were collected and used in the experiments, and out of these snails, 3,163 were challenged with different amphistome species (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The 27 snail species included in the experimental studies were <italic toggle="yes">B. glabrata, B. oligoza, B. orbignyi, B. peregrina, B. pfeifferi, B. straminea, B. tenagophila, B. globosus, B. natalensis, B. permembranaceus, B. truncatus, B. tropicus, G. truncatula, G. cubensis, G. humilis, G. neotropica, G. palustris, He. anceps, Lymnaea (L.) glabra, L. ovata, L. ventricose, M. tuberculata, Omphiscola (O.) glabra, Ph. acuta, Ps. columella, Radix (R.) natalensis,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Tarebia (T.) granifera</italic> (<xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Of these snail species, 23 species were susceptible to infection with a specific amphistome species, including <italic toggle="yes">C. daubneyi,</italic> which caused infections in nine snail species, <italic toggle="yes">C. microbothrium</italic> in six snail species, <italic toggle="yes">P. cervi</italic> in three snail species, and <italic toggle="yes">Z. lunata</italic> in six snail species (<xref rid="tab5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Frequency of snail species experimentally infected with amphistomes from 1984 to 2023.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Snail species</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No of studies</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No examined</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No infected</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infection rate (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bio. glabrata</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bio. oligoza</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bio, orbignyi</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bio. peregrina</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bio. pfeifferi</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bio. straminea</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.92</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bio. tenagophila</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.94</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">B. globosus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.82</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">B. natalensis</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.83</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">B. permembranaceus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">B. trancatus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">B. tropicus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">597</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">G. truncatula</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">934</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">671</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.84</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">G. cubensis</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,000</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">477</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.70</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">G. humilis</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,000</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">395</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">G. neotropica</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">G. palustris</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,166</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">997</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.51</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">He. anceps</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.69</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">L. glabra</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">L. ovata</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">159</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">L. ventricosa</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculata</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">O. glabra</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">461</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Ph. Acuta</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">187</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Ps. columella</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,108</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. natalensis</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">T. granifera</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,659</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,163</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.30</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tab5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Documented snail species experimentally infected with various amphistome species from 1984 to 2023.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Snail species</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Number of cases experimentally infected with various amphistome species</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">C. daubneyi</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">C. microbothrium</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P. cervi</italic>
</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Z. lunata</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bio. glabrata</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bio. oligoza</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bio. orbignyi</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bio. peregrina</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bio. pfeifferi</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bio. straminea</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bio. tenagophila</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">B. globosus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">B. natalensis</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">B. permembranaceus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">B. trancatus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">B. tropicus</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">597</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">207</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">G. cubensis</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,000</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">477</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">G. humilis</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,000</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">395</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">G. neotropica</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">G. palustris</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,166</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">987</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">G. truncatula</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">934</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">671</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">H. anceps</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">L. glabra</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">L. ovata</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">159</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">L. ventricosa</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculata</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">O. glabra</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">461</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Ph. Acuta</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">187</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Ps. columella</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,108</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. natalensis</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">T. granifera</italic>
</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="sec19"><title>An overall experimental infection rate of amphistome species in freshwater snails</title><p>The pooled experimental infection rate of amphistome species among freshwater snails was 40% (95% CI: 18 to 65%) (<xref rid="SM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S4</xref>). The results from the quality effects model revealed high heterogeneity (<italic toggle="yes">Q</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;5370.79, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001), with <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> =&#8201;99% (<xref rid="SM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec20"><title>Experimental infection rate of amphistomes in freshwater snail by continent</title><p>The pooled infection rate of amphistome species differed across continents (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3A</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">C</xref>). Americas showed the highest pooled infection rate of 66% (95% CI: 26&#8211;96%, <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref>) of amphistome species among freshwater snails, followed by 21% in Europe (95% CI: 0&#8211;54%, <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C</xref>) and 14% in Africa (95% CI: 0&#8211;38%, <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>). A significant degree of heterogeneity was demonstrated; <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> was 99% for both Americas and Europe and 97% for Africa.</p></sec><sec id="sec21"><title>Experimental infection rate of amphistomes in freshwater snails by amphistome species</title><p>The pooled infection rate of individual amphistome species among intermediate host snail species from experimental infections was computed and presented in <xref rid="tab6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>. The highest infection rate was caused by <italic toggle="yes">P. cervi</italic> with an overall infection rate of 65% (95% CI: 12&#8211;100%), followed by <italic toggle="yes">Z. lunata</italic> with 41% (95% CI: 11&#8211;75%), <italic toggle="yes">C. microbothrium with</italic> 22% (95% CI: 5&#8211;47%), and finally <italic toggle="yes">C. daubneyi with</italic> 11% (95% CI: 1&#8211;28%). The results from the quality effects model revealed a high degree of heterogeneity between studies on amphistome species (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> &gt;&#8201;95%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01; <xref rid="tab6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Pooled infection rate of amphistome species in snails from experimental infections across different continents (1984&#8211;2023).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amphistome species</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Continent</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No of studies</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No of snail hosts</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PP (95% CI)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">C. daubneyi</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Europe, Africa, South America</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (3&#8211;45)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">C. microbothrium</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Africa</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (5&#8211;47)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P. cervi</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North America</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (16&#8211;100)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Z. lunata</italic>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South America and North America</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="char" valign="top" char="(" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (11&#8211;75)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec22"><title>Experimental infection rate of amphistomes by snail species</title><p>Among the snails from the experimental infection, <italic toggle="yes">G. truncatula</italic> infected with <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">daubneyi and P. cervi</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. tropicus</italic> infected with <italic toggle="yes">C. microbothrium</italic> qualified for the meta-analysis with an overall infection rate of 66% (95% CI: 34&#8211;92%) and 30% (95% CI: 0&#8211;74%), respectively. Furthermore, the results from the quality effects model revealed a high degree of heterogeneity between studies on snail infections (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> &gt;&#8201;99%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01) for <italic toggle="yes">G. truncatula</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. tropicus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> &gt;&#8201;98%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01). Most infected snails were investigated in a few studies; hence, it was not possible to carry out a meta-analysis on them, and the frequency of infected snails with amphistomes is presented in <xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec23"><title>Experimental infection rate of amphistomes in freshwater by time in years</title><p><xref rid="SM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figures S5A&#8211;D</xref> display the pooled experimental infection rate of amphistomes by period. The highest pooled infection rate was observed between 1984 and 1993 at 61% (95% CI: 15&#8211;100%) (<xref rid="SM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S5A</xref>), followed by the years between 2004 and 2013 at 39% (95% CI: 4&#8211;82%) (<xref rid="SM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S5C</xref>), 1994&#8211;2003 at 28% (95% CI: 10&#8211;51%) (<xref rid="SM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S5B</xref>), and the lowest from 2014 to 2023 at 5% (95% CI: 2&#8211;9%) (<xref rid="SM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S5D</xref>). The results from the quality effects model revealed a high heterogeneity between studies at each given time period, between 1984 and 1993 (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> =&#8201;100%), between 1994 and 2003 (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> =&#8201;98%), between 2004 and 2013 (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> =&#8201;99%), and between 2014 and 2023 (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> =&#8201;69%), (<xref rid="SM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figures S5A&#8211;D</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec24"><title>Experimental infection rate of amphistomes in freshwater snails by detection techniques</title><p>The estimated pooled infection rate of amphistome species obtained by shedding of cercariae was 15% (95% CI: 3&#8211;33%) in contrast to 42% (95% CI: 17&#8211;69%) obtained by dissection techniques (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figures 5A</xref>,<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">B</xref>). The results from the quality effects model revealed a high heterogeneity between shedding (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> =&#8201;97%) and dissection (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>2</sup> =&#8201;99%) (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figures 5A</xref>,<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">B</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig5" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Forest plots of experimental infection rate of amphistome species in intermediate host snails as determined by <bold>(A)</bold> dissection and <bold>(B)</bold> shedding.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-11-1418979-g005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec25"><title>Publication bias of studies reporting on the experimental infections of amphistomes in intermediate host snails</title><p>Publication bias analysis revealed asymmetric funnel plots (<xref rid="SM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S6</xref>), which indicated a small sample size bias or publication bias in the articles.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec26"><title>Discussion</title><p>The results showed that field-based studies utilized a high number of snail species for assessing the prevalence of amphistome species in IHs. However, the prevalence of amphistome infection estimated from experimental infection was higher than that from natural infection. The variation may be due to differences in the environmental conditions set up, where the experimental conditions might have favored the success of the infections (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Dar et al. (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) also suggested that the higher infection rate of amphistome in snails from experimental infection studies may have been attributed to the decrease in snail&#8217;s resistance to infection due to the experimental conditions of breeding snails in the laboratory.</p><p>The study also revealed significant differences in amphistome prevalence among different continents, albeit with a limited number of studies. Although considerable work has been done on taxonomic aspects of ruminant amphistomes in livestock and wildlife in Africa (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28&#8211;32</xref>), limited to no focus has been given on the ecology of the parasites, particularly with reference to the prevalence rate in IHs despite the fact that diversity of amphistomes species and their IHs seem to be higher in the African continent than other continents.</p><p>The prevalence of specific amphistome species in snails were mostly limited to one continent following the distribution of their specific intermediate host. The availability and abundance of susceptible definitive hosts on distinct continents, as proposed by Pfukenyi and Mukaratirwa (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>) and Sibula et al. (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), may account for the distribution and prevalence of amphistome species in different snail species on different continents. The distribution of amphistome and their snail intermediate hosts could have been attributed to variations in environment and climate across these regions (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Furthermore, the variations in noted prevalence among different amphistome species in the reviewed studies could be due to differences in the life cycle and transmission dynamics of these parasite species, as stated by Gonz&#225;lez-Warleta et al. (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>).</p><p>The high overall prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">C. daubneyi</italic> in Europe may have been attributed to a higher number of studies conducted than in any other continent. This could also be attributed to the high endemicity of this amphistome species in Europe, where a higher prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">C. daubneyi</italic> was recorded in definitive hosts (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Furthermore, <italic toggle="yes">C. daubneyi</italic> natural infections were detected in a number of snails, which included <italic toggle="yes">G. truncatula</italic> (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35&#8211;46</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">L. ovata</italic> (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">O. glabra</italic> (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>), and <italic toggle="yes">Ph. acuta</italic> (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>) in Europe. Its ability to naturally infect a vast number of snail species was also noted in experimental infection, where it was implicated in nine snail species, making it the main rumen fluke of cattle, sheep, and goats in Europe (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). The presence of this amphistome species and its diverse intermediate host snails in Europe may be linked to the introduction of <italic toggle="yes">C. daubneyi</italic> to Western Europe during the movement of livestock (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>) and climate change (milder winters and higher rainfall), favoring the completion of the parasite lifecycle (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>).</p><p>The highest prevalence of amphistome species in snails from North America was <italic toggle="yes">S. subtriquetrus,</italic> with an overall prevalence of 6% (95% CI: 0&#8211;20%). The presence of different suitable IHs and definitive hosts in North America (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>) might have contributed to the presence of <italic toggle="yes">S. subtriquetrus. S. subtriquetrus</italic> was documented in three IHs including <italic toggle="yes">F. fragilis, He. anceps,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Ps. columella.</italic> These amphistome species have been reported as the dominant parasite in <italic toggle="yes">Castor canadensis</italic> in North America (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>), and this might have contributed to the overall high prevalence in snails. A high prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">S. subtriquetrus</italic> has also been reported in Poland (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>) and the Czech Republic (<xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>) in beavers, but no study reported the prevalence of IHs in the same countries.</p><p>The highest overall prevalence estimated in snails from Asia was for <italic toggle="yes">P. epiclitum</italic>, followed by <italic toggle="yes">E. explanatum</italic>. The known snail host that serves as IHs for <italic toggle="yes">P. epiclitum</italic> is <italic toggle="yes">I. exustus,</italic> which is primarily an Asiatic species, whose distribution includes India, Thailand, the Malay Peninsula, and Sumatra (<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). It was not possible to conduct a meta-analysis for various amphistome species as they were surveyed only in a limited number of studies and on one host species. This was also observed with other intermediate host snails, with only <italic toggle="yes">G. truncatula</italic> infected with <italic toggle="yes">C. daubneyi</italic> qualifying for meta-analysis from natural infection and <italic toggle="yes">G. truncatula</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. tropicus</italic> from experimental infection, whereas other infected snails were investigated in various studies.</p><p>The results from the experimental infection show that some amphistome species are more infective to a wider range of IH species, while others are specific to certain species. Of these, <italic toggle="yes">C. daubneyi</italic> (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">55&#8211;57</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">C. microbothrium</italic> (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">58&#8211;60</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">Z. lunata</italic> (<xref rid="ref61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, <xref rid="ref62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>), and <italic toggle="yes">P. cervi</italic> (<xref rid="ref63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>) infected multiple (&#8805;4) IHs. According to Richards and Shade (<xref rid="ref64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>), genetic variations within and between species may account for the variability observed in the degree of infection of each amphistome species to different snail host species.</p><p>The highest pooled prevalence of amphistome species in intermediate host snails was observed between 2004 and 2013 for natural infections and between 1984 and 1993 for experimental infections. However, the results also showed that the pooled prevalence of infection lowered with time, with both natural and experimental infections recording the lowest infection rate between 2014 and 2023. This may be due to greater awareness raised in snail control programs for natural infection. Arfaa (<xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>) previously reported that snail control strategies, such as the Anti-Bilharziasis campaign, will subsequently result in a significant decrease in the rate of <italic toggle="yes">Paramphistomum</italic> infections, and this might be the case, as confirmed by our results. Furthermore, the consequences of climate change may potentially be related to the variation noted in the prevalence of amphistomes (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). The lowest pooled infection rate shown by the experimental infection could be explained by the observed scarcity of epidemiological studies that have been conducted and published in recent years.</p><p>There was a significant difference in the pooled prevalence of amphistome species results among detection techniques. Cercarial shedding resulted in low pooled prevalence from both natural and experimental infections in this meta-analysis. Although it is a common method used to detect infections due to its relative affordability and ease of use, several authors have criticized it as inaccurate as it underestimates the true prevalence in the case of prepatent infection in intermediate host snails (<xref rid="ref66" ref-type="bibr">66&#8211;68</xref>). This was in line with Born-Torrijos et al. (<xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>), who found that snail dissection yielded more accurate results and subsequently greater prevalence than those based on cercarial shedding. The author further demonstrated that PCR-based methods were more accurate in determining the infection levels (<xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>), although the presence of DNA of an amphistome might not indicate the suitability of the snail as an intermediate host. This is consistent with the findings by Tigga et al. (<xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>), who suggested that because PCR-based techniques are sensitive and economical for large-scale detection, molecular approaches will lead to actual or higher prevalence than the shedding and snail dissection. However, only a few reviewed studies used PCR-based techniques, and this may be due to the cost of equipment and reagents and the requirement of trained personnel to carry out molecular analysis (<xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>).</p><p>A high level of heterogeneity and publication bias was observed across continents and among snails. This could be due to the differences in the seasons in which the data were collected, the study designs, and the lack of standard protocol in sample collection.</p></sec><sec id="sec27"><title>Strengths and limitations</title><p>The primary strengths of this systematic review and meta-analysis were adherence to the principle of PRISMA guidelines, the application of inclusion and exclusion criteria, and the provision of up-to-date estimates based on a quality effects model. Heterogeneity was analyzed using subgroup analyses. In addition, to the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to document the pooled prevalence of amphistome species in snails from various continents in a broad research period (1984&#8211;2023).</p><p>Limitations noted from this review included publication bias. The heterogeneity of the included studies in terms of study design, detection method, and quantification methods made it difficult to achieve a consistent meta-analysis despite using a standardized analysis process. Several studies failed to provide complete details on the information on the prevalence of amphistome species among snail species, and hence, few studies were eligible worldwide. From the few studies reviewed, the number of published studies was not evenly distributed across continents. Meta-analysis could not be conducted on some snail species and amphistome species due to the limited number of studies carried out. Thus, in this review, the prevalence data may not fully represent the prevalence of amphistome species among freshwater snail species worldwide.</p><p>The majority of the studies included in this review used cercarial shedding rather than PCR for the detection of amphistome infection. Cercarial shedding is less sensitive to the detection of amphistomes due to its inherent limitation, which may result in a low prevalence of amphistomes among snail species across continents. The estimated pooled prevalence of amphistome infections among freshwater snails observed in this review might be an underestimate of the true infection prevalence, especially in Africa, where the diversity of both amphistome species and freshwater snails is known to be high.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec28"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The review provides valuable insights into the prevalence of amphistome infections in snails across different IHs and continents. However, results indicated a paucity of information on the prevalence of amphistome species in IHs. Hence, future studies should focus on determining the geographical expansion and the prevalence of amphistome species and their intermediate snail hosts, accompanied by extensive experimental infection studies to determine the susceptibility of various freshwater snail species across different geographical regions.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec29"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref>, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="sec30"><title>Author contributions</title><p>IN: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Writing &#8211; original draft, Methodology, Investigation, Formal analysis, Data curation. MM: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Validation, Supervision, Conceptualization. SM: Writing &#8211; review &amp; editing, Validation, Supervision, Conceptualization.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="fn0001"><p>
<sup>1</sup>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.epigear.com" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.epigear.com</ext-link>
</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec32"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec33"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec34"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2024.1418979/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2024.1418979/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM2" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Image_1.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfukenyi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukaratirwa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Amphistome infections in domestic and wild ruminants in east and southern Africa: a review</article-title>. <source>Onderstepoort J Vet Res</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>85</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4102/ojvr.v85i1.1584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6244199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30456960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horak</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Paramphistomiasis of domestic ruminants</article-title>. <source>Adv Parasitol</source>. (<year>1971</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>72</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0065-308x(08)60159-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4927976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lotfy</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brant</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashmawy</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Devkota</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mkoji</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loker</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A molecular approach for identification of paramphistomes from Africa and Asia</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>174</volume>:<fpage>234</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2010.08.027</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20880634</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huson</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Paramphistomosis of ruminants: an emerging parasitic disease in Europe</article-title>. <source>Trends Parasitol</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>836</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pt.2017.07.002</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28754416</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajipour</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirshekar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajibemani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghorani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and risk factors associated with amphistome parasites in cattle in Iran</article-title>. <source>Vet Med Sci</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>105</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/vms3.330</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32767552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7840199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sibula</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyagura</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malatji</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukaratirwa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and geographical distribution of amphistomes of African wild ruminants: a scoping review</article-title>. <source>Int J Parasitol Parasites Wildl</source>. (<year>2024</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>100906</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijppaw.2024.100906</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38298202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10827595</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dutt</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Amphistomiasis in an adult buffalo [dairy cattle, India]</article-title>. <source>Indian Vet J</source>. (<year>1978</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>1006</fpage>. PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">751961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dube</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aisien</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Descriptive studies on Paramphistomes of small domestic ruminants in southern Nigeria</article-title>. <source>Zimbabwe J Sci Technol</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sey</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>CRC handbook of the zoology of Amphistomes</source>. <publisher-name>Boca Raton, USA: CRC Press</publisher-name> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Superfamily Paramphistomoidea Fischoeder</article-title> In: <source>Keys to the Trematoda</source>, vol. <volume>2005</volume>. <publisher-loc>Wallingford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CABI Publishing</publisher-name> (<year>1901</year>). <fpage>221</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tandon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shylla</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghatani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Amphistomes</article-title>. <source>Adv Exp Med Biol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>1154</volume>:<fpage>255</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>77</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-18616-6_9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31297765</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zadoks</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skuce</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A universal approach to molecular identification of rumen fluke species across hosts, continents, and sample types</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>605259</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2020.605259</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33748201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7969503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sey</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Handbook of the zoology of Amphistomes</source>. <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, Florida</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name> (<year>2000</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinnik</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Paramphistomum daubneyi</italic> sp. nov. from cattle and its snail host in the Kenya highlands</article-title>. <source>Parasitology</source>. (<year>1962</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>143</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182000024070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eduardo</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Zoogeographical affinities of paramphistomids of ruminants</article-title>. <source>Trans Natl Acad Sci Tech</source>. (<year>1987</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>229</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chingwena</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukaratirwa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chimbari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Susceptibility of freshwater snails to the amphistome <italic toggle="yes">Calicophoron microbothrium</italic> and the influence of the species on susceptibility of <italic toggle="yes">Bulinus tropicus</italic> to <italic toggle="yes">Schistosoma haematobium</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Schistosoma mattheei</italic> infections</article-title>. <source>J Parasitol</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>880</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1645/0022-3395(2002)088[0880:SOFSTT]2.0.CO;2</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12435124</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Kock</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolmarans</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Distribution, habitats and role as intermediate host of the freshwater snail, <italic toggle="yes">Bulinus forskalii</italic>, in South Africa</article-title>. <source>Onderstepoort J Vet Res</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>72</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4102/ojvr.v72i2.214</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16137134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanabria</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Titi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mekroud</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vignoles</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreyfuss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rondelaud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Paramphistomum daubneyi</italic>: characteristics of infection in three lymnaeid species</article-title>. <source>Parasite</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>445</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/parasite/2012194445</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23193532</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3671451</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laidemitt</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zawadzki</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brant</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mutuku</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mkoji</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loker</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Loads of trematodes: discovering hidden diversity of paramphistomoids in Kenyan ruminants</article-title>. <source>Parasitology</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>144</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>47</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182016001827</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27762185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5300004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rafiq</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeb</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaz Junior</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular characterization of <italic toggle="yes">Paramphistomum cervi</italic> in buffaloes</article-title>. <source>Acta Sci Vet</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>1755</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22456/1679-9216.107107</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rolfe</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boray</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology of paramphistomosis in cattle</article-title>. <source>Int J Parasitol</source>. (<year>1991</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>813</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0020-7519(91)90150-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1774118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oxman</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vist</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falck-Ytter</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso-Coello</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>GRADE: an emerging consensus on rating quality of evidence and strength of recommendations</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>336</volume>:<fpage>924</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.39489.470347.AD</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18436948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2335261</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doi</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thalib</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A quality-effects model for meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Epidemiology</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>94</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>100</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/EDE.0b013e31815c24e7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18090860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barendregt</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doi</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Meta-analysis of prevalence</article-title>. <source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>974</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jech-2013-203104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23963506</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deeks</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Measuring inconsistency in meta-analyses</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. (<year>2003</year>) <volume>327</volume>:<fpage>557</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.327.7414.557</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12958120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC192859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ostrowski de N&#250;&#241;ez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spatz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The life cycle of <italic toggle="yes">Zygocotyle lunata</italic> (Trematoda, Paramphistomoidea) in the subtropical region of South America</article-title>. <source>Rev Mex Biodiverse</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>82</volume>:<fpage>581</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22201/ib.20078706e.2011.2.470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dar</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rondelaud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vignoles</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreyfuss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Pseudosuccinea columella</italic>: age resistance to <italic toggle="yes">Calicophoron daubneyi</italic> infection in two snail populations</article-title>. <source>Parasitology</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/parasite/2015003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4321400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25664810</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Southgate</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rollinson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knowles</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Bulinus tropicus</italic> from Central Kenya acting as a host for <italic toggle="yes">Schistosoma bovis</italic></article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res</source>. (<year>1985</year>) <volume>71</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00932919</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3984452</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinnik</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinnik</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The life cycle of <italic toggle="yes">Paramphistomum microbothrium</italic> Fischoeder, 1901 (Trematoda, Paramphistomidae)</article-title>. <source>Parasitology</source>. (<year>1954</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>285</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>99</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182000018916</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13214899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinnik</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Paramphistomum phillerouxi</italic> sp. nov. (Trematoda: Paramphistomatidae) and its development in <italic toggle="yes">Bulinus forskalii</italic></article-title>. <source>J Helminthol</source>. (<year>1961</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0022149X00024792</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13723003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinnik</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The snail hosts of certain Paramphistomatidae and Gastrothylacidae (Trematoda) discovered by the late Dr. PL LeRoux in Africa</article-title>. <source>J Helminthol</source>. (<year>1965</year>) <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>141</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0022149X00020551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5886483</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Southgate</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A note on the life-cycles of some amphistome flukes in Zambia</article-title>. <source>J Helminthol</source>. (<year>1979</year>) <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>251</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0022149X00006039</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez-Warleta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lladosa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castro-Hermida</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;nez-Ibeas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conesa</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mu&#241;oz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Bovine paramphistomosis in Galicia (Spain): prevalence, intensity, aetiology and geospatial distribution of the infection</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>191</volume>:<fpage>252</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2012.09.006</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23022489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lean</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zadoks</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sargison</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skuce</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of the rumen fluke, <italic toggle="yes">Calicophoron daubneyi</italic>, in GB livestock: possible implications for liver fluke diagnosis</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>195</volume>:<fpage>65</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2013.01.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23411375</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrous</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rondelaud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreyfuss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cabaret</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Infection of <italic toggle="yes">Lymnaea truncatula</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Lymnaea glabra</italic> by <italic toggle="yes">Fasciola hepatica</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Paramphistomum daubneyi</italic> in farms of Central France</article-title>. <source>Vet Res</source>. (<year>1999</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10081118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrous</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rondelaud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreyfuss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A field study of natural infections in three freshwater snails with <italic toggle="yes">Fasciola hepatica</italic> and/or <italic toggle="yes">Paramphistomum daubneyi</italic> in Central France</article-title>. <source>J Helminthol</source>. (<year>2000</year>) <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>189</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0022149X00700897</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10953217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ates</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Umur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Paramphistome species in water buffaloes and intermediate hosts in the K&#305;z&#305;l&#305;rmak Delta in Samsun Province, Turkey</article-title>. <source>Acta Parasitol</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>213</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11686-020-00278-z</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32948931</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Degueurce</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrous</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreyfuss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rondelaud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gevrey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Paramphistomum daubneyi</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Fasciola hepatica</italic>: the prevalence of natural or experimental infections in four species of freshwater snails in eastern France</article-title>. <source>J Helminthol</source>. (<year>1999</year>) <volume>73</volume>:<fpage>197</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>202</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0022149X00700435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreyfuss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vignoles</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rondelaud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Paramphistomum daubneyi</italic>: the number of sporocysts developing in experimentally and naturally infected <italic toggle="yes">Galba truncatula</italic></article-title>. <source>J Parasitol Res</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>103</volume>:<fpage>345</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-008-0978-4</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18470698</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iglesias-Pi&#241;eiro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez-Warleta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castro-Hermida</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>C&#243;rdoba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez-Lanza</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manga-Gonz&#225;lez</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Transmission of <italic toggle="yes">Calicophoron daubneyi</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Fasciola hepatica</italic> in Galicia (Spain): temporal follow-up in the intermediate and definitive hosts</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>610</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-016-1892-8</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27894356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5126829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brophy</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rumen fluke (<italic toggle="yes">Calicophoron daubneyi</italic>) on welsh farms: prevalence, risk factors and observations on co-infection with <italic toggle="yes">Fasciola hepatica</italic></article-title>. <source>Parasitology</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>144</volume>:<fpage>237</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>47</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182016001797</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28145217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5300002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalesman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brophy</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Confirmation of <italic toggle="yes">Galba truncatula</italic> as an intermediate host snail for <italic toggle="yes">Calicophoron daubneyi</italic> in Great Britain, with evidence of alternative snail species hosting <italic toggle="yes">Fasciola hepatica</italic></article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>656</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-015-1271-x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26695066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4688931</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mage</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourgne</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toullieu</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rondelaud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreyfuss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Fasciola hepatica</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Paramphistomum daubneyi</italic>: changes in prevalences of natural infections in cattle and in <italic toggle="yes">Lymnaea truncatula</italic> from Central France over the past 12 years</article-title>. <source>Vet Res</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>439</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>47</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/vetres:2002030</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12387481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;nez-Ibeas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez-Warleta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;nez-Valladares</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castro-Hermida</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez-Lanza</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minambres</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Development and validation of a mtDNA multiplex PCR for identification and discrimination of <italic toggle="yes">Calicophoron daubneyi</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Fasciola hepatica</italic> in the <italic toggle="yes">Galba truncatula</italic> snail</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>195</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2012.12.048</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23333073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rondelaud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vignoles</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreyfuss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Larval trematode infections in <italic toggle="yes">Galba truncatula</italic> (gastropoda, Lymnaeidae) from the Brenne regional natural park, Central France</article-title>. <source>J Helminthol</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>256</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0022149X15000073</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25804319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rondelaud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vignoles</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreyfuss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in the populations of two Lymnaeidae and their infection by <italic toggle="yes">Fasciola hepatica</italic> and/or <italic toggle="yes">Calicophoron daubneyi</italic> over the past 30 years in Central France</article-title>. <source>Animals</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>3566</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani12243566</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36552486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9774278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zintl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Campos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trudgett</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chryssafidis</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Talavera-Arce</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Bovine paramphistomes in Ireland</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>204</volume>:<fpage>199</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>208</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2014.05.024</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24907069</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flowers</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Three amphistome cercariae (Paramphistomidae) from North Carolina</article-title>. <source>J Elisha Mitchell Sci Soc</source>. (<year>1996</year>) <volume>112</volume>:<fpage>80</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A review of helminth communities in beaver (<italic toggle="yes">Castor</italic> spp.) with a survey of <italic toggle="yes">Castor canadensis</italic> in Alberta, Canada</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pursley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>, editors. <conf-name>Worldwide furbearer conference proceedings. Frostburg, Maryland, USA. Volume II</conf-name>. <publisher-loc>Maryland</publisher-loc> (<year>1981</year>), <fpage>657</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>689</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dr&#243;zdz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Demiaszkiewicz</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lachowicz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Endoparasites of the beaver <italic toggle="yes">Castor fiber</italic> (L.) in Northeast Poland</article-title>. <source>Helminthologia</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>99</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>102</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Demiaszkiewicz</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lachowicz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuligowska</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pyziel</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Be&#322;&#380;ecki</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miltko</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Endoparasites of the European beaver (<italic toggle="yes">Castor fiber L</italic>. 1758) in North-Eastern Poland</article-title>. <source>J Vet Res</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>223</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2478/bvip-2014-0033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#225;ca</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavl&#225;sek</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vorel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Stichorchis subtriquetrus</italic> (Digenea: Paramphistomatidae) from Eurasian beaver (<italic toggle="yes">Castor fiber</italic>) in the Czech Republic</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>114</volume>:<fpage>2933</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-015-4495-y</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25916466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Benovics</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reslov&#225;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#352;korp&#237;kov&#225;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seidlov&#225;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikulka</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Helminth fauna of the Eurasian beaver in the Czech Republic with remarks on the genetic diversity of specialist <italic toggle="yes">Stichorchis subtriquetrus</italic> (Digenea: Cladorchiidae)</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>121</volume>:<fpage>633</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-021-07379-2</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35076776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malek</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Medical and economic malacology</source>. <publisher-name>New York, USA: Academic Press, Inc.</publisher-name> (<year>1974</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrous</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rondelaud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreyfuss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Paramphistomum daubneyi</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Fasciola hepatica</italic>: the effect of dual infection on prevalence and cercarial shedding in preadult <italic toggle="yes">Lymnaea glabra</italic></article-title>. <source>J Parasitol</source>. (<year>1996</year>) <volume>82</volume>:<fpage>1026</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3284217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8973417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Augot</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abrous</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rondelaud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreyfuss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Paramphistomum daubneyi</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Fasciola hepatica</italic>: the redial burden and cercarial shedding in <italic toggle="yes">Lymnaea truncatula</italic> subjected to successive unimiracidial cross-exposures</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res</source>. (<year>1996</year>) <volume>82</volume>:<fpage>623</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004360050175</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8875570</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dreyfuss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vignoles</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rondelaud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Pseudosuccinea columella</italic>: experimental co-infections of juvenile and pre-adult snails with the digeneans <italic toggle="yes">Calicophoron daubneyi</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Fasciola hepatica</italic></article-title>. <source>J Helminthol</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>753</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0022149X15001078</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26902671</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Southgate</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warlow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knowles</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The influence of <italic toggle="yes">Calicophoron microbothrium</italic> on the susceptibility of <italic toggle="yes">Bulinus tropicus</italic> to Schistosoma bovis</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res</source>. (<year>1989</year>) <volume>75</volume>:<fpage>381</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00931134</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2726720</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malatji</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Myende</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukaratirwa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Are freshwater snails, <italic toggle="yes">Melanoides</italic> sp. and invasive <italic toggle="yes">Tarebia granifera</italic> (Gastropoda: Thiaridae) suitable intermediate hosts for <italic toggle="yes">Calicophoron microbothrium</italic> (Trematoda: Paramphistomoidea)? An experimental study</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>705954</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.705954</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34368286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8336920</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mavenyengwa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukaratirwa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Obwolo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monrad</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Observations on mass production of <italic toggle="yes">Calicophoron microbothrium</italic> metacercariae from experimentally and naturally infected <italic toggle="yes">Bulinus tropicus</italic></article-title>. <source>Onderstepoort J Vet Res</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>73</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>100</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4102/ojvr.v73i2.153</pub-id> PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16958259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ostrowski de N&#250;&#241;ez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spatz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez Cappa</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>New intermediate hosts in the life cycle of <italic toggle="yes">Zygocotyle lunata</italic> in South America</article-title>. <source>J Parasitol</source>. (<year>2003</year>) <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>193</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1645/0022-3395(2003)089[0193:NIHITL]2.0.CO;2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12659330</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Etges</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Zygocotyle lunata</italic>: laboratory maintenance in snails and mice</article-title>. <source>Proc Helminthol Soc Wash</source>. (<year>1992</year>) <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>22</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Castro-Trejo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia-Vasquez</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casildo-Nieto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The susceptibility of Lymnaeid snails to <italic toggle="yes">Paramphistomum cervi</italic> infections in Mexico</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol</source>. (<year>1990</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0304-4017(90)90125-U</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2343525</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shade</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The genetic variation of compatibility in <italic toggle="yes">Biomphalaria glabrata</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Schistosoma mansoni</italic></article-title>. <source>J Parasitol</source>. (<year>1987</year>) <volume>73</volume>:<fpage>1146</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3282295</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3437352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arfaa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A study of <italic toggle="yes">Paramphistomum microbothrium</italic> in Khuzistan S.-W. Iran</article-title>. <source>Ann Parasitol Hum Comp</source>. (<year>1962</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>549</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/parasite/1962374549</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14013712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Trematode infections in a gastropod host misrepresented by observing shed cercariae</article-title>. <source>J Exp Mar Biol Ecol</source>. (<year>1990</year>) <volume>143</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-0981(90)90115-S</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Born-Torrijos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poulin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raga</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holzer</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Estimating trematode prevalence in snail hosts using a single-step duplex PCR: how badly does cercarial shedding underestimate infection rates?</article-title><source>Parasite Vectors</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>243</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-7-243</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24884978</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4068961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tigga</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauri</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deb</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kullu</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of snail's intermediate host infected with different trematodes cercariae in and around Ranchi</article-title>. <source>Vet World</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>630</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14202/vetworld.2014.630-634</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>