<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10437118</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC10437118.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">10437118</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">10437118</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37601747</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1227654</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effect of classical music on growth performance, stress level, antioxidant index, immune function and meat quality in broilers at different stocking densities</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names initials="X">Xinlei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn0002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names initials="J">Jiangang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn0002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names initials="B">Bowen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1719804/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yanci</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names initials="H">Hongjian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yanshuang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jing</surname><given-names initials="J">Jialin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhihua</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1809942/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="L">Lihua</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c002" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>College of Animal Science and Technology, Hebei Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Baoding</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>College of Food Science and Technology, Hebei Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Baoding</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Baoding Vocational and Technical College</institution>, <addr-line>Baoding</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Hebei Jiuxing Agriculture and Animal Husbandry Development Co., Ltd.</institution>, <addr-line>Baoding</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>College of Mechatronical and Electrical Engineering, Hebei Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Baoding</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn id="fn0003" fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Tugay Ayasan, Osmaniye Korkut Ata University, T&#252;rkiye</p></fn><fn id="fn0004" fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Khalid M. Mahrose, Zagazig University, Egypt; Zhigang Song, Shandong Agricultural University, China</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Zhihua Feng, <email>fzhauh@163.com</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Lihua Li, <email>274788053@qq.com</email></corresp><fn id="fn0002" fn-type="equal"><p><sup>&#8224;</sup>These authors have contributed equally to this work and share first authorship</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">427755</issue-id><elocation-id>1227654</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>19</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-08-21 14:25:10.263"><day>21</day><month>08</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 Gao, Gong, Yang, Liu, Xu, Hao, Jing, Feng and Li.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Gao, Gong, Yang, Liu, Xu, Hao, Jing, Feng and Li</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-10-1227654.pdf"/><abstract><p>High-stocking density is one of the factors that can easily cause oxidative stress and inflammatory reaction of broilers. Currently, music therapy has been proposed to help animals relieve stress to some extent. However, it is still unclear whether classical music can alleviate stress in broilers at high stocking densities. Hence, this study aimed to investigate the effects of classical music on growth performance, stress level, antioxidant index, immune function and meat quality of broilers under different stocking densities. A total of 540 one-day-old broilers with similar body weight were randomly divided into 6 treatment groups, with 6 replicates per group, which included two feeding environments (with/without classical music) and three stocking densities (15.5, 17.9, and 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup>), thereby making a 2&#8201;&#215;&#8201;3 factorial arrangement. The results showed as follows: increasing stocking density decreased the average daily feed intake and average daily gain (ADG), increased feed-to-gain ratio (F/G) and mortality of broilers. Moreover, increased density resulted in an increase in serum corticosterone (CORT) and adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH) levels. Increasing stocking density decreased spleen and bursal indices, serum immunoglobulin A (IgA), immunoglobulin G (IgG), and immunoglobulin M (IgM) levels. Increasing stocking density elevated serum malondialdehyde (MDA) and decreased catalase (CAT), superoxide dismutase (SOD) and glutathione peroxidase (GSH-PX) activities. Increasing stocking density decreased serum total protein (TP) levels and increased total cholesterol (TC) and glucose (GLU) levels. Additionally, increasing stocking density decreased the cooking liss of pectoralis and increased the L*<sub>24h</sub> value of pectoralis. Meanwhile, playing classical music for broilers increased their ADG and decreased F/G, and decreased serum CORT, ACTH, GLU content. In addition, the bursa of Fabricius index, serum IgA and IgG contents as well as the a*<sub>24h</sub> value of pectoralis was increased under the music therapy. In conclusion, high-stocking density (20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup>) harmed the growth performance and health of broilers, and the classical music stimulus ameliorated the negative effects to some extent.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>stocking density</kwd><kwd>classical music</kwd><kwd>broilers</kwd><kwd>growth performance</kwd><kwd>stress</kwd><kwd>antioxidation</kwd><kwd>immune function</kwd><kwd>meat quality</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="7"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="60"/><page-count count="11"/><word-count count="8985"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Animal Nutrition and Metabolism</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><label>1.</label><title>Introduction</title><p>In the modern poultry industry, high density is a common phenomenon in broiler rearing, which enables producers to reduce rearing costs and gain more profit. Regarding the breeding standard of broiler stocking density, it varies widely among different countries. For example, the welfare guidelines of the National Chicken Council advocate an ideal rearing density of 41.5&#8201;kg/m<sup>2</sup> for broilers over 2&#8201;kg (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), the stocking densities in Netherlands, the United Kingdom, and Switzerland are 45&#8211;54&#8201;kg/m<sup>2</sup>, 40&#8201;kg/m<sup>2</sup>, and 30&#8211;36&#8201;kg/m<sup>2</sup>, respectively (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). It is well known that high-density stocking is a major contributor to broiler stress. Intensive stocking not only increases corticosterone levels in broilers to induce physiological stress (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>) but also decreases average daily feed intake and average daily gain and increases feed-to-gain ratio in broilers (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Li et al. (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) indicated that serum immunoglobulins (immunoglobulin G and immunoglobulin A) decreased significantly in broilers as stocking density increased from 15 to 18 birds/m<sup>2</sup>, which also led to an imbalance in serum antioxidant levels (decreased superoxide dismutase and glutathione peroxidase activities and increased malondialdehyde levels). Simsek et al. (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) also indicated that when broiler stocking density reached 47.3&#8201;kg/m<sup>2</sup> may lead to oxidative stress and a decrease in bursal weight in broilers. Therefore, how to mitigate some of the adverse effects of increased stocking density on broilers has become an urgent issue in large-scale broiler breeding.</p><p>In humans, music is widely used to enhance well-being, reduce stress, and distract patients from unpleasant symptoms (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Music therapy is now being used to improve the environment of farm animals, which is considered an effective method to improve animal welfare. Playing music can not only cover up the background noise in the house environment, but also reduce anxiety, stress, and aggressive behavior by providing auditory enrichment. For example, cows exposed to classical music showed better performance in terms of milking time, milking speed, cortisol hormone and behavioral parameters (reduction in stereotyped behavior, etc.) (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Listening to classical music has a calming effect on pet dogs in the stressful environment of veterinary hospitals (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Short-term classical music stimulation increased activity, tail-dragging and playful behavior in fattening pigs, while long-term music stimulation increased serum interleukin-2, interferon-&#947; and immunoglobulin levels and decreased serum interleukin-4 levels (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Early studies suggested that music altered hypothalamic&#8211;pituitary&#8211;adrenal axis activity by modulating the hypothalamus (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), inducing an increase in dopamine levels in the brains of chicks and hypertensive rats, and inhibiting sympathetic activity (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). The well-developed cochlea of birds has been reported to guide the recognition of audio and thus can process relative tones as in the primary auditory cortex of most mammals (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). African grey parrots and sulfur-crested cockatoos spontaneously move in sync with the music (head bobbing and foot lifting) (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), suggesting that birds also have the ability to perceive external rhythms like mammals. Furthermore, according to our previous study, classical music was found to have better effects on broiler health compared to popular and ethnic music (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>).</p><p>Applying music to the production of animal farming is simple and easy. However, to the best of our knowledge, no studies have been reported on the effects of classical music on broilers, not to mention at high densities. Therefore, in our study, the effects of classical music on growth performance, stress level, antioxidant index, immune function and meat quality of broiler chickens at different densities were investigated.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><label>2.</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec3"><label>2.1.</label><title>Birds, experimental design, and management</title><p>Broilers in this study were purchased from Jiuxing Hatchery (Jiuxing Agricultural and Livestock Development Co., Ltd., Baoding, China). A total of 540 one-day-old Cobb broilers with average body weight of (44.66&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.05&#8201;g) were randomly divided into six treatment groups with six replicates per group. The six treatment groups included two feeding environments (with/without classical music) and three stocking densities (15.5, 17.9, and 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup>). The number of chickens per replicate for each density was 13, 15 and 17, respectively. The experiment lasted for 42 d. Classical music selected from Indian Raga included <italic toggle="yes">Raga khamaj</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Raga yaman</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Raga Gunkali</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Raga Durga</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Raga jayajavanti</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Raga bhupali</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Raga darbari</italic>. The tracks used in this study are searchable on Himalayan Audio Platform.<xref rid="fn0001" ref-type="fn"><sup>1</sup></xref></p><p>The experiment was conducted from June 21 to August 1, 2022. Two environmental control rooms (L&#8201;&#215;&#8201;W&#8201;&#215;&#8201;H&#8201;=&#8201;10&#8201;m&#8201;&#215;&#8201;5&#8201;m&#8201;&#215;&#8201;3&#8201;m) with the same feeding level and adjacent to each other were selected. The broilers without music in the house were taken as the control group, and broilers with music in the other coop were used as the music treatment group. Broilers in the experimental group began to play music from 1&#8201;day of age. There is no sound interference between the two houses. The chicken coop is a three-layer superimposed cage with a single cage area of 0.84&#8201;m<sup>2</sup> and semi-mechanical ventilation. The music playing cycle is 3&#8201;h each from 5:00 to 8:00, 9:00 to 12:00, 16:00 to 19:00, and 20:00 to 23:00 every day. The digital noise meter was used to measure the volume in the house. Two smart loudspeakers with the same specifications were placed 2&#8201;m above the music treatment house. The speakers were connected <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> an audio cable. The two speakers played music at the same time so that the music can evenly cover the whole music treatment house. The volume was kept constant during the playing process, and the music decibel was set at 65&#8211;75&#8201;dB. During the experiment, all birds were allowed to feed and drink freely. The temperature remained at 34&#176;C for the first week, then gradually decreased to 24&#176;C at a rate of 3&#8211;4&#176;C per week, and remained unchanged thereafter. From 14 to 35 d of age, broilers were kept in light for 20&#8201;h and dark for 4&#8201;h, and the remaining days were kept in light for 24&#8201;h. The average relative humidity in the chicken house was kept between 60% and 70%, and the chickens were fed according to the routine feeding management procedures and immunization procedures. The rations were prepared using a corn-soybean meal basal diet, referring to the Chinese Chicken Feeding Standard (NY/T3645-2020) and the National Research Council (<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). The composition and nutritional levels of the basal diet are shown in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Composition and calculation analysis of the basal diets (% dry basis).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Items</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Content (%)</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#8211;14 d of age</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15&#8211;35 d of age</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36&#8211;42 d of age</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" char="." colspan="4" rowspan="1">Ingredients</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corn</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.20</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.80</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.80</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean meal (43%CP)</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.90</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.10</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat flour</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corn gluten meal (60%CP)</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.90</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peanut meal</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feather meal</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soya-bean oil</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CaHPO4</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limestone</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-methionine</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Premix<xref rid="tfn1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" char="." colspan="4" rowspan="1">Nutrient levels<xref rid="tfn2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ME/(MJ/kg)</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.26</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.89</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.20</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.20</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lys</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Met+Cys</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thr</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trp</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TP</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn1"><label>a</label><p>Premix is a diet containing: Vitamin A 12,000&#8201;IU; Vitamin B<sub>1</sub> 3 mg; Vitamin B<sub>2</sub> 9 mg; Vitamin B<sub>6</sub> 4.5&#8201;mg; Vitamin B<sub>12</sub> 0.03&#8201;mg; Vitamin D<sub>3</sub> 4,500 IU; Vitamin E 36,000&#8201;mg; Vitamin K 36,000&#8201;mg; Vitamin H 0.18&#8201;mg; D-Calcium-Pantothenate 13.5&#8201;mg; folic acid 1.8&#8201;mg; Nicotinic acid 45&#8201;mg; Fe 110&#8201;mg; Cu 16&#8201;mg; Mn 120&#8201;mg; Zn 110&#8201;mg; Se 0.35&#8201;mg; Iodine 1.5&#8201;mg.</p></fn><fn id="tfn2"><label>b</label><p>Nutrient levels were all calculated values.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>2.2.</label><title>Growth performance</title><p>The total body weight and total feed intake of 42-day-old chickens were recorded for each replicate, and the daily gain and feed conversion ratio were calculated. The overall mortality rate for each replicate was considered as the total mortality rate during the experiment. The average daily feed intake (ADFI), average daily gain (ADG), feed-to-gain ratio (F/G), and mortality rate of broilers were calculated at the end of the experiment.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>2.3.</label><title>Serum stress, antioxidant, and biochemical indexes</title><p>The day the experiment ended (42 d), samples were selected from two average-weight broilers in each replicate after 12&#8201;h of fasting. Blood samples were collected from wing veins in 10&#8201;mL non-anticoagulated vacuum tubes, placed at room temperature, centrifuged at 3,000&#8201;r/min for 10&#8201;min to prepare serum, and stored at &#8722;20&#176;C. The concentrations of serum corticosterone (CORT, NO. HY-10063) and adrenocorticotropin (ACTH, NO. HY-10175) were determined by the enzyme-free method, and creatine kinase (CK, N-acetylcysteine method) was determined by the colorimetric method. The kit was purchased from the Beijing Huaying Institute of Biotechnology (Beijing, China). Analysis of serum total antioxidant capacity (T-AOC, NO. A015-2-1), catalase (CAT, NO. A007-1-1), superoxide dismutase (SOD, NO. A001-3-2), glutathione peroxidase (GSH-PX, NO. A005-1-2) activity, and malondialdehyde (MDA, NO. A003-1-2) content, serum biochemical indices total protein (TP, NO. A045-2-2), albumin (ALB, NO. A028-2-1), total cholesterol (TC, NO. A112-2-1) and glucose (GLU, NO. F006-1-1) content were carried out according to the instructions of the kit Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute (Nanjing, Jiangsu, P.R. China).</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><label>2.4.</label><title>Immunologic function</title><p>Selected broilers were dislocated and executed by neck dislocation after blood collection, and the thymus, spleen and bursa were quickly removed for weighing and calculation of immune organ index after confirmation of death.</p><p>The contents of immunoglobulin A (IgA, NO. H108-1-2), immunoglobulin M (IgM, NO. H109-1-2), and immunoglobulin G (IgG, NO. H106-1-2) in serum were detected with chicken specific enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay kit purchased from Nanjing Jiancheng Institute of Bioengineering(Nanjing, Jiangsu, P.R. China).</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><label>2.5.</label><title>Meat quality determination</title><p>The selected broilers were slaughtered and then uniformly stripped of the left pectoral muscle for 24&#8201;h. The lightness (L*), redness (a*), and yellowness (b*) of the pectoral muscle were determined using a CR-10 colorimeter (Tokyo, Japan) 24&#8201;h after stripping the left pectoral muscle of each slaughtered broiler. Cooking loss and shear force were determined by referring to Cai et al. (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><label>2.6.</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The experimental data were expressed as &#8220;mean&#8201;&#177;&#8201;standard deviation,&#8221; and the general linear model (GLM) program in SPSS 26.0 statistical software was used for two-factor ANOVA. The main effects of the model included classical music and stocking density and their interaction effects. When the interaction effects were significantly different, Duncan&#8217;s method was used to compare the significance of the difference between the mean values of each group. <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05 indicates a significant difference, while 0.05&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.10 indicates a trend of difference. The mortality of broiler was analyzed by the Chi-square test.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec9"><label>3.</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec10"><label>3.1.</label><title>Growth performance</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, different stocking densities had significant effects on ADFI, ADG, F/G, and mortality of broilers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The ADFI in the 15.5 birds/m<sup>2</sup> and 17.9 birds/m<sup>2</sup> groups was higher than that in the 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Increasing stocking density decreased the ADG of broilers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The F/G of the 15.5 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group was lower than that of the 17.9 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group and 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). With the increase in stocking density, the mortality of broilers increased (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Playing classical music increased ADG and decreased the F/G of broilers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). After classical music intervention, broilers F/G was significantly lower in the 17.9 and 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup> groups than in the group without music intervention (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The effect of interaction on broilers F/G was observed, where playing classical music significantly mitigated the increase in broilers F/G caused by increased stocking density at 17.9 and 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effect of classical music and stocking density on growth performance of broilers.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Items</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">ADFI/g</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">ADG/g</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">F/G</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Mortality (%)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stocking density (birds/m<sup>2</sup>)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Classical music</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">15.5</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104.76 &#177; 3.58</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.36 &#177; 1.90</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80 &#177; 0.03<sup>d</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 &#177; 3.14</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104.66 &#177; 2.38</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.57 &#177; 1.51</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82 &#177; 0.03<sup>cd</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 &#177; 3.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">17.9</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.40 &#177; 3.19</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.99 &#177; 1.04</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85 &#177; 0.03<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.22 &#177; 3.44</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104.68 &#177; 1.99</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.52 &#177; 0.87</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.92 &#177; 0.03<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.67 &#177; 4.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">20.3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.19 &#177; 1.46</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.31 &#177; 1.30</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90 &#177; 0.03<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.88 &#177; 5.26</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.51 &#177; 3.50</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.56 &#177; 1.88</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97 &#177; 0.02<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.82 &#177; 3.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Main factors</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Classical music</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.45 &#177; 3.65</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.55 &#177; 2.92</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85 &#177; 0.05</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.13 &#177; 4.32</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.95 &#177; 3.56</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.22 &#177; 3.26</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90 &#177; 0.07</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.59 &#177; 4.67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Stocking density (birds/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104.71 &#177; 2.90<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.97 &#177; 1.68<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80 &#177; 0.03<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 &#177; 2.99<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104.04 &#177; 2.60<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.25 &#177; 1.19<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88 &#177; 0.05<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.44 &#177; 4.34<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.35 &#177; 2.56<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.44 &#177; 1.79<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93 &#177; 0.04<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.35 &#177; 4.43<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Classical music</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.166</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.691</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Stocking density</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Interaction</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.595</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.720</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a&#8211;d</sup>Means within a row column with no common superscripts differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). ADFI, average daily feed intake; ADG, average daily gain; F/G, feed-to-weight ratio; Interaction, indicates the interaction effect of classical music and stocking density.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec11"><label>3.2.</label><title>Serum stress indices</title><p>Serum CORT and ACTH of broilers were affected by different stocking densities (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). With the increase in stocking density, serum CORT and ACTH contents of broilers were decreased (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The serum CK content of broilers had an increasing trend (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.067) with the increase in stocking density. Playing classical music increased serum CORT and ACTH contents of broilers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). There was an interaction between classical music and stocking density on serum CORT and ACTH levels in broilers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Serum CORT and ACTH levels in the 17.9 birds/m<sup>2</sup> music group decreased to the same level as in the 15.5 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&gt;0.05). Serum CORT and ACTH levels in the 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup> music group decreased to the same level as in the 17.9 birds/m<sup>2</sup> no music group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&gt;0.05). In addition, the serum CORT and ACTH levels of broilers in the music group at the same stocking density were significantly lower (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05), indicating that classical music can reduce the increase in stress levels in broilers caused by increased stocking density (<xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Effects of classical music and stocking density on serum stress indices of broilers.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Items</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">CORT (ng/mL)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">ACTH (pg/mL)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">CK (U/L)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stocking density (birds/m<sup>2</sup>)</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Classical music</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">15.5</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.58 &#177; 0.41<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.64 &#177; 2.31<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2877.02 &#177; 275.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.63 &#177; 0.50<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.54 &#177; 2.11<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2908.15 &#177; 213.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">17.9</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.13 &#177; 0.45<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.71 &#177; 2.53<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3047.47 &#177; 269.70</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.10 &#177; 0.67<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.36 &#177; 3.90<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3049.21 &#177; 300.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">20.3</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.18 &#177; 0.59<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.29 &#177; 2.33<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3097.50 &#177; 233.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.37 &#177; 0.63<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.03 &#177; 2.36<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3213.58 &#177; 299.41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Main factors</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Classical music</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.29 &#177; 0.82</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.22 &#177; 3.75</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3007.33 &#177; 261.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.03 &#177; 1.28</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.31 &#177; 5.24</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3056.98 &#177; 287.59</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Stocking density (birds/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.60 &#177; 0.44<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.09 &#177; 2.60<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2892.58 &#177; 235.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.61 &#177; 0.74<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.04 &#177; 5.50<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3048.34 &#177; 269.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.77 &#177; 0.85<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.66 &#177; 4.17<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3155.54 &#177; 262.88</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="5" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p-</italic>value</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Classical music</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.580</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Stocking density</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Interaction</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.862</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a&#8211;c</sup>Means within a row column with no common superscripts differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). CORT, corticosterone; ACTH, adrenocorticotropic hormone; CK, creatine kinase; interaction: indicates the interaction effect of classical music and stocking density.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec12"><label>3.3.</label><title>Serum antioxidant capacity</title><p>The activities of CAT, SOD, MDA and GSH-PX in broiler serum were affected by different stocking densities (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05; <xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Serum CAT activity of broilers in 15.5 birds/m<sup>2</sup> and 17.9 birds/m<sup>2</sup> groups was higher than that in the 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The serum SOD activity of the 15.5 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group was higher than that of the 17.9 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group and 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). With the increase in stocking density, the serum MDA content of broilers was increased (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Increasing density resulted in a decrease in serum GSH-PX activity of broilers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Playing classical music decreased the serum MDA content of broilers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05), and tended to increase the activities of serum SOD and GSH-PX (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.079, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.061). There was no interaction between classical music and stocking density on the serum antioxidant capacity of broilers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Effects of classical music and stocking density on serum immune function of broilers.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Items</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Thymus (g/kg)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Spleen (g/kg)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Bursa of Fabricius (g/kg)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">IgA (g/L)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">IgM (g/L)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">IgG (g/L)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stocking density (birds/m<sup>2</sup>)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Classical music</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">15.5</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90 &#177; 0.11</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56 &#177; 0.15</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 &#177; 0.10</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.74 &#177; 0.11</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21 &#177; 0.11</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.07 &#177; 0.13<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83 &#177; 0.13</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 &#177; 0.11</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42 &#177; 0.04</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70 &#177; 0.10</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 &#177; 0.06</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.14 &#177; 0.13<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">17.9</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85 &#177; 0.35</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52 &#177; 0.08</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 &#177; 0.04</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39 &#177; 0.16</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 &#177; 0.06</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.92 &#177; 0.21<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73 &#177; 0.17</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43 &#177; 0.05</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46 &#177; 0.07</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35 &#177; 0.19</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 &#177; 0.07</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.44 &#177; 0.30<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">20.3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.74 &#177; 0.21</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44 &#177; 0.06</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 &#177; 0.07</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.45 &#177; 0.18</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16 &#177; 0.05</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.11 &#177; 0.21<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62 &#177; 0.21</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 &#177; 0.06</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36 &#177; 0.07</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10 &#177; 0.08</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 &#177; 0.08</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.02 &#177; 0.10<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Main factors</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Classical music</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83 &#177; 0.21</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51 &#177; 0.11</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46 &#177; 0.08</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.54 &#177; 0.22</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 &#177; 0.08</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.81 &#177; 0.38</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73 &#177; 0.19</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44 &#177; 0.09</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42 &#177; 0.07</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39 &#177; 0.29</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 &#177; 0.08</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.66 &#177; 0.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Stocking density (birds/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86 &#177; 0.12</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 &#177; 0.13<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46 &#177; 0.08<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.72 &#177; 0.10<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23 &#177; 0.09<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.10 &#177; 0.13<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79 &#177; 0.27</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 &#177; 0.08<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 &#177; 0.06<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.37 &#177; 0.17<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 &#177; 0.06<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.68 &#177; 0.35<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68 &#177; 0.21</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42 &#177; 0.06<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38 &#177; 0.07<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20 &#177; 0.20<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 &#177; 0.06<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.07 &#177; 0.16<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p-</italic>value</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Classical music</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.162</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.050</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.820</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Stocking density</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.163</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Interaction</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.950</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.756</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.820</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.078</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.554</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a&#8211;c</sup>Means within a row column with no common superscripts differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). IgA, ImmunoglobulinA; IgM, ImmunoglobulinM; IgG, ImmunoglobulinG; Interaction, indicates the interaction effect of classical music and stocking density.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec13"><label>3.4.</label><title>Serum biochemical indices</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="tab5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>, serum TP, TC and GLU levels in broiler were influenced by different stocking densities (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The serum TP content in the 15.5 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group was higher than that in the 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Increasing stocking density increased serum TC levels of broilers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The content of serum GLU in the 15.5 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group was lower than that in the 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Serum ALB tended to decrease (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.078) by increasing stocking density. Playing classical music decreased the serum GLU content of broilers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05), and tended to decrease the serum TC content (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.083). There was no interaction effect between classical music and stocking density on the serum biochemical indices of broilers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Effects of classical music and stocking density on serum antioxidant capacity of broilers.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Items</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">T-AOC (nmol/L)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">CAT (U/mL)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">SOD (U/mL)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">MDA (nmol/mL)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">GSH-PX (U/mL)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stocking density (birds/m<sup>2</sup>)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Classical music</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">15.5</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 &#177; 0.03</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.83 &#177; 0.87</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.73 &#177; 5.81</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.14 &#177; 0.29</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">945.72 &#177; 43.59</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 &#177; 0.03</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.45 &#177; 0.73</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.24 &#177; 3.16</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.86 &#177; 0.55</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">935.48 &#177; 46.56</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">17.9</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 &#177; 0.04</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.78 &#177; 0.72</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.71 &#177; 2.55</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.69 &#177; 0.39</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">913.75 &#177; 51.20</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 &#177; 0.04</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.46 &#177; 0.55</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.24 &#177; 3.16</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.41 &#177; 0.49</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">811.23 &#177; 48.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">20.3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 &#177; 0.03</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.68 &#177; 0.52</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.22 &#177; 3.57</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.09 &#177; 0.47</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">861.23 &#177; 48.21</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 &#177; 0.03</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.22 &#177; 0.73</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.69 &#177; 4.41</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.63 &#177; 0.41</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">816.92 &#177; 39.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1">Main factors</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Classical music</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 &#177; 0.03</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.43 &#177; 0.87</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.40 &#177; 5.07</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80 &#177; 0.68</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">900.54 &#177; 61.55</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 &#177; 0.03</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.04 &#177; 0.87</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.05 &#177; 4.27</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.14 &#177; 0.56</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">871.21 &#177; 65.76</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Stocking density (birds/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 &#177; 0.03</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.64 &#177; 0.79<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.98 &#177; 4.82<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.42 &#177; 0.43<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">940.60 &#177; 43.33<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 &#177; 0.03</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.62 &#177; 0.64<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.49 &#177; 3.33<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.98 &#177; 0.51<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">887.49 &#177; 84.77<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 &#177; 0.03</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.45 &#177; 0.65<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.20 &#177; 3.47<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.52 &#177; 0.44<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">829.53 &#177; 40.37<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p-</italic>value</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Classical music</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.917</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.103</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.079</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Stocking density</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Interaction</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.949</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.969</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.737</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.606</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.516</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a&#8211;c</sup>Means within a row column with no common superscripts differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). T-AOC, total antioxidant capacity; CAT, catalase activity; SOD, superoxide dismutase; MDA, malondialdehyde; GSH-Px, glutathione peroxidase; Interaction, indicates the interaction effect of classical music and stocking density.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec14"><label>3.5.</label><title>Immune function</title><p>The indicators related to immune function were listed in <xref rid="tab6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>, spleen and bursal indices of broilers were affected by different stocking densities (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The relative weight of the spleen and bursa of Fabricius in the 15.5 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group was lower than that in the 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Playing classical music increased the relative weight of the bursa of Fabryssa (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05), and tended to increase the relative weight of the spleen (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.050). There was no interaction effect between playing classical music and stocking density on the immune organ index of broilers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05). The contents of IgA, IgM, and IgG in the serum of broilers were affected by different stocking densities (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Increasing stocking density decreased the serum IgA and IgG contents of broilers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The serum IgM content of broilers in the 15.5 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group was higher than that in the 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). Playing classical music increased the serum IgA and IgG contents of broilers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). An interaction effect was observed in the serum IgM levels of broilers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). After playing classical music, the IgM content of the 17.9 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group recovered to the same level as that of the 15.5 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05). It showed that classical music could improve the decrease of serum IgM level caused by the increase of stocking density (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Effect of classical music and stocking density on serum biochemical indexes of broilers.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Items</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">TP (g/L)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">ALB (g/L)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">TC (mmol/L)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">GLU (mmol/L)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stocking density (birds/m<sup>2</sup>)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Classical music</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">15.5</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.44 &#177; 2.96</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.89 &#177; 1.05</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97 &#177; 0.14</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.13 &#177; 0.93</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.77 &#177; 2.36</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.68 &#177; 1.23</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06 &#177; 0.12</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.51 &#177; 1.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">17.9</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.19 &#177; 2.23</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.98 &#177; 1.06</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.22 &#177; 0.11</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.92 &#177; 0.91</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.91 &#177; 1.99</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.66 &#177; 1.18</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29 &#177; 0.23</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.29 &#177; 1.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">20.3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.11 &#177; 2.31</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.57 &#177; 0.90</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.56 &#177; 0.19</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.01 &#177; 1.61</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.75 &#177; 3.31</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.26 &#177; 1.29</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.68 &#177; 0.11</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.71 &#177; 1.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Main factors</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Classical music</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.25 &#177; 2.59</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.15 &#177; 1.10</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25 &#177; 0.28</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.02 &#177; 1.37</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.81 &#177; 2.29</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.86 &#177; 1.43</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.34 &#177; 0.30</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.17 &#177; 1.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Stocking density (birds/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.61 &#177; 2.56<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.78 &#177; 1.09<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04 &#177; 0.10<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.82 &#177; 1.21<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.05 &#177; 2.02<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.82 &#177; 1.08<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25 &#177; 0.18<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.60 &#177; 1.26<sup>ab</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.43 &#177; 2.85<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.41 &#177; 1.07<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.62 &#177; 0.16<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.36 &#177; 1.43<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p-</italic>value</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Classical music</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.615</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.459</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Stocking density</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Interaction</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.719</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.992</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.915</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.738</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a&#8211;c</sup>Means within a row column with no common superscripts differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). TP, total protein; ALB, albumin; TC, total cholesterol; GLU, glucose; Interaction, indicates the interaction effect of classical music and stocking density.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec15"><label>3.6.</label><title>Meat quality</title><p>Breast muscle color and cooking loss of broilers were affected by different stocking densities (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05; <xref rid="tab7" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>). The L*<sub>24h</sub> value of breast muscle in broilers in the 15.5 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group was lower than that in the 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05), and the a*<sub>24h</sub> value of breast muscle in broilers in 15.5 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group was increased with the increase of stocking density. The cooking loss of breast muscle in broilers in 15.5 birds/m<sup>2</sup> and 17.9 birds/m<sup>2</sup> groups was lower than that in 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup> groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). With the increase in stocking density, the shear force of the breast muscle in broilers tended to increase (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.059). Playing classical music increased the a*<sub>24h</sub> value of breast muscle in broilers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). There was no interaction between classical music and stocking density on the meat quality of broilers (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab7" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Effect of classical music and stocking density on meat quality of broilers.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Items</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Meat color</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Cooking loss (%)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Shear force (N)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stocking density (birds/m<sup>2</sup>)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Classical music</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L*<sub>24h</sub></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">a*<sub>24h</sub></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">b*<sub>24h</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">15.5</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.89 &#177; 1.70</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.43 &#177; 0.52</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.87 &#177; 1.30</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.89 &#177; 0.78</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.58 &#177; 0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.55 &#177; 4.51</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.15 &#177; 0.52</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.28 &#177; 1.06</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.06 &#177; 1.10</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.61 &#177; 0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">17.9</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.85 &#177; 4.09</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.03 &#177; 0.47</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.65 &#177; 1.41</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.32 &#177; 1.02</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70 &#177; 0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.30 &#177; 2.81</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.08 &#177; 0.49</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.91 &#177; 2.45</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.09 &#177; 0.89</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60 &#177; 0.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">20.3</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.65 &#177; 4.45</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.81 &#177; 0.58</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.40 &#177; 1.22</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.64 &#177; 0.92</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.68 &#177; 0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.98 &#177; 4.66</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.86 &#177; 0.39</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.13 &#177; 1.59</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.06 &#177; 1.06</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78 &#177; 0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Main factors</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Classical music</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.46 &#177; 3.61</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.52 &#177; 0.73</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.30 &#177; 1.28</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.61 &#177; 1.15</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63 &#177; 0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.61 &#177; 4.49</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.16 &#177; 0.53</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.44 &#177; 1.77</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.07 &#177; 1.28</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.69 &#177; 0.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Stocking density (birds/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.23 &#177; 3.27<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.23 &#177; 0.52<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.07 &#177; 1.15</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.97 &#177; 0.91<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.59 &#177; 0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.07 &#177; 3.58<sup>ab</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.55 &#177; 0.67<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.28 &#177; 1.94</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.70 &#177; 1.00<sup>b</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64 &#177; 0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.3</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.31 &#177; 4.68<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.83 &#177; 0.47<sup>c</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.76 &#177; 1.41</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.85 &#177; 0.97<sup>a</sup></td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="&#xB1;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.74 &#177; 0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="7" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Classical music</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.106</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.797</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.245</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Stocking density</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.548</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.059</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Interaction</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.693</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.058</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.487</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.745</td><td align="char" valign="middle" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.856</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a&#8211;c</sup>Means within a row column with no common superscripts differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). L*, lightness; a*, redness; b*, yellowness; Interaction, indicates the interaction effect of classical music and stocking density.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussions" id="sec16"><label>4.</label><title>Discussion</title><p>Under the high-stocking density, broilers become extremely sensitive to the environment and are susceptible to stress, which may lead to impaired growth and development. Mohammed et al. (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) reported that, compared with the stocking density of 14 and 18 birds/m<sup>2</sup>, the stocking density of 20 birds/m<sup>2</sup> significantly reduced the ADFI, ADG, and F/G of broilers. Similar to the above results, this study showed that a stocking density of 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup> significantly reduced broiler feed intake and body weight, and increased F/G and mortality. Stress induced by high-stocking density may be the main reason for the decreased growth performance of broilers. Moreover, the high mortality of broilers in this experiment at two densities of 17.9 and 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup> may be due to the high number of broilers in the cages, and severe competition for food among the flock, resulting in sudden death due to severe stress (<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). In this study, body weight gain and F/G of broilers were improved by playing classical music. Similar to this result, Gvaryahu et al. (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) found that music increased daily weight gain in broilers, and Tolun et al. (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) showed that music significantly improved the F/G of Ross 308 broilers. The musical environment improved the growth performance of broilers, probably due to the exposure of broilers to music starting at 1 day of age, which enabled them to adapt to the audible environment, thus reducing various stresses and fears during growth, reducing the corresponding energy expenditure and improving feed conversion. This is in agreement with Hoffman (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) and Gaioni et al. (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>) who suggested that music may be beneficial in reducing fear in young chicks. On the other hand, the overall mortality rate of broiler chickens in the experimental group dropped by 44%, which may be attributed to classical music modulating the animals&#8217; nervous systems through sound waves to relieve stress (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>), this may also contribute to the reduction of mortality in broilers. In this study, there was an interaction effect between classical music and stocking density on broiler F/G. At the same stocking density, the F/G of broilers in the 17.9 and 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup> groups playing classical music was significantly lower than that of the group without music, and the F/G of both groups decreased to the level of low stocking density without music intervention. This suggests that classical music can reverse the growth inhibition caused by increased stocking density and improve broiler growth performance.</p><p>When birds experience stress, their HPA axis is activated, and the pituitary gland is stimulated to secrete ACTH and glucocorticoids synthesized by adrenal cortical cells (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Puvadolpirod et al. (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) found that the injection of high doses of exogenous ACTH increased corticosterone levels in the blood of broilers and increased stress levels by establishing a physiological stress model. In our study, serum CORT and ACTH levels were significantly higher in broilers in the 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group than in broilers in the 15.5 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group. Another study also showed that serum CORT levels were significantly increased when the stocking density of broilers was increased from 30 to 40&#8201;kg/m<sup>2</sup> (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). This means that broilers at high stocking densities are more susceptible to physiological stress. Many researchers have reported a positive effect of classical music on alleviating stress in animals (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). We found that playing classical music significantly reduced these two indicators in broiler serum at stocking densities of 17.9 and 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup>. And there was no significant difference in serum CORT and ACTH levels between 17.9 and 15.5 birds/m<sup>2</sup> and between the 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group (playing classical music) and the 17.9 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group (no music). This suggests that classical music can be useful in alleviating the stress caused by increasing stocking density in broilers. Similarly, D&#225;vila et al. (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) indicated that the auditory enrichment obtained from classical music can reduce stress in chicks. It may be that music can reduce the stress response in the HPA axis by inducing activity in the hippocampus of the brain (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), therefore, the stress-relieving effect of classical music on broiler chicks may be related to the ability to alter neuronal activity within these brain structures, however, the exact mechanisms involved need further investigation.</p><p>Oxidative stress can lead to biological damage and a variety of physiological disorders that can reduce the growth performance of broilers (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Important antioxidant enzymes such as GSH-PX and SOD play an important role in combating oxidative damage. MDA is a product of lipid peroxidation and its concentration reflects the state of oxidative stress (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Simsek et al. (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) reported that overcrowded rearing environments led to elevated blood MDA levels and increased oxidative damage in broilers. Li et al. (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) suggested that stress-induced lipid peroxidation effects may be due to decreased antioxidant enzyme activity at high stocking densities (18 birds/m<sup>2</sup>). The above-mentioned reports were similar to our results, with increased serum MDA levels and decreased CAT and GSH-PX activities in the 20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group compared with the other two densities. It is possible that the crowded space led to increased fighting behavior in broilers, resulting in metabolic disturbances that contributed to high lipid peroxidation and reactive oxygen species production <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>, increased oxidative damage and MDA production in broilers, and decreased antioxidant enzyme activities (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). In addition, we found that serum MDA concentration decreased, while serum SOD and GSH-PX activities tended to increase in broiler chickens by playing classical music. Previous studies have shown that classical music can increase the growth rate of human cells and increase the level of GSH (<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). This implied that classical music may reduce oxidative stress damage by increasing the antioxidant enzyme activity of the body. On the other hand, classical music stimulation can increase positive behavior, reduce aggressive behavior, and relieve stress and anxiety in livestock (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). In this study, it was hypothesized that classical music may serve to alleviate lipid peroxidation damage by reducing stress levels and increasing antioxidant enzyme activity in broilers.</p><p>Serum biochemical indicators reflect the nutritional metabolism, stress, and health status of the body (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Mohammed et al. (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) showed that serum TP and ALB levels in broilers were significantly reduced at a stocking density of 20 birds/m<sup>2</sup>. In this study, with the increase of stocking density, serum TP and ALB levels of broilers decreased, while serum TC and GLU levels increased. The decrease in serum protein levels suggested that high stocking densities had a negative impact on nutrient absorption and metabolic function in broilers. Elevated TC levels may be related to the fact that overproduction of CORT levels upregulated gene expression for cholesterol synthesis and uptake in broiler muscle, inducing the accumulation of cholesterol in muscle (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). In addition, stress-induced increases in glucocorticoid levels promote the breakdown of proteins and fats in the body, providing raw material for gluconeogenesis, and resulting in increased GLU levels in the blood (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). In this study, serum GLU levels in broilers were significantly reduced after stimulation by classical music. Similar to the results of this trial, Tabrizi et al. (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) showed that playing music not only reduced blood GLU levels in patients after surgery but also maintained relatively stable cortisol levels compared to the control group (no interference). Finn et al. (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>) also reported that listening to music reduced cortisol and blood GLU levels in humans. In our study, we hypothesized that classical music may reduce the secretion of CORT and ACTH in broilers by alleviating the stress response, thus lowering blood GLU.</p><p>The relative development of the thymus, bursa, and spleen can be used to assess the immune function and health status of poultry (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). Simitzis et al. (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>) found that increased stress levels in broilers at high stocking density resulted in lower bursal weights. Sanchez et al. (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>) showed that reduced lymphoid organ weight in poultry was associated with stress-induced high serum corticosterone levels. In this study, the spleen and bursa weight of broilers decreased with increasing stocking density. Elevated concentrations of corticosterone cause degeneration of the lymphoid organs spleen and bursa phalloides and dysregulate the immune response by depleting lymphocytes in germ cells (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Musical stimulation promotes T-cell proliferation in stressed mice (<xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). This is similar to our results that playing classical music increased the relative weight of the spleen and bursa of broilers. Serum immunoglobulins are important indicators of humoral immunity in animals and are a direct reflection of the immune function of the organism. Li et al. (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) showed that high-stocking density (18 birds/m<sup>2</sup>) significantly reduced serum IgG and IgA levels in broilers. Similarly, Hafez et al. (<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>) reported that serum IgA, IgG and IgM levels were significantly higher in the normal density group (10 birds/m<sup>2</sup>) than in the high-stocking density group (20 birds/m<sup>2</sup>). In the present study, increased stocking density significantly reduced serum IgA, IgM, and IgG levels in broilers, probably because high-stocking density induced stress increased glucocorticoid levels and inhibited the body&#8217;s immune function (<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). Li et al. (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) reported that classical music increased serum IgG levels and improved cytokine levels in piglets. We found that classical music increased the serum IgA and IgG levels in broilers. Classical music may affect immune function by stimulating the nervous system of broiler chickens and the autonomic signals emanating from it interact with immune cells to control their function and response (<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). However, the exact mechanism is unclear and further research is needed. The results of this study showed that there was an interactive effect between classical music and stocking density on the serum IgG content of broilers, and the IgG content of the 17.9 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group recovered to the same level as that of the 15.5 birds/m<sup>2</sup> group after classical music intervention, which indicated that classical music could alleviate the immunosuppression triggered by increased stocking density to some extent.</p><p>The quality of the muscle is usually assessed by color, tethering power, and shear force (<xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). Wu et al. (<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>) showed that 24&#8201;h after slaughter, high-stocking density (18.6 birds/m<sup>2</sup>) significantly increased L* and decreased a* values of breast muscle in broilers compared to low stocking density (12.9 birds/m<sup>2</sup>) and also resulted in higher drip losses. Hosseini et al. (<xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>) reported that water loss of breast muscle in broilers was significantly lower in the high-stocking density group (20 birds/m<sup>2</sup>) than in the stocking density group (10 birds/m<sup>2</sup>). Similar to these results, in this study, it was also found that L*<sub>24 h</sub> value and Cooking loss of breast muscle in broiler increased with the increase of stocking density, whereas a*<sub>24 h</sub> value of breast muscle decreased. It has been reported that the high brightness values of chicken meat may be related to oxidative stress caused by high-stocking density (<xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). The strength of muscle oxidative capacity is related to high red values (<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). High-stocking density caused high levels of nitric oxide production in broilers, increasing the accumulation of reactive oxygen and reactive nitrogen in the muscle, leading to massive oxidation of proteins, which reduced the strength of the myogenic fiber gel and increased the Cooking loss of chicken meat (<xref rid="ref60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). Therefore, the high stocking density in this experiment led to a decrease in meat quality by inducing oxidative stress in broilers, while playing classical music enhanced the antioxidant capacity of broilers and improved the breast muscle a*<sub>24h</sub> values.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec17"><label>5.</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our results suggested that high-stocking density (20.3 birds/m<sup>2</sup>) can reduce growth performance, induce a stress response, decrease antioxidant and immune function, and reduce the meat quality of broilers. However classical music stimulus can indeed alleviate the negative effects of high-stocking density on broilers to a certain extent. Therefore, this was an effective measure to relieve the stressful conditions and increase the growth performance and immune status of broilers raised at the high stocking density condition.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec18"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/Supplementary material, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding authors. The tracks used in this study are searchable on Himalayan Audio Platform (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ximalaya.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ximalaya.com/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="sec19"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by the protocols for the animal study were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Hebei Agricultural University and carried out under the Guidelines for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals of China.</p></sec><sec id="sec20"><title>Author contributions</title><p>XG and JG performed the experiments and drafted the manuscript. XG, ZF, and JG carried out the statistical analysis. BY, YL, HX, YH, JJ, and LL helped the revision of this manuscript. ZF and LL contributed to the supervision and guidance of the present study. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="sec21"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was supported by the Hebei Provincial Key R&amp;D Project (20326617D, Shijiazhuang, China) and the Hebei Modern Agricultural Industry Technology System Laying Hens &amp; Brolier Innovation Team Construction Project (HBCT2018150203, Shijiazhuang, China).</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec22"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>JJ was employed by Hebei Jiuxing Agriculture and Animal Husbandry Development Co., Ltd.</p><p>The remaining authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec100"><title>Publisher&#8217;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn id="fn0001"><p>
<sup>1</sup>
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ximalaya.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ximalaya.com/</ext-link>
</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll1">National Chicken Council</collab></person-group>. <source>National Chicken Council animal welfare guidelines and audit guidelines</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Chicken Council</publisher-name> (<year>2005</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Advances in density stress and nutrition regulation of poultry</article-title>. <source>China Poult</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.16372/j.issn.1004-6364.2017.17.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>QX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of stocking density on growth performance, growth regulatory factors, and endocrine hormones in broilers under appropriate environments</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>6611</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pez505</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31504910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8913966</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Increasing dietary vitamin D3 improves the walking ability and welfare status of broiler chickens reared at high stocking densities</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>3071</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.2013-03278</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24235214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of stocking density and alpha-lipoic acid on the growth performance, physiological and oxidative stress and immune response of broilers</article-title>. <source>Asian Australas J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1914</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5713/ajas.18.0939</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31010966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6819680</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simsek</surname><given-names>UG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalkilic</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciftci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuce</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The influences of different stocking densities on some welfare indicators, lipid peroxidation (MDA) and antioxidant enzyme activities (GSH, GSH-Px, CAT) in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>J Anim Vet Adv</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1568</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kemper</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danhauer</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Music as therapy</article-title>. <source>South Med J</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>282</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.SMJ.0000154773.11986.39</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15813154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kochewad</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaur</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maurya</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bharti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahoo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of milking environment enrichment through music on production performance and behaviour in cattle</article-title>. <source>Trop Anim Health Prod</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>219</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11250-022-03217-4</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35760924</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A role for classical music in veterinary practice: does exposure to classical music reduce stress in hospitalised dogs?</article-title><source>Aust Vet J</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>31</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/avj.12905</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31943134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of music stimulus on behavior response, cortisol level, and horizontal immunity of growing pigs</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>skab043</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jas/skab043</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33939813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8092926</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koelsch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skouras</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Functional centrality of amygdala, striatum and hypothalamus in a &#8220;small-world&#8221; network underlying joy: an fMRI study with music</article-title>. <source>Hum Brain Mapp</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>3485</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>98</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.22416</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25050430</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6869778</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sapolsky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of the hippocampus in feedback regulation of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenocortical axis</article-title>. <source>Endocr Rev</source>. (<year>1991</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>118</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/edrv-12-2-118</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2070776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Panksepp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernatzky</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Emotional sounds and the brain: the neuro-affective foundations of musical appreciation</article-title>. <source>Behav Process</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>60</volume>:<fpage>133</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0376-6357(02)00080-3</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12426066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Music improves dopaminergic neurotransmission: demonstration based on the effect of music on blood pressure regulation</article-title>. <source>Brain Res</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>1016</volume>:<fpage>255</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2004.05.018</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15246862</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levitin</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tirovolas</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Current advances in the cognitive neuroscience of music</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>1156</volume>:<fpage>211</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2009.04417.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19338510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iversen</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bregman</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Experimental evidence for synchronization to a musical beat in a nonhuman animal</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>827</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2009.03.038</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19409790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>HL</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>GX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of different types of music on growth performance, slaughter performance, digestive organ index, immune function and serum antioxidant indexes of broilers</article-title>. <source>Chinese J Anim Nutr</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>2940</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3969/j.issn.1006&amp;#x02043;267x.2022.05.023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll2">NRC</collab></person-group>. <source>National Research Council: nutrient requirements of poultry</source>. <edition>9th</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academic Press</publisher-name> (<year>1994</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Meat quality traits and proteome profile of woody broiler breast (pectoralis major) meat</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>97</volume>:<fpage>337</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pex284</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29053841</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasr</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alkhedaide</surname><given-names>AQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramadan</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd-El Salam</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Potential impact of stocking density on growth, carcass traits, indicators of biochemical and oxidative stress and meat quality of different broiler breeds</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>101442</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2021.101442</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34607150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8493580</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Imaeda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of the stocking density and rearing season on incidence of sudden death syndrome in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2000</year>) <volume>79</volume>:<fpage>201</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ps/79.2.201</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10735747</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olkowski</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wojnarowicz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alcorn</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laarveld</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A study on pathogenesis of sudden death syndrome in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Res Vet Sci</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>85</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rvsc.2007.08.006</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17904171</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gvaryahu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Tienhoven</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Filial imprinting, environmental enrichment, and music application effects on behavior and performance of meat strain chicks</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>1989</year>) <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>211</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.0680211</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tolun</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rathert</surname><given-names>T&#199;</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of music on growth performance, carcass and meat quality in broilers</article-title>. <source>BS J Eng Sci</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The control of distress vocalization by an imprinted stimulus</article-title>. <source>Behaviour</source>. (<year>1968</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>175</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1163/156853967x00316</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5661340</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaioni</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DePaulo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of group rearing on the control exerted by an imprinting stimulus</article-title>. <source>Anim Learn Behav</source>. (<year>1980</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>673</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/BF03197785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alworth</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buerkle</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effects of music on animal physiology, behavior and welfare</article-title>. <source>Lab Anim</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/laban.162</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23340788</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#225;vila</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of auditory and physical enrichment on 3 measurements of fear and stress (tonic immobility duration, heterophil to lymphocyte ratio, and fluctuating asymmetry) in several breeds of layer chicks</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>2459</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.2011-01595</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22010229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Latour</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laiche</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pond</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peebles</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Continuous infusion of adrenocorticotropin elevates circulating lipoprotein cholesterol and corticosterone concentrations in chickens</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>1996</year>) <volume>75</volume>:<fpage>1428</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.0751428</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8933597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Puvadolpirod</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thaxton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Model of physiological stress in chickens 1. Response parameters</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2000</year>) <volume>79</volume>:<fpage>363</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ps/79.3.363</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10735203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kridtayopas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rakangtong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bunchasak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loongyai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of prebiotic and synbiotic supplementation in diet on growth performance, small intestinal morphology, stress, and bacterial population under high stocking density condition of broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>4595</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>605</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pez152</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30951594</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Min</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of dietary tryptophan and stocking density on the performance, meat quality, and metabolic status of broilers</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci Biotechnol</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2049-1891-5-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25705377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4335389</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of natural capsicum extract on growth performance, nutrient utilization, antioxidant status, immune function, and meat quality in broilers</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>101301</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2021.101301</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34273651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8313837</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of alpha-lipoic acid on the behavior, serum indicators, and bone quality of broilers under stocking density stress</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>4653</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2020.05.007</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32988500</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7598135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Regulation of physiological systems by nutrients free radicals</article-title>. <source>Antioxidants Nutr</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>9007</volume>:<fpage>872</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1016/s0899-9007(02)00916-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12361782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of different music on HEK293T cell growth and mitochondrial functions</article-title>. <source>Explore (NY)</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>670</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.explore.2022.01.002</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35248473</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of short-term classical music stimulus on behavior and tonic immobility reaction of pullets</article-title>. <source>J Appl Anim Welf Sci</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>386</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10888705.2021.1983724</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34696632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalmendal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tauson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of a xylanase and protease, individually or in combination, and an ionophore coccidiostat on performance, nutrient utilization, and intestinal morphology in broiler chickens fed a wheat-soybean meal-based diet</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>91</volume>:<fpage>1387</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.2011-02064</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22582297</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L-M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>X-L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>F-Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of fermented biogas residue on growth performance, serum biochemical parameters, and meat quality in pigs</article-title>. <source>Asian Australas J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>1464</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5713/ajas.16.0777</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28423885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5582332</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Attia</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qota</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Recovery from adverse effects of heat stress on slow-growing chicks in the tropics 1: effect of ascorbic acid and different levels of betaine</article-title>. <source>Trop Anim Health Prod</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>807</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11250-008-9256-9</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18987986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pornanek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phoemchalard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Feed added curcumin with increased solubility on plasma lipoprotein, meat quality, and fat content in broiler chicks</article-title>. <source>Trop Anim Health Prod</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>647</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11250-019-02052-4</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31473881</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cholesterol deregulation induced by chronic corticosterone (CORT) stress in pectoralis major of broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Comp Biochem Physiol A Mol Integr Physiol</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>176</volume>:<fpage>59</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cbpa.2014.07.010</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25038300</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Magomedova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Glucocorticoids and metabolic control</article-title>. <source>Handb Exp Pharmacol</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>233</volume>:<fpage>73</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/164_2015_1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25917083</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabrizi</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahraei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rad</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hajizadeh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of music on the level of cortisol, blood glucose and physiological variables in patients undergoing spinal anesthesia</article-title>. <source>EXCLI J</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>556</fpage>. PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27350774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4920039</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Finn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fancourt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The biological impact of listening to music in clinical and nonclinical settings: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Prog Brain Res</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>237</volume>:<fpage>173</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>200</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/bs.pbr.2018.03.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29779734</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kil</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of dietary hatchery by-products on growth performance, relative organ weight, plasma measurements, immune organ index, meat quality, and tibia characteristics of broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Anim Biosci</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>1181</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5713/ab.20.0755</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33561330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8255869</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simitzis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalogeraki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goliomytis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charismiadou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Triantaphyllopoulos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayoutanti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of stocking density on broiler growth performance, meat characteristics, behavioural components and indicators of physiological and oxidative stress</article-title>. <source>Br Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>721</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00071668.2012.745930</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23398415</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez-Casanova</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarmiento-Franco</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Segura-Correa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of outdoor access and indoor stocking density on behaviour and stress in broilers in the subhumid tropics</article-title>. <source>Animals</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1016</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani9121016</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31766675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6940855</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>RX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>KX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>XA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of different stocking densities on growth performance, antioxidant ability, and immunity of finishing broilers</article-title>. <source>Anim Sci J</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>583</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/asj.13148</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30693597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heckert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Estevez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russek-Cohen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pettit-Riley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of density and perch availability on the immune status of broilers</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>81</volume>:<fpage>451</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ps/81.4.451</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11989743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quinteiro-Filho</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferraz-de-Paula</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baskeville</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Overcrowding stress decreases macrophage activity and increases <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella Enteritidis</italic> invasion in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Avian Pathol</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>82</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03079457.2013.874006</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24350836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>N&#250;&#241;ez</surname><given-names>Mar&#237;a J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma&#241;&#225;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li&#241;ares</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riveiro</surname><given-names>Mar&#237;a P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balboa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su&#225;rez-Quintanilla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Music, immunity and cancer</article-title>. <source>Life Sci</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>71</volume>:<fpage>1047</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>57</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0024-3205(02)01796-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12088764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hafez</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>el-Kazaz</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alharthi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghamry</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alshehri</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sayed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of curcumin on growth performance, growth-related gene expression, oxidative stress, and immunological biomarkers in broiler chickens at different stocking densities</article-title>. <source>Animals (Basel)</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>958</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani12080958</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35454205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9024619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pariante</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Glucocorticoid receptors in major depression: relevance to pathophysiology and treatment</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>. (<year>2001</year>) <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>391</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>404</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3223(00)01088-X</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11274650</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavlov</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chavan</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tracey</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular and functional neuroscience in immunity</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Immunol</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>783</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>812</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-immunol-042617-053158</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29677475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6057146</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernad</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casado</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murillo</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Picallo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garriz</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maceira</surname><given-names>NO</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Meat quality traits in the greater rhea (<italic toggle="yes">Rhea americana</italic>) as influenced by muscle, sex and age</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>97</volume>:<fpage>1579</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>87</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pey005</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29462477</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of nicotinamide and sodium butyrate on meat quality and muscle ubiquitination degradation genes in broilers reared at a high stocking density</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>1462</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2019.10.070</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32115032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7587854</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farhangfar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nourmohammadi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of a blend of essential oils and overcrowding stress on the growth performance, meat quality and heat shock protein gene expression of broilers</article-title>. <source>Br Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>92</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00071668.2017.1390209</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28990804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gentry</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGlone</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanton</surname><given-names>J</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>. <article-title>Environmental effects on pig performance, meat quality, and muscle characteristics</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>82</volume>:<fpage>209</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/2004.821209x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14753363</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Transcriptome analysis reveals a molecular understanding of nicotinamide and butyrate sodium on meat quality of broilers under high stocking density</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-020-06827-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7302154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32552672</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><glossary><def-list><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term>CORT</term><def><p>corticosterone</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ACTH</term><def><p>adrenocorticotropin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CK</term><def><p>creatine kinase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IgA</term><def><p>immunoglobulin A</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IgG</term><def><p>immunoglobulin G</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IgM</term><def><p>immunoglobulin M</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>T-AOC</term><def><p>total antioxidant capacity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CAT</term><def><p>catalase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SOD</term><def><p>superoxide dismutase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MDA</term><def><p>malondialdehyde</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GSH-PX</term><def><p>glutathione peroxidase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TP</term><def><p>total protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ALB</term><def><p>albumin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TC</term><def><p>total cholesterol</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GLU</term><def><p>glucose</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></back></article></pmc-articleset>