<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7835392</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7835392.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7835392</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7835392</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33511162</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2020.582338</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Impact of N-Acetylcysteine on the Gut Microbiota in the Piglets Infected With Porcine Epidemic Diarrhea Virus</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="T">Tao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>&#8224;</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/366731/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyu</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>&#8224;</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/889941/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="X">Xueni</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="M">Mengjun</given-names></name><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1029163/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names initials="K">Kui</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="S">Siyuan</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names initials="C">Changzheng</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qian</given-names></name><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/841442/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yanyan</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names initials="D">Di</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names initials="D">Dan</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yongqing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff><institution>Hubei Key Laboratory of Animal Nutrition and Feed Science, Wuhan Polytechnic University (WPHU)</institution>, <addr-line>Wuhan</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Michael Kogut, United States Department of Agriculture, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Jiangchao Zhao, University of Arkansas, United States; Dirk Werling, Royal Veterinary College (RVC), United Kingdom</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Yongqing Hou <email>houyq@aliyun.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Veterinary Infectious Diseases, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>&#8224;These authors have contributed equally to this work and share first authorship</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">351216</issue-id><elocation-id>582338</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>27</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-01-04 21:25:32.077"><day>04</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2021 Wu, Lyu, Li, Wu, Yu, Li, Ji, Zhang, Zhang, Zhao, Yi and Hou.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wu, Lyu, Li, Wu, Yu, Li, Ji, Zhang, Zhang, Zhao, Yi and Hou</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-07-582338.pdf"/><abstract><p>This study was to investigate the impact of N-acetylcysteine (NAC) on the gut microbiota in the healthy piglets and the piglets infected with porcine epidemic diarrhea virus (PEDV). Forty seven-day-old piglets were allocated into four groups: control group, NAC group (supplemented with 50 mg/kg body weight NAC), PEDV group (inoculated with 10<sup>4.5</sup> TCID<sub>50</sub> PEDV), and PEDV+NAC group (PEDV infection + NAC supplementation). The intestinal content was collected for DNA extraction and Illumina sequencing. The PEDV-infected piglets displayed distinct bacterial communities compared to the healthy piglets. PEDV infection decreased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Shigella</italic> and increased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus, Odoribacter, Anaerovibrio, Helicobacter</italic>, unclassified <italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Sutterella</italic>; affected several functions associated with metabolism, barrier, and immune. NAC supplementation decreased the abundance of unclassified <italic toggle="yes">Rikenellaceae</italic> and increased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus, Streptococcus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> in the healthy piglets, decreased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Oscillospira</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> and increased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> in the PEDV-infected piglets; altered multiple functions involving in amino acid metabolism, cell signaling, cellular community, disease-related pathways, endocrine, and excretory system. In conclusion, PEDV infection caused severe dysbiosis of gut microbiome, whereas NAC supplementation played a positive role in regulating the gut microbiome during PEDV infection. Therefore, substances that can regulate gut microbiota could be ideal candidates to prevent or treat PEDV infection.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>N-acetylcysteine</kwd><kwd>PEDV</kwd><kwd>dysbiosis</kwd><kwd>microbiome</kwd><kwd>piglets</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="47"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="6706"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Great progress has been made to understand the role of gut microbiota in humans and animals alike (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Biological functions of the gut microbiota to the host pertain to nutrition (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), metabolism (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), barrier, and immune (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), which are still expanding. Nevertheless, the relationship between gut microbiota and diseases remains unclear (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). For instance, increasing evidence have revealed that gut microbiota plays a vital role in the regulation, elimination, and potentiation of infectious diseases (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), while profound shifts of gut microbiota have frequently been reported in various diseases as well (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Moreover, several enteric pathogens, such as <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella, Clostridium perfringens</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>, can also be found in healthy mammals (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Therefore, more experiments are warranted to be established for a deeper understanding of microbiota alterations during diseases.</p><p>Porcine epidemic diarrhea virus (PEDV) received increasing attention since the large-scale outbreaks in the last decades (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). PEDV is a devastating cause of diarrhea in pigs, which induces great economic losses to the pig industry worldwide (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). It causes severe diarrhea, vomiting, anorexia, dehydration, weight loss and high morbidity, and mortality in pigs of any age (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Currently, research on PEDV mainly focused on molecular characterization, evolution, pathology, the host immune response and vaccinations, only limited knowledge has been expanded to the relationship between PEDV infection and porcine microbiota (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Recent research has reported that PEDV infection induced dysbiosis of fecal and colonic microbiota in piglets and sows, leading to an increase in pathogenic bacteria and a decrease in commensal bacteria (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). However, only few studies focused on the microbiota alterations associated with the (expecting) anti-PEDV substances or compounds.</p><p>N-acetylcysteine (NAC) is a source of sulfhydryl groups in cells and scavenger of free radicals as it interacts with reactive oxygen species such as hydroxide and hydrogen peroxide (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). NAC is rapidly metabolized by the small intestine to produce glutathione. Enterocytes, colonocytes, and other intestinal cells readily transport NAC and convert it into L-cysteine (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), which helps to maintain the integrity, growth, and function of the intestinal mucosa (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Moreover, glutathione is a well-described and established antioxidant, it participates in detoxification of xenobiotics, regulation of cellular growth, modulation of immune response, and even inherent antibacterial properties (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>), which is an important modulator of antibiotic activity in bacteria (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). This makes NAC a promising supplement for the piglets to regulate the porcine gut microbiome and alleviate dysbiosis during pathogenic infection (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>), including PEDV (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Our previous study also demonstrated that dietary NAC supplementation improved intestinal integrity and functions in PEDV-infected piglets (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Based on the potential anti-PEDV effect of NAC in the piglets, this study was conducted to evaluate the impact of NAC on small intestinal microbiota in suckling piglets infected with PEDV. Findings of this study can contribute to understand the role of the gut microbiota during PEDV infection and provide vital clues for the treatment for PEDV infection.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Animals Experiments and Sample Collection</title><p>The animal use protocol for this research was approved by the Animal Care and Use Committee of Wuhan Polytechnic University (1204-2016-0028). Forty seven-day-old crossbred (Duroc &#215; Landrace &#215; Large White) healthy piglets with 3.17 &#177; 0.25 kg initial body weight were purchased from a PEDV-negative farm. All piglets were randomly allocated into one of four treatment groups (Control, NAC, PEDV, PEDV+NAC; 10 replicates per group). All piglets were housed in clean pens with strict control of cross-infection. A commercial milk replacer (Wuhan Anyou Feed Co., Ltd.; Wuhan, China) formulated to meet the nutrition requirement for suckling piglets, was used as the basal diet during the trial. Prior to feeding, the milk replacer (powder) was dissolved in warm water (45&#8211;55&#176;C) to form a liquid feed (dry matter content of 20%), as described by Wang et al. (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>).</p><p>The entire trial period was 12 days. During day 5&#8211;9 of the trial, the piglets in the NAC and the PEDV + NAC groups were orally administered with 50 mg/kg body weight NAC (Sigma Chemical Inc., St. Louis, MO, USA; dissolved in the liquid milk replacer), and the piglets in the other two groups received the same volume of the liquid milk replacer. On day 9 of the trial, PEDV at a dose of 10<sup>4.5</sup> TCID<sub>50</sub> (50% tissue culture infectious dose) per piglet was orally inoculated to the piglets in the PEDV and the PEDV + NAC groups, the same volume of sterile saline was inoculated to the piglets in control and NAC groups. On day 12, all piglets were sacrificed to obtain the intestinal content from jejunum, ileum, colon, and cecum. All samples were rapidly frozen in liquid nitrogen and then stored at &#8722;80&#176;C until analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>DNA Extraction</title><p>The bacterial DNA was extracted from the intestinal content using the QIAampDNA Stool Mini Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) according to the manufacturer's protocol. The extracted DNA was purified by using the QIAamp spin column (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany). Total DNA was quantified by determining the OD 260 nm/OD 280 nm ratio using the NanoDrop&#174;ND-1000A UV-VIS spectrophotometer (Thermo Scientific, Wilmington, DE, USA). The quality of microbial DNA in each sample was evaluated by 1% denatured agarose gel electrophoresis and the quantity of DNA with Picogreen assay. The microbial DNA were normalized with 10 mM Tris buffer (pH 8.5) to 5 ng/ul.</p></sec><sec><title>Amplification and Sequencing</title><p>The V3-V4 region of the 16S rRNA gene was amplified by two stage polymerase chain reaction (PCR). The first stage of PCR was processed using the HiFi HotStart ReadyMix kit (Kapa Biosystems, Wilmington, MA, USA) with the forward primer: 5&#8242;-TCGTCGGCAGCG TCAGATGTGTATAAGAGACAGCCTACGGGNGGCWGCAG-3&#8242; and the reverse primer 5&#8242;-GTCTCGTGGGCTCGGAGATGTGTATAAGAGACAGGACTACHVGGGTATCT AATCC-3&#8242;. The total reaction volume of PCR was 25 &#956;L, containing 12.5 &#956;L of 2 &#215; HotStart ReadyMix Buffer, 0.5 &#956;L of each primer (5 mM) and 10 ng of template DNA. PCR thermocycling conditions were denaturation at 95&#176;C for 3 min (1 cycle), 95&#176;C for 30 s, annealing at 55&#176;C for 30 s, elongation at 72&#176;C for 30 s and a final extension at 72&#176;C for 5 min. The second stage was index PCR. This step attaches dual indices and Illumina sequencing adapters using the Nextera XT Index Kit (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA). The total reaction volume was 50 &#956;L, containing 25 &#956;L of 2 &#215; HotStart ReadyMix Buffer, 5 &#956;L Cleaned PCR product, 5 &#956;L N7 index and 5 &#956;L S5 index primer. PCR thermocycling conditions were 95&#176;C for 3 min (1 cycle), 95&#176;C for 30 s, annealing at 55&#176;C for 30 s, elongation at 72&#176;C for 30 s (8 cycles), and a final extension at 72&#176;C for 5 min. The PCR production was purified with the Agencourt AMPure XP purification system (Beckman, Brea, CA, USA) and the concentration was measured with SpectraMax i3X Multi-mode detection platform (Molecular Devices, San Jose, CA, USA). The purified DNA samples were sequenced using Illumina MiSeq platform (San Diego, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>Data Processing and Statistical Analysis</title><p>The raw reads were put for quality control after base calling, and then were subjected to pipeline QIIME for OTU picking and taxonomy as described (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Alpha diversity (Shannon, Simpson, and Chao1) were calculated, and the one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with a Turkey's test as <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> was used to compare between the groups. The beta diversity (Bray-Curtis Index) was calculated using principal coordinate analysis (PCoA), with further comparison of groups by analysis of similarities (ANOSIM). Dendrograms and colinear relation diagrams were generated using Majorbio Cloud Platform (Shanghai Majorbio Bio-pharm Technology, Shanghai, China). Relative abundance of operational taxonomic units (OTUs) were compared by one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) using Majorbio Cloud Platform, with a Turkey's test as <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-values adjusted by false discovery rate (FDR). Functional potentials of OTUs were evaluated by KEGG (Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes) pathway enrichment using PICRUSt (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://huttenhower.sph.harvard.edu/galaxy/">http://huttenhower.sph.harvard.edu/galaxy/</ext-link>), a heatmap was generated using TBtools (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/CJ-Chen/TBtools">https://github.com/CJ-Chen/TBtools</ext-link>), and the comparison was processed by ANOVA using Majorbio Cloud Platform with a Turkey's test as <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic>. Significance was set at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 for all comparisons.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Sequencing Data and OUT Clustering</title><p>A total of 3,629,889 reads were obtained with an average length of 460.36 bp across all samples, with 3,629,889 reads from jejunum, 4,658,260 reads from ileum, 2,987,358 reads from colon, and 2,936,753 reads from cecum. The good coverage was obtained over 99.9% for all samples, reflecting reliable accuracy of the sequencing.</p><p>Evenness, diversity, and richness were calculated by Shannon, Simpson, and Chao1 indices, respectively (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Compared to the control group, the NAC group increased the Chao1 index in the ileum, the PEDV group increased the Shannon index in the jejunum, and the PEDV and the PEDV+NAC group increased the Simpson index in the jejunum (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). No significant difference was observed in the colon and cecum.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Alpha diversity of gut microbiota in piglets.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Item</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Control</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NAC</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PEDV</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PEDV+NAC</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Jejunum</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Shannon</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76 &#177; 0.66<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76 &#177; 0.74<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.32 &#177; 0.28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.72 &#177; 0.78<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Simpson</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 &#177; 0.21<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59 &#177; 0.24<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 &#177; 0.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 &#177; 0.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Chao1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.98 &#177; 5.65</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.19 &#177; 2.79</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.74 &#177; 2.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.22 &#177; 4.77</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.134</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Ileum</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Shannon</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80 &#177; 0.74</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.98 &#177; 0.57</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.11 &#177; 0.72</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30 &#177; 0.58</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.403</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Simpson</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56 &#177; 0.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 &#177; 0.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65 &#177; 0.21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 &#177; 0.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.329</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Chao1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102.57 &#177; 4.57<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106.68 &#177; 2.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105.37 &#177; 4.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105.19 &#177; 4.69<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.170</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Colon</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Shannon</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40 &#177; 0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.09 &#177; 0.41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.34 &#177; 0.37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.18 &#177; 0.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.257</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Simpson</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 &#177; 0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 &#177; 0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 &#177; 0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 &#177; 0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.207</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Chao1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">166.09 &#177; 10.57</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">159.63 &#177; 16.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156.78 &#177; 25.73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157.53 &#177; 26.75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.777</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Cecum</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Shannon</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.23 &#177; 0.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10 &#177; 0.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.22 &#177; 0.40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.16 &#177; 0.33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.850</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Simpson</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 &#177; 0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 &#177; 0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 &#177; 0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 &#177; 0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.340</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Chao1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162.66 &#177; 11.78</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162.71 &#177; 12.96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">161.02 &#177; 17.26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148.52 &#177; 22.34</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.214</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><label>a,b</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Values with different letters are significantly different (p &lt; 0.05)</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Beta diversity was calculated by PCoA based on the Bray-Curtis index. There is no clear clustering in the ileum (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.398) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>), while distinct bacterial communities were observed in the jejunum (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.002) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>), colon (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref>), and cecum (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1D</xref>). Particularly, the result illustrated obvious clusters between the control and the NAC groups as well as between the PEDV and the PEDV+NAC groups in the jejunum, colon, and cecum.</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Beta diversity of gut microbiota in piglets. <bold>(A)</bold> Jejunum, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.002; <bold>(B)</bold> ileum, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.398; <bold>(C)</bold> colon, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001; <bold>(D)</bold> cecum, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-07-582338-g0001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Structure of Intestinal Microbiota</title><p>The majority of microbiota in all samples was composed of four predominant bacterial phyla: <italic toggle="yes">Proteobacteria, Firmicutes, Bacteroidetes</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Fusobacteria</italic>, accounting for an average of over 96% of total sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). In the jejunum, the proportions of the four phyla in the control group were 72.5, 23.5, 2.2, and 1.2%; that in the NAC group were 59.4, 37.7, 2.1, and 0.4%; that in the PEDV group were 20.9, 75.0, 3.0, and 0.6%; that in the PEDV+NAC group were 18.7, 69.6, 9.4, and 1.2%. In the ileum, the proportions of the four phyla were 83.0, 12.9, 3.3, and 0.5% in the control group; 68.1, 24.9, 5.7, and 0.5% in the NAC group; 74.3, 15.8, 8.6, and 0.6% in the PEDV group; 59.1, 32.9, 6.4, and 0.6% in the PEDV+NAC group. In the colon, the proportions were 6.7, 24.1, 63.6, and 0.1% in the control group; 6.2, 25.0, 61.8, and 0.1% in the NAC group; 15.0, 38.4, 38.7, and 2.0% in the PEDV group, 14.9, 36.9, 42.1, and 1.3% in the PEDV+NAC group. In the cecum, the proportions were 4.8, 21.7, 65.0, and 0.2% in the control group; 6.9, 18.9, 60.4, and 1.4% in the NAC group; 14.3, 36.4, 36.0, and 8.0% in the PEDV group, 20.2, 39.7, 32.7, and 2.5% in the PEDV+NAC group.</p><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Relative abundance of sequences at the phylum level (%). Only sequences with relative abundance over 0.01% were presented.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-07-582338-g0002.jpg"/></fig><p>A total of 13 genera was identified as the dominant bacterial populations (&gt; 2%) in all groups. <italic toggle="yes">Shigella, Lactobacillus, Actinobacillus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Veillonella</italic> were the most abundant genera in the jejunum, accounting for 53, 13, 12, and 6.4% in the control group, 52, 27, 5.1, and 7.1% in the NAC group, 63, 9, 5.7, and 6.1% in the PEDV group, 51, 13, 1.6, and 3.3% in the PEDV+NAC group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Shigella, Actinobacillus, Lactobacillus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Veillonella</italic> were the most abundant genera in the ileum, accounting for 63, 7.9, 1.9, and 3.3% in the control group, 59, 5.4, 5.9, and 6.4% in the NAC group, 48, 8.7, 4.4, and 2.4% in the PEDV group, 46, 8.1, 17, and 3.0% in the PEDV+NAC group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroides, Anaerovibrio, Alloprevotella, Prevotella, Parabacteriodies</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Oscillospria</italic> were the most abundant genera in the colon, accounting for 27, 3.8, 9.5, 1.9, 5.4, and 11% in the control group, 35, 3.3, 6.4, 3.8, 8.1, and 4.8% in the NAC group, 11, 16, 11, 6.1, 5.3, and 1.7% in the PEDV group, 8.5, 19, 11, 15, 2.3, and 2.2% in the PEDV+NAC group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3C</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroides, Anaerovibrio, Alloprevotella, Prevotella, Parabacteriodies</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Oscillospria</italic> were the most abundant genera in the cecum, accounting for 36, 4.6, 8.3, 1.7, 3.7, and 10% in the control group, 34, 2.5, 8.3, 2.9, 9.3, and 5% in the NAC group, 14, 18, 9.1, 5, 4.3, and 1.3% in the PEDV group, 11, 16, 4.8, 10, 2.1, and 0.1% in the PEDV+NAC group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3D</xref>).</p><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Relative abundance of OTUs at the genus level (%). <bold>(A)</bold> Jejunum; <bold>(B)</bold> ileum; <bold>(C)</bold> colon; <bold>(D)</bold> cecum. Only OTUs with relative abundance over 2% were presented.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-07-582338-g0003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Comparison of OTUs Abundance</title><p>The differences in the percentage of OTU abundance between all groups were summarized in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. In the jejunum, compared to the control group, both the PEDV and the PEDV+NAC groups decreased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Shigella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae</italic>_g (an unclassified genus that belongs to family <italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae</italic>, same as others), increased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). No significant difference was observed between the control and the NAC groups as well as between the PEDV and the PEDV+NAC groups. In the ileum, compared to the control group, the NAC group increased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus, Streptococcus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic>, the PEDV group increased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Odoribacter</italic>, and the PEDV+NAC group increased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05); compared to the PEDV group, the PEDV+NAC group decreased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> and increased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). In the colon, compared to the control group, the NAC group decreased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Rikenellaceae</italic>_g and increased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Acidaminococcus</italic>, the PEDV group decreased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Rikenellaceae</italic>_g and increased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Anaerovibrio, Lachnospiraceae</italic>_g, <italic toggle="yes">Lachnoclostridium, Helicobacter</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Sutterella</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05); compared to the PEDV group, the PEDV+NAC group increased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Allisonella</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). In the cecum, compared to the control group, the PEDV group decreased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> and increased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Anaerovibrio, Oscillospira, Lachnospiraceae</italic>_g, <italic toggle="yes">Helicobacter, Sutterella</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Butyricimonas</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05); compared to the PEDV group, the PEDV+NAC group decreased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Oscillospira</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of OUT abundance (%).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Taxonomy</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Control</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NAC</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PEDV</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PEDV+NAC</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Jejunum</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Shigella</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.43 &#177; 22.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.93 &#177; 20.91<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.44 &#177; 9.79<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.57 &#177; 9.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Shigella</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.94 &#177; 9.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.70 &#177; 9.91<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.71 &#177; 4.71<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.18 &#177; 3.99<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.038</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 &#177; 0.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 &#177; 1.42<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.31 &#177; 3.27<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.48 &#177; 5.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Clostridiales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae</italic>; g_</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 &#177; 0.42<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11 &#177; 0.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 &#177; 0.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 &#177; 0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 &#177; 0.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 &#177; 0.07<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 &#177; 0.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 &#177; 0.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Ileum</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 &#177; 0.47<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63 &#177; 2.53<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.53 &#177; 1.78<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>bc</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.32 &#177; 9.49<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Streptococcaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 &#177; 0.07<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 &#177; 0.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 &#177; 0.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11 &#177; 0.11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Paraprevotellaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 &#177; 0.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 &#177; 0.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08 &#177; 0.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 &#177; 0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Enterococcaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 &#177; 0.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 &#177; 0.07<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 &#177; 0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 &#177; 0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Odoribacteraceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Odoribacter</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 &#177; 0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 &#177; 0.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 &#177; 0.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 &#177; 0.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Colon</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Selenomonadales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Selenomonadaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Anaerovibrio</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.75 &#177; 4.07<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40 &#177; 1.98<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.65 &#177; 5.76<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.78 &#177; 6.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Selenomonadales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Selenomonadaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Anaerovibrio</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.89 &#177; 2.91<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 &#177; 1.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.19 &#177; 3.72<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.83 &#177; 3.47<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Selenomonadales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Selenomonadaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Anaerovibrio</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 &#177; 2.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62 &#177; 0.87<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.83 &#177; 2.82<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.48 &#177; 2.75<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Lachnospirales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae</italic>; g_</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 &#177; 0.67<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08 &#177; 0.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.81 &#177; 3.70<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.05 &#177; 2.72<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Lachnospirales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Lachnoclostridium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 &#177; 0.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44 &#177; 0.39<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.08 &#177; 1.67<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50 &#177; 1.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Campylobacterales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Helicobacteraceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Helicobacter</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 &#177; 0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 &#177; 0.11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 &#177; 0.95<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 &#177; 1.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Acidaminococcales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Acidaminococcaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Acidaminococcus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 &#177; 0.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 &#177; 1.56<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01 &#177; 0.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 &#177; 0.32<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Burkholderiales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Sutterellaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Sutterella</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 &#177; 0.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 &#177; 0.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46 &#177; 0.51<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 &#177; 0.36<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Oscillospirales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Oscillospiraceae</italic>; g_</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 &#177; 0.11<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08 &#177; 0.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 &#177; 0.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 &#177; 0.61<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 &#177; 0.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 &#177; 0.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 &#177; 0.22<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 &#177; 0.75<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Veillonellales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Veillonellaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Allisonella</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 &#177; 0.41<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06 &#177; 0.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 &#177; 0.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 &#177; 1.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Lachnospirales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Lachnoclostridium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 &#177; 0.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10 &#177; 0.07<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51 &#177; 0.39<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35 &#177; 0.26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Rikenellaceae</italic>; g_</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43 &#177; 0.45<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 &#177; 0.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 &#177; 0.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03 &#177; 0.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.167</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Cecum</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Selenomonadales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Selenomonadaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Anaerovibrio</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.88 &#177; 4.38<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.08 &#177; 4.57<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.60 &#177; 7.13<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.78 &#177; 5.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Selenomonadales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Selenomonadaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Anaerovibrio</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60 &#177; 3.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 &#177; 0.74<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.86 &#177; 4.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.53 &#177; 2.91<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Clostridiales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Ruminococcaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Oscillospira</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 &#177; 0.72<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 &#177; 0.54<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97 &#177; 2.79<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 &#177; 1.41<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.070</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Clostridiales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae</italic>; g_</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19 &#177; 0.21<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 &#177; 0.51<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97 &#177; 1.69<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55 &#177; 1.45<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Prevotellaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23 &#177; 2.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44 &#177; 1.65<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 &#177; 0.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02 &#177; 0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Burkholderiales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Alcaligenaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Sutterella</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 &#177; 0.26<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21 &#177; 0.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 &#177; 0.93<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 &#177; 0.56<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Clostridiales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae</italic>; g_</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 &#177; 0.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13 &#177; 0.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 &#177; 0.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16 &#177; 0.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Odoribacteraceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Butyricimonas</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09 &#177; 0.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13 &#177; 0.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 &#177; 0.35<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16 &#177; 0.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">o_<italic toggle="yes">Clostridiales</italic>; f_<italic toggle="yes">Ruminococcaceae</italic>; g_<italic toggle="yes">Oscillospira</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20 &#177; 0.17<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 &#177; 0.20<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25 &#177; 0.18<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08 &#177; 0.05<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN2"><label>a,b,c</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Values with different letters are significantly different (p &lt; 0.05)</italic>.</p></fn><p><italic toggle="yes">f_Lachnospiraceae; g_ means an unclassified genus that belongs to family Lachnospiraceae, same as others</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Functional Potentials of OUTs</title><p>Functional potentials of the microbiome profile were evaluated by KEGG pathway enrichment, the relative abundance of 25 pathways was found with significant differences between groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). In the jejunum, compared to the control group, the PEDV group increased the abundance of pathways &#8220;nucleotide metabolism,&#8221; &#8220;lipid metabolism,&#8221; &#8220;translation,&#8221; &#8220;replication and repair,&#8221; &#8220;transcription,&#8221; and &#8220;immune diseases,&#8221; the PEDV+NAC group increased the abundance of pathway &#8220;immune diseases&#8221; (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05); compared to the NAC group, the PEDV group increased the abundance of pathway &#8220;infectious diseases: parasitic&#8221; and decreased the abundance of pathway &#8220;excretory system&#8221; (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). In the ileum, compared to the control group, the NAC group increased the abundance of pathways &#8220;signaling molecules and interaction&#8221; and &#8220;cellular community&#8212;eukaryotes&#8221; (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05); compared to the NAC group, the PEDV+NAC group decreased the abundance of pathways &#8220;cell motility,&#8221; &#8220;infectious diseases: bacterial&#8221; and &#8220;excretory system&#8221; (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). In the colon, compared to the control and the NAC groups, the PEDV and the PEDV+NAC groups increased the abundance of pathways &#8220;cell motility,&#8221; &#8220;infectious diseases: viral,&#8221; and &#8220;circulatory system&#8221; (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). In the cecum, compared to the control group, the PEDV group also increased the abundance of pathways &#8220;xenobiotics biodegradation and metabolism,&#8221; &#8220;cellular community&#8212;prokaryotes,&#8221; &#8220;cellular community&#8212;eukaryotes,&#8221; and &#8220;cancers: specific types&#8221; (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05); compared to the control and the NAC groups, the PEDV group increased the abundance of pathways &#8220;signal transduction,&#8221; &#8220;membrane transport,&#8221; &#8220;signaling molecules and interaction,&#8221; &#8220;cell motility,&#8221; &#8220;infectious diseases: bacterial,&#8221; &#8220;infectious diseases: viral,&#8221; &#8220;environmental adaptation,&#8221; and &#8220;circulatory system&#8221; (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05); compared the PEDV group, the PEDV+NAC group decreased the abundance of pathways &#8220;amino acid metabolism,&#8221; &#8220;signaling molecules and interaction,&#8221; &#8220;cellular community&#8212;eukaryotes,&#8221; &#8220;cancer&#8212;overview,&#8221; &#8220;drug resistance&#8212;antineoplastic,&#8221; &#8220;endocrine and metabolic diseases,&#8221; &#8220;cancers: specific types,&#8221; &#8220;endocrine system&#8221;, and &#8220;excretory system&#8221; (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>KEGG pathway enrichment of gut microbiome in piglets. Different colors represent the values of log-transformed abundances of KEGG pathways. <sup>&#8743;</sup>means significant difference compared to the control group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05); <sup>#</sup>means significant difference compared to the NAC group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05); *means significant difference compared to the PEDV group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-07-582338-g0004.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Several studies have revealed the dysbiosis of porcine gut microbiome induced by PEDV infection (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), which was associated with the increased abundance of pathogenic bacteria (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">Shigella, Enterococcus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Fusobacterium</italic>) and the decreased abundance of short-chain fatty acid (SCFA)-producing bacteria (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroides, Prevotella, Butyricimonas</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Alistipes</italic>). However, for the first time this study investigated the effect of a potential anti-PEDV substance on the gut microbiota in piglets, NAC was supplemented to the diet of both the healthy and PEDV-infected piglets. Our previous study indicated that NAC improved mucosal structure and intestinal permeability, reduced oxidative stress, and modulated the expression of genes associated with intestinal immune in the piglets during PEDV infection (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Therefore, we hypothesize that the supplementation of NAC is promising to protect piglets from the microbiome dysbiosis caused by PEDV infection.</p><p>In the present study, the ileal samples displayed a higher similarity of bacterial community than other intestinal sections, as evaluated by insignificant data of alpha and beta diversity. However, several significant differences of diversity indices were observed in the jejunum, colon, and cecum, particularly the obvious clusters of beta diversity between the healthy and the PEDV-infected piglets, indicating the community of the gut microbiota was markedly altered by PEDV infection. Similar findings were obtained by Huang et al. (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) and (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Interestingly, increased alpha diversity indices (Shannon and Simpson) were observed in the PEDV-infected piglets, implying PEDV infection led to the dysbiosis of porcine microbiome. This result is similar to the finding of Huang et al. (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) that alpha diversity increased with time during PEDV infection, but is contrary to results of Song et al. (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) and (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Nevertheless, Chao index in the ileum was found as the only difference between the control and NAC groups, no other variation was found between the control and NAC groups and between the PEDV and the PEDV+NAC groups, suggesting a slight effect of NAC on the bacterial community.</p><p>Characterization of bacterial composition in this research demonstrated remarkable variations caused by PEDV infection. Profound shifts in the microbiota composition at the phylum level were found in the jejunum, colon, and cecum. Particularly, the PEDV and the PEDV+NAC groups displayed a lower abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> and a higher abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Proteobacteria, Firmicutes</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Fusobacteria</italic> than the control and the NAC groups in the colon and cecum. The phylum <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroides</italic> is important for carbohydrate fermentation and polysaccharide catabolism, as well as amino acid and protein utilization (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). The phylum <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> has been shown to be involved in energy resorption, and potentially related to the development of obesity and inflammation (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Many studies suggested that <italic toggle="yes">Proteobacteria</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Fusobacteria</italic> are associated with the imbalance of microbiota, inflammations, and various clinical anaerobic infections (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). These results suggest that PEDV infection caused severe alterations in the composition of the gut microbiota in piglets, which could lead to the dysbiosis and affect intestinal metabolism and host health. However, similar microbiota composition was observed between the control and the NAC groups as well as between the PEDV and the PEDV+NAC groups, implying a limited effect of NAC supplementation on the composition of bacterial community in either the healthy or the PEDV-infected piglets.</p><p>The abundance of several OTUs showed significant differences between the healthy and the PEDV infected piglets. Interestingly, PEDV infection was associated with decreased proportions of <italic toggle="yes">Shigella</italic> and increased proportions of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus, Odoribacter, Anaerovibrio, Helicobacter, Lachnospiraceae</italic>_g and <italic toggle="yes">Sutterella</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">Shigella</italic> species generally invade the epithelial lining of the colon, causing severe inflammation and death of the cells lining the colon, which could result in the diarrhea and even dysentery (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). However, the reduction of <italic toggle="yes">Shigella</italic> in this study was only observed in the jejunum, which may be ascribed to the frequent flow of intestinal content induced by the diarrhea. Genera <italic toggle="yes">Helicobacter</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Sutterella</italic> are typical pathogenic bacteria, which have been frequently associated with human diseases, such as stomach cancer and inflammatory bowel disease (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Increased <italic toggle="yes">Helicobacter</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Sutterella</italic> abundances suggested the adverse healthy effect of PEDV infection. <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> is commonly investigated as probiotic agents, which influences host immunity and disease susceptibility (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Increased <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> was also observed in PEDV-infected piglets (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), which was hypothesized to be the effect of pathogen inhibition or immunomodulation of the host. The genus <italic toggle="yes">Odoribacter</italic> and the family <italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae</italic> are SCFAs-producing bacteria (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">Anaerovibrio</italic> is often associated with lipolysis (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). The increase of these metabolic-related bacteria may involve in metabolic regulations of the host, or metabolic disorder induced by the dysbiosis during PEDV infection. Future investigation is warranted to unravel the complex relationship between the microbiome shifts and PEDV infection.</p><p>In this study, NAC supplementation presented different trends in the alteration of gut microbiome in the healthy piglets vs. the PEDV-infected piglets. In the healthy piglets, NAC supplementation decreased the proportion of family <italic toggle="yes">Rikenellaceae</italic> and increased the proportion of genera <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic>; while in the PEDV-infected piglets, NAC was associated with decreased proportions of <italic toggle="yes">Oscillospira</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic>. Previous evidence showed that the members of family <italic toggle="yes">Rikenellaceae</italic> showed a high potential for fermenting dietary proteins (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), and enriched in mice fed a high-fat diet (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Streptococcus populations are primary fermenters of diet-derived simple sugars in the small intestine (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>), as evaluated by the high expression of genes involved in primary carbohydrate transport systems by the small intestinal <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus</italic> (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Decreased <italic toggle="yes">Rikenellaceae</italic> and increased Streptococcus by NAC supplementation indicated that NAC played a positive role in the metabolic regulation of the healthy piglets. Moreover, <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> spp. have been reported to produce bacteriocins which inhibit Gram-positive food-borne bacteria and intestinal pathogens (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>), increased <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> by NAC supplementation implied a potential to improve immunity of the healthy piglets. Recent research reported that <italic toggle="yes">Oscillospira</italic> is often associated with leanness (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>), while <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> was negatively associated with the severity of diarrhea-predominant irritable bowel syndrome (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). NAC supplementation decreased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Oscillospira</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> in the PEDV-infected piglets, implying that NAC could promote the growth of piglets and mitigate diarrhea during PEDV infection. Additionally, NAC supplementation increased the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> in both the healthy and the PEDV-infected piglets, suggesting a beneficial effect of NAC on the regulation of the gut microbiota in the suckling piglets.</p><p>A few studies have revealed changes in the functional potential of microbiome in relation to PEDV infection, which was found to attenuate metabolism and defense mechanisms and enhance transcription and membrane transport (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Similar results were obtained in the present study, reflecting that attenuating metabolism, barrier, and immune is the major functional shift of microbiome during PEDV infection. However, in the PEDV-infected piglets, many functional potentials of the microbiome were remarkably influenced by NAC supplementation. For instance, decreased amino acid metabolism, cell signaling, cellular community, multiple disease-related pathways, and endocrine and excretory system in the cecum. These results demonstrated that functional changes of the gut microbiome may be a way that NAC protects the piglets from PEDV infection.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>This study evaluated the effect of dietary supplementation with NAC on the gut microbiome in the healthy and PEDV-infected piglets. PEDV infection caused severe dysbiosis of gut microbiome, as demonstrated by the community variation (beta diversity) and the composition shifts (decreased <italic toggle="yes">Shigella</italic> and increased <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus, Odoribacter, Anaerovibrio, Helicobacter, Lachnospiraceae</italic>_g, and <italic toggle="yes">Sutterella</italic>), resulted in functional changes associated with metabolism, barrier and immune. However, NAC supplementation played a positive role in regulating the gut microbiome during PEDV infection, as indicated by the altered bacterial populations (decreased <italic toggle="yes">Oscillospira</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> and increased <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic>) and function potentials (amino acid metabolism, cell signaling, cellular community, diseases, endocrine, and excretory system). Therefore, regulating the gut microbiome by anti-PEDV(antiviral) substances or compounds could be taken as a promising candidate for the prevention or treatment of PEDV infection.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are deposited in the Majorbio Cloud Platform database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.majorbio.com">www.majorbio.com</ext-link>). The datasets generated for this study are available on request to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by Animal Care and Use Committee of Wuhan Polytechnic University.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>TW and YH planned the project and designed the experiments. TW, YL, and XL conducted the experiments. YL carried out the data analysis. MW, KY, SL, and CJ contributed the animal trials. XL and DZ contributed reagents preparation and samples collection. YL and TW wrote the manuscript and reviewed by QZ, YZ, and DY. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This research was supported by the National Key R&amp;D Program of China (2017YFD0500505), Open Project of Hubei Key Laboratory of Animal Nutrition and Feed Science (Grant Number 201905), and Hubei Provincial Technology and Innovation Program (2017AHB062).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jandhyala</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Talukdar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanyam</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vuyyuru</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasikala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of the normal gut microbiota</article-title>. <source>World J Gastroenterol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>8787</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3748/wjg.v21.i29.8787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26269668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4528021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolnerhanssen</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer-Gerspach</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schweinfurth</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mallien</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Common pathways in depression and obesity: the role of gut microbiome and diets</article-title>. <source>Curr Behav Neurosci Rep.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40473-020-00199-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baothman</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zamzami</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taher</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abubaker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abu-Farha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of gut microbiota in the development of obesity and diabetes</article-title>. <source>Lipids Health Dis.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>108</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12944-016-0278-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27317359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4912704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andoh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Physiological role of gut microbiota for maintaining human health</article-title>. <source>Digestion.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>93</volume>:<fpage>176</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000444066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26859303</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albenberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomov</surname><given-names>VT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gut microbiota and IBD: causation or correlation?</article-title><source>Nat Rev Gastro Hepat.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>573</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrgastro.2017.88</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5880536</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28743984</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pickard</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caruso</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Gut microbiota: role in pathogen colonization, immune responses, and inflammatory disease</article-title>. <source>Immunol Rev.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>279</volume>:<fpage>70</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>89</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/imr.12567</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28856738</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5657496</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Gut microbiota: an integral moderator in health and disease</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.00151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29515527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5826318</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santana</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morcatti Coura</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>RGC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>CAG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira Junior</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Identification and characterization of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>, salmOnella spp., <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">C. difficile</italic> isolates from reptiles in Brazil</article-title>. <source>BioMed Res Int.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>2019</volume>:<fpage>9530732</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2019/9530732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31263711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6556801</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Porcine epidemic diarrhea virus: an emerging and re-emerging epizootic swine virus</article-title>. <source>Virol J.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>193</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12985-015-0421-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26689811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4687282</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvajal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arguello</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;nez-Lobo</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costillas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miranda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de nova</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Porcine epidemic diarrhoea: new insights into an old disease</article-title>. <source>Porc Health Manag.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40813-015-0007-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28405418</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5382377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallien</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lediguerher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catinot</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paboeuf</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bigault</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evidence of porcine epidemic diarrhea virus (PEDV) shedding in semen from infected specific pathogen-free boars</article-title>. <source>Vet Res.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13567-018-0505-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29368629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5784731</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Altered gut microbiota profiles in sows and neonatal piglets associated with porcine epidemic diarrhea virus infection</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-17830-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29234140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5727058</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in the swine gut microbiota in response to porcine epidemic diarrhea infection</article-title>. <source>Microbes Environ.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>284</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1264/jsme2.ME15046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26212519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4567570</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Porcine epidemic diarrhea virus infection induced the unbalance of gut microbiota in piglets</article-title>. <source>Curr Microbiol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>71</volume>:<fpage>643</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00284-015-0895-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26319658</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Differences in the intestinal microbiota between uninfected piglets and piglets infected with porcine epidemic diarrhea virus</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>e0192992</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0192992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29447243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5814011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dynamic change of gut microbiota during porcine epidemic diarrhea virus infection in suckling piglets</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>322</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.00322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30858839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6397872</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Porcine epidemic diarrhea altered colonic microbiota communities in suckling piglets</article-title>. <source>Genes.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/genes11010044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31905830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7016528</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ZG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>N-acetylcysteine reduces inflammation in the small intestine by regulating redox, EGF and TLR4 signaling</article-title>. <source>Amino Acids.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>513</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00726-012-1295-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22532030</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ZG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Protective effects of N-acetylcysteine on intestinal functions of piglets challenged with lipopolysaccharide</article-title>. <source>Amino Acids.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>1233</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00726-011-1191-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22180025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary requirements of synthesizable amino acids by animals: a paradigm shift in protein nutrition</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci Biotechnol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>34</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2049-1891-5-34</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24999386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4082180</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schairer</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chouake</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kutner</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Makdisi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nosanchuk</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of the antibiotic properties of glutathione</article-title>. <source>J Drugs Dermatol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1272</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2014.01.131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24196336</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goswami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jawali</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>N-acetylcysteine-mediated modulation of bacterial antibiotic susceptibility</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>3529</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.00710-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20547812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2916349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samuni</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The chemistry and biological activities of N-acetylcysteine</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>1830</volume>:<fpage>4117</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>29</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagen.2013.04.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23618697</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Manipulation of intestinal antiviral innate immunity and immune evasion strategies of porcine epidemic diarrhea virus</article-title>. <source>BioMed Res. Int.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>2019</volume>:<fpage>e1862531</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2019/1862531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31781594</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6874955</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>N-Acetylcysteine supplementation alleviates intestinal injury in piglets infected by porcine epidemic diarrhea virus</article-title>. <source>Amino Acids.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>1931</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00726-017-2397-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28258325</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of baicalin-aluminum complexes on fecal microbiome in piglets</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>2390</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms20102390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31091773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6566245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hooper</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Midtvedt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>How host-microbial interactions shape the nutrient environment of the mammalian intestine</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Nutr.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>283</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>307</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.nutr.22.011602.092259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12055347</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ley</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turnbaugh</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Human gut microbes associated with obesity</article-title>. <source>Nature.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>444</volume>:<fpage>1022</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/4441022a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17183309</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swidsinski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorel</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loening-Baucke</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Theissig</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruckert</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Acute appendicitis is characterised by local invasion with fusobacterium nucleatum/necrophorum</article-title>. <source>Gut.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>60</volume>:<fpage>34</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gut.2009.191320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19926616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blaser</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Mandell, Douglas, and Bennett's Principles and Practice of Infectious Diseases</source>. <volume>Vol. 2</volume><publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier Health Sciences</publisher-name> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kotloff</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nataro</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blackwelder</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasrin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farag</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panchalingam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Burden and aetiology of diarrhoeal disease in infants and young children in developing countries (the Global Enteric Multicenter Study, GEMS): a prospective, case-control study</article-title>. <source>Lancet.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>382</volume>:<fpage>209</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(13)60844-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23680352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wierzba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Status of vaccine research and development for Shigella</article-title>. <source>Vaccine.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>2887</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2016.02.075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26979135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Species differentiation and identification in the genus of helicobacter</article-title>. <source>World J Gastroenterol.</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3748/wjg.v5.i1.7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11819372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4688506</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hiippala</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kainulainen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalliomaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arkkila</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Satokari</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mucosal prevalence and interactions with the epithelium indicate commensalism of Sutterella spp</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1706</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.01706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27833600</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5080374</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niederwerder</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Role of the microbiome in swine respiratory disease</article-title>. <source>Vet Microbiol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>209</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>106</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2017.02.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28318782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez-Arango</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nitert</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Increased systolic and diastolic blood pressure is associated with altered gut microbiota composition and butyrate production in early pregnancy</article-title>. <source>Hypertension.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>974</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.116.07910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27528065</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boutard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cerisy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Functional diversity of carbohydrate-active enzymes enabling a bacterium to ferment plant biomass</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e1004773</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25393313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4230839</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shingfield</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CHAPTER 1:synthesis of conjugated linoleic acid in ruminants and humans, in conjugated linoleic acids and conjugated vegetable oils</article-title>. <source>Roy Soc Chem</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/9781782620211-00001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>XZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Acetobacteroides hydrogenigenes gen. <italic toggle="yes">nov., sp. nov.,</italic> an anaerobic hydrogen-producing bacterium in the family Rikenellaceae isolated from a reed swamp</article-title>. <source>Int J Syst Evol Microbiol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>2986</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.063917-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24899658</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joh</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>High fat diet-induced gut microbiota exacerbates inflammation and obesity in mice via the TLR4 signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e47713</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23091640</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3473013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Bogert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meijerink</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zoetendal</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kleerebezem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Immunomodulatory properties of Streptococcus and veillonella isolates from the human small intestine microbiota</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e114277</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25479553</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4257559</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zoetendal</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Bogert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arumugam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Booijink</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Troost</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The human small intestinal microbiota is driven by rapid uptake and conversion of simple carbohydrates</article-title>. <source>ISME J.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1415</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ismej.2011.212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22258098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3379644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franz</surname><given-names>CMAP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Worobo</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quadri</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schillinger</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holzapfel</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vederas</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Atypical genetic locus associated with constitutive production of enterocin B by <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecium</italic> BFE 900</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol.</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>2170</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.65.5.2170-2178.1999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10224016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC91313</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toit</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franz</surname><given-names>CMAP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dicks</surname><given-names>LMT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holzapfel</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Preliminary characterization of bacteriocins produced by <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecium</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecalis</italic> isolated from pig faeces</article-title>. <source>J Appl Microbiol.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>482</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2672.2000.00986.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10747229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gophna</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Konikoff</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Oscillospira and related bacteria-From metagenomic species to metabolic features</article-title>. <source>Environ Microbiol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>835</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1462-2920.13658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28028921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tap</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Derrien</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tornblom</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brazeilles</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cools-Portier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dore</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of an intestinal microbiota signature associated with severity of irritable bowel syndrome</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>152</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2016.09.049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27725146</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Altered intestinal microbiota with increased abundance of prevotella is associated with high risk of diarrhea-predominant irritable bowel syndrome</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterol Res Pract.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>2018</volume>:<fpage>e6961783</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2018/6961783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29967640</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6008816</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>