<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7855973</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7855973.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7855973</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7855973</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33553279</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2020.600587</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A First Report of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> Infection of the Sea Bass, <italic toggle="yes">Lateolabrax maculatus</italic> in China</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="B">Baotun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names initials="C">Can</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names initials="J">Juan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/584615/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names initials="J">Jianmei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names initials="B">Biao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qunhong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names initials="Y">Youlu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1073099/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Innovative Institute of Animal Healthy Breeding, Zhongkai University of Agriculture and Engineering</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Key Laboratory of South China Sea Fishery Resources Development and Utilization, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>National Demonstration Center for Experimental Fisheries Science Education, Shanghai Ocean University</institution>, <addr-line>Shanghai</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Modern Agricultural Development Center of Zhuhai City</institution>, <addr-line>Zhuhai</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Lixing Huang, Jimei University, China</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Peng Luo, South China Sea Institute of Oceanology (CAS), China; Xueming Dan, South China Agricultural University, China</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Youlu Su <email>youlusu@zhku.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Veterinary Infectious Diseases, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>1</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">351216</issue-id><elocation-id>600587</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>8</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>04</day><month>02</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-01-04 21:25:32.077"><day>04</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2021 Wang, Mao, Feng, Li, Hu, Jiang, Gu and Su.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wang, Mao, Feng, Li, Hu, Jiang, Gu and Su</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-07-600587.pdf"/><abstract><p>The sea bass, <italic toggle="yes">Lateolabrax maculatus</italic> is commercially farmed in Zhuhai, located in the Guangdong Province of China. <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> in aquaculture have suffered acute death, characterized by ulcerations on the body surface, congestion, and hemorrhage in internal organs such as liver, kidney, and spleen. The dominant infecting strain of bacteria isolated from the kidneys of diseased fish was identified as <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> (strain 18BJ181). This identification was based on analysis of morphological, physiological, and biochemical features, as well as 16S rRNA and <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic> gene sequences. Drug sensitivity testing showed that the strain 18BJ181 isolate was resistant to four antibacterial drugs, including amoxicillin, madinomycin, penicillin and sulfamethoxazole, while moderately sensitive to erythromycin and rifampicin. The detection of growth characteristics showed that the strain 18BJ181 exhibited adaptability to the environment. In addition, some virulence genes, such as <italic toggle="yes">aer, act, gcaT, tapA</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">fla</italic>, were detected in the strain 18BJ181. The median lethal dosage of the strain 18BJ181 isolate in <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> was 8.5 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup> and 4.2 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup> cfu/g under the conditions of intraperitoneal injection and intramuscular injection, respectively. The experimentally induced infection showed that the 18BJ181 isolate caused considerable histological lesions in <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic>, including tissue degeneration, necrosis, and different degrees of hemorrhage. These results provided evidence for a more comprehensive understanding of <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> strain 18BJ181 infection in <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic>.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic></kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Lateolabrax maculatus</italic></kwd><kwd>physiological and biochemical characteristics</kwd><kwd>pathogenicity</kwd><kwd>pathology</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="47"/><page-count count="12"/><word-count count="6623"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic>, a Gram-negative bacterial pathogen, has a wide range of hosts and can cause diarrhea and sepsis in humans (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). In particular, <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> is a common pathogen in aquaculture, which can infect a variety of aquatic animals, including freshwater goldfish (<italic toggle="yes">Carassius auratus</italic>) (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), Nile tilapia (<italic toggle="yes">Oreochromis niloticus</italic>,) (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), Chinese Longsnout catfish (<italic toggle="yes">Leiocassis longirostris g&#252;nther</italic>) (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) and catfish (<italic toggle="yes">Ictalurus punctatus</italic>,) (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). The clinical symptoms of infected fish are skin ulcers and visceral hemorrhage. The histopathological changes caused by <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> are manifested as cerebral vascular hyperemia, inflammatory cell infiltration, osteoporosis, renal tubular necrosis, and hepatocyte degeneration (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). The virulence of <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> was shown to be stronger than <italic toggle="yes">Aermonas hydrophila</italic>, which could cause septicemia in fish (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). At present, <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> is the primary pathogen isolated from freshwater fish in South China.</p><p>The sea bass, <italic toggle="yes">Lateolabrax maculatus</italic>, is an economically important, cultured species in East Asia and is an important aquaculture fish in China in particular (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Viral and bacterial diseases can cause significant damage to cultured <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). In 2018, a continuous epidemiological investigation was carried out in the <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> culture area in the Zhuhai, Guangdong Province in China, and found that <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> was an important pathogen. In this study, the results of isolation, identification, drug sensitivity, growing characteristics, virulence gene distribution and pathogenicity of the <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> isolate are described.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Sampling of Diseased Fish and Isolation of Bacteria</title><p>Diseased <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> were sampled from a freshwater fish farm in Zhuhai, Guangdong Province, China. Moribund fish were taken from the pond to a laboratory at the Modern Agricultural Development Center of Zhuhai City, Zhuhai, Guangdong Province, China. Only diseased fish with typical clinical symptoms were used for bacterial examination. The fish were dissected after their skin was cleaned with 75% ethyl alcohol. Liver, spleen, and kidney were used for bacterial isolation. A Nutrient Agar medium (NA) was employed for bacteria isolation for 24 h at 28&#176;C and the dominant uniform bacterial colonies were purified by streaking onto the NA plates twice. A single bacterial colony was selected and inoculated in nutrient broth (NB) for 14 h at 28&#176;C, then preserved at &#8722;80&#176;C in the NB medium containing 20% (v/v) sterile glycerol. A dominant strain was tentatively named 18BJ181.</p></sec><sec><title>Analysis of Physiological and Biochemical Characterization</title><p>Thirty-eight biochemical reactions were performed using Vitek 2 Compact (Biomerieux, France) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Identification results of bacterial species were generated based on the combination of biochemical activities.</p></sec><sec><title>Sequence Analysis of 16S rRNA and <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic> Gene</title><p>The genomic DNA of the strain 18BJ181 was extracted using a TIANamp Bacterial DNA Kit (Tiangen-Biotech, Beijing, China) following the manufacturer's guidelines. Genomic DNA was stored at &#8722;20&#176;C. A pair of universal primers, 8 F:5&#8242;- AGAGTTTGATCCTGGCTCAG-3&#8242; and 1492 R: 5&#8242;-GGTTACCTTGTTACGACTT-3&#8242;, was used for amplification of the 16S rRNA gene. A pair of primers, 3 F:5&#8242;-TCCGGCGGTCTGCACGGCGT-3&#8242; and 14 R: 5&#8242;-TTGTCCGGG TTGTACTCGTC-3&#8242;, was used for amplification of the <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic> gene. The mixtures were incubated in a cycle of 95&#176;C for 5 min, followed by 30 cycles of 95&#176;C for 15 s, 55&#176;C for 15 s, and 72&#176;C for 15 s, and extension at 72&#176;C for 10 min. The amplified products were observed and sequenced, then were sent to Guangzhou Tian Yihui Gene Technology Co., Ltd. A BLAST search for sequences was carried out via the NCBI website (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>). The phylogenetic trees were established using the Neighbor-joining method in the MEGA 5.1 software package (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Growing Characteristics</title><p>The pH value and NaCl concentration were adjusted based on the NB medium. Before sterilization by autoclaving, the pH was adjusted to the desired values with NaOH (1 mol/L) or HCl (1 mol/L). The target salinity values were obtained by adding NaCl to NB. The isolate cultured in NB was incubated at 28&#176;C with pH value of 3, 5, 7, 9, and 11 to evaluate growth characteristics. Similarly, the growth characteristics of the isolate was evaluated in NB at 28&#176;C with a salinity of 5, 10, 20, 40, and 80 ppt, respectively. All flasks were inoculated with 0.2 mL of bacterial suspension (optical density, OD<sub>600</sub>= 0.1) and cultured at 180 rpm in 96-well plates. Growth was monitored for 23 h by measuring the OD with a micrometer at 600 nm every 1 h.</p></sec><sec><title>Antimicrobial Resistance Test</title><p>The antibiotic resistance of the strain 18BJ181 was determined by the disk diffusion method [K-B method (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>)]. The strain 18BJ181 was cultured in Mueller-Hinton medium and the concentration of the bacterial solution was adjusted to 1 &#215; 10<sup>8</sup> cfu/ml. The suspension was spread on Mueller-Hinton agar containing either trimethoprim, amoxicillin, chloramphenicol, doxycycline, erythromycin, enrofloxacin, florfenicol, furazolidone, gentamicin, madinomycin, neomycin, norfloxacin, oxytetracycline, penicillin, rifampicin or sulfamethoxazole (all purchased from Hangzhou microbial Reagent Co. Ltd). According to the size of the bacteriostatic zone, the results of drug sensitivity were judged by sensitivity, mediating, and drug resistance.</p></sec><sec><title>Virulence Genes Detection</title><p>Conventional PCR assays for the amplification of the aerolysin (<italic toggle="yes">aer</italic>), cytotoxic enterotoxin (<italic toggle="yes">act</italic>), heat-stable enterotoxin (<italic toggle="yes">ast</italic>), glycerophospholipid-cholesterol acyltransferase (<italic toggle="yes">gcaT</italic>), extracellular deoxyribonuclease (<italic toggle="yes">exu</italic>), Type IV pilus (<italic toggle="yes">tapA</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">lip</italic> and flagellin (<italic toggle="yes">fla</italic>) were performed with the template DNA of the strain 18BJ181. Primers used for amplification of the eight genes are shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Each PCR reaction contained 12.5 &#956;l of PCR Mix (Tiangen Biotech, Beijing Co., Ltd., China), 1&#956;l of each paired primer, 1 &#956;l of template DNA, and 9.5 &#956;l of ddH<sub>2</sub>O. The PCR reaction commenced with denaturation at 94&#176;C for 2 min, then 35 cycles of amplification, and finally extension at 72&#176;C for 10 min. Each cycle consisted of denaturation at 94&#176;C for 30 s, annealing for 50 s and extension at 72&#176;C for 30 s (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The amplified PCR products were maintained at 4&#176;C. The results were recorded after electrophoresis on 2% agarose gel stained with ethidium bromide and the positive product of PCR were sent to were sent to Guangzhou Tian Yihui Gene Technology Co., Ltd for analysis and verification (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The information for the eight virulence genes pairs of primers.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Target gene</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Primer sequence (5<sup><bold>&#8242;</bold></sup>-3<sup><bold>&#8242;</bold></sup>)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Product size (bp)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>T<sub><bold>m</bold></sub> (<sup><bold>&#176;</bold></sup>C)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">aer</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: TCTCCATGCTTCCCTTCCACT<break/> R: CCAGTTCCAGTCCCACCACT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">431</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">act</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: AGAAGGTGACCACCACCAAGAACA<break/> R: AACTGACATCGGCCTTGAACTC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ast</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: TCTCCATGCTTCCCTTCCACT<break/> R: GTGTAGGGATTGAAGAAGCCG</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">331</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">gcaT</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: CTCCTGGAATCCCAAGTATCAG<break/> R: GGCAGGTTGAACAGCAGTATCT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">237</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">exu</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: AGACATGCACAACCTCTTCC<break/> R: GATTGGTATTGCCTTGCAAG</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">323</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">tapA</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: ATGACCTCTAGCCCCAATA<break/> R: ACCCGATTGATTTCTGCC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">550</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">lip</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: ATCTTCTCCGACTGGTTCGG<break/> R: CCGTGCCAGGACTGGGTCTT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">382</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">fla</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: TCCAACCGTYTGACCTC<break/> R: GMYTGGTTGCGRATGGT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">608</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Fish Infection Experiments</title><p>The <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> weighing approximately 18 g were cultured in aerated ponds at the Zhuhai experimental base of the South China Sea fisheries Research Institute of the Chinese Academy of Fishery Sciences, Guangzhou, China. The water temperature was controlled at 28 &#177; 1&#176;C. During the temporary feeding period, fish were fed a basal diet of 5% body weight at 7 am and 6 pm every day. After feeding for 15 min, the residual feed was removed to prevent the water from becoming contaminated and fish were temporarily reared for a week. Before the experiment, three fish were randomly selected for visceral bacteriological examination and gill parasite monitoring. <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> was transferred to NB medium at 5% and cultured for 10 h at 28&#176;C and 200 rpm/min. The concentration of bacterial suspension was adjusted to 3.9 &#215; 10<sup>9</sup>, 3.9 &#215; 10<sup>8</sup>, 3.9 &#215; 10<sup>7</sup>, 3.9 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup> and 3.9 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup> cfu/ml, respectively. Three hundred healthy <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> were randomly selected. Eugenol was used to anesthetize the <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> before infection. Intraperitoneal injection and intramuscular injection was carried out using 0.1 ml of the above different concentrations of the bacterial suspension. The control group received an intraperitoneal injection and intramuscular injection of an equal volume of 0.85% normal saline. Bacteria from the liver, spleen, and ascites fluid of experimentally infected fish were re-isolated. All protocols for experiments involving live animals conducted in this study were approved by the Animal Care and Use Committee of Zhongkai University of Agriculture and Engineering, Guangzhou, China.</p></sec><sec><title>Histopathological Examination</title><p>Heart, liver, kidney and spleen tissue from the moribund fish after infection were fixed in 10% buffered formalin solution, dehydrated in ethanol, embedded in paraffin wax blocks and sectioned, then stained with hematoxylin and eosin for histopathological observation.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Clinical Symptoms of Naturally Infected Fish</title><p>The <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> naturally infected with <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> typically show acute death in aquaculture conditions. After 2&#8211;3 days of infection, fish begin to swim slowly leading to high mortality (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>). Some diseased fish exhibit large areas of ulceration on the body surface, limited to the surface of the skin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>). After dissecting the fish, it was found that there were mild ascites in the abdomen. Hemorrhage of internal organs and intestinal inflammation were often observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref>). Some fish showed typical clinical lesions, as well as swelling and hemorrhage of the kidney (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1D</xref>), ischemia and hemorrhage in the liver, and darkening of the spleen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1E</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Clinical symptoms of natural or artificial infection of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">Lateolabrax maculatus</italic>. Acute death of <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> in fish farms <bold>(A)</bold>. Obvious clinical symptoms of natural infection with <italic toggle="yes">A.veronii</italic> in diseased <italic toggle="yes">L.maculatus</italic>, such as ulceration on the body surface (solid arrow) <bold>(B)</bold>, hemorrhages in internal organs (solid arrows) and intestinal inflammation (hollow arrows) <bold>(C)</bold>, hemorrhage and swelling of the kidney (solid arrows) <bold>(D)</bold>, liver with both ischemia (black box), hemorrhage (solid arrow) and darkened spleen (hollow arrows) <bold>(E)</bold>. Clinical symptoms of <italic toggle="yes">L.maculatus</italic> artificially infected with <italic toggle="yes">A.veronii</italic>: the anal fin is slightly inflamed (solid arrow) <bold>(F)</bold>, slightly darkened spleen (black box), congestion in the abdominal wall and liver (hollow arrows), and hemorrhage and swelling in the kidney (solid arrows) <bold>(G)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-07-600587-g0001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Physiological and Biochemical Characteristics of the Bacteria</title><p>The strain 18BJ181 is a typical gram-negative bacterium isolated directly from diseased <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic>. Physiological and biochemical results in this study showed that 16 biochemical reactions of the strain 18BJ181 were positive, such as Ala-Phe-Pro arylamidase, L-Proline arylamidase, and sucrose, while 22 biochemical reactions were negative, such as H<sub>2</sub>S production and &#946;-glucuronidase in a total of 38 biochemical reactions (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). This species strain is distinguishable from the other three <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> species [<italic toggle="yes">A. veronii bv. veronii, A. hydrophila</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">A. caviae</italic>, (16]]. Due to the complexity of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> members and the limited number of biochemical reactions of Vitek 2, the test identified these isolates as <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> species (probability &gt; 99%), but failed to correctly differentiate them to the species level.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Biochemical characterization of the strain 18BJ181 from naturally infected <italic toggle="yes">Lateolabrax maculatus</italic> in GuangDong province using Vitek 2 compact.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Characteristics</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>18BJ181</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> ATCC9071</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila</italic> CGMCC1.2017</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas caviae</italic> CGMCC1.1960</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ala-Phe-Pro arylamidase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H<sub>2</sub>S production</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#946;-glucoronidase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Proline arylamidase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sucrose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Lactate alkalinization</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycine arylamidase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">O/129 resistance</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#946;-Galactosidase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D-Maltose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lipase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ornithine decarboxylase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glu-Gly-Arg-arylamidase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D-Mannitol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D-Trehalose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Succinate alkalinisation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Malate assimilation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D-Glucose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D-Mannose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tyrosine arylamidase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Citrate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#946;-N-Acetyl-glucosaminidase</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ellman</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D-Cellobiose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Courmarate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Lactate alkalinization</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">The results of 12 biochemical reactions including adonitol, D-tagatose, L-pyrrolydonyl-arylamidase, glutamyl arylamidase pNA, lysine decarboxylase, L-arabitol, L-histidine assimilation, &#947;-glutamyl-transferase, &#946;-xylosidase, urease, malonate and &#945;-glucosidase of the strain 18BJ181 and reference Aeromonas were all negative (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>)</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Phylogenetic Analyses of the 16S rRNA and <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic> Genes</title><p>The gene sequences of different <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> were downloaded from the NCBI database and a phylogenetic tree was constructed. The 16S rRNA gene sequence of the strain 18BJ181 was 1,445 bp in length. The BLAST alignments showed that it was most similar to strain <italic toggle="yes">A. vernoii</italic> XG3-1-1 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MF716697.1">MF716697.1</ext-link>). The <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic> gene sequence of the strain 18BJ181 was 1,045 bp in length. The BLAST alignments showed that it was most similar to strain <italic toggle="yes">A. vernoii</italic> CB51 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="CP015448.1">CP015448.1</ext-link>). Identities were approximately 99.81%. In addition, the results showed that the strain 18BJ181 was grouped with a cluster of known species of <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> strains according to phylogenetic trees established on the 16S rRNA sequence and <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic> sequence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Based on biochemical tests and phylogenesis through 16S rRNA and <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic> genes, the strain 18BJ181 was determined to be a member of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic>.</p><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Neighbor-Joining phylogenetic tree generated based on 16S rRNA <bold>(A)</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic>
<bold>(B)</bold> gene sequences of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> isolates detected in the present study and the other <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> spp. from Genbank. <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> was used as an outgroup species. Bootstrap values out of 1,000 repetitions were indicated above each branch.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-07-600587-g0002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Growth Characteristics of the Strain 18BJ181</title><p>Growth characteristics of the strain 18BJ181 were tested (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>, growth was similar at salinity concentrations of 5, 10, 20, and 40 ppt. Growth was improved at 20 and 40 ppt and significantly inhibited at a salinity of 80 ppt. In terms of pH, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>, the growth of this isolate was maximal at an optimum of pH 7. The latent phase of growth was somewhat extended at pH 11 and growth capacity was reduced. At pH 7 and 9, the growth of the strain 18BJ181 showed that trends were similar, and considerable final concentrations were obtained. Growth was halted at pH 3.</p><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Growing characteristics of the strain 18BJ181. Growth under the conditions of different salinity <bold>(A)</bold>, different pH <bold>(B)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-07-600587-g0003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Drug Sensitivity</title><p>The drug sensitivity results indicated that the strain 18BJ181 showed different sensitivities to 16 antibacterial drugs. Strain 18BJ181 was sensitive to 10 antibacterial drugs such as sulfamethoxazole, trimethoprim, and chloramphenicol, showed moderate sensitivity to erythromycin and rifampicin, and was resistant to amoxicillin, madinomycin, penicillin and sulfamethoxazole (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Antibiotic sensitivity of the strain 18BJ181.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Antibiotics</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Content (ug/disc)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sensitivity</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sulfamethoxazole and Trimethoprim</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amoxicillin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloramphenicol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Doxycycline</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Erythromycin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enrofloxacin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Florfenicol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Furazolidone</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gentamicin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Madinomycin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neomycin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Norfloxacin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxytetracycline</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Penicillin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rifampicin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sulfamethoxazole</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><p><italic toggle="yes">S, sensitive, M, moderately susceptible, R, resistant</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Virulence Factors</title><p>The PCR profiles of eight virulence genes screened in this study showed that five genes (<italic toggle="yes">aer, act, gcaT</italic>, tap<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">fla</italic>) was present in the strain 18BJ181 isolate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>).</p><fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Agarose gel electrophoresis of eight virulent genes (<italic toggle="yes">aer, act</italic>, ast, <italic toggle="yes">gcaT, exu, tapA, lip</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">fla</italic>) were present in the strain 18BJ181.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-07-600587-g0004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Experimental Infections</title><p><italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> can be infected successfully by intraperitoneal injection and intramuscular injection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). The results showed that mortality of <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> occurred within 24 h, and the number of deaths decreased significantly within a 48 h period. When the concentration of intraperitoneal injection and intramuscular injection was 2.2 &#215; 10<sup>7</sup> cfu/g, the mortality rate of the fish reached 100%. When the infection concentration was 2.2 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup> cfu/g, the mortality rate for intraperitoneal injection and intramuscular injection was 83.3 and 87.5%, respectively. Using an infection concentration of 2.2 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup> cfu/g, the mortality rate for intraperitoneal injection and intramuscular injection was 4 and 25%, respectively. When the infection concentrations were 2.2 &#215; 10<sup>4</sup> cfu/g and 2.2 &#215; 10<sup>3</sup> cfu/g, respectively, fish with intraperitoneal injection did not die and the mortality rate of fish infected by intramuscular injection was also very low, no more than 5%. The median lethal dosage (LD<sub>50</sub>) through intraperitoneal injection and intramuscular injection was calculated by Karber's method as 8.5 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup> and 4.2 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup> cfu/g, respectively.</p><fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>The cumulative mortality of <italic toggle="yes">Lateolabrax maculatus</italic> from different infection routes of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> in 10 days.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-07-600587-g0005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Pathological Analysis of Artificially Infected Fish</title><p>There were no obvious lesions on the body surface of <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> that were artificially infected with the strain 18BJ181 isolate. The predominant symptoms were redness and swelling of the anal fin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1F</xref>). After dissection of the infected fish, it was observed that the ascites fluid in the abdominal cavity increased significantly. The abdominal wall and liver were congested. Kidney enlargement and hemorrhage were observed, and the spleen became darker in color (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1G</xref>).</p><p>The histopathology of <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> infected by intraperitoneal injection of <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> was as follows: cardiomyocyte vacuolization with myofibrillar degeneration was observed in the heart (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6A</xref>), the liver showed different levels of hepatocellular steatosis, congestion, and hemorrhage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6C</xref>), the renal tubular epithelial lining was severely necrotic, and detached from the basement membrane, and interstitial tissue hemorrhage was evident (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6E</xref>), and moderate splenitis was observed with numerous lymphocytes and macrophages aggregated around ellipsoids, in addition to an accumulation of a proteinaceous substance accumulated in the spleen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6G</xref>). The histopathological changes of <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> infected by intramuscular injection were as follows: myocardial hemorrhage with myofibrillar edema, rupture, and necrosis was observed in the heart (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6B</xref>), the liver had histopathological changes such as hepatocellular steatosis, congestion, and inflammation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6D</xref>), necrosis and desquamation of the renal tubular epithelial lining and interstitial tissue hemorrhage were relatively mild in the kidney (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6F</xref>), and the spleen showed pathological changes such as splenitis with diffuse fibrinoid necrosis of ellipsoids, aggregation of inflammatory cells, and accumulation of hemozoin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6H</xref>).</p><fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Histopathological changes of <italic toggle="yes">Lateolabrax maculatus</italic> with artificial infection of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> (<bold>A,C,E,G</bold>: intraperitoneal injection, <bold>B,D,F,H</bold>: intramuscular injection). Cardiomyocyte vacuolization (solid arrows) with myofibrillar degeneration (rectangular) <bold>(A)</bold> and myocardial hemorrhage (rectangular) with myofibrillar edema (ovals), rupture (solid arrows) and necrosis (hollow arrows) <bold>(B)</bold>. Hepatocellular steatosis (solid arrows), congestion (ovals), hemorrhage (rectangular), and inflammation (hollow arrows) in the liver <bold>(C,D)</bold>. Kidney with marked necrosis and desquamation of the renal tubular epithelial lining leaving the basement membrane (solid arrows) notice the hemorrhage in the interstitial tissue (rectangular) <bold>(E,F)</bold>. Moderate splenitis with numerous lymphocytes and macrophages aggregated around ellipsoids (ovals) in addition to an accumulation of proteinaceous substance (rectangular) <bold>(G)</bold>. Splenitis with diffuse fibrinoid necrosis of ellipsoids (rectangular), aggregation of inflammatory cells (ovals), and hemozoin accumulation (solid arrows) <bold>(H)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-07-600587-g0006.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p><italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> is widely distributed and can be isolated from diseased aquatic animals and aquatic environments (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) in various countries such as Poland (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), Mexico (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>), and Japan (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). The pathogen can cause human biliary sepsis and diarrhea in clinical practice (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). The physiological and biochemical characteristics of the strain 18BJ181, such as L-Proline arylamidase, &#946;-Galactosidase and O/129 resistance, were positive with <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> ATCC9071. Due to the wide variety of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> species and the limited number of reactions of Vitek 2, the molecular method is required to distinguish the species level of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). 16S rRNA is one of the most commonly used molecular biological detection methods for identifying bacteria (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) and the <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic> gene has certain advantages for the identification of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> species (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). In this study, BLAST alignments showed that both 16S rRNA and <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic> gene sequences of the strain 18BJ181 shared the highest identities with those of other known <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> strains. The phylogenetic trees built based on the sequences of the two genes showed the strain 18BJ181 clustered with <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> strains. For the identification of <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic>, it is important to use multiple molecular markers for phylogenetic analysis. If this is not possible, another approach is to conduct genomic sequence analysis for a specific strain, then combine them with epidemiological evidence for a more comprehensive analysis. Using these methods, it is possible to provide new insights into the complex evolutionary history of <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic>.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> has a variety of hosts and can live in aquatic animals and in the environment, which may bring harm to aquaculture in the future. Bacterial resistance to antibiotics affects the health of animals, the environment, and humans (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Previous research results showed that <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> was resistant to antibacterial drugs, including ampicillin, amoxicillin and oxacillin (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). In this study, we confirmed part of these results, specifically that strain 18BJ181 is resistant to amoxicillin and penicillin. Over time, <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> has developed a certain resistance to sulfamethoxazole. The results of drug sensitivity testing on the strain 18BJ181 isolate in this study provides a reference for when antimicrobials may be a potential treatment for <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic>.</p><p>The pathogenicity of <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> is related to the expression of virulence factors (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Aer</italic> is a cytotoxic pore-forming enterotoxin, which is one of the most important and abundant virulence factors of <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic>. Isolates from all tissue necrosis and ulcerations in fish of <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> induced aeromonas septicemia and bacterial haemorrhagic septicemia were positive for the <italic toggle="yes">aer</italic> gene. The <italic toggle="yes">aer</italic>-positive isolates from crap fish and catfish were 52.9% and 82.4%, respectively. Fish injected with <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> exhibited significantly higher mortality than carp fish [<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>)]. Using an infection route via intestine, a comparison of <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> strain Hm091 with <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic> showed that different expression and activity of the <italic toggle="yes">aer</italic> gene was the key factor that caused the difference in virulence between the two species (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). We detected the <italic toggle="yes">aer</italic> gene from <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic>, which may have indicate a connection with its strong pathogenicity. <italic toggle="yes">Act</italic> gene plays an important role in <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic> and can significantly reduce capacity to evoke fluid secretion (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Glycerophospholipid-cholesterol acyltransferase and lipases paly a common role in the pathogenicity of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> spp and, together, are secreted into the environment through the secretion system (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">TapA</italic> of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas salmonicida</italic> participates in the process of infecting Atlantic salmon (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">fla</italic> is involved in the formation of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> spp biofilms and has potential pathogenicity (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). In this study, virulence genes <italic toggle="yes">aer, act, gcaT, tap</italic>A and <italic toggle="yes">fla</italic> were detected from strain 18BJ181, but the more complex mechanism of toxicity action of <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> still needs to be further explored.</p><p>In this study, the time of death of <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> was concentrated within 24 h after <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> was infected by <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> infection. This finding is consistent with the death of <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> infection in <italic toggle="yes">Carassius auratus gibelio</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Xiphophorus helleri</italic> (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). This suggests that the rapid death of the host will accelerate the spread of the disease. The LD<sub>50</sub> in the intramuscular injection group was slightly lower than in the intraperitoneal injection group, but the mortality of both showed a &#8220;cliff&#8221; decline. <italic toggle="yes">Z</italic>ebrafish is also a susceptible host of <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic>. It has been found that this fish can be successfully infected with <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> through different infection routes (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Likewise, <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic> showed muscle liquefaction and furuncle lesions in infected rainbow trout (<italic toggle="yes">Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>) after intramuscular injection (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). The difference in the expression and activity of the <italic toggle="yes">aer</italic> gene between <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic> resulted in <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> being slightly more virulent than <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic>, and this in turn activates the activity of the <italic toggle="yes">aer</italic> gene and functions in enhancing the adhesion ability of bacteria in host cells (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). In addition, the quorum-sensing system plays a key role in the infection of <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> and is a major metabolic regulator in <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> and participating in sturgeon spoilage (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). This is related to the quorum-sensing system of <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">A. hydrophila</italic> in regulating virulence in catfish (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). The virulence regulation effect of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> on burbot (<italic toggle="yes">Lota Lota</italic>) was also regulated by quorum sensing (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). N-acyl homoserine lactone (AHL) mediated by the quorum-sensing mechanisms may be involved in regulating the type VI secretion system (T6SS), metalloprotease production, biofilm formation, and virulence of <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). As previously reported, AHL molecules are not only involved in bacterial virulence regulation but also interact with several eukaryotic cells and play function in the immuno-modulation of the host response in <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). However, the exact mechanism of action is unclear. <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> infected with <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> died acutely in a short period of time and correlated with the concentration of infection. This indicates that it may be closely related to the quorum-sensing system, but the details still need to be further studied.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> can cause an infection characterized by septicemia and spread within 1 hpi through the organs, affecting irreversible lesions to the liver, kidney and spleen. The pathogen was detected in the spleen at 3 hpi, and the greatest amounts of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> and lesions were observed at 6 and 9 hpi in all evaluated organs (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> infection of fish also cause skin ulcers, intra-abdominal hemorrhage, and other clinical symptoms. Interestingly, there are a variety of symptoms caused by different types of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> infections (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). For example, the clinical signs of bacterial septicemia in catfish caused by <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> were pale gills, slight abdominal distension, and swollen and inflamed vents (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). When <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> infect Sheatfish, petechial skin hemorrhages appear, as well as ascitic distension of the abdomen, redness, and swelling of the anus (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> can cause histopathological changes such as hemorrhage, congestion, and ulcers in different organs (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Some cases of <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> infected fish showed degenerative histopathological changes such as cellular vacuolation, intravascular congestion, and cell necrosis (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). In this study, the histopathological results were similar to those of previous studies. For example, in some internal organs there were histopathological changes, especially the necrosis of the renal tubular epithelial lining and interstitial tissue hemorrhage. These symptoms provided direct evidence of the cause of death in <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic>.</p><p>In conclusion, this is the first study to report a case of <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> infection in <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> in China. Clinical symptoms of naturally infected fish were acute death, ulceration on the body surface, congestion, and hemorrhages in internal organs. <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> is resistant to amoxicillin, madinomycin, and other antimicrobial agents and is suitable for survival in the environment. Using artificial infection, <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> can infect <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic> through intraperitoneal injection and intramuscular injection, causing abdominal hemorrhage and congestion, as well as pathological damage to the heart, liver, kidney, and spleen including degeneration, necrosis, and hemorrhage. As a newly reported bacterial disease in <italic toggle="yes">L. maculatus</italic>, this report sheds new light on understanding the characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> regarding host pathogenicity. Further epidemiological investigation and retrospective studies are needed, as well as further exploration of the relationship between pathogenic bacteria and the host.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s5"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The datasets presented in this study can be found in online repositories. The names of the repository/repositories and accession number(s) can be found in the GenBank: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="MW362188">MW362188</ext-link> for <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> strain 18BJ181 16S ribosomal RNA gene and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MW371213">MW371213</ext-link> for <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> strain 18BJ181 <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic> gene partial cds, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by the Animal Care and Use Committee of Zhongkai University of Agriculture and Engineering.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>YS and BW conceived and designed as well as analyzed the experiments. BW performed all the experiments and wrote the paper. CM completed the Antimicrobial resistance test. JH, YL, and QG assisted in laboratory experiments and data analysis. JF, BJ, and YS participated in discussions and revisions and critically examines the final uploaded manuscripts. All authors read and agreed to the final version of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work was supported by grants from the Central Public-interest Scientific Institution Basal Research Fund, South China Sea Fisheries Research Institute, CAFS (2018ZD01) and the Key Project of Department of Education of Guangdong Province (2019KZDXM043).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Bravo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fort-Gallifa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ballester</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pujol</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez-Bertomeu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dominguez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A case of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas trota</italic> in an immunocompromised patient with diarrhea</article-title>. <source>Microorganisms.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>399</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms8030399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32178464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7143958</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shameena</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rathore</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Virulence characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii biovars</italic> isolated from infected freshwater goldfish (<italic toggle="yes">Carassius auratus</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Aquaculture.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>518</volume>:<fpage>734819</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquaculture.2019.734819</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El Latif</surname><given-names>AMA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elabd</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eldeen</surname><given-names>AIN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaheen</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High mortalities caused by <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic>:identification, pathogenicity, and histopathologicalstudies in <italic toggle="yes">Oreochromis niloticus</italic></article-title>. <source>Aquaculture Int</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1725</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>37</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10499-019-00429-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jian</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of pathogenic Aeromonas veronii bv. <italic toggle="yes">Veronii</italic> associated with ulcerative syndrome from chinese longsnout catfish (<italic toggle="yes">Leiocassis longirostris Gunther</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Braz J Microbiol.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>382</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1517-838220120001000046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24031843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3768999</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nawaz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerdahi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Detection and characterization of virulence genes and integrons in <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> isolated from catfish</article-title>. <source>Food Microbiol.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>327</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2009.11.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20227596</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoai</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trang</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Tuyen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giang</surname><given-names>NTH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Van</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> caused disease and mortality in channel catfish in Vietnam</article-title>. <source>Aquaculture.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>513</volume>:<fpage>734425</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquaculture.2019.734425</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zepeda-Vel&#225;zquez</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vega-S&#225;nchez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salgado-Miranda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soriano-Vargas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Histopathological findings in farmed rainbow trout (<italic toggle="yes">Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>) naturally infected with 3 different <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> species</article-title>. <source>Can J Vet Res.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>79</volume>:<fpage>250</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26130859</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4445519</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ran</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> and aerolysin are important for the pathogenesis of motile aeromonad septicemia in cyprinid fish</article-title>. <source>Environ Microbiol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>3442</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1462-2920.14390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30136361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of apolipoprotein multigene family in spotted sea bass (<italic toggle="yes">Lateolabrax maculatus</italic>) and their expression profiles in response to <italic toggle="yes">Vibrio harveyi</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>Fish Shellfish Immunol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fsi.2019.06.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31176005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Vibrio harveyi</italic>: a significant pathogen of marine vertebrates and invertebrates</article-title>. <source>Lett Appl Microbiol.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>119</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1472-765X.2006.01989.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16869892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular cloning and expression analysis of five heat shock protein 70 (HSP70) family members in <italic toggle="yes">Lateolabrax maculatus</italic> with <italic toggle="yes">Vibrio harveyi</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>Fish Shellfish Immunol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>60</volume>:<fpage>299</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>310</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fsi.2016.11.056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27908666</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Isolation, identification and characterization of <italic toggle="yes">Shewanella algae</italic> from reared tongue sole, <italic toggle="yes">Cynoglossus semilaevis</italic> G&#252;nther</article-title>. <source>Aquaculture.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>468</volume>:<fpage>356</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquaculture.2016.10.038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pate</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tenover</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turnidge</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Susceptibility test methods: dilution and disk diffusion methods</article-title>. In: <source>Manual of Clinical Microbiology</source>. (<year>2011</year>). p. <fpage>1122</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/9781555816728.ch68</pub-id>827239</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution characteristics and virulence gene analysis of intestinal and extraintestinal <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic></article-title>. <source>Chin J Clin Lab Sci</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>503</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.13602/j.cnki.jcls.2017.07.06</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xian</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Isolation, identification and characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> from diseased crucian carp (<italic toggle="yes">Carassius auratus gibelio</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>2742</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.02742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32038507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6988821</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>First case of soft shell disease in Chinese soft-shelled turtle (<italic toggle="yes">Trionyx sinens</italic>) associated with <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas sobria</italic>&#8211;<italic toggle="yes">A. veronii</italic> complex</article-title>. <source>Aquaculture.</source> (<year>2013</year>) 406&#8211;<volume>407</volume>:<fpage>62</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquaculture.2013.05.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lye</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Gastrointestinal colonization rates for human clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> using a mouse model</article-title>. <source>Curr Microbiol.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>332</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00284-011-9982-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21779939</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kovalerchick</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lieman-Hurwitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murik</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Philippis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carmeli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Increased algicidal activity of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> in response to <italic toggle="yes">Microcystis aeruginosa</italic>: interspecies crosstalk and secondary metabolites synergism</article-title>. <source>Environ Microbiol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1140</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1462-2920.14561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30761715</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kovalerchick</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murik</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sukenik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carmeli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Secondary metabolites of <italic toggle="yes">aeromonas veronii</italic> strain a134 isolated from a <italic toggle="yes">microcystis aeruginosa</italic> bloom</article-title>. <source>Metabolites.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>110</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/metabo9060110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31181869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6631032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dworaczek</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drzewiecka</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pekala-Safinska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turska-Szewczuk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Structural and serological studies of the O6-related antigen of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> bv. <italic toggle="yes">sobria</italic> strain K557 isolated from <italic toggle="yes">Cyprinus carpio</italic> on a polish fish farm, which contains L-perosamine (4-amino-4,6-dideoxy-L-mannose), a unique sugar characteristic for <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> serogroup O6</article-title>. <source>Mar Drugs.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>399</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/md17070399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31284525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6669630</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reyes-Becerril</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerra</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Velazquez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ascencio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Caspase&#8722;1,&#8722;3,&#8722;8 and antioxidant enzyme genes are key molecular effectors following <italic toggle="yes">Vibrio parahaemolyticus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> infection in fish leukocytes</article-title>. <source>Immunobiology.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>223</volume>:<fpage>562</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.imbio.2018.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30001906</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De</surname><given-names>SJSS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Honein</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arulkanthan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ushio</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asakawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Genome sequencing and annotation of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> strain Ae52, a multidrug-resistant isolate from septicaemic gold fish (<italic toggle="yes">Carassius auratus</italic>) in Sri Lanka</article-title>. <source>Genom Data.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>46</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gdata.2016.11.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27942459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5137324</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ottaviani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leoni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocchegiani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santarelli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Annibale</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A severe case of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> biovar sobria travellers' diarrhoea characterized by <italic toggle="yes">Vibrio parahaemolyticus</italic> co-isolation</article-title>. <source>Med Microbiol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>62</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.044743-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23002063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amadori</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartolini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casadei</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii biovar</italic> veronii and sepsis-infrequent complication of biliary drainage placement: a case report</article-title>. <source>World J Clin Cases.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>759</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12998/wjcc.v7.i6.759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30968041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6448070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Busse</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Denner</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lubitz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Classification and identification of bacteria: current approaches to an old problem. Overview of methods used in bacterial systematics</article-title>. <source>Biotechnology.</source> (<year>1996</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>38</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0168-1656(96)01379-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8782421</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gasteiger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bairoch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isono</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Construction of the <italic toggle="yes">gyrB</italic> database for the identification and classification of bacteria</article-title>. <source>Genome Inform Int Conference on Genome Inform.</source> (<year>1998</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11234/gi1990.9.13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11072317</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and distribution of antibiotic resistance in marine fish farming areas in Hainan, China</article-title>. <source>Sci Total Environ.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>653</volume>:<fpage>605</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.10.251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30414589</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nawaz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Biochemical and molecular characterization of tetracycline-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> isolates from catfish</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>72</volume>:<fpage>6461</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00271-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17021193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1610303</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chenia</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of integrons and tetracycline resistance determinants in <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> spp. isolated from South African aquaculture systems</article-title>. <source>Int J Food Microbiol.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>114</volume>:<fpage>295</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>306</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2006.09.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17173998</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koksal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oguzkurt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samasti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Altas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and antimicrobial resistance patterns of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> strains isolated from drinking water samples in istanbul, Turkey</article-title>. <source>Chemotherapy.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>30</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000098248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17191011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhixiu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xinhua</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shunzhou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bei</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huihong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation, identification and <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> antimicrobial susceptibility of pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">aeromonas veronii</italic> from soft-shelled turtles</article-title>. <source>Agric Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>804</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.16175/j.cnki.1009-4229.2016.04.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>YuanHuan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Research advances of virulence factors in <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> veronii</article-title>. <source>Chin Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>1038</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.16656/j.issn.1673-4696.2018.0152</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foysal</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Momtaz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siddik</surname><given-names>MAB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaklader</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular characterization and interactome analysis of aerolysin (<italic toggle="yes">aer</italic>) gene from fish pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic>: The pathogenicity inferred from sequence divergence and linked to histidine kinase (cheA)</article-title>. <source>J Fish Dis.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>465</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>75</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jfd.12954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30734315</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozlova</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chopra</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Role of various enterotoxins in <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila</italic>-induced gastroenteritis: generation of enterotoxin gene-deficient mutants and evaluation of their enterotoxic activity</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>1924</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/iai.70.4.1924-1935.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11895956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC127858</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Glycerophospholipid:cholesterol acyltransferase complexed with lipopolysaccharide (LPS) is a major lethal exotoxin and cytolysin of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas salmonicida</italic>: LPS stabilizes and enhances toxicity of the enzyme</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol.</source> (<year>1990</year>) <volume>172</volume>:<fpage>5382</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2394687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1128/jb.172.9.5382-5393.1990</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC213203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dacanay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knickle</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Touhami</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jericho</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Contribution of Type IV Pili to the Virulence of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas salmonicida</italic> subsp</article-title>. <source>salmonicida in Atlantic Salmon (Salmo salar L). Infect Immun.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>76</volume>:<fpage>1445</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/iai.01019-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18212071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2292863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freire</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magalh&#227;es</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunes Soares</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Costa</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gouveia</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nutritional interference for phenotypic biofilm quantification in <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> spp. isolates containing the fla gene</article-title>. <source>Microb Pathog.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>127</volume>:<fpage>198</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>201</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2018.11.044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30500410</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aswani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jasim</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sebastian</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Radhakrishnan</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Distribution of multi-virulence factors among <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> spp. isolated from diseased <italic toggle="yes">Xiphophorus hellerii</italic></article-title>. <source>Aquac Int</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>235</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>48</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10499-019-00456-5</pub-id>33144215</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orozova</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and pathogenicity to rainbow trout, <italic toggle="yes">Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic> (Walbaum), of some aeromonads</article-title>. <source>J Fish Dis.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>865</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2761.2009.01065.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19602093</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Talagrand-Reboul</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jumas-Bilak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The social life of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas</italic> through biofilm and quorum sensing systems</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.00037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28163702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5247445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tekedar</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumru</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelhamed</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative genomics of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic>: identification of a pathotype impacting aquaculture globally</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>e0221018</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0221018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31465454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6715197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Natrah</surname><given-names>FMI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pawar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harzevili</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nevejan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The impact of quorum sensing on the virulence of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas salmonicida</italic> towards burbot (<italic toggle="yes">Lota lota</italic> L</article-title>.) larvae. <source>Vet Microbiol.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>159</volume>:<fpage>77</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2012.03.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22465799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khajanchi</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kozlova</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erova</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suarez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sierra</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>N-acylhomoserine lactones involved in quorum sensing control the type VI secretion system, biofilm formation, protease production, and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> virulence in a clinical isolate of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila</italic></article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>155</volume>:<fpage>3518</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mic.0.031575-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19729404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2888131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulation of host biology by <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> quorum sensing signal molecules: messengers or traitors</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1226</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2015.01226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26617576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4637427</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marinho-Neto</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Claudiano</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yunis-Aguinaga</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cueva-Quiroz</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobashigawa</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz</surname><given-names>NRN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Morphological, microbiological and ultrastructural aspects of sepsis by <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas hydrophila</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">Piaractus mesopotamicus</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>e0222626</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222626</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31539396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6754153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peatman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Winter kill in intensively stocked channel catfish (<italic toggle="yes">Ictalurus punctatus</italic>): coinfection with <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii, Streptococcus parauberis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Shewanella putrefaciens</italic></article-title>. <source>J Fish Dis</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>1339</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>47</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jfd.12827</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29882217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiucai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiaoxue</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aijun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jingfeng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yajiao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization and pathology of <italic toggle="yes">Aeromonas veronii</italic> biovar sobria from diseased sheatfish <italic toggle="yes">Silurus glanis</italic> in China</article-title>. <source>Isr J Aquacult-Bamid.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>71</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage> Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hdl.handle.net/10524/61076">http://hdl.handle.net/10524/61076</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>