<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="systematic-review" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7755596</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7755596.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7755596</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7755596</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33363233</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2020.584162</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Systematic Review</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Floor Substrate Preferences of Chickens: A Meta-Analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monckton</surname><given-names initials="V">Valerie</given-names></name><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1027719/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names initials="JL">Jennifer L.</given-names></name><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1079198/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harlander-Matauschek</surname><given-names initials="A">Alexandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/483406/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff><institution>Department of Animal Biosciences, University of Guelph</institution>, <addr-line>Guelph, ON</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Paul Koene, Wageningen University and Research, Netherlands</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Manja Zupan &#352;emrov, University of Ljubljana, Slovenia; Lisette M. C. Leliveld, Leibniz Institute for Farm Animal Biology (FBN), Germany</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Alexandra Harlander-Matauschek <email>aharland@uoguelph.ca</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Animal Behavior and Welfare, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">351216</issue-id><elocation-id>584162</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>7</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>24</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-03-29 17:25:12.070"><day>29</day><month>03</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2020 Monckton, Ellis and Harlander-Matauschek.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Monckton, Ellis and Harlander-Matauschek</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-07-584162.pdf"/><abstract><p>Environmental enrichment promotes sensory and motor stimulation for species-typical behaviors, which in turn enhance animal well-being. For farmed Galliformes, housing systems often limit enrichment to bedding and litter, that simultaneously act as material for dustbathing and foraging. Therefore, this meta-analysis sought to systematically review and synthesize the substrate preference test literature for Galliformes. Data based on the following four welfare-related behaviors were extracted for analysis: (1) dustbathing, (2) foraging, (3) pecking, and (4) time spent on a given substrate. Literature searches in CAB Direct, Web of Science, and Google Scholar yielded 239 articles, and hand searching yielded an additional five articles. Ten publications that used different chicken strains as test subjects, met the criteria to be included in the systematic review. The effects of bedding type, the number of days birds had access to tested substrates, enclosure area, and substrate area, on the examined behaviors were determined. We found that birds preferred dustbathing in sand and peat moss more than on any other substrates. The bedding type, size of the enclosure, and size of the substrate area affected the amount of time that birds spent on the tested substrates. When provided the choice between bedding materials, birds spent more time on sand or peat moss than on any other substrate or on no substrate. Notably, most studies did not report relevant physical or chemical characteristics of substrate that may influence birds' preferences, such as grain size, moisture content and the level of soiling. Focusing future studies on identifying substrate characteristics that influence preferences can lead to the discovery of new, practical, enriching beddings that can be easily implemented in housing systems for Galliformes.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>dustbathing</kwd><kwd>foraging</kwd><kwd>bedding</kwd><kwd>litter</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Gallus gallus domesticus</italic></kwd><kwd>Galliformes</kwd><kwd>pecking</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100000038</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn001">04985</award-id><award-id rid="cn001">400983</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002">University of Guelph<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/100008986</named-content></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="4"/><equation-count count="4"/><ref-count count="66"/><page-count count="11"/><word-count count="7909"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Galliformes encompass the largest group of farmed land animals, with chickens alone numbering 23.7 billion in 2018 (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). While many factors affect Galliformes' welfare, bedding is often overlooked and chosen principally based on price and regional availability (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), although other factors such as labor requirements, wear and tear on equipment, cost, accessibility, sustainability, and manure handling and storage may impact bedding choice as well. Yet, while bedding may vary globally, many farmers in Canada and the United States use wood shavings (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Choice of bedding has been shown to impact many aspects of health and welfare, including the air the birds (and farmers) breathe and the incidence of disease (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Moreover, bedding can act as environmental enrichment&#8212;by enhancing &#8220;animal welfare through sensory and motor stimulation, using structures and resources that permit the expression of species-typical behaviors and promote psychological well-being through physical exercise, manipulative activities, and cognitive challenges according to species-specific characteristics&#8221; (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). As a substrate for foraging and dustbathing, bedding can increase Galliformes' behavioral repertoire, and reduce frustrated behaviors. For example, select beddings can reduce the incidence of injurious feather pecking, a repetitive and undesirable behavior common in many breeds of farmed Galliformes (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p><p>Commercial farms commonly use bedding in cage-free systems to absorb moisture from drinkers and birds' excreta, while cage systems may provide bedding in small areas as enrichment for birds to dustbathe and forage in, or beneath cages to absorb moisture from fallen excreta. Whether its primary purpose is moisture absorption or enrichment, bedding is invariably used to both regulate the barn environment and provide environmental enrichment.</p><p>To serve both these purposes well, good bedding must first efficiently absorb moisture quickly and facilitate its rapid evaporation, preventing moisture buildup that increases the incidence of disease. Indeed, high bedding moisture has been linked to higher rates of contact dermatitis, respiratory disease, and keratoconjunctivitis (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Moreover, a study by Drake et al. (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) found that the use of bell drinkers (open water) were a risk factor for the development of feather pecking in laying hens, thereby suggesting that moist and caked litter may contribute to adverse health conditions that could spur undesirable behaviors. However, like feather pecking, wet litter substrate is also less loose (friable) and more prone to caking, which makes it an inferior substrate for dustbathing.</p><p>Galliformes are motivated to dustbathe (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), and will even dustbathe without substrate present (sham dustbathing) (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Behavioral elements of dustbathing including vertical wing shaking, bill raking and head rubbing, with the goal of incorporating substrate throughout Galliformes' plumage (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). In so doing, it allows birds to remove stale lipids from their feathers (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) and dislodge ectoparasites (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Furthermore, poor or absent dustbathing substrate can lead Galliformes to become more fearful, leading to higher incidences of feather pecking (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p><p>A combination of pecking and scratching, foraging occupies about 40% of chickens' daylight hours (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). While foraging is used by wild Galliformes as an appetitive behavior to find food, Galliformes will forage even in the presence of readily available feed, suggesting that the behavior itself is motivating (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Consequently, Galliformes' frustrated motivation to forage is strongly related to severe, injurious feather pecking of conspecifics (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>), while the provision of high quality pecking substrates is suggested to protect against feather pecking [(<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>), van Staaveren, et al., submitted] and reduces fearfulness (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), acting as an enrichment. Therefore, providing foraging substrate&#8212;one that is nutritive (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) and that requires a longer amount of time to search, manipulate, and consume (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>)&#8212;can also act as enrichment.</p><p>First conducted in the 1970s, preference tests investigate where and how animals spend their time when provided different, but similar resources. These results are then used to ascribe preference (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). The preferences demonstrated are then presumed to present conditions that benefit the animals' health and well-being. Many external and internal factors, including animals' previous experiences, the time of day, the animals' mental state, and the differences between the presented options, can impact the outcome of a preference test. It is also important to consider that animals may make decisions that do not align with their welfare, and that their preferences are often restricted by the choices that humans offer them (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>).</p><p>Therefore, this meta-analysis used floor substrate preference studies to assess the bedding material that provided the best enrichment based on where Galliformes spent time, dustbathed, foraged, and pecked. Moreover, it sought to verify claims that peat and sand were preferred dustbathing substrates, and that Galliformes do not have a preference for foraging substrates (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Although bedding type is the focus of this review, many studies included did not distinguish between litter and bedding. Therefore, this review uses the term &#8220;substrate&#8221; to refer to both bedding (fresh material) and litter (bedding mixed with excreta, feathers and waste feed).</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Database</title><p>Three primary groups of search terms were used to amass literature. These terms were (1) bedding, litter, or substrate, (2) Galliformes, poultry, fowl, chicken, turkey, or galliform, and (3) preference, motivation, behavior, behavior, forage, foraging, dustbathing, or dust bathing. The search terms were used to hand-search for literature, and to search the following databases: Web of Science (Thomson Reuters Science, New York, NY), CAB Direct (CAB International, Wallingford, UK) and Google Scholar (specified to Animal Welfare and Applied Animal Behavior journals). The search was conducted between January and March 2020, and there were no time period exclusion criteria. The search resulted in 239 related references. The abstracts and titles of all 239 references were examined to determine if they met the five inclusion criteria:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Subjects are Galliformes.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Study reports at least one of the following: amount of dustbathing (or vertical wing shakes), foraging in, pecking in, or time spent on substrates. Substrate use for nesting purposes is not within the scope of this meta-analysis.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Because many countries are moving toward non-cage systems (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>), and because substrate has a larger presence in non-cage systems, tested substrates must be practical for non-cage systems. In other words, they must be able to absorb moisture, so studies that assessed preference for astroturf, plastic or feed as a bedding were excluded.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Study measured the amount of behavior performed as a percentage, count, or time spent. For example, measuring the time spent dustbathing on sand (time spent dustbathing on sand/total time dustbathing). Due to inability to synchronize all data types/units with the information provided, studies that only provided demand curves, or that measured the number of birds performing a behavior could not be used. For example, measuring the percent of birds dustbathing on sand (percent of birds dustbathing on sand/total number of birds).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Experiment must be set up as a substrate preference test.</p></list-item></list><p>Of the 239 articles found, ten were accessible and met these criteria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). All accessible, relevant articles that met criteria used strains of chickens as subjects. One article described the effect of substrate on the behavior of Japanese quail (<italic toggle="yes">Coturnix japonica</italic>) (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>); however, it was excluded as the study was not a preference test. Web Plot Digitizer software (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>) was used to extract data from many of these articles that only reported outcomes through graphs. A summary of the database used for this meta-analysis is reported in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Due to the small number of studies that met the aforementioned criteria, and the diversity of substrates tested, all beddings excluding peat moss, sand and wood were grouped together as &#8220;other.&#8221; This category included a variety of beddings such as straw, paper, feathers, rice hulls, and wheat bran. Since only two studies reported foraging while many reported pecking and scratching (the two behavioral components of foraging), these last two behaviors were combined to represent foraging for all studies. Vertical wing shakes were grouped with dustbathing, as it was used to measure dustbathing in several studies.</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Schematic of the literature search.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-07-584162-g0001.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap-group id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Database summary.</p></caption><table-wrap id="d39e346" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Publication/Reference number</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Study</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Birds observed<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Species (breed)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Days on substrate<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Enclosure area (m<sup><bold>2</bold></sup>)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>c</sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Stocking density<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN4"><sup>d</sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Animals/m<sup><bold>2</bold></sup> /day<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>e</sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Substrate area (m<sup><bold>2</bold></sup>)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN6"><sup>f</sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Substrate depth (cm)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jong et al., 2007 (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Layer</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13&#8211;2.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sanotra et al., 1995 (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Layer</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.94</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118.52</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03&#8211;0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shields et al., 2004 (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broiler</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37&#8211;0.82</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Villagra et al., 2014 (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broiler</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shields et al., 2005 (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broiler</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.65</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Toghyani et al., 2010 (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broiler</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">van Liere et al., 1990 (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Layer</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hogan and Vestergaard, 1992 (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jungle Fowl</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">171.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Petherick and Duncan, 1989 (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Layer</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guinebreti&#232;re et al., 2014 (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Layer</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.81</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><label>a</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Total number of birds observed in each study (some studies picked focal birds)</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN2"><label>b</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Number of days birds were allowed access to tested substrates (in enclosure area). Small numbers represent studies that moved animals into a separate area to observe</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN3"><label>c</label><p><italic toggle="yes">The size of the total enclosure, encompassing all substrate areas, in m<sup>2</sup></italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN4"><label>d</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Animals per m<sup>2</sup>; Stocking density = animals per group (not shown; some studies used focal birds) &#247; enclosure area (m<sup>2</sup>)</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN5"><label>e</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Proxy for degree of substrate soiling (higher numbers indicate more soiling); animals/m<sup>2</sup>/day = stocking density &#247; days on substrate</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN6"><label>f</label><p><italic toggle="yes">The area (m<sup>2</sup>) occupied by one substrate within the enclosure</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="d39e708" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Study</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Outcome measure<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="5" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Substrates tested</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="5" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Outcomes reported</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Peat moss</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sand</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Wood</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Other<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN8"><sup>b</sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>None</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Time spent</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Dustbathing</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Foraging<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN9"><sup>c</sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Pecking</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Scratching<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN10"><sup>d</sup></xref></bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Count</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time budget</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time budget</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time budget</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Time budget</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Count</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Count</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Count</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#10003;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN7"><label>a</label><p><italic toggle="yes">How behaviors were recorded by the study. Count = behaviors per time period; Time budget = time spent doing behavior divided by total time spent on a substrate; Percent = total time spent doing a behavior divided by substrate</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN8"><label>b</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Other substrates include: straw, feathers, recycled paper, rice hulls, and wheat bran</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN9"><label>c</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Foraging = (percent of pecking + percent of scratching) &#247; 2</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN10"><label>d</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Scratching was not reported without pecking. Therefore, it was combined to make foraging, and is not analyzed alone</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></table-wrap-group><p>All outcomes were converted to percentages of behavior performed on each substrate (time based). Count data was converted as follows:</p><disp-formula id="E1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="right center left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#215;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Behavioral time budgets were often broken down as a division of time spent on substrate by behavior (e.g., resting on wood + dustbathing on wood + foraging on wood = 100% of behaviors on wood). To convert this time budget to a division of a single behavior by substrate (e.g., dustbathing on wood + dustbathing on sand + dustbathing on straw = 100% of dustbathing), we used the following equation:</p><disp-formula id="E3"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="right center left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#215;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>followed by an adapted version of Equation (1).</p></sec><sec><title>Model Development</title><p>The methodology employed for this meta-analysis is described in St-Pierre (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>) and Sauvant et al. (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Within this approach, study is treated as a random effect, and within-study patterns are examined while accounting for sources of between study variance (as the random study effect, or via inclusion of covariates). Data were analyzed using SAS Studio (SAS Inst. Inc., Cary, NC). Relationships between fixed effects were first examined using the Proc Reg MAX R procedure to assess the significance of continuous variables (stocking density, substrate area, enclosure area, number of days with access to substrate, animals/m<sup>2</sup>/day, substrate depth, and grain size) on the outcomes (time spent, dustbathing, foraging, and pecking at substrate). Categorical variables [species (breed), outcome measure (to ensure no effect of measurement)] were manually assessed for significance on outcomes one at a time with bedding type (which was always included regardless of significant outcomes) by running the generalized linear mixed model (GLIMMIX). This preliminary analysis was utilized to advise model development within a GLIMMIX procedure considering the random effect of study. A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was the criterion for statistical significance and for inclusion of fixed effects in the analysis, while tendencies are reported at 0.05 &#8804; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#8804; 0.1. The incidence of dustbathing, foraging and pecking on substrate followed a gaussian distribution whereas time spent on substrate followed a lognormal distribution. The cook's D influence analysis was then used with a mixed model to identify influential outliers in the gaussian models, while extreme observations exceeding &#177;3.4 (identified by Proc Univariate) were used to identify outliers in the lognormal model. However, no outliers were removed. The percentage of dustbathing, foraging, and pecking at substrate is shown as LS means &#177; SEM, and time spent is shown as omega backtransformed LS means &#177; SEM. Wald-type F-statistics were used to test general linear hypotheses, while differences for LS means were tested using <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-tests. In our description of results, F<sub>v1</sub>,<sub>v2</sub> denotes a Wald-type F-statistic on v1 numerator and v2 denominator degrees of freedom, and t<sub>v</sub> denotes a t-statistic on v error degrees of freedom.</p></sec><sec><title>Model Evaluation</title><p>Model evaluation was performed to assess model goodness of fit. Models were evaluated based on the normality of residuals, which were examined graphically and using the Shapiro-Wilk statistic. Normality and homogeneity of the random effect was observed graphically with QQ and sample distribution plots, and time spent, the only non-normal model, was evaluated for over dispersion by ensuring that ChiSquare/DF &lt;1.0.</p><p>Further model evaluations were performed using the study-adjusted Y predicted values. These evaluations employed the use of percent root mean square prediction error (rMSPE%), which estimates the overall prediction error and identifies the best model as one with a smaller rMSPE% value. The mean square prediction error (MSPE) is calculated as:</p><disp-formula id="E5"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="right center left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover accentunder="false" accent="false"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#8721;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover></mml:mstyle><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> is the total number of observations, <italic toggle="yes">O</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> is the observed value, and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> is the predicted value. The MSPE was then decomposed to determine the model's mean bias (ECT), regression slope deviation (ER) and error from disturbance (random error; ED), as well as the percent of error that each of these make up (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>).</p><p>Lastly, the model was evaluated using the concordance correlation coefficient (CCC), which identifies a model's relationship as perfectly unrelated (&#8722;1), not related (0) or perfectly related (1). The CCC is calculated as:</p><disp-formula id="E6"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="right center left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#215;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where <italic toggle="yes">R</italic>&#8212;the Pearson correlation coefficient&#8212;measures precision and <italic toggle="yes">C</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">b</italic></sub> measures accuracy. Precise models display means that are strongly associated to one another, while accurate models have predicted means that are close to observed means. Calculating <italic toggle="yes">C</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">b</italic></sub> also requires two other variables: <italic toggle="yes">v</italic> and &#956;. A measure of scale shift, <italic toggle="yes">v</italic> expresses the change in standard deviation between predicted and observed values. Greater variance in the predicted data compared to observed is shown in a <italic toggle="yes">v</italic> value larger than one, while values less than one indicate a smaller variance. &#956; measures location shift relative to the scale, with negative &#956; values implying underprediction and positive values indicating overprediction (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Results of Final Models</title><sec><title>Percent of Time Spent</title><p>All independent variables were analyzed for significance in predicting percent of time spent on a substrate. <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents a summary of variables' effects on time spent. Bedding type [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(4, 10)</sub> = 11.82, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0008], substrate area [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 10)</sub> = 39.18, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001], and enclosure area [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 10)</sub> = 8.89, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0138] all significantly affected which substrate chickens preferred spending their time on <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. Birds spent more time on sand (41 &#177; 33.6%) than on wood [23 &#177; 18.6%; <italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>(10)</sub> = 3.47, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0376], other substrates [17 &#177; 13.8%; <italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>(10)</sub> = 5.09, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0033], and no substrate [9 &#177; 8.0%; <italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>(10)</sub> = 5.58, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0017]. Additionally, birds spent more time on peat moss (35 &#177; 31.5%) than on no substrate [<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>(10)</sub> = 3.67, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0280]. However, there was no significant difference between the amount of time chickens spent on peat moss, wood and other substrates (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05). <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> shows the predictive equations produced for time spent on floor substrates if all substrates are given at the same time.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The significance of independent variables on outcomes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Independent variables</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Models</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Time spent</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Dustbathing</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Foraging</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Pecking</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bedding type</td><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#93c953" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#93c953" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Substrate area</td><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#93c953" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enclosure area</td><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#93c953" rowspan="1" colspan="1">*</td><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of days birds were allowed access to tested substrates</td><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#f4ed1a" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stocking density</td><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Animals/m<sup>2</sup>/day</td><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species (breed)</td><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Substrate depth</td><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grain size</td><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" style="background-color:#ed1f24" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">Green indicates a significant effect (P &lt; 0.05), yellow indicates a tendency (0.05 &#8804; P &#8804; 0.1), and red indicates a non-significant effect (P &gt; 0.1). Starred (*) variables were included in model equations</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Percent of time spent (LS means &#177; SEM) on substrates (sand, peat moss, wood, other substrates and no substrate). Different letters indicate significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Number of treatments (t) and studies (s) that include each substrate are noted below each bar. The numbers of t and s differ because some studies used multiple floor substrates of the same kind with distinct differences (e.g., wire floors and a concrete &#8220;home&#8221; area for no substrate).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-07-584162-g0002.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Equations for time spent.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Percent of time spent on:</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Equation<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN11"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sand</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">= 1.3 (&#177;0.17) + 2.0 (&#177;0.32) &#215; Substrate area (m<sup>2</sup>) &#8211; 1.0 (&#177;0.34) &#215; Enclosure area (m<sup>2</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peat moss</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">= 1.1 (&#177;0.33) + 2.0 (&#177;0.32) &#215; Substrate area (m<sup>2</sup>) &#8211; 1.0 (&#177;0.34) &#215; Enclosure area (m<sup>2</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wood</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">= 0.7 (&#177;1.84) + 2.0 (&#177;0.32) &#215; Substrate area (m<sup>2</sup>) &#8211; 1.0 (&#177;0.34) &#215; Enclosure area (m<sup>2</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other substrates</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">= 0.4 (&#177;0.18) + 2.0 (&#177;0.32) &#215; Substrate area (m<sup>2</sup>) &#8211; 1.0 (&#177;0.34) &#215; Enclosure area (m<sup>2</sup>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No substrate</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">= &#8722;0.2 (&#177;0.27) + 2.0 (&#177;0.32) &#215; Substrate area (m<sup>2</sup>) &#8211; 1.0 (&#177;0.34) &#215; Enclosure area (m<sup>2</sup>)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">Each equation represents the predicted time that chickens would spend on each resource if given all five options. The estimate and SEM are presented for each independent variable in the equation</italic>.</p><fn id="TN11"><label>a</label><p><italic toggle="yes">The output of all equations must be backtransformed from a lognormal distribution to obtain the result on the original data scale (e<sup>equation</sup>)</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Percent of Dustbathing</title><p>All independent variables were analyzed for significance in predicting percent of dustbathing. <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents a summary of variables' effects on dustbathing. Bedding type [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(3, 30)</sub>= 8.98, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0002] alone significantly affected substrate preference for dustbathing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). Chickens dustbathed significantly more on peat moss (79 &#177; 16.3%) than on wood [16 &#177; 8.3%; <italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>(30)</sub> = 3.51, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0074] and other substrates (9 &#177; 8.3%; <italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>(30)</sub> = 3.87, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0029]. Chickens dustbathed more on sand (50 &#177; 7.5%) than on wood [<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>(30)</sub> = 3.21, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0158] and other substrates [<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>(30)</sub> = 3.85, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0031]. Percent of dustbathing was similar between peat moss and sand. Because bedding is the only variable that impacts the percent of dustbathing, the equations produced by this model are identical to the LS means &#177; SEM presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, and are therefore not shown.</p><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Percent of dustbathing (LS means &#177; SEM) on substrates (sand, peat moss, wood, and other). Different letters indicate significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Number of treatments (t) and studies (s) that include each substrate are noted below each bar. The numbers of t and s differ for sand and wood because some studies used multiple beddings of the same kind with distinct differences (e.g., different colors or grain sizes).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-07-584162-g0003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Percent of Foraging</title><p>All independent variables were analyzed for significance in predicting percent of foraging. <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents a summary of variables' effects on foraging. None of the analyzed variables, including bedding type [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(3, 21)</sub> = 80.73, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.5430], significantly affected substrate preference for foraging behavior (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). Birds spent equal percentages of time foraging on peat moss, sand, wood and other substrates. Furthermore, analysis of the residuals vs. other factors revealed that none of the independent variables significantly affected the accuracy of model predictions (data not shown).</p><fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Percent of foraging (LS means &#177; SEM) on substrates (sand, peat moss, wood, and other). Different letters indicate significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Number of treatments (t) and studies (s) that include each substrate are noted below each bar. The numbers of t and s differ for sand and wood because some studies used multiple beddings of the same kind with distinct differences (e.g., different colors or grain sizes).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-07-584162-g0004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Percent of Pecking</title><p>All independent variables were analyzed for significance in predicting percent of pecking. <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents a summary of variables' effects on pecking. Similar to foraging, none of the analyzed variables, including bedding type [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(3, 22)</sub> = 1.30, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.3002], significantly affected substrate preference for pecking behavior at substrate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). However, the number of days birds were allowed access to each tested substrate impacted the percentage of pecking (0.05 &#8804; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#8804; 0.1). Further analysis of the residual vs. other factors revealed similar results to foraging. However, plotting the residual vs. the number of days birds were allowed access to each tested substrate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>) showed a non-constant distribution of residuals across days on substrate. One study in particular (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>) influenced the model to over-predict higher values, which decreased the pecking model's accuracy.</p><fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Percentage of pecking (LS means &#177; SEM) on substrates (sand, peat moss, wood, and other). Different letters indicate significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Number of treatments (t) and studies (s) that include each substrate are noted below each bar. The numbers of t and s differ for sand and wood because some studies used multiple beddings of the same kind with distinct differences (e.g., different colors or grain sizes).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-07-584162-g0005.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Residual of pecking vs. the number of days birds were allowed access to tested substrates. Different symbols indicate different studies. All numbers correspond to a study (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-07-584162-g0006.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Model Evaluation</title><p>Model evaluation statistics based on the study-adjusted <italic toggle="yes">Y</italic> values for each of the final models are presented in <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. These results provide a metric of each model's ability to predict the identified outcome, and how well the model described the observed variation (be it due to fixed or random effects). Results indicate that, given its high CCC, the time spent model has both high accuracy (C<sub>b</sub>) and precision (R), describing the data well. However, the breakdown of rMSPE% shows that almost 10% of error is due to regression (ER%). Evaluation of the observed vs. adjusted predicted values shows that this error due to regression is driven entirely by observations of no substrate. Given the variety in what may be considered &#8220;no substrate&#8221; (e.g., wire flooring, a home compartment with feed and water etc.), this discrepancy between observed and predicted outcomes in the &#8220;no substrate&#8221; category makes sense.</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Final model evaluation parameters by outcome (time spent, dustbathing, foraging, pecking).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Time spent</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Dustbathing</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Foraging<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN12"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Pecking<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN12"><sup>b</sup></xref></bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rMSPE%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN13"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1597</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.1658</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.9937</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.0356</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECT%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN14"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0541</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ER%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN15"><sup>e</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.4228</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3797</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.2886</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5253</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ED%<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN16"><sup>f</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.5232</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6203</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.7114</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.4747</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCC<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN17"><sup>g</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9410</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0168</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0887</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN18"><sup>h</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9421</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6686</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0231</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1085</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C<sub>b</sub></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9988</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8974</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7272</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8171</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN12"><label>a, b</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Non-significant equations</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN13"><label>c</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Root means squared prediction error, % of mean</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN14"><label>d</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Error due to mean bias; % of total MSPE</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN15"><label>e</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Error due to regression; % of total MSPE</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN16"><label>f</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Error due to disturbance; % of total MSPE</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN17"><label>g</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Concordance correlation coefficient; C = R &#215; Cb</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN18"><label>h</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Pearson correlation coefficient; measure of precision</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Conversely, the distribution of rMSPE% in dustbathing is mostly weighted onto random error. However, despite this expected, preferred distribution of error, the CCC of dustbathing is relatively low. This may be because, while the model shows good accuracy, it also has a relatively low precision (R), implying that a great deal of random error is yet to be accounted for. Similarly, the foraging and pecking models showed good accuracy but very low precision, which is unsurprising given that both of these models are non-significant.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The meta-analysis presented herein systematically reviewed chickens' preferences for substrates based on the time spent on a given substrate, as well as dustbathing, foraging, and pecking behaviors on the substrate. While the search criteria for the meta-analysis included Galliformes, the eligible studies, in the end, only included chickens (laying hens, broilers, or red jungle fowl) as test subjects. The effect of substrates on the behavior and preferences of other commercially farmed Galliformes such as pheasants, guinea fowl, Japanese quail, bobwhite quail, and turkeys is therefore unknown. Nevertheless, the stimulating and motivating qualities of substrates for dustbathing, pecking, and foraging is expected to be similar, if not the same, for other commercially relevant Galliformes (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>).</p><p>We found that bedding type, substrate area and the enclosure area influenced where chickens chose to spend their time. Birds spent more time on areas with sand than on those with wood, other substrates, or no substrate. Interestingly, the time spent on peat moss was similar to all other substrates tested, although they spent more time on peat moss than on no substrate. These findings suggest that chickens may decide where they spend time based on the comfort and feel of the substrate. For example, compared to peat moss and sand, many wood shavings contain chemical irritants (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>) in addition to being physically abrasive. Therefore, it is likely that, when provided with an alternative, birds avoided physically uncomfortable beddings like wood. This would be particularly relevant for heavier birds like broiler chickens and turkeys that have reduced perching ability (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>) and spend much of their time sitting or lying down (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). It is, however, important to note that few studies have examined the impact of various substrates on comfort behaviors [e.g., preening, stretching, etc.; (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>)]. The time spent on a substrate also correlated positively with amount of space it covered, with chickens spending more time on substrates that covered larger areas (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Given that many chickens like to explore, the positive effect of a larger substrate area was likely counterbalanced when the enclosure areas were also large, as birds tended to spend less time on any given substrate with increasing enclosure space.</p><p>It is, however, important to note that only five studies reported the amount of time spent on each tested substrate. Moreover, model evaluation revealed that, despite the model's high accuracy and precision, it had a high error due to regression likely caused by observations of no substrate. As such, the equations produced from the percent of time spent model should be taken with caution. Additionally, even though only one study reported time spent with peat moss, it was analyzed as a separate substrate due to its reputation as a preferred bedding (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). Thus, conclusions for peat moss based on this analysis, while interesting, should also be approached with caution.</p><p>We report that chickens' dustbathing preferences were only influenced by the bedding type. Birds dustbathed on peat moss and sand significantly more than on wood and other substrates. Since peat moss and sand look and feel like dirt: the natural dustbathing substrate for Galliformes, the birds may find the naturalness of these beddings appealing. Galliformes are also known to prefer dustbathing in substrates with low lipid content (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>) that are easily distributed throughout the plumage (friable and of small grain size (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>)). It follows then that they would choose beddings that readily absorb lipids from plumage (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) and that are less prone to caking. However, only three studies tested dustbathing preference for peat moss, while 10 studies used sand, making conclusions about chickens' preference for peat moss less robust than the findings for sand.</p><p>Bedding type did not influence chickens' preference for foraging or pecking at substrates. Moreover, unlike dustbathing and time spent on a substrate, chickens did not show a substrate preference to forage or peck in. Given that foraging and pecking are frequently performed, exploratory behaviors (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>), studies may require greater contrast in bedding type to see preference for foraging or pecking. For example, offering birds the choice between highly palatable, nutritive substrates compared to inorganic, non-nutritive substrates (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). The number of days birds could access each tested substrate tended to affect the frequency of substrate pecking (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>). Increasing the number of days exposed to substrates caused the model to over-predict, decreasing the accuracy of the pecking model. This over-prediction was largely driven by one study (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>) that exposed birds to the same substrate for 49 days, whereas other studies that reported pecking exposed birds to tested substrates for 5 days or less. Therefore, proper understanding of the effect of the number of days birds were allowed access to tested substrates requires that more research examine pecking behavior on substrate over longer periods of time.</p><p>Most studies did not explicitly state if litter was cleaned out or if fresh bedding was ever applied on top of litter, making the true number of days birds were allowed access to tested substrates an estimated variable. Nevertheless, the proxy variable for cleanliness, animals per m<sup>2</sup> per day, did not significantly affect any of the behaviors analyzed. With regards to foraging and pecking behavior, chickens are known to forage in and consume excreta in the absence of substrates (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>), and are reported to consume 5&#8211;24% of their group's excreta even when housed on bedding (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). Therefore, substrates may become equally attractive foraging and pecking material as they soil. Moreover, soiled bedding degrades to a soil-like consistency over time, and a study by Moesta et al. (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>) found that soiled, degraded wood shavings were more stimulating and adequate for dustbathing compared to fresh wood shavings. The data presented here, in addition to the literature, would therefore support the idea that degree of soiling has little impact on the behaviors quantified in this meta-analysis.</p><p>In general, substrate characteristics are under-studied or inconsistently reported in the current literature. For example, only three of the 10 studies in this meta-analysis reported grain size of select substrates. Of these studies, none reported grain size for all substrates included in the preference test and five grain sizes reported were ranges. While every study reported dustbathing or its various behavioral elements, none reported caking which severely impact behavioral activities, including dustbathing. Other measures that might influence dustbathing, such as moisture content, analogous measurements for degree of substrate friability, or lipid content were all lacking from the examined studies, and may have contributed to the low precision of the dustbathing model. Reporting measurable or observable substrate characteristics that may influence Galliformes' preferences can contribute to understanding reported observations, improve study reproducibility (<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>), and applicability across species. Despite chickens' preference for sand and peat moss, farmers are reticent to their use due to labor requirements, wear and tear on equipment, cost, accessibility and unsustainability. Therefore, knowledge of important substrate qualities for dustbathing, foraging, and other high priority behaviors (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) can aid in the search for practical, cost-effective, sustainable, healthy, and enriching substrates. For example, knowledge of chickens' preference for low lipid content substrates for dustbathing and nutritive substrates for foraging led Guinebretiere et al. (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) to test laying hens' preference for wheat bran (evaluated in this meta-analysis under &#8220;other substrates&#8221;) compared to peat moss and sand. Refocussing on substrate characteristics may also reduce the number of animals used for substrate preference research, thereby satisfying one of the &#8220;3 Rs (Reduce, Replace, Refine)&#8221; of non-human animal research (<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>). Specifically, evaluations of substrate characteristics instead of, or before, performing multiple preference tests with different species of Galliformes could be used in the place of many exploratory preference tests using new substrates.</p><p>Finally, this meta-analysis also highlighted the need for consistent methods of measurement. For instance, all studies measured dustbathing, but this behavior was measured using six different observations: vertical wing shakes per hour, percent of vertical wing shakes, mean dust-baths per hen per day, mean total dust-baths, dust-baths per hour, and percent of time (on substrate) spent dustbathing. This variation in measurement methods and the lack of reported SEM prevented weighting studies by SEM.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>As the first meta-analysis of chickens' floor substrate preferences, this review confirmed that chickens preferred to dustbathe and generally spend time on sand and peat moss over wood shavings, other substrates and no substrate. However, only 30% of the studies used in the analysis examined preference for peat moss, suggesting that the data related to peat moss are less robust than those of sand. We also report that the bedding type, enclosure area and substrate area affected the time that birds spent on the tested substrates. Interestingly, none of the examined variables affected foraging and pecking behavior.</p><p>We noted that few studies reported physical and chemical properties of substrates, which, in the future, can be used to develop and discover novel beddings. Moreover, variations in data reporting and the lack of reporting standard error of the mean limited analysis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be made available by the authors, without undue reservation.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>VM, JE, and AH-M conceived and designed the study. JE provided statistical analysis support. VM analyzed the data and wrote the main manuscript. All authors reviewed and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors would like to thank Dr. Michelle Edwards for her additional support in statistical analysis.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> VM received support from the Resource Allocation for Graduates (RAG) Scholarship from the University of Guelph Department of Animal Biosciences. JE would like to acknowledge the support of the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC), (#04985). Additionally, AH-M also received funding from NSERC (Discovery Grant #400983).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Statista Statistics Portal</collab></person-group><source>Number of chickens worldwide from 1990 to 2018</source>. (<year>2020</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/263962/number-of-chickens-worldwide-since-1990/">https://www.statista.com/statistics/263962/number-of-chickens-worldwide-since-1990/</ext-link> (accessed April 23, 2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ritz</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fairchild</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacy</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><source>Litter Quality and Broiler Performance</source> (<year>2009</year>) <publisher-loc>Athens, GA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>University of Georgia</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Staaveren</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leishman</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harlander-Matauschek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baes</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Housing and management of Turkey flocks in Canada</article-title>. <source>Animals.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1159</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani10071159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32650501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7401629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cathcart</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>High litter moisture content suppresses litter ammonia volatilization</article-title>. <source>Poultry Sci.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>1397</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>405</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.2010-01114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21673154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cathcart</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Litter ammonia generation: moisture content and organic versus inorganic bedding materials</article-title>. <source>Poultry Sci.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>1162</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.2010-01113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21597054</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bilgili</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Macklin</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saenmahayak</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sibley</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of bedding material on footpad dermatitis in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>J Appl Poultry Res.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>583</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/japr.2009-00023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Else</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hocking</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>High litter moisture alone is sufficient to cause footpad dermatitis in growing turkeys</article-title>. <source>Br Poultry Sci.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>538</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00071660701573045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17952724</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fairchild</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ritz</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alternative bedding materials and litter depth impact litter moisture and footpad dermatitis</article-title>. <source>J Appl Poultry Res.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>518</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/japr/pfx024</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National Research Council</collab></person-group><source>Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals</source>. <edition>8th ed</edition><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber-Eicher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Feather pecking in domestic chicks: its relation to dustbathing and foraging</article-title>. <source>Anim Behav.</source> (<year>1997</year>) <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>757</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>68</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/anbe.1996.0506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9344430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber-Eicher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of quality and availability of foraging materials on feather pecking in laying hen chicks</article-title>. <source>Anim Behav.</source> (<year>1998</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>861</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/anbe.1997.0715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9632473</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Erasmus</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Welfare issues in turkey production</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mench</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group> editor. <source>Advances in Poultry Welfare.</source><publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Woodhead Publishing</publisher-name> (<year>2018</year>). p. <fpage>263</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-08-100915-4.00013-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hocking</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Turkeys are equally susceptible to foot pad dermatitis from 1 to 10 weeks of age and foot pad scores were minimized when litter moisture was less than 30%</article-title>. <source>Poultry Sci.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>1170</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.2010-01202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21597055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wathes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ammonia and poultry welfare: a review</article-title>. <source>World's Poultry Sci J.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>235</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/WPS20000018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawkins</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of rearing and lay risk factors on propensity for feather damage in laying hens</article-title>. <source>Br Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2010</year>). <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>725</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00071668.2010.528751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21161778</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Liere</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The significance of fowls' bathing in dust</article-title>. <source>Anim Welf.</source> (<year>1992</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>202</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Widowski</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>IJH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Working for a dustbath: are hens increasing pleasure rather than reducing suffering?</article-title><source>Appl Anim Behav Sci.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-1591(00)00088-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10771314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>IAS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>IJH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why do hens sham dustbathe when they have litter?</article-title><source>Appl Anim Behav Sci.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>76</volume>:<fpage>53</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-1591(01)00181-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Rooijen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dust bathing and other comfort behaviours of domestic hens</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sambraus</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steiger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> editors. <source>Das Wohlergehen von Legehennen in Europa&#8212;Berichte, Analysen und Schlussfolgerungen.</source><publisher-loc>Wageningen</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Internationale Gesellschaft f&#252;r Nutztierhaltung IGN; Verlag Universit&#228;t Kassel</publisher-name> (<year>2005</year>). p. <fpage>110</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scholz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjaer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urselmans</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schrader</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Litter lipid content affects dustbathing behavior in laying hens</article-title>. <source>Poultry Science.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>2433</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.2011-01480</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22010226</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mullens</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Housing and dustbathing effects on northern fowl mites (<italic toggle="yes">Ornithonyssus sylviarum</italic>) and chicken body lice (<italic toggle="yes">Menacanthus stramineus</italic>) on hens</article-title>. <source>Med Vet Entomol.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>323</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2915.2011.00997.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22458590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vestergaard</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kruijt</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Feather pecking and chronic fear in groups of red junglefowl: their relations to dustbathing, rearing environment and social status</article-title>. <source>Animal Behaviour.</source> (<year>1993</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1127</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/anbe.1993.1137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bubier</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The behavioural priorities of laying hens: the effects of two methods of environment enrichment on time budgets</article-title>. <source>Behav Proces.</source> (<year>1996</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>239</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>49</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0376-6357(96)00018-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24897446</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bubier</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The behavioural priorities of laying hens: the effect of cost/no cost multi-choice tests on time budgets</article-title>. <source>Behav Proces.</source> (<year>1996</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>225</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>38</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0376-6357(96)00019-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24897445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeltner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber-Eicher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Are genetic differences in foraging behaviour of laying hen chicks paralleled by hybrid-specific differences in feather pecking?</article-title><source>Appl Anim Behav Sci.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>143</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-1591(00)00147-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11080557</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Inglis</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forkman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lazarus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Free food or earned food? A review and fuzzy model of contrafreeloading</article-title>. <source>Anim Behav.</source> (<year>1997</year>) <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>1171</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/anbe.1996.0320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9236014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>IJH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Free and operant feeding in domestic fowls</article-title>. <source>Anim Behav.</source> (<year>1972</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>775</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-3472(72)80150-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4661320</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aerni</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Lethey</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of foraging material and food form on feather pecking in laying hens</article-title>. <source>Br Poultry Sci.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00071660086349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10821517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Jong</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reuvekamp</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunnink</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Can substrate in early rearing prevent feather pecking in adult laying hens?</article-title><source>Anim Welf.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>305</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7120/09627286.22.3.305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scholz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urselmans</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kjaer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schrader</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Food, wood, or plastic as substrates for dustbathing and foraging in laying hens: a preference test</article-title>. <source>Poultry Sci.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>1584</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.2009-00598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20634510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preference and motivation testing</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Appleby</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group> editors. <source>Animal Welfare</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>CAB International</publisher-name> (<year>1997</year>). p. <fpage>159</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franks</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What do animals want</article-title>. <source>Anim Welf.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7120/09627286.28.1.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guinebreti&#232;re</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beyer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnould</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The choice of litter material to promote pecking, scratching and dustbathing behaviours in laying hens housed in furnished cages</article-title>. <source>Appl Anim Behav Sci.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>155</volume>:<fpage>56</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.applanim.2014.02.013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><source>Understanding Animal Welfare: The Science in its Cultural Context</source>. <publisher-loc>Chichester</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Staaveren</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Decina</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baes</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Widowski</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berke</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harlander-Matauschek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A description of laying hen husbandry and management practices in Canada</article-title>. <source>Animals.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>114</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani8070114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29997334</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6071255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Said</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Hamid</surname><given-names>SEL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of different litter materials on behaviour, growth performance, feet health and plumage score of Japanese quail (<italic toggle="yes">Coturnix japonica</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Eur Poultry Sci.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>81</volume>:<fpage>719</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1399/eps.2017.172</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rohatgi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>WebPlotDigitizer</source>. <edition>4.2 ed</edition><publisher-loc>Pacifica</publisher-loc> (<year>2015</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://automeris.io/WebPlotDigitizer/citation.html">https://automeris.io/WebPlotDigitizer/citation.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jong</surname><given-names>ICD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolthuis-Fillerup</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reenen</surname><given-names>CGv</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strength of preference for dustbathing and foraging substrates in laying hens</article-title>. <source>Appl Anim Behav Sci</source>. (<year>2007</year>). <volume>104</volume>:<fpage>24</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.applanim.2006.04.027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanotra</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vestergaard</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agger</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relative preferences for feathers, straw, wood-shavings and sand for dustbathing, pecking and scratching in domestic chicks</article-title>. <source>Appl Anim Behav Sci.</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>263</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>77</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0168-1591(95)00562-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garner</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mench</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dustbathing by broiler chickens: a comparison of preference for four different substrates</article-title>. <source>Appl Anim Behav Sci.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>87</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.applanim.2004.01.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Villagra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olivas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Althaus</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lainez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Behavior of broiler chickens in four different substrates: a choice test</article-title>. <source>Brazil J Poultry Sci.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>67</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>75</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1516-635X2014000100010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garner</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mench</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of sand and wood-shavings bedding on the behavior of broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Poultry Sci.</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>84</volume>:<fpage>1816</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ps/84.12.1816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16479936</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toghyani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gheisari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Modaresi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabeidian</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toghyani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of different litter material on performance and behavior of broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Appl Anim Behav Sci.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>122</volume>:<fpage>48</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.applanim.2009.11.008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Liere</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kooijman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiepkema</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dustbathing behaviour of laying hens as related to quality of dustbathing material</article-title>. <source>Appl Anim Behav Sci.</source> (<year>1990</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>127</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0168-1591(90)90093-S</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vestergaard</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The development of a behavior system: dustbathing in the Burmese red junglefowl. III. Effects of experience on stimulus preference</article-title>. <source>Behaviour.</source> (<year>1992</year>) <volume>121</volume>:<fpage>215</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1163/156853992X00372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petherick</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>IJH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Behaviour of young domestic fowl directed towards different substrates</article-title>. <source>Br Poultry Sci.</source> (<year>1989</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>229</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>38</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00071668908417143</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>St-Pierre</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Invited review: Integrating quantitative findings from multiple studies using mixed model methodology</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>84</volume>:<fpage>741</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(01)74530-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11352149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sauvant</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidely</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daudin</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>St-Pierre</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Meta-analyses of experimental data in animal nutrition</article-title>. <source>Animal Int J Anim Biosci.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1203</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1751731108002280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22443733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sauvant</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Letourneau-Montminy</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidely</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boval</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loncke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Review: use and misuse of meta-analysis in animal science</article-title>. <source>Animal.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>207</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>s22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1751731120001688</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32662377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bibby</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toutenburg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Prediction and Improved Estimation in Linear Models</source>. <publisher-loc>Chichester</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name> (<year>1977</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A concordance correlation coefficient to evaluate reproducibility</article-title>. <source>Biometrics</source>. (<year>1989</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>255</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>68</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2532051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2720055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pokharel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><source>The Impact of Excreta/Excreta Gas Control Strategies on the Behaviour and Physiology of Laying Hens</source>. <publisher-name>University of Guelph Department of Animal Biosciences</publisher-name> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monckton</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Staaveren</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harlander-Matauschek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Broiler chicks' motivation for different wood beddings and amounts of soiling</article-title>. <source>Animals.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1039</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani10061039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32560113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7341187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monckton</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Staaveren</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baes</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balzani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harlander-Matauschek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Are turkeys (<italic toggle="yes">Meleagris gallopavo</italic>) motivated to avoid excreta-soiled substrate?</article-title><source>Animals.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>2015</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani10112015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33147707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7692265</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pesonen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suuronen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suomela</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aalto-Korte</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Occupational allergic contact dermatitis caused by colophonium</article-title>. <source>Contact Dermat.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>80</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cod.13114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30229960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Estlander</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jolanki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alanko</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanerva</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Occupational allergic contact dermatitis caused by wood dusts</article-title>. <source>Contact Dermat.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>213</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1600-0536.2001.044004213.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11260236</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pettit-Riley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Estevez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of density on perching behavior of broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Appl Anim Behav Sci.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>71</volume>:<fpage>127</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-1591(00)00174-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11179565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weeks</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danbury</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kestin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The behaviour of broiler chickens and its modification by lameness</article-title>. <source>Appl Anim Behav Sci.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-1591(99)00102-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10719194</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailie</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Connell</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An evaluation of potential dustbathing substrates for commercial broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Animal.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1933</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1751731117003408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29271337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Liere</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bokma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Short-term feather maintenance as a function of dust-bathing in laying hens</article-title>. <source>Appl Anim Behav Sci.</source> (<year>1987</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>197</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>204</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0168-1591(87)90193-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pokharel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boecker</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeyachanthiran</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McBride</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harlander-Matauschek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>How does the presence of excreta affect the behavior of laying hens on scratch pads?</article-title><source>Poultry Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>97</volume>:<fpage>743</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pex375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29272459</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Von</surname><given-names>Waldburg-Zeil C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Staaveren</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harlander-Matauschek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Do laying hens eat and forage in excreta from other hens?</article-title><source>Animal.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>367</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1751731118001143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29804554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6340106</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#246;rnicke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bj&#246;rhag</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group> editors. <article-title>Digestive physiology and metabolism in ruminants</article-title>. In: <source>Coprophagy and Related Strategies for Digesta Utilization 5th International-Symposium on Ruminant Physiology</source>. <publisher-loc>Clermont-Ferrand</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Annales De Recherches Veterinaires</publisher-name> (<year>1979</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-94-011-8067-2_34</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">43695</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moesta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knierim</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Briese</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of litter condition and depth on the suitability of wood shavings for dustbathing behaviour</article-title>. <source>Appl Anim Behav Sci.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>115</volume>:<fpage>160</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.applanim.2008.06.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koroshetz</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Behrman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brame</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Branchaw</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Research culture: framework for advancing rigorous research</article-title>. <source>Elife.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e55915</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.55915</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32127131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7056268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tannenbaum</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Russell and Burch's 3Rs then and now: the need for clarity in definition and purpose</article-title>. <source>J Am Assoc Lab Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>120</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25836957</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4382615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>