<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7982812</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC7982812.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">7982812</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">7982812</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33763461</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.606197</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Polyphenols and Cannabidiol Modulate Transcriptional Regulation of Th1/Th2 Inflammatory Genes Related to Canine Atopic Dermatitis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Massimini</surname><given-names initials="M">Marcella</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/698379/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalle Vedove</surname><given-names initials="E">Elena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1087339/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bachetti</surname><given-names initials="B">Benedetta</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1196896/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Pierro</surname><given-names initials="F">Francesco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribecco</surname><given-names initials="C">Cataldo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1196899/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Addario</surname><given-names initials="C">Claudio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/228385/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pucci</surname><given-names initials="M">Mariangela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c002"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/232654/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>R&amp;D Division, C.I.A.M. Srl</institution>, <addr-line>Ascoli</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Velleja Research</institution>, <addr-line>Milan</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Faculty of Bioscience and Technology for Food, Agriculture and Environment, University of Teramo</institution>, <addr-line>Teramo</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Luisella Verotta, University of Milan, Italy</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Mohamed E. Abd El-Hack, Zagazig University, Egypt; Emiliano Lasagna, University of Perugia, Italy; Vito Laudadio, University of Bari Aldo Moro, Italy</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Marcella Massimini <email>marcella@nilitaly.com</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Mariangela Pucci <email>mpucci@unite.it</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Animal Nutrition and Metabolism, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">374996</issue-id><elocation-id>606197</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>9</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>02</day><month>2</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>23</day><month>03</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-02 17:25:15.200"><day>02</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2021 Massimini, Dalle Vedove, Bachetti, Di Pierro, Ribecco, D'Addario and Pucci.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Massimini, Dalle Vedove, Bachetti, Di Pierro, Ribecco, D'Addario and Pucci</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-08-606197.pdf"/><abstract><p>Canine atopic dermatitis (AD) is a multifactorial allergic disease associated with immune and abnormal skin barrier dysfunction and it is one of the primary causes of pruritus. Using a novel <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> model of AD, here we tried to revert the alteration of transcriptional regulation of AD canine key genes testing a nutraceutical mixture containing flavonoids, stilbene, and cannabinoids, which are already well-known for their applications within dermatology diseases. The nutraceutical mixture induced in inflamed cells a significant downregulation (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) of the gene expression of <italic toggle="yes">ccl2, ccl17</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic> in keratinocytes and of <italic toggle="yes">ccl2, ccl17</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">il31ra</italic> in monocytes. Consistent with the observed alterations of <italic toggle="yes">tslp, ccl2, ccl17</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">il31ra</italic> messenger RNA (mRNA) levels, a significant increase (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) of DNA methylation at specific CpG sites on the gene regulatory regions was found. These results lay the foundation for the use of these natural bioactives in veterinary medicine and provide a model for deeper understanding of their mechanisms of action, with potential translation to human research.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>epigenetic</kwd><kwd>polyphenols</kwd><kwd>phytocannabinoids</kwd><kwd>skin inflammation</kwd><kwd>veterinary research</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="7"/><table-count count="6"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="76"/><page-count count="14"/><word-count count="9188"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>In veterinary dermatology practice, canine atopic dermatitis (AD) is a multifactorial allergic disease that affects up to 27% of dogs; it is associated with immune and abnormal skin barrier dysfunction and it is one of the primary causes of pruritus (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Many pharmacological options for its treatment already exist; however, due to elevated costs, side effects, and/or a long lag phase, treatments based on natural compounds are constantly being developed (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). In fact, due to their low toxicity and high efficacy, nutraceuticals are helpful for AD prevention and treatment (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>).</p><p>Nutrigenomic studies in humans and animal models have clearly shown that nutraceuticals can influence signaling processes, cell apoptosis, metabolism, immune regulation, and modulate gene expression through epigenetic control (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Taking into account epigenetic modulations within AD and considering the importance of environment in disease progression, food supplements can delay the onset and improve the prognosis of the disease, giving support when anti-inflammatory feedback mechanisms fail to switch off, thereby avoiding an inflammatory over-response (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>).</p><p>Atopic dermatitis treatment represents a challenge also in human medicine, given the high incidence and the substantial psychosocial burden involved; for these reasons, many studies are focused on characterizing the disease pathomechanisms in our and other species to find an optimal preclinical model for drug development (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Transcriptomic analysis was performed for dogs in both skin biopsies from spontaneously occurring AD and from lesions induced by epicutaneous allergen challenge in <italic toggle="yes">Dermatophagoides farinae</italic> house dust mite-sensitized subjects (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). AD-related hypersensitivity is originally considered to be a Th2-polarized lymphocyte response, especially in the clinical acute phase of the disease; a large number of Th2 genes are upregulated in canine AD models, especially in those induced by house dust mites (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). It is known, to date, that, AD is often associated with multiple lymphocyte phenotypes characterized by the production of a complex variety of cytokines, including both Th1 and Th2 response mediators (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Increased mRNA levels of interleukin (IL)-4 and other Th2-related interleukins, such as IL-13 and IL-31, were seen in non-lesional and lesional atopic dogs (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), but recent <italic toggle="yes">ex vivo</italic> studies showed an high presence of interferon gamma (IFN-&#947;), the principal mediator of the Th1 response, in whole blood samples and skin biopsies from atopic dogs (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>).</p><p>On the basis of the abovementioned mechanisms, advanced <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> models were developed to enhance preclinical study for drug discovery, with the aim of decreasing <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> tests (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Our purpose was to test the effects of a nutraceutical mixture in a canine AD <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> model, which takes into account the Th1/Th2 inflammation. Keratinocytes and monocytes were chosen for their significant involvement in AD progression (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). In particular, the efficacy of the mixture was evaluated in terms of its ability to modulate the transcriptional regulation of the Th1-/Th2-related genes, known to lead to a massive migration and maturation of blood leukocytes at the site of injury and to an increase of itch stimulus in AD (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>).</p><p>The active principles included in the mixture are two polyphenols, flavone luteolin and stilbene piceatannol, and cannabidiol. They were selected for their already known involvement in reducing skin inflammation and allergic diseases (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Materials</title><p>Chemicals were of the purest analytical grade. IFN-&#947; (781-CG) and IL-13 (5894-CL) were purchased from R&amp;D System (Minneapolis, MN, USA), and IL-4 (754-CL) and IL-31 (59591) from Novus Biologicals (Centennial, CO, USA). Luteolin (sc-203119A) was from Santa Cruz Biotechnology (Dallas, TX, USA), while piceatannol (S3026) and cannabidiol (C6395) were from Selleckchem (Houston, TX, USA) and Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA), respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell Culture and Inflammatory Stimulation</title><p>Canine monocyte-macrophage, DH82 (ATCC, Manassas, VA, USA) and canine epidermal keratinocyte progenitor (CPEK; CELLnTEC, Bern, Switzerland) cell lines were grown at 37&#176;C in humidified 5% CO<sub>2</sub> atmosphere, in accordance with the manufacturer's recommended protocols. The DH82 cell line was seeded in complete growth medium containing Eagle's minimum essential medium (EMEM), 15% fetal bovine serum, and 1% penicillin/streptomycin; CPEK cells were seeded in complete epidermal keratinocyte medium (CELLnTEC, Bern, Switzerland) supplemented with 1% penicillin/streptomycin. At the optimal culture conditions and considering each cell line doubling time, 5 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup> DH82 cells and 2.5 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup> CPEK cells were seeded onto 60-mm Petri dishes; after 24 h, cells were prestimulated with the Th1 cytokine IFN-&#947; (5 ng/ml) for 48 h, then subjected to the inflammatory stimulation (&#8220;inflamed&#8221;) with a Th2 interleukin mixture composed of IL-4 (50 ng/ml), IL-13 (50 ng/ml), and IL-31 (50 ng/ml) for 4 h and 8 h. Inflammatory stimuli and dosage have been chosen from the literature with the aim to upregulate canine AD marker genes (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Nutraceutical Dosage Information and Effects on Cell Viability</title><p>Inflamed cells were treated with the nutraceutical mixture containing luteolin, piceatannol, and cannabidiol at doses established through the literature and MTT assay results (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). The effects of the individual mixture components on the skin inflammation markers were already known in the literature so their synergic ability has been evaluated here (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Piceatannol [dissolved in dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO)] and luteolin and cannabidiol (dissolved in methanol) were added directly to the culture medium at the following concentrations (Mix 1: cannabidiol 10 &#956;M, luteolin 10 &#956;M, and piceatannol 10 &#956;M; Mix 2: 10:25:25; Mix 3: 10:50:50; and Mix 4: 10:100:100 &#956;M) for 4 h and 8 h. The culture medium containing vehicles alone was added to controls under the same conditions.</p><p>To determine the mixtures effect on the cell proliferation, 7.5 &#215; 10<sup>2</sup> cells/well were seeded onto 96-well plates. At the beginning of the experiment, the complete growth medium was replaced with fresh medium containing the nutraceutical mixture or vehicles. After 4 h and 8 h of incubation, the supernatants were replaced with 0.1 ml of the fresh medium without phenol red, containing 0.5 mg/ml of MTT; the plates were then returned to the incubator for 4 h and were gently shaken occasionally. Crystals of formazan (the MTT metabolic product) were solubilized by 0.1 ml ethanol/DMSO 1:1 lysis buffer and spectrophotometrically quantified at a wavelength of 570 nm with the reference at a wavelength of 695 nm. The differences in the cell growth were measured as a percentage of the growth rates of treated cells compared to untreated cultures.</p></sec><sec><title>Gene Expression</title><p>Total RNA was extracted from &#8771;1 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup> cells using the All Prep DNA/RNA Mini Kit (QIAGEN, Hilden, Germany) following the manufacturer's recommended protocol. Starting with 1 &#956;g of RNA templates, first strand complementary DNA (cDNA) was synthesized using the RevertAid H Minus First Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). The relative abundance of the canine AD marker genes was evaluated by real-time PCR using the SensiFAST SYBR Lo-ROX kit (Bioline, London, UK) on a 7500 Fast Real-Time PCR System (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) in both cell lines. The primers used for the amplification are reported in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, and all of the data were normalized to the endogenous reference gene &#946;-actin.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Primer sequences used to analyze mRNA expression levels of canine genes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gene</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Forward (5&#8242; &#8594; 3&#8242;)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Reverse (5&#8242; &#8594; 3&#8242;)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">il4r</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAAAGGATGGTGGGATCAGA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAAGCTCCTGCCCTGTCTAC</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">il31ra</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATGGATGCTCCTTCTACTCTGTAAACT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAGGAAATGTTCTCAGGCTTAGC</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">il31</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTCTCCCACACAGGACCATC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGGGAGGACAGCAAGGTTTC</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCTGCTGCTATACACTCA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCTTCTTTGGGACACTTG</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ccl5</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAGTCGTCTTTGTCACCCGA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGTACTCCCGCACCCATTTC</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCCATCGTGTTTGTAACT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTCCCTTCCAGGTTCTTTGT</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGTACACGGGGTGGCTGA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTCATTTACCAAGCCCTGGA</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ctss</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAAGCGAGCTGCCACATGT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTAAGGCATCTTCACTGCCAAA</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#946;-<italic toggle="yes">actin</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTCCGCTGCCCAGAGGCTCT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCTCAGGGGGTGCGATGATCTTG</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>DNA Methylation Analysis by Pyrosequencing</title><p>The DNA methylation levels of the specific CpG sites were determined using bisulfite-converted DNA from DH82 and CPEK cells by pyrosequencing. The genomic DNA was simultaneously purified with RNA as mentioned above, and DNA (1 &#956;g) was subjected to bisulfite modification using the EZ DNA Methylation Kit (Zymo Research, Irvine, CA, USA).</p><p>The bisulfite-treated DNA was amplified using the PyroMark PCR Kit (QIAGEN, Hilden, Germany) according to the protocol of the manufacturer. The PCR conditions were as follows: 95&#176;C for 15 min, followed by 45 cycles of 94&#176;C for 30 s, 56&#176;C for 30 s, 72&#176;C for 30 s, and finally, 72&#176;C for 10 min. After product quality verification by 1.8% agarose electrophoresis, the pyrosequencing methylation analysis was conducted using the PyroMark Q24 (QIAGEN, Hilden, Germany). The level of methylation was analyzed using PyroMark Q24 software (QIAGEN, Hilden, Germany), which calculates the methylation percentage using the following formula: methylated cytosine/methylated cytosine + unmethylated cytosine. Quantitative methylation results were considered, both as a percentage of single CpG sites and as an average of the methylation percentage of all the investigated CpG sites. A schematic representation of a CpG island and the details of the pyrosequencing assay are given in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> and <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, respectively.</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The schematic representation of the analyzed canine genes.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-606197-g0001.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Primer sequences used to analyze DNA methylation levels of canine genes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gene</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Forward (5<bold>&#8242;</bold> &#8594; 3<bold>&#8242;</bold>)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGGAAGTTTTGTGTATTTTATAGGTATTG</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGGGAATTAGAGGGAAGGTAGGA</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">il31ra</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAGGGTTTAAGAATAGATTTTATTGTAGGT</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTTTAGTAAGTGTTATAGGGGTTAAGAGAT</td></tr><tr style="border-top: thin solid #000000;"><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gene</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Reverse biotinylated (5</bold><bold>&#8242;</bold>
<bold>&#8594;</bold>
<bold>3</bold><bold>&#8242;</bold><bold>)</bold></td></tr><tr style="border-top: thin solid #000000;"><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AACAAAAAAAAAAACAAACTCCATAC</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TAAAAACCCCCAACAACCTCC</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Il31ra</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAACCCCCTACCACCTTATCTT</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACTCCCTCCCCTAAACTACAAC</td></tr><tr style="border-top: thin solid #000000;"><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gene</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sequencing (5</bold><bold>&#8242;</bold>
<bold>&#8594;</bold>
<bold>3</bold><bold>&#8242;</bold><bold>)</bold></td></tr><tr style="border-top: thin solid #000000;"><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AATGATTTTATAAGAAAGAAGATT</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGTTGGAAGGGAAAG</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">il31ra</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AATAGATTTTATTGTAGGTATT</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGGGTTAAGAGATTTTTG</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Data were expressed as the mean &#177; SEM for each group and were analyzed using the GraphPad Prism version 8.0.0 (GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA, USA). Data from the MTT assay were statistically evaluated by the one-way ANOVA followed by the Bonferroni's multiple comparison test for further examination of group differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><p>The gene expression was analyzed by three-way ANOVA using the factors &#8220;inflammation,&#8221; &#8220;nutraceuticals treatment,&#8221; and &#8220;time&#8221; followed by the Bonferroni's <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> test to follow up on significant interactions or main effects (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) from the factorial ANOVA. The effects of the nutraceutical treatment on inflamed cells were evaluated using the two-way ANOVA, and the one-way ANOVA was used in cases of no interaction between factors (nutraceuticals and time). The statistical differences with respect to average DNA methylation changes at gene promoters were analyzed by multiple <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-tests (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Effects of Inflammation on AD Markers Gene Expression</title><p>The effects evoked by the inflammatory stimulation on canine DH82 and CPEK cells on the expression of selected genes were assessed by real-time PCR, and the results are shown in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> (CPEK cell line; &#8220;keratinocytes&#8221;) and <bold>4</bold> (DH82 cell line; &#8220;monocytes&#8221;). Selected genes derived from a previous screening aimed to sort markers of inflammation in stimulated cells (the data regarding model time course are not shown). Three-way ANOVA showed, among the selected genes, an increase in mRNA levels in inflamed cells (Inflamed: yes; Mix: no) with respect to the control (Inflamed: no; Mix: no). The Bonferroni's <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> test results are shown in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Tables 3</xref>, <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The effects of the nutraceutical treatment on the relative expression (fold change) of canine AD marker genes on CPEK keratinocytes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" colspan="9" rowspan="1"><bold>CPEK</bold></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Time</bold></th><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>4 h</bold></th><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>8 h</bold></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Inflamed</bold></th><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>No</bold></th><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></th><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>No</bold></th><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mix</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 &#177; 0.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39 &#177; 0.39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>9.65</bold> &#177; <bold>0.34</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5.74</bold> &#177; <bold>0.77</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>c</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62 &#177; 0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 &#177; 0.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>16.53</bold> &#177; <bold>1.44</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>c</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>e</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.67</bold> &#177; <bold>0.88</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN4"><sup>d</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>e</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN6"><sup>f</sup></xref></bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ccl5</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 &#177; 0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 &#177; 0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.47</bold> &#177; <bold>0.88</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.20</bold> &#177; <bold>1.42</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62 &#177; 0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.21 &#177; 0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.82</bold> &#177; <bold>0.89</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>e</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.68</bold> &#177; <bold>0.4</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN6"><sup>f</sup></xref></bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 &#177; 0.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 &#177; 0.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.77</bold> &#177; <bold>0.2</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.56</bold> &#177; <bold>0.03</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>c</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 &#177; 0.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51 &#177; 0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.88</bold> &#177; <bold>0.32</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>e</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.78</bold> &#177; <bold>0.4</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN6"><sup>f</sup></xref></bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 &#177; 0.41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 &#177; 0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.17</bold> &#177; <bold>0.81</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.48</bold> &#177; <bold>0.23</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>c</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 &#177; 0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 &#177; 0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.41</bold> &#177; <bold>0.04</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 &#177; 0.24</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">il31r</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 &#177; 0.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 &#177; 0.46</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73 &#177; 0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52 &#177; 0.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 &#177; 0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 &#177; 0.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.74</bold> &#177; <bold>0.46</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>c</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>e</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.72</bold> &#177; <bold>0.91</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN4"><sup>d</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>e</sup></xref></bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">il4r</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 &#177; 0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 &#177; 0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.36</bold> &#177; <bold>0.14</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.25</bold> &#177; <bold>0.21</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 &#177; 0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37 &#177; 0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.93</bold> &#177; <bold>0.22</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>c</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.95</bold> &#177; <bold>0.41</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN4"><sup>d</sup></xref></bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ctss</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 &#177; 0.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 &#177; 0.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.11 &#177; 0.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00 &#177; 0.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 &#177; 0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 &#177; 0.35</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.29</bold> &#177; <bold>0.42</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>e</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87 &#177; 0.86</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">il31</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 &#177; 0.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62 &#177; 0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 &#177; 0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 &#177; 0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 &#177; 0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 &#177; 0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 &#177; 0.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 &#177; 0.15</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><label>a</label><p>p &lt; 0.05 vs. no inflamed 4 h no mix 4 h;</p></fn><fn id="TN2"><label>b</label><p>p &lt; 0.05 vs. no inflamed 4 h yes mix 4 h;</p></fn><fn id="TN3"><label>c</label><p>p &lt; 0.05 vs. yes inflamed 4 h no mix 4 h;</p></fn><fn id="TN4"><label>d</label><p>p &lt; 0.05 vs. yes inflamed 4 h yes mix 4 h;</p></fn><fn id="TN5"><label>e</label><p>p &lt; 0.05 vs. no inflamed 8 h no mix 8 h;</p></fn><fn id="TN6"><label>f</label><p><italic toggle="yes">p &lt; 0.05 vs. yes inflamed 8 h no mix 8 h</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>The effects of the nutraceutical treatment on the relative expression (fold change) of canine AD marker genes on DH82 monocytes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" colspan="9" rowspan="1"><bold>DH82</bold></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Time</bold></th><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>4 h</bold></th><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>8 h</bold></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Inflamed</bold></th><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>No</bold></th><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></th><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>No</bold></th><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mix</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 &#177; 0.21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37 &#177; 0.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.52</bold> &#177; <bold>0.61</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.92</bold> &#177; <bold>0.11</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN8"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN9"><sup>c</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 &#177; 0.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 &#177; 0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2.60</bold> &#177; <bold>0.71</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN8"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN11"><sup>e</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80 &#177; 0.12</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ccl5</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 &#177; 0.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63 &#177; 0.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>35.89</bold> &#177; <bold>4.94</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>36.31</bold> &#177; <bold>1.69</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN8"><sup>b</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 &#177; 0.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75 &#177; 0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>27.91</bold> &#177; <bold>1.45</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN8"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN9"><sup>c</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN11"><sup>e</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>30.34</bold> &#177; <bold>1.03</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN10"><sup>d</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN11"><sup>e</sup></xref></bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 &#177; 0.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 &#177; 0.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>17.06</bold> &#177; <bold>3.06</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.27 &#177; 0.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40 &#177; 0.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 &#177; 0.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>39.90</bold> &#177; <bold>4.48</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN8"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN9"><sup>c</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN11"><sup>e</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.98</bold> &#177; <bold>0.83</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN12"><sup>f</sup></xref></bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 &#177; 0.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 &#177; 0.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.30</bold> &#177; <bold>0.64</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.30</bold> &#177; <bold>0.79</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN8"><sup>b</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 &#177; 0.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 &#177; 0.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.69</bold> &#177; <bold>0.09</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN9"><sup>c</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.65</bold> &#177; <bold>0.11</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN10"><sup>d</sup></xref></bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">il31r</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 &#177; 0.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69 &#177; 0.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>10.45</bold> &#177; <bold>0.52</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.90</bold> &#177; <bold>1.72</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN8"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN9"><sup>c</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 &#177; 0.13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44 &#177; 0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.41</bold> &#177; <bold>1.14</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN8"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN9"><sup>c</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN11"><sup>e</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.45</bold> &#177; <bold>0.56</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN11"><sup>e</sup></xref></bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ctss</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 &#177; 0.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 &#177; 0.34</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.58</bold> &#177; <bold>0.53</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.42</bold> &#177; <bold>0.43</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN8"><sup>b</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 &#177; 0.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29 &#177; 0.54</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.21</bold> &#177; <bold>1.02</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN8"><sup>b</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN11"><sup>e</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.38</bold> &#177; <bold>0.84</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN11"><sup>e</sup></xref></bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">il4r</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 &#177; 0.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 &#177; 0.72</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66 &#177; 0.53</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43 &#177; 0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 &#177; 0.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 &#177; 0.59</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 &#177; 0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 &#177; 0.17</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">il31</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 &#177; 0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 &#177; 0.35</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 &#177; 0.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 &#177; 0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 &#177; 0.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36 &#177; 0.18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.59</bold> &#177; <bold>0.05</bold><bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN8"><sup>b</sup></xref></bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36 &#177; 0.07</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN7"><label>a</label><p>p &lt; 0.05 vs. no inflamed 4 h no mix 4 h;</p></fn><fn id="TN8"><label>b</label><p>p &lt; 0.05 vs. no inflamed 4 h yes mix 4 h;</p></fn><fn id="TN9"><label>c</label><p>p &lt; 0.05 vs. yes inflamed 4 h no mix 4 h;</p></fn><fn id="TN10"><label>d</label><p>p &lt; 0.05 vs. yes inflamed 4 h yes mix 4 h;</p></fn><fn id="TN11"><label>e</label><p>p &lt; 0.05 vs. no inflamed 8 h no mix 8 h;</p></fn><fn id="TN12"><label>f</label><p><italic toggle="yes">p &lt; 0.05 vs. yes inflamed 8 h no mix 8 h</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Effects of the Nutraceutical Mixture on Cell Viability</title><p>The effects of different nutraceutical mixtures on cell viability were tested on CPEK and DH82 cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Inflamed cells, previously stimulated as shown in section Materials and Methods, were exposed to different concentrations of cannabidiol, luteolin, and piceatannol (Mix 1: cannabidiol 10 &#956;M, luteolin 10 &#956;M, and piceatannol 10 &#956;M; Mix 2: 10:25:25 &#956;M; Mix 3: 10:50:50 &#956;M, and Mix 4: 10:100:100 &#956;M) for 4 h and 8 h. One-way ANOVA showed that the exposure to the nutraceutical mixtures induced a significant change in the percentage viability of CPEK cells [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(9, 20)</sub> = 30.45], and <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> comparisons using the Bonferroni's test revealed a significant decrease in the groups treated for 4 and 8 h with Mix 4 with respect to control (4 h = 63.80 &#177; 1.17, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001; 8 h = 45.04 &#177; 5.81, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). Moreover, 8 h of exposure to Mix 2 induced a significant increase in cell viability (127.96 &#177; 3.95; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0081) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The effects of nutraceutical mixtures on the viability of inflamed cells. Inflamed <bold>(A)</bold> CPEK and <bold>(B)</bold> DH82 cells were treated with nutraceutical mixtures containing an increasing ratio of luteolin and piceatannol to cannabidiol for 4 and 8 h. Cell viability is expressed as the percentage of untreated cells (vehicle alone = 100% cell viability). The bar graphs show the mean + SEM of three independent experiments performed in triplicate. The statistically significant differences between experimental conditions and untreated control cells are shown by asterisks (*<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-606197-g0002.jpg"/></fig><p>The nutraceutical mixtures induced changes in DH82 cell viability [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(9, 20)</sub> = 22.58; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001]. The Bonferroni's comparison test revealed a decrease in cell viability with respect to control after Mix 4 treatment for 4 and 8 h (4 h = 76.87 &#177; 2.45, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001; 8 h = 68.22 &#177; 1.16, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001). Moreover, a significant decrease in the percentage viability was observed in the DH82 cells treated with Mix 3 for 8 h (79.59 &#177; 2.37; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0029) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref>). Due to its ability to enhance CPEK viability without provoking cell death in the DH82 cell line, Mix 2 was chosen for all the subsequent experiments.</p></sec><sec><title>Effects of the Nutraceutical Mixture on Transcriptional Regulation in Inflamed Cells</title><p>The consequences of the nutraceutical mixture (Mix 2) treatment after 4 and 8 h on the inflamed cells are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref> and <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> (CPEK) and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref> and <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> (DH82).</p><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The relative expression of canine atopic dermatitis (AD) marker genes after the nutraceutical mixture treatment in CPEK cells. Inflamed cells were treated (Mix yes) or not (Mix no) with the nutraceutical mixture (Mix 2) for 4 and 8 h. The bar graphs show the mean + SEM of three independent experiments performed in triplicate. The gene expression of <italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic>
<bold>(A)</bold>, <italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic>
<bold>(B)</bold>, <italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic>
<bold>(C)</bold>, and <italic toggle="yes">il4r</italic>
<bold>(D)</bold> was calculated using the delta&#8211;delta Ct (&#916;&#916;Ct) method. The statistically significant differences between experimental conditions are reported as follows: *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001 vs. no mix 4 h; &#167;&#167; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, vs. yes mix 4 h; &#176;&#176;&#176;<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001 vs. no mix 8 h.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-606197-g0003.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The relative expression of canine AD marker genes after the nutraceutical mixture treatment in DH82 cells. Inflamed cells were treated (Mix yes) or not (Mix no) with the nutraceutical mixture (Mix 2) for 4 and 8 h. The bar graphs show the mean + SEM of three independent experiments performed in triplicate. The gene expression of <italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic>
<bold>(A)</bold>, <italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic>
<bold>(B)</bold>, <italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic>
<bold>(C)</bold>, and <italic toggle="yes">il31ra</italic>
<bold>(D)</bold> was calculated using the delta&#8211;delta Ct (&#916;&#916;Ct) method. The statistically significant differences between experimental conditions are reported as follows: *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001 vs. no mix 4 h; <sup>&#167;</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs. yes mix 4 h.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-606197-g0004.jpg"/></fig><p>The statistical analysis using two-way ANOVA showed that <italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic> mRNA levels in inflamed CPEK cells were affected by time [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 19.32; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0023] and Mix 2 treatment [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 234.0; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001], with a significant interaction between these two factors [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 66.62; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001]. The Bonferroni's <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> test results are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>.</p><p>An alteration of <italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic> expression was observed in CPEK cells inflamed and exposed to the Mix 2 for 4 and 8 h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>). The two-way ANOVA showed that mRNA levels were affected by the Mix 2 treatment [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 50.79; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001] but not by time [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 1.03; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.3403], without an interaction between the two factors [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 0.11; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.7502]. The one-way ANOVA further showed that the <italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic> mRNA levels in CPEK cells were significantly affected by treatment [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(3, 8)</sub> = 17.31; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001], and <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> comparisons are indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>.</p><p>The statistical analysis using the two-way ANOVA showed that <italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic> expression in CPEK cells was also affected by treatment [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 26.19; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001] but not by time [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 2.16; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.18], without a significant interaction between these two factors [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 2.37; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.16]. The one-way ANOVA further showed that the <italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic> gene expression was affected by treatment [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(3, 8)</sub> = 10.24; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.004] (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3C</xref>). The Bonferroni's <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> test results are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3C</xref>.</p><p>The two-way ANOVA showed that the <italic toggle="yes">il4r</italic> mRNA levels in CPEK cells were not affected by the Mix 2 treatment [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 0.08; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.80] but were affected by time [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 76.64; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001], without an interaction between the two factors [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 0.15; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.71]. As mentioned earlier, time affected the <italic toggle="yes">il4r</italic> gene expression [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(3, 8)</sub> = 25.62; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001], and <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> comparisons are indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3D</xref>.</p><p>In inflamed monocytes, the <italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic> gene expression was affected by the Mix 2 treatment [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 18.80; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.002] but not by time [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 3.51; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.10], without an interaction between the factors [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 2.12; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.18]. The one-way ANOVA further showed that the <italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic> mRNA levels were affected by treatment [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(3, 8)</sub> = 8.146; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0082]. The Bonferroni's <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> test results are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>.</p><p>The gene expression of <italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic> in DH82 cells was affected by time [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 14.04; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.006] and Mix 2 treatment [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 44.48; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001] with a positive interaction between factors [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 12.87; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.007]. The <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> comparison test results are reported in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4B</xref>.</p><p>The expression of <italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic> in DH82 cells was dependent on time [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 29.59; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001] but was not affected by the Mix 2 treatment [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 0.004; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.95], with no interaction between factors [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 0.004; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.95]. The one-way ANOVA further showed that the <italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic> gene expression was affected by time [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(3, 8)</sub> = 9.86; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.005] (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4C</xref>). The Bonferroni's <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> test results are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4C</xref>.</p><p>Finally, the <italic toggle="yes">il31ra</italic> expression in DH82 cells was affected by treatment [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 18.68; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.002] but not by time [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 0.4520; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.5203], with no interaction between factors [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(1, 8)</sub> = 5.07; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.05]. The one-way ANOVA further showed that the <italic toggle="yes">il31ra</italic> gene expression was affected by the treatment [<italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub>(3, 8)</sub> = 8.07; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.008], and the <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> comparisons are indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4D</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Nutraceutical Effects on DNA Methylation</title><p>In order to evaluate whether the epigenetic mechanisms could account for the gene expression changes, we analyzed the DNA methylation at specific promoter regions. The DNA methylation analysis for each CpG site as well as the average values for inflamed cells is shown in <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Tables 5</xref>, <xref rid="T6" ref-type="table">6</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>The DNA methylation (%) changes at inflamed modulated gene promoters after the mixture treatment of inflamed CPEK cells.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>CPEK</bold></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Time</bold></th><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>4 h</bold></th><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>8 h</bold></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Inflamed</bold></th><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Mix</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.33 &#177; 0.44</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.18 &#177; 0.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.15 &#177; 4.58</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.23 &#177; 9.23</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.20 &#177; 2.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.68 &#177; 0.88</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.53 &#177; 0.60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.00 &#177; 37.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.81 &#177; 1.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.84 &#177; 1.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.18 &#177; 13.94</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.03 &#177; 17.83</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.98 &#177; 0.83</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.76 &#177; 0.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.20 &#177; 15.53</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.54 &#177; 20.69</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.23 &#177; 0.60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.83 &#177; 1.70</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.71 &#177; 6.95</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.70 &#177; 16.44</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.11 &#177; 0.65</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.66 &#177; 0.75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.35 &#177; 11.55</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.30 &#177; 17.46</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.69 &#177; 2.33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.33 &#177; 1.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.82 &#177; 1.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00 &#177; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.55 &#177; 3.47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.36 &#177; 2.33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.02 &#177; 7.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.82 &#177; 3.66</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.44 &#177; 1.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>75.22</bold> &#177; <bold>2.35</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN15"><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.09 &#177; 1.63</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.53 &#177; 7.99</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.47 &#177; 1.80</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.31 &#177; 2.92</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.56 &#177; 12.89</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.78 &#177; 2.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.80 &#177; 7.61</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.41 &#177; 8.85</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.95 &#177; 4.45</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.99 &#177; 0.93</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.94 &#177; 2.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.15 &#177; 4.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.37 &#177; 0.91</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.06 &#177; 0.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>96.43</bold> &#177; <bold>0.44</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN15"><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.83 &#177; 1.79</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.85 &#177; 1.59</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.97 &#177; 0.54</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.82 &#177; 0.58</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96,05 &#177; 2.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.05 &#177; 2.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.29 &#177; 0.94</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.21 &#177; 2.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.17 &#177; 2.78</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.17 &#177; 2.78</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.38 &#177; 1.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.79 &#177; 4.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.72 &#177; 3.80</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.72 &#177; 3.80</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.05 &#177; 1.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.25 &#177; 11.77</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.38 &#177; 9.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.38 &#177; 9.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.01 &#177; 0.89</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.44 &#177; 0.35</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.66 &#177; 1.58</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.66 &#177; 1.58</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.29 &#177; 0.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.82 &#177; 1.91</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.96 &#177; 1.83</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.14 &#177; 3.14</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN15"><label>a</label><p><italic toggle="yes">p &lt; 0.05 vs. yes inflamed 4 h no mix 4 h</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>The DNA methylation (%) changes at inflamed modulated gene promoters after the mixture treatment of inflamed DH82 cells.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>DH82</bold></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Time</bold></th><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>4 h</bold></th><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>8 h</bold></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Inflamed</bold></th><th valign="top" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Mix</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ccl2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.20 &#177; 6.39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.95 &#177; 1.80</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.91 &#177; 5.97</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.43 &#177; 1.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN17"><sup>b</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.52 &#177; 6.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>91.46</bold> &#177; <bold>1.19</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN16"><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.31 &#177; 4.53</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.29 &#177; 5.13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.20 &#177; 4.96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.93 &#177; 0.88</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.41 &#177; 5.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.13 &#177; 3.28</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.49 &#177; 3.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.06 &#177; 0.85</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.06 &#177; 0.38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.34 &#177; 0.39</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.51 &#177; 6.96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.62 &#177; 1.52</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.15 &#177; 4.97</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.60 &#177; 1.71</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.32 &#177; 2.95</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.90 &#177; 3.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.88 &#177; 4.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>84.39</bold> &#177; <bold>3.86</bold><bold><sup>b</sup><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN18"><sup>c</sup></xref></bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.54 &#177; 3.69</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.65 &#177; 0.79</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.29 &#177; 3.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.53 &#177; 0.97</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.38 &#177; 0.88</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.25 &#177; 1.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00 &#177; 0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.46 &#177; 11.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.98 &#177; 15.70</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.25 &#177; 8.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.22 &#177; 2.79</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.20 &#177; 2.40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.70 &#177; 5.50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>76.27</bold> &#177; <bold>1.33</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN16"><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>84.17</bold> &#177; <bold>0.97</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN18"><sup><bold>c</bold></sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.95 &#177; 0.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.76 &#177; 2.15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.29 &#177; 2.20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.11 &#177; 1.75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.12 &#177; 2.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.79 &#177; 1.81</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.60 &#177; 1.54</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.34 &#177; 2.94</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.39 &#177; 5.18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.71 &#177; 2.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.25 &#177; 2, 38</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">il31ra</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.88 &#177; 1.34</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.25 &#177; 4.57</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.30 &#177; 3.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.46 &#177; 0.59</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.07 &#177; 1.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>47.21</bold> &#177; <bold>2.20</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN16"><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.46 &#177; 3.59</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.49 &#177; 1.92</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.98 &#177; 0.86</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.23 &#177; 3.38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.88 &#177; 3.38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.98 &#177; 1.10</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN16"><label>a</label><p>p &lt; 0.05 vs. yes inflamed 4 h no mix 4 h;</p></fn><fn id="TN17"><label>b</label><p>p &lt; 0.05 vs. yes inflamed 4 h yes mix 4 h;</p></fn><fn id="TN18"><label>c</label><p><italic toggle="yes">p &lt; 0.05 vs. yes inflamed 8 h no mix 8 h</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In the inflamed CPEK cells exposed to the Mix 2 for 4 and 8 h, we failed to observe any overall alteration in the percentage of DNA methylation at <italic toggle="yes">ccl2, ccl17</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic> gene promoters with respect to the CpG sites analyzed. Multiple <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test comparisons showed, in inflamed cells exposed for 4 h to Mix 2, a significant decrease in the percentage of DNA methylation at the third CpG site in the promoter region of <italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic> (75.22 &#177; 2.35 Yes Mix vs. 81.44 &#177; 1.87 No Mix; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.02) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5A</xref>) and an increase in the first CpG site of <italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic> evaluated (96.43 &#177; 0.44 Yes Mix vs. 95.06 &#177; 0.43 No Mix; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.02) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5B</xref>).</p><fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>The effects of the nutraceutical mixture on CpG island methylation in CPEK cells. Inflamed cells were treated (Mix yes) or not (Mix no) with the nutraceutical mixture (Mix 2) for 4 and 8 h. The bar graphs represent the mean + SEM of three independent experiments performed in triplicate. The figure shows the methylation percentage with respect to <italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic>
<bold>(A)</bold> and <italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic>
<bold>(B)</bold> expressed as methylated cytosine/methylated cytosine + unmethylated cytosine. The statistically significant differences between experimental conditions are reported as follows: *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-606197-g0005.jpg"/></fig><p>In the inflamed DH82 cells, the <italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic> gene promoter showed a substantial methylation increase in CpG site 2 for cells treated for 4 h with respect to untreated cells (Yes Mix 91.46 &#177; 1.19, No Mix 79.52 &#177; 6.16; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.03) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6A</xref>). Moreover, an increase in the percentage of DNA methylation was observed in CpG site 6 in cells treated for 8 h (Yes Mix 84.39 &#177; 3.86) with respect to untreated cells (No Mix 73.88 &#177; 4.11; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.03) and 4 h treated cells (76.90 &#177; 3.31; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.016) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6B</xref>). A decrease in the percentage of methylation, after 8 h of Mix 2 exposure, was also observed in site 1 with respect to 4 h Mix 2-treated cells (77.43 &#177; 1.06 Yes Mix 8 h vs. 87.95 &#177; 1.80 Yes Mix 4 h; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6C</xref>). The nutraceutical mixture exposure induced a significant increase in the percentage of methylation in <italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic> site 3 after 8 h (Yes Mix 84.17 &#177; 0.97 vs. No Mix 76.27 &#177; 1.33; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6D</xref>). A significant increase in the percentage of methylation in <italic toggle="yes">il31ra</italic> site 2 was observed after 4 h in the treated cells (47.21 &#177; 2.20 vs. 43.07 &#177; 1.29 No Mix; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.047) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6E</xref>).</p><fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>The effects of the nutraceutical mixture on modulated gene CpG island methylation in DH82 cells. Inflamed cells were treated (Mix yes) or not (Mix no) with nutraceutical mixture (Mix 2) for 4 and 8 h. The bar graphs represent the mean + SEM of three independent experiments performed in triplicate. The figure shows the methylation percentage with respect to <italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic>
<bold>(A&#8211;C)</bold>, <italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic>
<bold>(D)</bold>, and <italic toggle="yes">il31ra</italic>
<bold>(E)</bold> expressed as methylated cytosine/methylated cytosine + unmethylated cytosine. The statistically significant differences between experimental conditions are reported as follows: *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05; <sup>&#167;</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, <sup>&#167;&#167;&#167;</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001 vs. yes mix 4 h; &#176;<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, &#176;&#176;<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01 vs. no mix 8 h.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-606197-g0006.jpg"/></fig><p>Moreover, the significant differences between groups, considering also those not inflamed, were evaluated through the three-way ANOVA, and multiple <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test comparisons are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Tables 1, 2</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The first goal of our study was to identify a set of inflammation markers in an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> model of canine AD. Of relevance, the transcriptional regulation of many of these markers was modulated by the nutraceutical exposure. It is well-established that the regular use of dietary supplements, such as essential fatty acids (EFAs), polyphenols, probiotics, or vitamins, has benefits for atopic animals (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Their mechanisms of action in canine AD are not completely elucidated but may involve binding of toll-like receptors and downregulation of the predominately Th2-mediated allergic response (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). The AD pharmacological treatments targeted the JAK/STAT pathway to prevent the downstream signaling of cytokines associated with the Th1/Th2 inflammatory response, an approach particularly supported by recent evidence which demonstrated the strong involvement of a Th1-mediated immune response (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). In this work, the tested mixture containing luteolin, piceatannol, and cannabidiol interfered with the expression of marker genes associated with both Th1- and Th2-mediated inflammation. In particular, it reverted <italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic> overexpression in both tested cell lines and also downregulated <italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic> expression in CPEK cells and <italic toggle="yes">il31ra</italic> expression in DH82 cells, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>. The effects of the nutraceutical mixture were also evident with respect to <italic toggle="yes">il4r</italic> gene expression in CPEK cells and <italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic> gene expression in DH82 cells, but these effects were only time dependent. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study in a canine <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> model with a focus on the evaluation of epigenetic mechanisms at the basis of gene regulation evoked by the Th1/Th2 response and nutraceutical mixture treatment. CCL2 and CCL17 belong to a superfamily of secreted proteins involved in immunoregulatory and inflammatory processes driven by the Th1 and Th2 response, respectively (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). They are highly overexpressed in canine AD provoking leukocyte activation and infiltration at the inflammatory sites in several pathologies (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). They represent new target molecules for AD therapy, together with TSLP, IL-4, and IL-31, that could dampen Th2 responses regulating the immune cell proliferation and stimulation of sensory cutaneous neurons to transmit itch sensation (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>).</p><fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>The effects of the nutraceutical mixture in a canine AD model: the nutraceutical mixture (red cross) inhibited the overexpression of homing chemokines <italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic> in stimulated CPEK cells, reducing leukocyte infiltration from blood vessels, and of <italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic>, reducing its activity in inflammatory cell recruitment and maturation. The nutraceuticals also decreased <italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic> expression in inflamed DH82 cells and downregulated <italic toggle="yes">il31ra</italic> expression, restraining Th2-mediated response amplification.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-606197-g0007.jpg"/></fig><p>The data in literature related to <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> effects of polyphenols and cannabidiol on Th1 homing cytokines support our results (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). In this regard, <italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic> expression was inhibited in human keratinocytes and skin treated with polyphenols <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>); in murine monocyte cell lines, <italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic> blunting was observed after the luteolin treatment (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) and furthermore, piceatannol and cannabidiol are both capable of inhibiting <italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic> expression in activated macrophages <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). The ability of polyphenols and cannabidiol to modulate Th2 response mediators (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>), including CCL17 and TSLP in AD models (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>), is equally well-known. Nutraceutical effects on both Th1/Th2 inflammatory mediators are uncommon, especially in dogs, whereas this represents a target for treating inflammatory stress and allergies in humans (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). The use of different active ingredients contained in food allows regulation of the different inflammation pathways involved in the chronic complex diseases. The mechanisms through which polyphenols and cannabidiol exert their gene modulatory functions are various and include epigenetic modifications (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). The results show that the tested nutraceutical mixture affected the cell lines differently, even inhibiting the same genes. The <italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic> promoter was strongly methylated in monocytes, for both exposure times and in different sites, while the mixture did not exert any effect on <italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic> promoter methylation in keratinocytes. In fact, our data agree with literature that <italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic> gene promoter methylation is widely reported in human monocytes <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>, whereas no evidence can be found for the methylation of the <italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic> promoter in keratinocytes (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). This can be explained by taking into account that the transcriptional regulation of <italic toggle="yes">ccl2</italic>, in the context of non-resolving inflammation, appears to be more related to histone modification (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). Methylation of the <italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic> gene promoter affects both cell lines; an increase of <italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic> expression <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> can be reverted with food supplements administration in patients with AD (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic>, the transcriptional regulation of <italic toggle="yes">ccl17</italic> has been associated only with the transcriptional factor STAT6, which in turn plays a fundamental role in the activation of Th2 cells for ILs secretion (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). Of relevance, both animal and human studies suggest that functional nutrition can downregulate different proinflammatory transcriptional factors, including STAT6 (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). The association between <italic toggle="yes">tslp</italic> overexpression and AD onset has already been established <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>, as well as its modulation through botanicals or probiotic supplementation (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>), Here, we demonstrated for the first time that the gene expression is ruled by epigenetic mechanisms; in fact, we observed an increase of the DNA methylation as a consequence of the nutraceutical mixture treatment. Likewise, literature reports less information on the transcriptional regulation of the <italic toggle="yes">il31ra</italic> gene despite its great relevance in AD, especially with regard to therapeutic applications; indeed, IL-31RA has such a pivotal role in the AD pathogenesis that an anti-IL-31RA monoclonal antibody was developed as a novel strategy for targeting pruritus associated with AD (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). Finally, it has been observed that Th2 cells <italic toggle="yes">in situ</italic> are exposed to considerable changes in chromatin architecture and gene expression (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>), suggesting a strong influence of the environment on their activation, and therefore, the possibility of intervention with nutritional supplements.</p><p>The health impact of natural substances depends on their pharmacokinetic features, particularly pertinent when these are administered by the oral route. Most ingredients from botanicals demonstrate very poor absorption features, and are extensively metabolized by intestinal and hepatic enzymes and interact, with often unpredictable effects, with the gut microbiota (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>). Thus, not knowing the precise oral bioavailability of the active ingredients of the tested mixture could be a limitation of the study here. After oral administration of <italic toggle="yes">Chrysanthemum morifolium</italic> extract to rats at 1.7 g/kg body weight, equivalent to 22.8 and 58.3 &#956;mol/kg of luteolin and luteolin-7-O-glucoside, respectively, luteolin and its glycosides were quickly absorbed and luteolin, luteolin monoglucoside, and luteolin monoglucuronide were easily detected in the plasma with the highest levels of pure luteolin observed 1 h after oral administration, corresponding to 0.76 &#177; 0.27 &#956;M (<xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>). Although this result appears to be quite far from the dosage used here, the absorption rate of luteolin is known to be dose- and time- dependent with plasma concentrations, increasing several-fold after repeated administration or higher doses, especially if it is coadministered with other ingredients (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>). Moreover, the levels of absorbed luteolin, detected in plasma in the free form, can reach the values used in our work (25 &#956;M) by formulation with lipid carriers (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>). With respect to piceatannol, the extent of its oral bioavailability characterizes this stilbene as also being an incompletely absorbed compound (<xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>). In any case, in rats, the absolute oral bioavailability was as high as 50.7 &#177; 15% of the administered dose (<xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>). Regarding cannabidiol, this lipophilic phytocannabinoid is poorly water soluble and subjected to extensive first-pass metabolism in the gastrointestinal tract, leading to a limited oral bioavailability of ~9% (<xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>). However, natural substances, such as polyphenols, that can interfere with phase I and/or II enzymes and/or with enteric P-glycoprotein enhance its plasma levels in rats ~6-fold (<xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>). Finally, among the three compounds tested in our investigation, cannabidiol is the only ingredient that has been studied in dogs, where its detected oral bioavailability ranged from 13 to 19% of the administered dose (<xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>, <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>). Therefore, despite our study being performed <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>, these previously reported findings suggest that our results could be considered valid with respect to a nutraceutical approach to treating canine AD.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Considering the role of the Th1/Th2 inflammatory response in the pathomechanism of AD, this canine model can be considered as an important development for the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> assessment of drugs and active ingredients. The tested nutraceutical mixture containing polyphenols and cannabinoids showed an ability to revert, through an epigenetic mechanism, the overexpression of canine AD key inflammatory genes, laying the groundwork for its application to sustained drug therapy or relapse prevention. The epigenetic modulation is involved in the induction, maintenance, heterogeneity, and recall response of memory T cells in Th1- and Th2-related immunity (<xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>), enabling the management of chronic inflammation through nutraceuticals that modulate DNA methylation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be made available by the authors, without undue reservation.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>MM, CD'A, and MP: conceptualization and writing, reviewing, and editing. MM: methodology. MM, EDV, and BB: investigation. MM and MP: formal analysis and writing (original draft preparation). FDP: visualization. CR and CD'A: supervision and project administration. All authors have contributed to and have approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that this study received funding from C.I.A.M. Srl. The funder has the following involvement with the study: the writing of this article and the decision to submit it for publication.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>This investigation was supported by C.I.A.M. Srl.</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s8"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2021.606197/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2021.606197/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Br&#233;ment</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laly</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Combarros</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guillemaille</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bourdeau</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruet</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Reliability of different sets of criteria in diagnosing canine atopic dermatitis applied to a population of 250 dogs seen in a veterinary teaching hospital</article-title>. <source>Vet Dermatol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>188</fpage>-<lpage>e59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vde.12729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30828878</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olivry</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DeBoer</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Favrot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nuttall</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Treatment of canine atopic dermatitis: 2015 updated guidelines from the International Committee on Allergic Diseases of Animals (ICADA)</article-title>. <source>BMC Vet Res.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>210</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12917-015-0514-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26276051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4537558</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marsella</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahrens</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Investigation of the effect of probiotic exposure on filaggrin expression in an experimental model of canine atopic dermatitis</article-title>. <source>Vet Dermatol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>260.e57</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vde.12006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23432387</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colitti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stefanon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gabai</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gelain</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonsembiante</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Oxidative stress and nutraceuticals in the modulation of the immune function: current knowledge in animals of veterinary interest</article-title>. <source>Antioxidants.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>28</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antiox8010028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30669304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6356544</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carlos-Reyes</surname><given-names>&#193;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#243;pez-Gonz&#225;lez</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meneses-Flores</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallardo-Rinc&#243;n</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ru&#237;z-Garc&#237;a</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marchat</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary compounds as epigenetic modulating agents in cancer</article-title>. <source>Front Genet.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fgene.2019.00079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30881375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6406035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>DYM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic and epigenetic studies of atopic dermatitis</article-title>. <source>Allergy, Asthma Clin Immunol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13223-016-0158-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27777593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5069938</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freudenberg</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olivry</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayhew</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubenstein</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajpal</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The comparison of skin transcriptomes confirms canine atopic dermatitis is a natural homologue to the human disease</article-title>. <source>J Invest Dermatol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>139</volume>:<fpage>968</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jid.2018.10.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30393079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Plager</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>SMF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Gene transcription abnormalities in canine atopic dermatitis and related human eosinophilic allergic diseases</article-title>. <source>Vet Immunol Immunopathol.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>149</volume>:<fpage>136</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetimm.2012.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22749291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4459581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schamber</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwab-Richards</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauersachs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Gene expression in the skin of dogs sensitized to the house dust mite <italic toggle="yes">Dermatophagoides farinae</italic></article-title>. <source>G3</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>1787</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.114.013003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25098772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4199687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martel</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lovato</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>B&#228;umer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olivry</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Translational animal models of atopic dermatitis for preclinical studies</article-title>. <source>Yale J Biol Med.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>389</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>402</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28955179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5612183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guttman-Yassky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>DYM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The immunology of atopic dermatitis and its reversibility with broad-spectrum and targeted therapies</article-title>. <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>139</volume>:<fpage>S65</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2017.01.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28390479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5405702</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>GDC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Oliveira Melo J&#250;nior</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Botoni</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nogueira</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Costa Val</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical-pathological and immunological biomarkers in dogs with atopic dermatitis</article-title>. <source>Vet Immunol Immunopathol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>205</volume>:<fpage>58</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetimm.2018.10.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30459002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nuttall</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McAleese</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Expression of Th1, Th2 and immunosuppressive cytokine gene transcripts in canine atopic dermatitis</article-title>. <source>Clin Exp Allergy.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>789</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2222.2002.01356.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11994107</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schlotter</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rutten</surname><given-names>VPMG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riemers</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knol</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willemse</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Lesional skin in atopic dogs shows a mixed Type-1 and Type-2 immune responsiveness</article-title>. <source>Vet Immunol Immunopathol.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>143</volume>:<fpage>20</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetimm.2011.05.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21684616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Vuyst</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salmon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evrard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lambert de Rouvroit</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poumay</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Atopic dermatitis studies through <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> models</article-title>. <source>Front Med.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>119</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2017.00119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28791291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5523664</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asahina</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A review of the roles of keratinocyte-derived cytokines and chemokines in the pathogenesis of atopic dermatitis in humans and dogs</article-title>. <source>Vet Dermatol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>16.e5</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vde.12351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27426268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fici</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitton-Fry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Oclacitinib (APOQUEL(&#174;)) is a novel Janus kinase inhibitor with activity against cytokines involved in allergy</article-title>. <source>J Vet Pharmacol Ther.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>317</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvp.12101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24495176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4265276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iuchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Potential beneficial effects of wine flavonoids on allergic diseases</article-title>. <source>Diseases.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/diseases7010008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30650667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6473930</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Knowledge, attitudes, and perceptions of cannabinoids in the dermatology community</article-title>. <source>J Drugs Dermatol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1273</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30586258</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gotovina</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fazekas-Singer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hufnagl</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bianchini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Canine macrophages can like human macrophages be <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> activated toward the M2a subtype relevant in allergy</article-title>. <source>Dev Comp Immunol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>82</volume>:<fpage>118</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dci.2018.01.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29329953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stott</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavender</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pennino</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Durham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt-Weber</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Human IL-31 is induced by IL-4 and promotes TH2-driven inflammation</article-title>. <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>132</volume>:<fpage>446</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>54.e5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2013.03.050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23694808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrosino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verde</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allar&#224;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iuvone</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Marzo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anti-inflammatory properties of cannabidiol, a nonpsychotropic cannabinoid, in experimental allergic contact dermatitis</article-title>. <source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>365</volume>:<fpage>652</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/jpet.117.244368</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29632236</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greiner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Witzeneder</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmetterer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eisenwort</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schiefer</surname><given-names>A-I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>CCL2 is a KIT D816V-dependent modulator of the bone marrow microenvironment in systemic mastocytosis</article-title>. <source>Blood.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>129</volume>:<fpage>371</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2016-09-739003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27856463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7115851</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasiadi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Therianou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Theoharides</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Luteolin inhibits human keratinocyte activation and decreases NF-&#954;B induction that is increased in psoriatic skin</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e90739</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24587411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3938790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jegal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Stellera chamaejasme</italic> and its main compound luteolin 7- O -glucoside alleviates skin lesions in oxazolone- and 2,4-dinitrochlorobenzene-stimulated murine models of atopic dermatitis</article-title>. <source>Planta Med.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>85</volume>:<fpage>583</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/a-0746-8698</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30273950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheriff</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khorasani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The potential role of cannabinoids in dermatology</article-title>. <source>J Dermatol Treat.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>839</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09546634.2019.1675854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31599175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Piceatannol inhibits <italic toggle="yes">P. acnes</italic>&#8211;induced keratinocyte proliferation and migration by downregulating oxidative stress and the inflammatory response</article-title>. <source>Inflammation.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>347</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>57</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10753-019-01125-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31728743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marchegiani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fruganti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spaterna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalle Vedove</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bachetti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Massimini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of nutritional supplementation on canine dermatological disorders</article-title>. <source>Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>38</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vetsci7020038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32260299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7355824</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenkrantz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pilot evaluation of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecium</italic> SF68 as adjunctive therapy for oclacitinib-responsive adult atopic dermatitis in dogs</article-title>. <source>J Small Anim Pract.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>60</volume>:<fpage>499</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>506</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsap.13042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31257599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anturaniemi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zald&#237;var-L&#243;pez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Savelkoul</surname><given-names>HFJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hielm-Bj&#246;rkman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of atopic dermatitis and diet on the skin transcriptome in staffordshire bull terriers</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>552251</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2020.552251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33178726</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7596200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Witzel-Rollins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becvarova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Werre</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cadiergues</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Non-controlled, open-label clinical trial to assess the effectiveness of a dietetic food on pruritus and dermatologic scoring in atopic dogs</article-title>. <source>BMC Vet Res.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>220</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12917-019-1929-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31253166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6599232</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gedon</surname><given-names>NKY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Atopic dermatitis in cats and dogs: a difficult disease for animals and owners</article-title>. <source>Clin Transl Allergy.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>41</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13601-018-0228-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30323921</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6172809</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Roock</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Elk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Dijk</surname><given-names>MEA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Timmerman</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rijkers</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prakken</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Lactic acid bacteria differ in their ability to induce functional regulatory T cells in humans</article-title>. <source>Clin Exp Allergy.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>103</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2222.2009.03344.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19817754</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Atopic dermatitis and the intestinal microbiota in humans and dogs</article-title>. <source>Vet Med Sci.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>105</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/vms3.24</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29067183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5645856</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>JAK/STAT inhibitors for the treatment of atopic dermatitis</article-title>. <source>J Dermatolog Treat.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09546634.2019.1577549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30703333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kieslinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swoboda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pratscher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolfesberger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgener</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Companion animals as models for inhibition of STAT3 and STAT5</article-title>. <source>Cancers.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>2035</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cancers11122035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31861073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6966487</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hulshof</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hack</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasnoe</surname><given-names>QCJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dontje</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakasa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riethm&#252;ller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A minimally invasive tool to study immune response and skin barrier in children with atopic dermatitis</article-title>. <source>Br J Dermatol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>180</volume>:<fpage>621</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bjd.16994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29989151</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Storan</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Gorman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steinhoff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Role of cytokines and chemokines in itch</article-title>. <source>Handb Exp Pharmacol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>226</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-662-44605-8_9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25861779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klonowska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gle&#324;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowicki</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trzeciak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>New cytokines in the pathogenesis of atopic dermatitis-new therapeutic targets</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>3086</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms19103086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30304837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6213458</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joffre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>C-C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thete</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zlatanova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Activation of CB 1 R promotes lipopolysaccharide-induced IL-10 secretion by monocytic myeloid-derived suppressive cells and reduces acute inflammation and organ injury</article-title>. <source>J Immunol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>204</volume>:<fpage>3339</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.2000213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32385136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7276941</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yahfoufi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alsadi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jambi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The immunomodulatory and anti-inflammatory role of polyphenols</article-title>. <source>Nutrients.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1618</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu10111618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30400131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6266803</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wedler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weston</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rausenberger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Butterweck</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> modulation of inflammatory target gene expression by a polyphenol-enriched fraction of rose oil distillation waste water</article-title>. <source>Fitoterapia.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>114</volume>:<fpage>56</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fitote.2016.08.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27575323</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carbone</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lulli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Passarelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pastore</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Topical plant polyphenols prevent type I interferon signaling in the skin and suppress contact hypersensitivity</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>2652</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms19092652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30200670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6164211</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>T-W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>K-T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Luteolin inhibits recruitment of monocytes and migration of Lewis lung carcinoma cells by suppressing chemokine (C-C motif) ligand 2 expression in tumor-associated macrophage</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>470</volume>:<fpage>101</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2016.01.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26766793</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Er&#228;salo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#228;m&#228;l&#228;inen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lepp&#228;nen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#228;ki-Opas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laavola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haavikko</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Natural Stilbenoids Have Anti-inflammatory properties <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> and down-regulate the production of inflammatory mediators NO, IL6, and MCP1 possibly in a PI3K/Akt-dependent manner</article-title>. <source>J Nat Prod.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>81</volume>:<fpage>1131</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jnatprod.7b00384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29726680</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muthumalage</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cannabidiol differentially regulates basal and LPS-induced inflammatory responses in macrophages, lung epithelial cells, and fibroblasts</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Appl Pharmacol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>382</volume>:<fpage>114713</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.taap.2019.114713</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31437494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6917034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piao</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyeon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eom</surname><given-names>J-E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Gallic acid alleviates nasal inflammation via activation of Th1 and inhibition of Th2 and Th17 in a mouse model of allergic rhinitis</article-title>. <source>Int Immunopharmacol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>512</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2019.02.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30884431</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gugliandolo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cordaro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Amico</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peritore</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Licata</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Canine atopic dermatitis: role of luteolin as new natural treatment</article-title>. <source>Vet Med Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>926</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/vms3.325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32741111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7738746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>H-K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>C-S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anti-allergic and anti-inflammatory effects of kuwanon G and morusin on MC/9 mast cells and HaCaT keratinocytes</article-title>. <source>Molecules.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>265</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules24020265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30642008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6359505</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caglayan Sozmen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karaman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cilaker Micili</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arikan Ayyildiz</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagriyanik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Resveratrol ameliorates 2,4-dinitrofluorobenzene-induced atopic dermatitis-like lesions through effects on the epithelium</article-title>. <source>PeerJ.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e1889</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.1889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27069818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4824908</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahimi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassanzadeh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soleimani</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sathyapalan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Targeting the balance of T helper cell responses by curcumin in inflammatory and autoimmune states</article-title>. <source>Autoimmun Rev.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>738</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>48</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.autrev.2019.05.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31059845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajneesh</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Padwad</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prunus cerasoides fruit extract ameliorates inflammatory stress by modulation of iNOS pathway and Th1/Th2 immune homeostasis in activated murine macrophages and lymphocytes</article-title>. <source>Inflammopharmacology.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>1483</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10787-018-0448-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29429000</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garc&#237;a-Mart&#237;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrido-Rodr&#237;guez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Navarrete</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Del</surname><given-names>R&#237;o C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellido</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Appendino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>EHP-101, an oral formulation of the cannabidiol aminoquinone VCE-004.8, alleviates bleomycin-induced skin and lung fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Biochem Pharmacol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>157</volume>:<fpage>304</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bcp.2018.07.047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30076848</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pucci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rapino</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Francesco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dainese</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Addario</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maccarrone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epigenetic control of skin differentiation genes by phytocannabinoids</article-title>. <source>Br J Pharmacol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>170</volume>:<fpage>581</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bph.12309</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23869687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3791996</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sureda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belwal</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#199;etinkaya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#252;ntar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tejada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Polyphenols in the treatment of autoimmune diseases</article-title>. <source>Autoimmun Rev.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>647</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>57</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.autrev.2019.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31059841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6588481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerrick</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerrick</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wheelan</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yegnasubramanian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaffee</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Transcriptional profiling identifies novel regulators of macrophage polarization</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>e0208602</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0208602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30532146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6286176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sy</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lue</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shih</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial assessing the oral administration of a heat-treated lactobacillus paracasei supplement in infants with atopic dermatitis receiving topical corticosteroid therapy</article-title>. <source>Skin Pharmacol Physiol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>201</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000499436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31117100</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiguchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saika</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kishioka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epigenetic regulation of CC-chemokine ligand 2 in nonresolving inflammation</article-title>. <source>Biomol Concepts.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>265</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/bmc-2014-0022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25372758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruickshank</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giacomantonio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marcato</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McFarland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gujar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dying to be noticed: epigenetic regulation of immunogenic cell death for cancer immunotherapy</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>654</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2018.00654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29666625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5891575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al Mijan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Diets, functional foods, and nutraceuticals as alternative therapies for inflammatory bowel disease: present status and future trends</article-title>. <source>World J Gastroenterol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>2673</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3748/wjg.v24.i25.2673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29991873</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6034142</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus rhamnosus</italic> on allergic march model by suppressing Th2, Th17, and TSLP responses via CD4+CD25+Foxp3+ Tregs</article-title>. <source>Clin Immunol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>153</volume>:<fpage>178</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>86</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clim.2014.04.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24769377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fermented <italic toggle="yes">Morinda citrifolia</italic> (Noni) Alleviates DNCB-induced atopic dermatitis in NC/Nga mice through modulating immune balance and skin barrier function</article-title>. <source>Nutrients.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>249</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu12010249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31963703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7019744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Otsuka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kabashima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Interleukin-31 and interleukin-31 receptor: new therapeutic targets for atopic dermatitis</article-title>. <source>Exp Dermatol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>327</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/exd.13533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29524262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tibbitt</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coquet</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The metabolic requirements of Th2 cell differentiation</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>2318</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2019.02318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31611881</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6776632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buglio</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Georgakis</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanabuchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khaskhely</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Vorinostat inhibits STAT6-mediated TH2 cytokine and TARC production and induces cell death in Hodgkin lymphoma cell lines</article-title>. <source>Blood.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>112</volume>:<fpage>1424</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2008-01-133769</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18541724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2515130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lupancu</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fleetwood</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Epigenetic and transcriptional regulation of IL4-induced CCL17 production in human monocytes and murine macrophages</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>293</volume>:<fpage>11415</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.RA118.002416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29871928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6065189</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manach</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scalbert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morand</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>R&#233;m&#233;sy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jim&#233;nez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Polyphenols: Food sources and bioavailability</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>79</volume>:<fpage>727</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>47</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ajcn/79.5.727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15113710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosoya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimoi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Absorption and metabolism of luteolin and its glycosides from the extract of <italic toggle="yes">Chrysanthemum morifolium</italic> flowers in rats and Caco-2 cells</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>7693</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.5b00232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25843231</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacokinetic comparisons of different combinations of yigan jiangzhi formula in rats: simultaneous determination of fourteen components by UPLC-MS/MS</article-title>. <source>J Anal Methods Chem.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>2020</volume>:<fpage>9353975</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2020/9353975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32280556</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7114774</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nanostructured lipid carriers versus microemulsions for delivery of the poorly water-soluble drug luteolin</article-title>. <source>Int J Pharm.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>476</volume>:<fpage>169</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>77</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpharm.2014.09.052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25280882</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roupe</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Y&#225;&#241;ez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>XW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacokinetics of selected stilbenes: rhapontigenin, piceatannol and pinosylvin in rats</article-title>. <source>J Pharm Pharmacol.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>1443</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1211/jpp.58.11.0004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17132206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tringali</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spatafora</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A simple and sensitive HPLC-UV method for the quantification of piceatannol analog trans-3,5,3&#8242;,4&#8242;-tetramethoxystilbene in rat plasma and its application for a pre-clinical pharmacokinetic study</article-title>. <source>J Pharm Biomed Anal.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>679</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpba.2009.09.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19836182</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cherniakov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Izgelov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Domb</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of Pro NanoLipospheres (PNL) formulation containing natural absorption enhancers on the oral bioavailability of delta-9-tetrahydrocannabinol (THC) and cannabidiol (CBD) in a rat model</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pharm Sci.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>109</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejps.2017.07.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28736128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samara</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bialer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mechoulam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacokinetics of cannabidiol in dogs</article-title>. <source>Drug Metab Dispos.</source> (<year>1988</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>469</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>72</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2900742</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tufarelli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pero</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Infascelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Della Rocca</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Salvo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hemp in veterinary medicine: from feed to drug</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>387</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2020.00387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32850997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7399642</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Onodera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kokubo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epigenetic and transcriptional regulation in the induction, maintenance, heterogeneity, and recall-response of effector and memory Th2 Cells</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>2929</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2018.02929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30619290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6299044</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>