<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8546189</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8546189.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8546189</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8546189</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34712721</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.726117</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Managing African Swine Fever: Assessing the Potential of Camera Traps in Monitoring Wild Boar Occupancy Trends in Infected and Non-infected Zones, Using Spatio-Temporal Statistical Models</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bollen</surname><given-names initials="M">Martijn</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1367100/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neyens</surname><given-names initials="T">Thomas</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1465892/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fajgenblat</surname><given-names initials="M">Maxime</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1465913/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Waele</surname><given-names initials="V">Val&#233;rie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Licoppe</surname><given-names initials="A">Alain</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manet</surname><given-names initials="B">Beno&#238;t</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Casaer</surname><given-names initials="J">Jim</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1374692/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beenaerts</surname><given-names initials="N">Natalie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1465920/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Centre for Environmental Sciences, UHasselt &#8211; Hasselt University</institution>, <addr-line>Hasselt</addr-line>, <country>Belgium</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Data Science Institute, UHasselt &#8211; Hasselt University</institution>, <addr-line>Hasselt</addr-line>, <country>Belgium</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Research Institute Nature and Forest, Brussels</institution>, <country>Belgium</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Laboratory of Aquatic Ecology, Evolution and Conservation, KU Leuven &#8211; Leuven University</institution>, <addr-line>Leuven</addr-line>, <country>Belgium</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Department of Natural and Agricultural Environment Studies, Public Service of Wallonia</institution>, <addr-line>Gembloux</addr-line>, <country>Belgium</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Francisco Ruiz-Fons, Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Cient&#237;ficas (CSIC), Spain</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Fedor Korennoy, Federal Center for Animal Health (FGBI ARRIAH), Russia; Denis V. Kolbasov, Federal Research Center of Virology and Microbiology, Russia</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Martijn Bollen <email>martijn.bollen@uhasselt.be</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Veterinary Epidemiology and Economics, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">374996</issue-id><elocation-id>726117</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>9</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>27</day><month>10</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-09-20 13:25:20.370"><day>20</day><month>09</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2021 Bollen, Neyens, Fajgenblat, De Waele, Licoppe, Manet, Casaer and Beenaerts.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Bollen, Neyens, Fajgenblat, De Waele, Licoppe, Manet, Casaer and Beenaerts</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-08-726117.pdf"/><abstract><p>The recent spreading of African swine fever (ASF) over the Eurasian continent has been acknowledged as a serious economic threat for the pork industry. Consequently, an extensive body of research focuses on the epidemiology and control of ASF. Nevertheless, little information is available on the combined effect of ASF and ASF-related control measures on wild boar (<italic toggle="yes">Sus scrofa</italic>) population abundances. This is crucial information given the role of the remaining wild boar that act as an important reservoir of the disease. Given the high potential of camera traps as a non-invasive method for ungulate trend estimation, we assess the effectiveness of ASF control measures using a camera trap network. In this study, we focus on a major ASF outbreak in 2018&#8211;2020 in the South of Belgium. This outbreak elicited a strong management response, both in terms of fencing off a large infected zone as well as an intensive culling regime. We apply a Bayesian multi-season site-occupancy model to wild boar detection/non-detection data. Our results show that (1) occupancy rates at the onset of our monitoring period reflect the ASF infection status; (2) ASF-induced mortality and culling efforts jointly lead to decreased occupancy over time; and (3) the estimated mean total extinction rate ranges between 22.44 and 91.35%, depending on the ASF infection status. Together, these results confirm the effectiveness of ASF control measures implemented in Wallonia (Belgium), which has regained its disease-free status in December 2020, as well as the usefulness of a camera trap network to monitor these effects.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>African swine fever</kwd><kwd>camera traps</kwd><kwd>occupancy</kwd><kwd>spatio-temporal</kwd><kwd>Bayesian inference</kwd><kwd>Stan</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="3"/><ref-count count="38"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="6941"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>African swine fever (ASF), a viral disease that causes high mortality among domestic pigs (<italic toggle="yes">Sus scrofa domesticus</italic>) and wild boar (<italic toggle="yes">Sus scrofa</italic>), originates from East Africa and is regarded as one of the most important threats to the European pig industry. Recently, ASF has been re-introduced to the wild boar populations on the European mainland, presumably due to infected meat spills in the environment (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Most likely, this spillage mediated the recent spread of ASF through a new epidemiological cycle, designated the wild boar-habitat cycle, which involves both direct and indirect viral transmissions. Direct transmissions occur through contacts among wild boar, whereas indirect cases result from viral reservoirs in the environment, such as ASF-infected carcasses (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). This new role of wild boar in the epidemiology of ASF has led to new management guidelines of wild boar populations in infected areas (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Management strategies include continuous carcass removal from the infected zone, coupled with intense culling of wild boar within a buffer zone (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Together, these strategies are expected to effectively reduce ASF transmission by removing viral sources from the environment in the infected zone and by depleting the susceptible wild boar population in the buffer zone. The latter is essential, since the number of individuals remaining in the host population of the buffer zone will determine the probability of the spread to a non-infected area, i.e., host threshold density. In the infected zone, after the epidemic phase, culling of the remaining wild boar will determine the probability for the disease to become endemic, i.e., critical community size (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). To evaluate measures aimed at counteracting ASF, sound information on the joint effect of the disease and culling efforts on population trends of wild boar within the managed areas is crucial (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>).</p><p>Over the last decade, the use of remote cameras, henceforth referred to as camera traps (CTs), has become popular when monitoring trends in medium-size to large-size mammals, including wild boar (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Photographic captures (i.e., detections) by CTs can be translated into information on the distribution and density of a focal species. However, density estimation by CTs is still hindered by imperfect detection in many cases (i.e., not detecting a focal species, when present) (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Given the elusiveness and nocturnality of wild boar, it is among the species subjected to severely limited detectability. Moreover, traditional density estimation methodology requires individual identification, hence cannot be applied to many common species that lack natural markings, including wild boar (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Statistical frameworks such as the random encounter model (REM) allow for density estimation of unmarked populations, while accounting for imperfect detection, using CTs (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). However, the need for auxiliary data collection restricts the use of REM in many cases (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Occupancy models on the other hand overcome both imperfect detectability and the need for individual recognition of animals, without requiring additional information. They proceed by simultaneously estimating site-occupancy and the probability of detecting a focal species, given its presence (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Extending occupancy models to so-called multi-season site-occupancy (MSO) models, enables estimating rates expressing population changes through time. One of these rates, the extinction rate, is of prime interest when assessing the combined effect of a viral disease, such as ASF, and culling efforts on a host population.</p><p>In the current study we evaluate wild boar population trends throughout the recent ASF epidemic in Wallonia (Belgium), using a camera trap network. The first cases of this outbreak were reported on September 13, 2018 (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Further, we aim to uncover the roles of ASF and control measures (i.e., primarily culling efforts) on inferred population dynamics. To our knowledge, only one study so far attempted to quantify the effects of ASF on a wild boar population using CTs (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Here, we develop a different statistical framework, that can be adapted to model management strategies of multiple species, in diverse settings. We apply it in our study of wild boar population dynamics in an ASF-infected and non-infected zone. The latter has been subjected to an intensive culling regime (January 2019&#8211;March 2021) during the entire ASF episode. While in the infected zone, both ASF-induced mortality and culling efforts determine wild boar extinction rates. Moreover, this zone is fenced off from the surrounding non-infected zones. Using detection/non-detection data (March 2019&#8211;May 2020) from 92 CTs, we estimate monthly site-occupancy of wild boar in both ASF-infected and non-infected zones, through a Bayesian MSO. In addition, we provide wild boar distribution maps for the area under study. Finally, we use these results to draw conclusions about the ASF management in Wallonia (Belgium). We believe this case is important beyond its own setting for two reasons: (i) wildlife managers are often asked by funders to justify the use of CT networks, hence being able to show the usefulness of CTs to monitor population trends is important; (ii) authorities need to assess the effectiveness of control measures taken to prevent the spreading of ASF. Camera trapping is an understudied method that could provide valuable information on the effectiveness of these measures.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Study Area</title><p>The study area (longitudes: 5.2847&#176;E - 5.8156&#176;E; latitudes: 49.5485&#176;N - 49.6955&#176;N) is situated between the cities of Virton (South), Florenville (Northwest) and Arlon (Northeast), and has been subdivided into three management zones. An ASF-infected zone (red), a non-infected zone, i.e., free of ASF (turquoise) and a zone that was excluded from the study due to its ambiguous disease status and limited number of deployments (gray), see <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. It has a total forested area of 223 km<sup>2</sup>, part of a larger ASF management zone of 1,106 km<sup>2</sup> encompassing a total of 572 forested km<sup>2</sup>. The study area has a cool temperate and moist climate, with a mean annual temperature of 8.94&#176;C and 966 mm rainfall (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). The landscape is characterized by rugged terrain crossed by numerous rivers and fragmented by several roads, while its vegetation is dominated by deciduous forests.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Map of the study area with the overlaying hexagonal grids. Camera deployments are indicated by the black dots. Black lines represent fences. Colors represent the African swine fever management zones; ASF-infected (red), non-infected (turquoise) and excluded (gray). The inset map (bottom) shows the study area within Belgium.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-726117-g0001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Camera Trap Network and Data</title><p>Within the study area, a CT network was deployed since March 2019. The network consists out of 97 Snapshot Extra Black 12.0 l HD (D&#246;rr) cameras. For more detailed information on the camera specifications, consult <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 1</xref>.</p><p>Camera placement was done according to a stratified random sampling scheme. Proportional to its area, a number of cameras was deployed in each management zone (stratum) (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 2</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">A posteriori</italic>, the strata were superimposed by a hexagonal grid layer (x-spacing of 500 m, area of 21.65 ha/ site) ensuring that each camera was assigned a unique grid cell (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Throughout the sampling period, camera locations were fixed. All cameras were installed by mounting them on trees ~50 centimeters above ground, facing North. We did not use baiting, nor did we select for trails. Monthly check-ups were performed to determine battery levels and to verify camera operability. Each camera trigger was followed by a series of five photographs, without a delay between consecutive triggers. All images were manually annotated, using the Agouti software platform (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). After omitting data from the excluded zone (5 deployments; 5.15%) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>), we retained data from 92 deployments between March 2019 and May 2020, resulting in a total of 42,136 24-h observation periods.</p><p>We considered three classes of covariates, potentially important to explain wild boar population trends: (1) time, (2) land use, and (3) infection status. As will be clarified in section Statistical Model, for time, we evaluated three alternative definitions: (1.i) month since the start of the monitoring program (observation month; <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>), (1.ii) a binary variable indicating whether the observation month is in April&#8211;September (biannual; <italic toggle="yes">BIA</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></sub>), and (1.iii) a similar indicator variable consisting of four seasonal periods, i.e., Spring, Summer, Autumn and Winter (quarterly; <italic toggle="yes">QRT</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></sub>). For land use, we only considered a single covariate: the (<italic toggle="yes">z</italic>-scored) proportion of broad-leaved forest land cover class (<italic toggle="yes">BL</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></sub>), which was extracted from the LifeWatch Ecotope dataset (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Finally, infection status (<italic toggle="yes">ASF</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub>) is encoded as follows: 1 when a site is within the ASF-infected zone, 0 otherwise (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Note that the infection status for each zone was assigned, based on the occurrence of ASF virus (ASFV)-positive carcasses within a zone. We refer readers wanting to access the ASFV occurrence data or searching for more information on the dispersal history and dynamics of the ASFV in Belgium to Dellicour et al. (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). An overview of all covariates discussed in this section and <italic toggle="yes">a priori</italic> defined models are given in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. For model-specific predictions [P (<italic toggle="yes">Model</italic>)] consult <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 3</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">A priori</italic> defined occupancy (step 1) and detection (step 2) models.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Model</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Logit<bold>(</bold>&#968;<sub>it</sub><bold>)</bold></bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Logit<bold>(</bold><italic toggle="yes">p</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></sub><bold>)</bold></bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<bold>Occupancy models (step 1)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#968;1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="M1" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#945;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#945;<sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#968;2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="M2" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#945;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#183;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#968;3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="M3" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#945;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#183;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#183;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#968;4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="M4" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#945;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#183;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#183;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#183;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#968;</bold>
<bold>5</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="M5" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#945;</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#183;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#183;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#183;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#183;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#183;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#183;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#160;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#968;(6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="M6" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#945;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#183;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#183;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<bold>Detection models (step 2)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Top-ranking &#968; &#8211; model from step 1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#945;<sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="M7" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#945;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#183;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="M8" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#945;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#183;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>p4</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="M9" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#945;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">Top-ranked models for each step are indicated in bold. ASF infection status (ASF<sub>i</sub>), z-scored proportion of broad-leaved tree land cover class (BL<sub>i</sub>), observation month (t), biannual (spring &#8211; summer, autumn &#8211; winter) seasons (BIA<sub>t</sub>), quarterly (spring, summer, autumn, winter) seasons (QRT<sub>t</sub>), smooth function for temporal variation f<sub>1</sub>(t), smooth function for spatial variation f<sub>2</sub>(lon, lat). Intercepts and slope parameters are given by &#945; and &#946;, respectively</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Statistical Model</title><p>We analyse the CT data using a longitudinal multi-season occupancy model (MSO), defined as a state-space model (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>), to make inference on wild boar's site-occupancy. The sampling grids used are smaller than wild boar's home range, hence occupancy should be interpreted as habitat use (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Detection histories were constructed using the R package <italic toggle="yes">CamtrapR</italic> (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). For site <italic toggle="yes">i</italic> = 1, 2, &#8230;, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>, at survey day <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> = 1, 2, &#8230;, <italic toggle="yes">J</italic>, in observation month <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> = 1, 2, &#8230;, <italic toggle="yes">T</italic>, the detection history is 1 when wild boar were observed during a 24-h period (<italic toggle="yes">y</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ijt</italic></sub> = 1) or 0 when no boars are caught on camera that day (<italic toggle="yes">y</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ijt</italic></sub> = 0). These are assumed to follow a Bernoulli distribution, such that,</p><disp-formula id="E1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M10" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where <italic toggle="yes">p</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ijt</italic></sub> is the probability of detecting the focal species and <italic toggle="yes">z</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">it</italic></sub> is the latent occupancy status (unoccupied <italic toggle="yes">z</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">it</italic></sub> = 0; occupied <italic toggle="yes">z</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">it</italic></sub> = 1) at site <italic toggle="yes">i</italic> during observation month <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>. Note that we do not use survey day-specific, nor site-specific covariates to model <italic toggle="yes">p</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ijt</italic></sub>, hence the detection probability simplifies to <italic toggle="yes">p</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></sub>. The occupancy status is modeled as,</p><disp-formula id="E2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M11" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Where &#968;<sub><italic toggle="yes">it</italic></sub> is the occupancy probability, from now on simply referred to as &#8220;occupancy,&#8221; at site <italic toggle="yes">i</italic> during observation month <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>. Unlike dynamic MSO, we do not take probabilities of wild boar surviving or colonizing a site <italic toggle="yes">i</italic> from observation month <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> to <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>+1 into account, as the high degree of zero-inflation in our data complicates joint inference on all these processes. We define &#977;<sub><italic toggle="yes">l</italic></sub> = {<italic toggle="yes">p</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ijt</italic></sub>, &#968;<sub><italic toggle="yes">it</italic></sub>}, which collects all processes that will be modeled as a function of covariates and random effects, using a logit link. A general model formulation for &#977;<sub><italic toggle="yes">l</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">l</italic> = 1, 2, can be defined as</p><disp-formula id="E3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M12" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#977;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#945;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where &#945;<sub><italic toggle="yes">l</italic></sub> are intercepts, &#946;<sub><italic toggle="yes">l</italic></sub> are vectors of process-specific slope parameters with their corresponding covariate matrix <italic toggle="yes">X</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">l</italic></sub>. The term <italic toggle="yes">u</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">l</italic></sub> models spatially unstructured overdispersion as a normally distributed random effect, <italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">l</italic>, 1</sub> is a smooth function modeling temporal variation for each observation month <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">l</italic>, 2</sub> is an isotropic two-dimensional smooth function modeling spatial variation in occupancy patterns, for the longitude <italic toggle="yes">lon</italic> and latitude <italic toggle="yes">lat</italic> of each site's centroid. Both <italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">l</italic>, 1</sub>and <italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">l</italic>, 2</sub> are modeled using Gaussian processes (GP), with an exponentiated quadratic covariance function. While <italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">l</italic>, 1</sub> uses an exact GP, we model <italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">l</italic>, 2</sub> by means of the Hilbert space reduced-rank Gaussian process (HSGP) approach as the number of sites in our study area is large (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). This approach yields substantial speed gains when dealing with large number of sites through approximate series expansions of the GP's covariance function.</p><p>Model fitting was performed using <italic toggle="yes">Stan</italic> (via the R package <italic toggle="yes">rstan</italic>), a probabilistic programming language that enables Bayesian estimation through a dynamic Hamiltonian Monte Carlo (HMC) sampler (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). For each MCMC iteration, we also derive site-specific growth rates <inline-formula><mml:math id="M13" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#955;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula>, average monthly growth rates <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>&#955;</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#8722;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>&#8721;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#955;</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and total growth rates <inline-formula><mml:math id="M15" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#955;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> in site-occupancy (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). We choose weakly informative <italic toggle="yes">Student t</italic>(3, 0, 5) priors for all the regression parameters {&#945;<sub><italic toggle="yes">l</italic></sub>, &#946;<sub><italic toggle="yes">l</italic></sub>} and a nonnegative <italic toggle="yes">Student t</italic><sup>+</sup>(3, 0, 5) prior for the marginal standard deviation of the hyperparameters &#963;<sub><italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub>1</sub></sub> and &#963;<sub><italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub>2</sub></sub> of the GPs. For the scale parameters &#961;<sub><italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub>1</sub></sub> and &#961;<sub><italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub>2</sub></sub> of the GPs, we, respectively, used an inverse gamma <italic toggle="yes">IG</italic>(10.9, 4.00) and a generalized inverse Gaussian <italic toggle="yes">GIG</italic>(3, 12, 0.01), ensuring most prior evidence is placed on scales that can be estimated from the data (i.e., larger than the smallest difference between any pair of CT locations and smaller than the largest difference between any of these pairs).</p><p>The full model that would contain two random effects terms for each of these processes, in addition to covariates, was computationally infeasible to fit and, furthermore, does not necessarily reflect a sensible data-generating process. Hence, we consider a set of sensible reduced models based on ecologically plausible considerations, preventing multicollinearity, and computational feasibility (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Multicollinearity was avoided by including one of two covariates, when their Spearman rho correlation estimate |<italic toggle="yes">r</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">s</italic></sub>| &lt; 0.6. Subsequently, we select the most appropriate model by means of a model selection procedure.</p><p>Model selection through approximate leave-one-out cross-validation was performed using the R package <italic toggle="yes">loo</italic> (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Following the authors' recommendations, leave-one-out (LOO) expected log-predictive densities were used to rank our <italic toggle="yes">a priori</italic> selected candidate models (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Our ranking procedure consists of a two-step approach. First, the top-ranked occupancy model is retained by comparing LOO for selected combinations of fixed and random effects at the occupancy (&#968;) level, while keeping detectability (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>) constant (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, step 1). Secondly, the detection process is modeled using fixed effects only, while adopting the top-ranked occupancy model from step 1 (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, step 2).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Model selection of candidate occupancy models (step 1) and detection models (step 2).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Model</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>P<sub><bold>D</bold></sub></bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SE(P<sub><bold>D</bold></sub>)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>LOO</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SE(LOO)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#916; LOO</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SE(&#916; LOO)</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>Occupancy models (step 1)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#968;(5)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.55</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.84</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;992.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#968;(4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.49</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;995.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;3.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.38</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#968;(6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;999.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;6.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.56</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#968;(3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.92</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.44</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1,044.70</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;52.41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.84</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#968;(2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.64</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1,045.91</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;53.62</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.94</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#968;(1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.83</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1,049.73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;57.44</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.45</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="7" rowspan="1">
<bold>Detection models (step 2)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>(4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.93</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;979.88</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>(2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;985.54</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;5.66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.41</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>(1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.55</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.84</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;992.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;12.40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.88</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>(3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.92</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;993.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;13.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.49</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">Note that P<sub>D</sub> represents the effective number of parameters rather than the true number of parameters. Leave-one-out expected log-predictive density (LOO), in addition to the difference in LOO between each model and the top-ranked model (&#916; LOO), along with their standard errors (SE) are presented</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>All models were fitted using four parallel MCMC chains with 4,000 iterations, which included 2,000 iterations that were discarded as burn-in iterations for all candidate models; this always resulted in satisfactory convergence (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>), following the guidelines by Vehtari et al. (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). After the selection procedure, a prior sensitivity analysis was performed for the top-ranked model from step 2, by comparing results of the default prior specification with <italic toggle="yes">Student t</italic>(3, 0, 2.5) and <italic toggle="yes">Student t</italic>(3, 0, 10) priors for {&#945;<sub><italic toggle="yes">l</italic></sub>, &#946;<sub><italic toggle="yes">l</italic></sub>, &#963;<sub><italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub>1</sub></sub>, &#963;<sub><italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub>2</sub></sub>}; this analysis revealed posterior invariance under the considered prior specifications.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p><xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents the model selection process, which yielded a final model consisting of an occupancy process and detection process that will be detailed in the following subsections.</p><sec><title>Detectability</title><p>The detection model according to LOO (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>4) models temporal variation in wild boar's detectability for each observation month as a GP. Modeling the detection probability using biannual seasons (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>2) results in a better fit compared to the intercept only model (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>1). Using quarterly instead of biannual seasons, results in the lowest ranking detection model (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>3). Note that the accuracy in &#916; LOO, measured as the standard error of this metric, is relatively low for all detection models (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, step 2). The posterior mean probability of detecting wild boar ranges between 0.0279 and 0.1106 regardless of the observation month. Despite low detectability in general, monthly differences can be observed (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figures 2</xref>, <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">3</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Occupancy</title><p>All of the tested covariate combinations perform better than the intercept model (&#968;1), with the multiplicative model of <italic toggle="yes">ASF</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">BL</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></sub> (&#968;5) outranking all other models. Similar to the detection models, not all &#916; LOO values are very accurate. For the difference between the two top-ranking models the standard error exceeds |&#916; LOO| (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, step 1). According to the top-ranked occupancy model, ASF infection status has a strong effect on the occupancy of wild boar. Posterior mean odds ratios (OR) of wild boar occupancy are 17.71 (3.49&#8211;95.12) and 0.01 (0.00&#8211;0.08) for non-infected and ASF-infected zones, respectively. Moreover, the OR for season, 0.76 (0.65&#8211;0.88), reveals a highly probable overall decline in wild boar occupancy for observation month (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>). Finally, the posterior distributions of ORs for both proportion of broad-leaved forest land cover class (<italic toggle="yes">BL</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></sub>) and the ASF infection status&#8212;season interaction term (<italic toggle="yes">ASF</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub>&#183;<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) have one enclosed by the 95% HPDI (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 4</xref>). Posterior mean occupancy and 95% HPDI at each observation month, averaged over the ASF management zones (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>), reveal an overall decline in occupancy, both in the ASF-infected and non-infected zone. Moreover, regression analyses using an ordinary least squares estimation of the cumulative number of wild boar culled per km<sup>2</sup> result in positive trends for both zones (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>). Finally, prediction maps for the estimated occupancy from March 2019 until May 2020, are displayed in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref> (see <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figures 4</xref>, <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">5</xref> for 2.5th and 95th percentile maps).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Monthly posterior mean occupancy estimates (dots) and 95% highest posterior density intervals (vertical lines) per ASF management zone <bold>(A)</bold>. Cumulative number of wild boar culled per km<sup>2</sup> in function of the observation month. Trend lines derived from ordinary least squares regression estimation <bold>(B)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-726117-g0002.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Posterior mean occupancy of wild boar in the ASF-infected (enclosed by the black line) and non-infected (non-enclosed) zone in Wallonia (Belgium). Panels ranging from March 2019 until May 2020.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-726117-g0003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Occupancy Growth Rate</title><p>Posterior means of occupancy growth rates, i.e., &#955;<sub><italic toggle="yes">it</italic></sub>, are lower than one regardless of the site and season (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 6</xref>). For &#955;<sub><italic toggle="yes">Tot, i</italic></sub>, total growth rates (in fact, extinction rates, due to their negative trend) in occupancy, posterior means range between 0.0865 and 0.7756 (0.9135 and 0.2244), while those for average monthly growth rates <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#955;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext></mml:math></inline-formula>lie between 0.8049 and 0.9757 (0.1951 and 0.1243). Finally, posterior mean and 95% HPDI for &#955;<sub><italic toggle="yes">Tot, i</italic></sub> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M17" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#955;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext></mml:math></inline-formula>averaged over the ASF management zones (designated &#955;<sub><italic toggle="yes">Tot, z</italic></sub> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M18" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#955;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) are given in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Posterior mean and 95% highest posterior density values for the total growth rate (&#955;<sub><italic toggle="yes">Tot, z</italic></sub>) and average monthly growth rate (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M22" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#955;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) per ASF management zone, obtained by averaging over all corresponding sites.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Zone</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mean</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2.5%</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>97.5%</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mean</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2.5%</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>97.5%</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="M23" overflow="scroll"><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false" class="mml-overline"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#955;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo accent="true">&#175;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mstyle></mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<bold>&#955;<sub><bold><italic toggle="yes"><bold>Tot</bold></italic></bold>, <italic toggle="yes"><bold>z</bold></italic></sub></bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASF-infected</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8670</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8083</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9264</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1772</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0494</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3432</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-infected</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9032</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8105</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9900</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3848</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0739</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7946</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>To assess wild boar population trends throughout the recent ASF epidemic in Wallonia (Belgium), we have built a spatio-temporal MSO model using data from CTs. This was done according to a two-step approach, selecting the best detection covariates and subsequently occupancy covariates with respect to the LOO (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) statistics from a set of <italic toggle="yes">a priori</italic> defined models.</p><sec><title>Detectability</title><p>For all model comparisons (relative to the top-ranked detection model) the standard errors for &#916; LOO values are smaller than two times |&#916; LOO|, hence a certain degree of uncertainty as to which model provides the best fit to the data remains after our selection procedure (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, step 2). Nevertheless, we believe that using a GP to model monthly temporal variation in wild boar detection probability is a sensible choice, given the ability of GPs to balance ecological realism with model flexibility (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>).</p><p>When using CTs, detection probabilities are known to be affected by, among others, vegetation denseness, background surface temperature and weather conditions (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>), all of which depend on the seasonal variation to some extent. Hence, a certain degree of seasonality in detection probabilities is not uncommon. Morelle et al. (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) report higher probabilities of detecting wild boar in summer months compared to fall (4.90E+04), winter (4.34E-03) and spring (4.90E+04). In this study, posterior mean detection probability for wild boar is low, although some additional heterogeneity attributed to the observation month was observed. In 2019, summer months display a somewhat higher probability of detecting wild boar as compared to winter months, yet there is insufficient evidence that a periodic trend exists. Instead, we suggest that the main effect at play is a density-dependent effect (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), more specifically a decline in detection probability governed by a decreasing wild boar density. In addition, the intensive culling regime adopted throughout the ASF epidemic possibly led to an increased risk perception by wild boar, incentivizing them to restrict their movements and seek hiding places. Lower activity levels negatively relate with photographic rates (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Similarly, low probabilities of detecting wild boar could reflect decreased movement.</p></sec><sec><title>Occupancy</title><p>The top-ranked occupancy model consists of a multiplicative effect the ASF infection status (<italic toggle="yes">ASF</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub>) of the zone, the observation month (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) and the proportion of deciduous forest land-use class (<italic toggle="yes">BL</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></sub>), closely followed by a fully additive model of these covariates (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, step 1). A large difference in wild boar occupancy was already present during the first month of the study period (March 2019), with posterior mean occupancies of 0.2352 and 0.8677 in infected and non-infected zones, respectively (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 5</xref>). Hence, ASF-governed mortality, which had already decimated the population in the infected zone at the beginning of the monitoring program (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 6</xref>), strongly affects wild boar occupancy [posterior mean OR(<inline-formula><mml:math id="M19" overflow="scroll"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>) of 0.01; <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 4</xref>]. This is not surprising given that the zone was already infected with ASF for several months (i.e., since September 2019) before the study's onset. Although it is uncertain whether the low initial occupancy in the infected zone is driven by ASF alone, mortality rates approaching 100% have been reported (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Interestingly, the inclusion of a HSGP that achieves a degree of spatial smoothing depending on &#961;<sub><italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub>2</sub></sub>, did not result in smoothly varying occupancies at the infected/non-infected boundary. Instead, the occupancy abruptly changes at this boundary, a trend that is seen throughout the entire study period (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). This pattern persists, even after omitting the information about ASF infection status (i.e., a potential driver of abrupt changes in occupancy, due to its binary encoding) from our model (results not shown). In that case, the variation in occupancy previously accounted for by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M20" overflow="scroll"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>, remains explained by the spatial GP (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M21" overflow="scroll"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>). Hence, we are confident that this absence of smooth occupancy patterns is not an artifact of our choice of covariates. Instead, we argue that fences placed at the infected/non-infected boundary (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>) serve as an effective measure to stop the passage of wild boars, explaining the patterns observed in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>. By impeding wild boar's movement, fences also prevent the inflow of ASFV throughout an epidemic. Hence, we regard fencing, as it was adopted in Wallonia (Belgium), as an essential element in the ASF-management strategy.</p><p>Despite the strong impact of ASF, the infected zone has quite some refugee sites that display higher occupancies compared to surrounding areas as of March 2019 (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). As the epidemic progressed, occupancy drops in most of these subareas, with only one patch in the South displaying markedly higher occupancy toward May 2020. Given the remoteness of this patch, it could be that wild boar in this area are shielded from ASF to some extent. A more likely explanation is that these refugee sites reflect the area's suitability for remaining wild boar in terms of habitat quality and food availability. Similarly, we argue that latent ecological preferences drive the heterogeneity in occupancy observed within the non-infected zone, where higher occupancies are observed in the central axis (horizontally) throughout the study period (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). Indeed, looking at the spatial random effect alone, both the Southern patch of the ASF-infected zone and central axis of the non-infected zone are associated with some of the highest values (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 7</xref>). A number of potential ecological drivers of wild boar occupancy are observed and subsequently modeled; we have considered the proportion of broad-leaved tree land cover class, which is known to positively affect its occupancy (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>), as a fixed effect in our final model. The 95% HPDI for the OR (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M24" overflow="scroll"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>) (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 4</xref>), which encompasses one, suggests an effect that needs further investigation in future studies.</p><p>Importantly, we obtain an overall declining trend [posterior mean OR (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M25" overflow="scroll"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>) of 0.76; <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 4</xref>] in wild boar occupancy for both ASF-infected an non-infected zones (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). Interestingly, these declines are inversely related with the positive trends of the cumulative number of wild boar culled per km<sup>2</sup> in function of the observation month (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>). Although hunting statistics are sensitive to search effort, these findings indicate that occupancy probabilities continue to drop in response to maintained culling efforts. In addition, ASF-induced mortality contributes to the occupancy decline seen in the ASF-infected zone, where its effect is strongest during the first months of our study period, when ASFV-positive wild boars are still found occasionally <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 6</xref>. Finally, we find that occupancy declines have different rates between the zones, with a more moderate decline seen in the ASF-infected zone [posterior mean OR (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M26" overflow="scroll"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#183;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#968;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>) of 1.13; <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 4</xref>]. Possibly, differences in hunting pressure could explain this variation in rates of occupancy decline. Although wild boars have been culled in both ASF-infected and non-infected zones, the latter was more densely populated throughout the entire study period, which likely reduces the search effort by hunters and leads to increased hunting success (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 7</xref>). In addition, we note that between the epidemic-onset and its peak (September 2019 &#8211; February 2019), an occupancy decline was likely much higher in the ASF-infected zone. Importantly, our model reveals that an effect of the <italic toggle="yes">ASF</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub>&#183;<italic toggle="yes">t</italic> interaction term is not highly probable when looking at 95% HPDI. Uncertainty about the existence of zone-specific occupancy rates, is also reflected in the small &#916; LOO between a model with and one without the interaction term (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, step 1).</p></sec><sec><title>Occupancy Growth Rate</title><p>We will not discuss growth rates in depth, since they carry on the same messages as the occupancy probabilities discussed earlier, but see <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 6</xref> for a graphical representation. However, it is worthwhile to briefly focus on total occupancy growth rates, as they provide a summary statistic for net change in occupancy. Posterior means of 0.1772 and 0.3848 (extinction rates of 0.9228 and 0.7152) for, respectively, ASF-infected and non-infected zones, confirm the strong decline in wild boar occupancy. In line with these results, Morelle et al. (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) report declines in wild boar abundance, obtained through fitting a REM (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) to CT data, of 83.8 &#177; 25.5% and 94.8 &#177; 6.4% in unmanaged and managed zones, respectively, one year after an ASF outbreak in the Bia&#322;owieza Primeval Forest (Poland). Moreover, average monthly growth rates of 0.8670 and 0.9032 (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>) indicate that monitoring highly lethal diseases, such as ASF, which typically lead to rapid depletion of individuals, demands for shorter primary sampling periods.</p></sec><sec><title>Limitations</title><p>The data used in this study do not cover the full ASF episode as it occurred in Wallonia (Belgium). As such, we are unable to report on the full course of the epidemic. Secondly, it has been reported by (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) that sample sizes smaller than 40 lead to insufficient power to detect declines in occupancy under most circumstances. Here, we deploy 69 cameras in the ASF-infected and only 23 cameras in the non-infected zone. Nonetheless, we were able to capture meaningful declines in occupancy for both zones throughout the study period. Importantly, both ASF management zones had sampling intensities higher than the best scenario (2% of sites sampled) considered by Banner et al. (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). From a modeler's perspective, we did not attempt a full spatio-temporal analysis. However, we believe that it is reasonable to assume that temporal dynamics in site-occupancy are spatially independent, given the relatively small surface area (ASF-infected: 162.826 km<sup>2</sup>, non-infected: 48.229 km<sup>2</sup>) of both zones in our study. Finally, we did not include structured and unstructured random effects for both the detection and occupancy process, due to unidentifiability.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Based on our results, we conclude that ASF infection status was the main driver of wild boar occupancy at the beginning of the monitoring period, which led to higher occupancies in the ASF-infected zone compared to the non-infected zone. Moreover, we find that fences placed at the infected/non-infected boundary act as an effective barrier throughout the entire study period, resulting in abrupt changes in occupancy from one zone to the other. This suggests that wild boar's movement across this barrier is severely impeded, preventing inflow of the ASFV to the non-infected zone. Starting from March 2019, our model strongly supports an overall decline in occupancy until May 2020, presumably due to maintained culling efforts. Together, these results confirm (1) a declining trend in wild boar occupancy resulting from ASF (only in the infected zone) and ASF control measures implemented in Wallonia (Belgium), and (2) the potential of using a CT network to monitor wild boar population trends and impacts thereon during an ASF outbreak.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The datasets presented in this study can be found in online repositories. The names of the repository/repositories and accession number(s) can be found below: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://figshare.com/projects/African_Swine_Fever_Monitoring/115092" ext-link-type="uri">https://figshare.com/projects/African_Swine_Fever_Monitoring/115092</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>Ethical review and approval was not required for the animal study because the data used in this work were obtained through a non-invasive method (camera trapping), which does not disturb the natural behavior of animal.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>MB: methodology, formal analysis, visualization and writing&#8212;original draft preparation. TN: methodology and validation. MF: methodology and visualization. AL, VD, and BM: resources. JC and NB: supervision. MB, TN, VD, AL, JC, and NB: writing&#8212;review &amp; editing, conceptualization. Each author's contribution is described using the CRediT roles. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="s9"><title>Funding</title><p>MB and MF are PhD fellows, MB is funded by a BOF-mandate at Hasselt University, MF is funded by the Research Foundation &#8211; Flanders (FWO) (grant number 11E3220N). The camera trapping infrastructure was provided and funded by the Public Service of Wallonia. Services used in this work were provided by the VSC (Flemish Supercomputer Center), funded by the Research Foundation &#8211; Flanders (FWO) and the Flemish Government. Finally, the ecotope dataset, used in this work, is derived from the LifeWatch ecotope database, which is led by the Earth &amp; Life Institute (UC Louvain) and funded by the Wallonia-Brussels Federation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s10"><title>Publisher's Note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Guillaume Morrel for installing the camera trapping network during his master thesis (ULi&#232;ge). Further, we are grateful to the municipalities and residents in Gaume to allow us to place camera traps on their property. Finally, we would like to thank the reviewers for their thoughtful comments and efforts toward improving our manuscript.</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s11"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2021.726117/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2021.726117/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#225;nchez-Cord&#243;n</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montoya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>African swine fever: a re-emerging viral disease threatening the global pig industry</article-title>. <source>Vet J.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>233</volume>:<fpage>41</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tvjl.2017.12.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29486878</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5844645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chenais</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Depner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guberti</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dietze</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Viltrop</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiological considerations on African swine fever in Europe 2014-2018</article-title>. <source>Porcine Health Manag.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40813-018-0109-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30637117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6325717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>More</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miranda</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bicout</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>B&#248;tner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Butterworth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calistri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>African swine fever in wild boar</article-title>. <source>EFSA J.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>e05344</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2903/j.efsa.2018.5344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32625980</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7009363</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Commision Implementing Regulation (EU) 2021/605 of 7 April 2021 Laying Down Special Control Measures for African Swine Fever Was Adopted by the Commission Based on the New Legal Framework of Regulation (EU) 2016/429 (Animal Health Law) OJ L 126</collab></person-group>. Brussels: EU Commission (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nurmoja</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#245;tus</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kristian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niine</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Depner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiological analysis of the 2015&#8211;2017 African swine fever outbreaks in Estonia</article-title>. <source>Prev Vete Med.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>181</volume>:<fpage>104556</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.prevetmed.2018.10.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30482617</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guberti</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thulke</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Understanding ASF spread and emergency control concepts in wild boar populations using individual-based modelling and spatio-temporal surveillance data</article-title>. <source>EFSA Supp Public.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1521E</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2903/sp.efsa.2018.EN-1521</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bubnicki</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Churski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diserens</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuijper</surname><given-names>DPJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Linking spatial patterns of terrestrial herbivore community structure to trophic interactions</article-title>. <source>eLife.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e44937</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.44937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31577225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6805123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hegel</surname><given-names>CGZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pichorim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marini</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Wild pig (Sus scrofa L</article-title>.) occupancy patterns in the Brazilian Atlantic forest. <source>Biota Neotrop.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1676-0611-bn-2018-0719</pub-id>5544761</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neilson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ladle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steenweg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>REVIEW: Wildlife camera trapping: a review and recommendations for linking surveys to ecological processes</article-title>. <source>J Appl Ecol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>675</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2664.12432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harmsen</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A critique of density estimation from camera-trap data</article-title>. <source>J Wildlife Manag.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>76</volume>:<fpage>224</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jwmg.275</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seber</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schofield</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Capture-Recapture: Parameter Estimation for Open Animal Populations</article-title>. Cham: Springer (<year>2019</year>). p. 663.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rowcliffe</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Field</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turvey</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carbone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Estimating animal density using camera traps without the need for individual recognition</article-title>. <source>J Appl Ecol.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1228</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2664.2008.01473.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fukasawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samejima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Estimating animal density without individual recognition using information derivable exclusively from camera traps</article-title>. <source>J Appl Ecol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>735</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2664.13059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palencia</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vicente</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barroso</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barasona</surname><given-names>J&#193;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soriguer</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Acevedo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Estimating day range from camera-trap data: the animals' behaviour as a key parameter</article-title>. <source>J Zool.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>309</volume>:<fpage>182</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jzo.12710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>MacKenzie</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lachman</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Droege</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrew Royle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langtimm</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Estimating site occupancy rates when detection probabilities are less than one</article-title>. <source>Ecology.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>83</volume>:<fpage>2248</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/0012-9658(2002)083[2248:ESORWD]2.0.CO;2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Linden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Licoppe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Volpe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paternostre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lesenfants</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassart</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Summer 2018: African swine fever virus hits north-western Europe</article-title>. <source>Transb Emerg Dis.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tbed.13047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30383329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morelle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bubnicki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Churski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gryz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Podg&#243;rski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuijper</surname><given-names>DPJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Disease-induced mortality outweighs hunting in causing wild boar population crash after african swine fever outbreak</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>378</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2020.00378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32850993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7399055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>[Dataset]</surname><given-names>LifeWatch</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>LifeWatch-WB Ecotope Database</article-title>. (<year>2018</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.lifewatch.be/en/lifewatch-wb-ecotope-database" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.lifewatch.be/en/lifewatch-wb-ecotope-database</ext-link> (accessed October 8, 2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Casaer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milotic</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liefting</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desmet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Agouti: a platform for processing and archiving of camera trap images</article-title>. <source>Biod Inform Sci Stand.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e46690</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/biss.3.46690</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dellicour</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desmecht</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paternostre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malengreaux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Licoppe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Unravelling the dispersal dynamics and ecological drivers of the African swine fever outbreak in Belgium</article-title>. <source>J Appl Ecol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>1619</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>29</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2664.13649</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Royle</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>K&#233;ry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A bayesian state-space formulation of dynamic occupancy models</article-title>. <source>Ecology.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>1813</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/06-0669.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17645027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>MacKenzie</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Royle</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hines</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Occupancy Estimation and Modeling: Inferring Patterns and Dynamics of Species Occurrence</article-title>. Amsterdam: Elsevier (<year>2017</year>). p. 641.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niedballa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sollmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Courtiol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilting</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>camtrapR: an R package for efficient camera trap data management</article-title>. <source>Meth Ecol Evol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1457</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/2041-210X.12600</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Riutort-Mayol</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>B&#252;rkner</surname><given-names>P-C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michael Solin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vehtari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>arXiv Pre-Print Server</article-title> [Preprint] (<year>2020</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.11408" ext-link-type="uri">https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.11408</ext-link> (accessed April 23, 2020).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Solin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#228;rkk&#228;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hilbert space methods for reduced-rank Gaussian process regression</article-title>. <source>Stat Comp.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>419</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11222-019-09886-w</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gelman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodrich</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Betancourt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Stan: A probabilistic programming language</article-title>. <source>J Stat Softw.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>76</volume>:<fpage>32</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18637/jss.v076.i01</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9788645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36568334</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Banner</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Irvine</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodhouse</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Litt</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Statistical power of dynamic occupancy models to identify temporal change: informing the North American bat monitoring program</article-title>. <source>Ecol Ind.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>105</volume>:<fpage>166</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolind.2019.05.047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vehtari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gelman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gabry</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Practical Bayesian model evaluation using leave-one-out cross-validation and WAIC</article-title>. <source>Stat Comp.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1413</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11222-016-9696-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vehtari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gelman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>B&#252;rkner</surname><given-names>P-C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rank-Normalization, folding, and localization: an improved r for assessing convergence of MCMC</article-title>. <source>Bayes Anal.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1214/20-BA1221</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Purse</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fast and flexible Bayesian species distribution modelling using Gaussian processes</article-title>. <source>Meth Ecol Evol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>598</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>608</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/2041-210X.12523</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hofmeester</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cromsigt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Odden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andr&#233;n</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kindberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linnell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Framing pictures: a conceptual framework to identify and correct for biases in detection probability of camera traps enabling multi-species comparison</article-title>. <source>Ecol Evol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.4878</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30847112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6392353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rovero</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Camera trapping photographic rate as an index of density in forest ungulates</article-title>. <source>J Appl Ecol.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>1011</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2664.2009.01705.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Broadley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Avgar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boutin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Density-dependent space use affects interpretation of camera trap detection rates</article-title>. <source>Ecol Evol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>14031</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.5840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31938501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6953673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rowcliffe</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kays</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kranstauber</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carbone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Quantifying levels of animal activity using camera trap data</article-title>. <source>Meth Ecol Evol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1170</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/2041-210X.12278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jori</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vial</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfeiffer</surname><given-names>DU</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>African swine fever epidemiology and control</article-title>. <source>Ann Rev Animal Biosci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-animal-021419-083741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31743062</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morelle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fattebert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mengal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lejeune</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Invading or recolonizing? Patterns and drivers of wild boar population expansion into Belgian agroecosystems</article-title>. <source>Agricul Eco Environ.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>222</volume>:<fpage>267</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>75</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agee.2016.02.016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wevers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fattebert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casaer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Artois</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beenaerts</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Trading fear for food in the anthropocene: how ungulates cope with human disturbance in a multi-use, suburban ecosystem</article-title>. <source>Sci Total Environ.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>741</volume>:<fpage>140369</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.140369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32610236</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rutten</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casaer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swinnen</surname><given-names>KRR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herremans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leirs</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Future distribution of wild boar in a highly anthropogenic landscape: models combining hunting bag and citizen science data</article-title>. <source>Ecol Mod.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>411</volume>:<fpage>108804</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2019.108804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>