<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8818852</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8818852.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8818852</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8818852</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35141310</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.840635</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial: The Epidemiology, Diagnosis and Prevention of Infectious Diseases in Livestock</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sekiguchi</surname><given-names initials="S">Satoshi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/377889/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiratsudakul</surname><given-names initials="A">Anuwat</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c002" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/852516/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names initials="VG">Van Giap</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c003" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/852628/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Veterinary Science, Faculty of Agriculture, University of Miyazaki</institution>, <addr-line>Miyazaki</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Faculty of Veterinary Science, Mahidol University</institution>, <addr-line>Nakhon Pathom</addr-line>, <country>Thailand</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Vietnam National University of Agriculture</institution>, <addr-line>Hanoi</addr-line>, <country>Vietnam</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited and reviewed by: Michael Kogut, Agricultural Research Service (USDA), United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Satoshi Sekiguchi <email>sekiguchi@cc.miyazaki-u.ac.jp</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Anuwat Wiratsudakul <email>anuwat.wir@mahidol.edu</email></corresp><corresp id="c003">Van Giap Nguyen <email>nguyengiap83@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Veterinary Infectious Diseases, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">374996</issue-id><elocation-id>840635</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>08</day><month>02</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-10 04:25:28.280"><day>10</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2022 Sekiguchi, Wiratsudakul and Nguyen.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sekiguchi, Wiratsudakul and Nguyen</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-08-840635.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="commentary-article" xml:lang="en" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/12251/the-epidemiology-diagnosis-and-prevention-of-infectious-diseases-in-livestock"/><kwd-group><kwd>epidemiology</kwd><kwd>diagnosis</kwd><kwd>infectious diseases</kwd><kwd>prevention</kwd><kwd>livestock</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="0"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="1741"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>The infectious disease in livestock plays a vital role in the economy and food security of many developing countries. An approach in veterinary epidemiology to animal infectious diseases focuses on controlling and managing disease in the livestock population. Additionally, the risk of transmission and spread of emerging diseases is increasing because of intensive human traffic. In such circumstance, those outbreaks cause severe economic losses when the livestock industry become affected. Therefore, a major component of animal disease policies and disease management strategies are a viable prevention measure. However, the same prevention doesn't work everywhere due to strategies has changed over time. An emergency preparedness needs to do before outbreaks were reported.</p><p>This Research Topic yielded 45 articles of which 10 were brief research report, 30 original research articles, one clinical trial, one opinion, two systematic reviews, and one review, involving 321 authors from 17 countries. The two areas of research cover by this Research Topic are included: (i) infectious disease and control or eradication in livestock; (ii) development of diagnosis, monitoring, and surveillance program.</p><p>A first line of research includes the infectious disease and control or eradication in livestock. Intervention can vary depending on clinical fields and local circumstances. In this part, their works presents the appropriate framework needed for strengthening a surveillance program in each region. Serology has been performed for many years and the present of antibody refer as a marker to identify reservoir that may boost the outbreaks. In their work, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.00363" ext-link-type="uri">Sun et al.</ext-link> report of <italic toggle="yes">Chlamydia</italic> seroprevalence in domestic, black-boned sheep and goats in southwest China. Involving same methods, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.00526" ext-link-type="uri">Ullah et al.</ext-link> also reported anti-<italic toggle="yes">Brucella</italic> antibodies in sheep and goats at these livestock farms in Punjab, Pakistan. Furthermore, serological cross-reactivity was detected between alphaherpesvirus-2 and alphaherpesvirus&#8722;1 in a calf located in Central Italy by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.587885" ext-link-type="uri">Petrini et al.</ext-link> However, this method is only required for early diagnosis and infection occurring in previously vaccinated animals may not be detectible. To overcome the limitation mentioned above, the molecular epidemiology of infectious diseases is also discussed in this Research Topic. For examples, isolation and characterization of a porcine transmissible gastroenteritis coronavirus in Northeast China by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2021.611721" ext-link-type="uri">Yuan et al.</ext-link>; epidemiology of bovine tuberculosis in Ethiopia by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2021.595511" ext-link-type="uri">Tulu et al.</ext-link> Similarly, an interesting work led by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.00608" ext-link-type="uri">Hamada et al.</ext-link> described the new investigation on molecular prevalence of bovine leukemia virus in Egyptian cattle. In an article by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.00197" ext-link-type="uri">Shi et al.</ext-link>, they revealed bovine pestivirus isolates from cattle have extensive genetic variations in Central China.</p><p>There were still many studies highlighted the evaluation of the prevention of infectious disease in livestock. As the case in Vietnam, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.00433" ext-link-type="uri">Mai et al.</ext-link> find out the possible risk factors for transmission pattern of PEDV in an endemic region. They indicated that there have three of these 29 variables such as farrow-to-wean production type, distance from the farm to the slaughterhouse, and the presence of chickens on site. Recently, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.00614" ext-link-type="uri">Makita et al.</ext-link> also examined the decision-making process for farm biosecurity among livestock farmers through elevated attitudes and self-efficacy. An integrated community-based intervention is also applied for control and prevention of epizootic lymphangitis in mules, Bahir Dar, Ethiopia, which was reported by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2021.648267" ext-link-type="uri">Duguma et al.</ext-link></p><p>This Research Topic is further investigating the role of wildlife in the epidemiology of infectious diseases. In addition, the identification of microorganisms by vectors has been useful for identifying reservoirs and verifying modes of transmission. An outcome of the papers by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.569901" ext-link-type="uri">Chang et al.</ext-link> indicated pigeons play an important role in transmission pattern of Pigeon paramyxovirus type I. Works reporting the evidence of wild animals, as the case in Korea, wild leopard cat and Asian badger may spread feline parvovirus and its related viruses, which was reported by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2021.650866" ext-link-type="uri">Kim et al.</ext-link> or in Germany, Q fever is presented by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2021.623786" ext-link-type="uri">Winter et al.</ext-link> in ruminant. In particular, the work led by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.573480" ext-link-type="uri">Shimizu et al.</ext-link> shown that infected wild boars are a major source of infection for the current classical swine fever occurred in Japan. A retrospective survey by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2021.666254" ext-link-type="uri">Zhou et al.</ext-link> indicated that the blue fox's outbreak of abortions was derived from brucellosis which caused by <italic toggle="yes">B. melitensis</italic> strain. Moreover, a survey by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.00554" ext-link-type="uri">Kivali et al.</ext-link> identified trypanosome species in cattle and their spatial distribution in western Kenya.</p><p>It was well-known that those novel pathogens are also responsible for emerging infectious diseases. A work led by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.00538" ext-link-type="uri">Yu et al.</ext-link> shown that, as in goat, the impact of endogenous and exogenous factors affecting susceptibility to orf virus will likely reflect the host's specific in term of a particular strain such as NZ7-like orf viruses. An additional paper by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.573480" ext-link-type="uri">Shimizu et al.</ext-link>, presented the report of genetic variability of orf viruses in Japan, which can be spread to sheep or farmers and can be transmit to Japanese serows. Along this line, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.00462" ext-link-type="uri">Su et al.</ext-link> showed that a coinfection porcine astrovirus with PEV and GARV in diarrheic piglets in China. Furthermore, Getah virus was reported by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.552517" ext-link-type="uri">Ren et al.</ext-link> in southern China.</p><p>A second related aspects of research that drew the development of diagnosis, monitoring, and surveillance program. The application of new innovative diagnostic technologies for rapidly detect of pathogens is required for limit the economic impact of emerging infectious animal diseases. The desirable characteristics are fast, simple, cost-effective, highly sensitive, and specific. In these lines, a rapid detection of PCV2 and direct identification of PCV2 genotypes from clinical samples was developed by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.00200" ext-link-type="uri">Wang, Song, Shin, Kim et al.</ext-link>, examined the performance of two newly available methods, multiplex real-time PCR assay and PCR-reverse blot hybridization assay. These techniques can also yield results in 2&#8211;3 h for differentiate between the PCV2 genotypes and detect PCV2 from clinical specimens. Continuing with the search of novel diagnostic, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.586045" ext-link-type="uri">Wang, Song, Shin, Choi et al.</ext-link> also highlighted that using the new clinical molecular assay for diagnosis in porcine cytomegalovirus (PCMV) can be used to screen with dramatic reduction in false positives and negatives. Besides, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.00374" ext-link-type="uri">Arrieta-Villegas et al.</ext-link> examined the applicability of the P22 antigen complex as a complementary tool for TB diagnostics in goats with a cost-effective alternative. The review by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2021.635155" ext-link-type="uri">Rodr&#237;guez-Hern&#225;ndez et al.</ext-link> also highlight application of Volatilome analysis to the diagnosis of mycobacteria infection in livestock, which was fulfills part of the mycobacterial diagnosis requirements.</p><p>The remaining works further highlighted the novel methods such as one-tube nested RT-PCR which required ~1.5 h for completion for the characterizing pathogen responsible for porcine cytomegalovirus infection (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.586045" ext-link-type="uri">Wang, Song, Shin, Choi et al.</ext-link>); or multiplex PCR is design to provide a rapid, specific and sensitive detection method for the identification of four pathogenic bacteria in minks (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.588173" ext-link-type="uri">Li et al.</ext-link>) and thermal image scanning for the early detection of fever induced by highly pathogenic avian influenza virus infection in chickens and ducks (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2021.616755" ext-link-type="uri">Noh et al.</ext-link>). Similarly, a procedure for partial or full genome sequencing of peste-des-petits-ruminants virus is described by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.542724" ext-link-type="uri">Torsson et al.</ext-link> The use of a portable laboratory such as miniPCR and MinION to the field and to the production of a full genome with the results just 24 h of collection. On the other hand, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.00636" ext-link-type="uri">Ruggeri et al.</ext-link> indicated that the newly scoring system could be used to exam pathological lesions in the respiratory tracts in porcine respiratory disease complex.</p><p>Taken together, all the published papers in this Research Topic reflects that a combined effort across borders is needed to control infectious diseases in livestock on such epidemiology, diagnosis, and prevention and coordinated action around the globe required to fill gaps in the literature regarding control and eradication programs for infectious diseases.</p><sec id="s1"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>VN and SS wrote the first part of the infectious disease and control or eradication in livestock. AW wrote the second part of the development of the diagnosis, monitoring, and surveillance program. All authors contributed to conception, design of the project, manuscript revision, read, edited, added sections, provided critical comments of the manuscript, and agreed on the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s2"><title>Publisher's Note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors would like to thank the reviewers and scientists who contributed to this Research Topic.</p></ack></back></article></pmc-articleset>