<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8907520</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8907520.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8907520</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8907520</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35280128</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.808293</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ensiling Grape Pomace With and Without Addition of a <italic toggle="yes">Lactiplantibacillus plantarum</italic> Strain: Effect on Polyphenols and Microbiological Characteristics, <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> Nutrient Apparent Digestibility, and Gas Emission</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Bellis</surname><given-names initials="P">Palmira</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/239559/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maggiolino</surname><given-names initials="A">Aristide</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/958448/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Albano</surname><given-names initials="C">Clara</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/457282/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Palo</surname><given-names initials="P">Pasquale</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/694077/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blando</surname><given-names initials="F">Federica</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/580549/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Institute of Sciences of Food Production (ISPA), National Research Council (CNR)</institution>, <addr-line>Bari</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Veterinary Medicine, University of Bari &#8220;Aldo Moro&#8221;</institution>, <addr-line>Bari</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Institute of Sciences of Food Production (ISPA), National Research Council (CNR)</institution>, <addr-line>Lecce</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Anil Kumar Puniya, National Dairy Research Institute (ICAR), India</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Federica Mannelli, University of Florence, Italy; Anusorn Cherdthong, Khon Kaen University, Thailand</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Aristide Maggiolino <email>aristide.maggiolino@uniba.it</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Animal Nutrition and Metabolism, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>2</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">400313</issue-id><elocation-id>808293</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>11</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>07</day><month>1</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>11</day><month>03</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2022-03-14 16:16:50.267"><day>14</day><month>03</month><year>2022</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2022 De Bellis, Maggiolino, Albano, De Palo and Blando.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder>De Bellis, Maggiolino, Albano, De Palo and Blando</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-09-808293.pdf"/><abstract><p>The present study investigated the effects of different grape pomace storage techniques on the effectiveness as feed on <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> ruminant digestion efficiency. Grape pomace from an autochthonous red grape variety (cv Nero di Troia) was used as fresh (GP) or ensiled, both without additives (SIL) and with the addition of a bacterial strain, <italic toggle="yes">Lactiplantibacillus plantarum</italic> 5BG (SIL+). All the different storage treatments were subject to chemical and microbiological evaluation, as well as <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> digestibility, and gas production. Microbiological data revealed the good quality of grape pomace and silages due to the lactic acid bacteria populations and low presence, or absence, of undesirable microorganisms. The addition of <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG influenced the chemical characteristics of the silage (SIL+). Ensiling technique deeply changed the polyphenolic composition, reducing anthocyanins, flavonols, and flavanols (condensed tannins precursors), particularly when <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG was added. Antioxidant capacity was reduced by ensiling, in correlation with the polyphenolic content decrease. The oxygen radical absorbance capacity (ORAC) value of SIL+ was the lowest (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01) and its total phenol content was lower than SIL (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). No statistical differences were observed between GP, SIL, and SIL+ on the antioxidant capacity by TEAC assay (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05). Ensiling did not affect the grape pomace nutrient profile, except for the reduction in NFC content. Apparent <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> digestibility showed how ensiling increased dry matter (DM), organic matter (OM), neutral detergent fiber (NDF), crude protein (CP), ether extract (EE), and non-fiber carbohydrates (NFC) disappearance (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01), particularly with the <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG inoculation. Moreover, SIL+ showed the lowest propionic acid (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) and the highest methane (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01), butyric acid (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01), and nitrogen (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> production. Ensiling GP resulted in a better <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> digestibility, particularly if <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG strain is added, probably due to the reduction of flavanols and their lower microbial activity inhibition.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>grape pomace</kwd><kwd>silage</kwd><kwd>polyphenol</kwd><kwd>antioxidant capacity</kwd><kwd>lactic acid bacteria</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> digestion</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001"><institution-wrap><institution>Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100004462</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="6"/><equation-count count="3"/><ref-count count="79"/><page-count count="13"/><word-count count="10920"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The use of agricultural by-products as animal dietary supplement is the result of multiple efforts in reducing the carbon footprint of the livestock industry (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). By-products are generally inexpensive and their production can be considered free of greenhouse gas emissions as they are allocated to the primary product (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). This leads to an increased interest in exploiting plant products and by-products as feed additives to solve both animal nutrition problems and livestock production impact. In fact, plant by-products are often rich in readily fermentable carbohydrates and fats, useful for animal digestion processes, but also in plant secondary compounds that have been reported to suppress CH<sub>4</sub> concentration, reduce rumen protozoa counts, and modulate rumen fermentation patterns (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p><p>Grape pomace (GP) is the by-product of a winemaking process and consists of pressed grapes (skin and seeds with residual pulp) and stalk residues. Considering that the winemaking process does not allow a complete extraction of polyphenolic compounds, GP represents an abundant and inexpensive polyphenols source. In particular, GP is rich of flavonoids, the largest group of polyphenols predominantly found in skins, seeds, and stems (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Polyphenols have been intensively studied for their anti-inflammatory and anti-microbial properties and for their health-associated effects against chronic diseases, such as cancer, neurodegeneration, and cardiovascular pathologies (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). The health benefits of GP polyphenols, especially flavonoids, have received great interest of researchers, and the food and nutraceutical industries (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Grape pomace also might be considered an important feed ingredient in ruminants' diet, being rich in bioactive polyphenols and soluble fiber, particularly when climatic conditions limit the availability of other feeds (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p><p>In contrast to humans, in farm animals the potential health-promoting effects of bioactive polyphenols have been considered only recently (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). The use of GP is suggested as an alternative ingredient in animal feeding, effective in enhancing the oxidative stability of the meat (inhibiting the meat lipid peroxidation), in reducing the addition of synthetic antioxidant as vitamin E, and in modulating the intestinal microbiota (increasing the presence of specific beneficial bacteria strains) (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Moreover, the addition of GP to dairy cows' feed was found to modulate milk's fatty acid composition and methane emissions (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). So, when shortage of feeds occurs, the addition of GP could represent an alternative feed resource in ruminants (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>).</p><p>Although GP can be used fresh as a feeding ingredient, the seasonality in its production combined to not suitable storage techniques can lead to nutrient losses and spoilage processes (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Ensiling is an appropriate method to preserve this product along the time, allowing farmers to use it continuatively in the year. Moreover, the use of suitable bacterial inoculants could improve the quality and aerobic stability of silages (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Most of the inoculants used belong to lactic acid bacteria (LAB) (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). During the ensiling process, LAB converts water-soluble carbohydrates (WSC) into organic acids (e.g., lactic acid and acetic acid) which rapidly reduce the silage pH. The acidic and anaerobic conditions help to inhibit the proliferation of undesirable microorganisms (e.g., Clostridia) and preserve nutrient components (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Furthermore, LAB is known to degrade phenolic compounds (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>), but few studies have focused on the effects of LAB inoculants on changes of phenolic compounds in silages (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) and on silage digestibility. Considering the results of previous publications, it could be hypothesized that ensiling GP could improve its nutritive characteristics as animal feeding and that the addition of starter strains could be useful both to improve its digestibility as well as its impact on rumen gas production. Therefore, the aim of this research was to evaluate the effects of ensiling with and without addition of <italic toggle="yes">Lactiplantibacillus plantarum</italic> 5BG (previously named <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus plantarum</italic>) (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) on the chemical composition, in particular polyphenolic compounds, microbiological, and nutritional quality of GP silages.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>The protocol for animal research was approved by the Ethics Committee for animal testing&#8211;CESA (process number 2-X/17) of the Department of Veterinary Medicine of the University of Bari &#8220;Aldo Moro&#8221;, Bari, Italy.</p><sec><title>Preparation of Silage Grape Pomace</title><p>Fresh grape pomace samples (<italic toggle="yes">Vitis vinifera</italic> L., cv Nero di Troia) from red cultivars were collected in the Puglia Region (South Italy), immediately after the crush of grape juice and fermentation processes for red wine production had been completed. The whole sampled grape pomace was randomly subdivided in three experimental treatments: (A) fresh grape pomace (GP); (B) silage (SIL); and (C) silage inoculated with <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG (SIL+).</p><p>For silage, grape pomace was randomly assigned to SIL or SIL+, and 8 silos for each experimental group were prepared. Fresh GP was subdivided in 8 parts of similar volume of each silo. Silos were a cylindric plastic container (35 L vol; about 30 cm diameter &#215;50 cm high). Each silo was filled with manually pressed pomace. In the SIL+ group, inoculation of GP was performed with the strain <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) belonging to the Culture Collection of the Institute of Sciences of Food Production, National Research Council (ITEM 17403, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://server.ispa.cnr.it/ITEM/Collection/" ext-link-type="uri">http://server.ispa.cnr.it/ITEM/Collection/</ext-link>). A freeze-dried powder of <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG was inoculated in GP at a final concentration of ~6 log cfu/g of GP. All the silos had a gas release valve in the lid and were stored upright at ambient temperature (18&#8211;25&#176;C). The silage density was calculated as the ratio between the ensiled GP and silo volume (kg GP m<sup>3</sup>) and it was on average value of 658.54 &#177; 16.20 kg GP m<sup>3</sup>. The silos were opened after 1 month from the starting of the experiment (T0).</p><p>Fresh (GP) and ensiled grape pomace (SIL and SIL+) were subjected to the evaluation of pH, chemical and microbiological characteristics, <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> digestibility, and gas production.</p><p>All samples (GP, SIL, SIL+) were stored lyophilized (Labconco Corp., Kansas City, MO) at &#8722;20&#176;C until polyphenolic analysis. Afterward samples (GP, SIL, and SIL+) were ground using a CT 193 Cyclotec mill fitted with 1-mm screen (FOSS, Hilleroed, Denmark), and analyzed for phenols and antioxidant capacity at least in triplicate.</p></sec><sec><title>Chemical Analyses</title><p>Before and after <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> digestion, all GP, SIL, and SIL+ samples were analyzed in triplicate, considering each silo as the experimental unit. Dry matter (DM) was determined using standard procedures (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) (method 930.15). Ash was determined by standard procedures (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) (method 942.05) using a muffle furnace at 550&#176;C for 16 h. Fat was determined using the Soxhlet extraction procedure (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) (Method 991.36), crude protein (CP) was determined by Kjeldahl N &#215;6.25 procedures (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) (Method 968.06). Neutral detergent fiber (NDF) and acid detergent fiber (ADF) were determined with the ANKOM fiber analyzer according to Van Soest et al. (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) and was corrected for residual acid-insoluble ash. Sodium sulfite was added to the solution for NDF determination. Non-fiber carbohydrates (NFC) were calculated by subtracting CP, ether extract (EE), and NDF from the organic matter (OM) and the metabolizable energy (ME) values were calculated using the equation:</p><disp-formula id="E1"><mml:math id="M1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#8201;</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#8201;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.82</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#8201;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#215;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#8201;</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.4</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#8201;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#215;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#8201;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#8201;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#8201;</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>3.9</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#8201;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#215;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#8201;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#8201;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;&#8201;</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.8</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#8201;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#215;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#8201;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#8201;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#8201;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#215;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#8201;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#8201;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>as suggested by Robinson et al. (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>), where CP, EE, and OM residual are as g/kg of DM. The water soluble carbohydrate (WSC) content was determined as described by McDonald et al. (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Microbiological Analyses</title><p>Microbiological analyses were carried out on SIL and SIL+ at different times (0, 24, 48, 144 h) after silos opening, as well as on GP. Twenty grams of samples were homogenized with 180 mL of sterile buffered peptone water (BPW, Biolife) in a Stomacher (Seward, London, United Kingdom) for 2 min. The resulting suspensions were serially diluted in the same diluent and plated in duplicate on the following agar media for the detection and enumeration of microorganisms: Plate Count Agar (PCA, Difco, Franklin Lakes, NJ) supplemented with 100 mg/L of cycloheximide (EMD Millipore Corp., Billerica, MA) incubated at 30&#176;C for 24 h to determine the total aerobic mesophilic bacterial counts (AMB); de Man Rogosa Sharpe (MRS) agar (Oxoid Ltd, Basingstoke, UK) supplemented with 100 mg/l of cycloheximide incubated at 30&#176;C for 48 h for the determination of LAB; Sabouraud Dextrose Agar (SDA, Oxoid) supplemented with 200 mg/L chloramphenicol (Sigma, Milan, Italy) for the enumeration of yeasts and molds, incubated at 25&#176;C for 72 h; violet red bile glucose agar (VRBGA, Difco) for total <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae</italic>, incubated aerobically at 37&#176;C for 24 h; sulfite polymyxin sulfadiazine (SPS) agar (Biolife, Milan, Italy) for detecting <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic>, incubated anaerobically at 37&#176;C for 24 h; the chromogenic and selective <italic toggle="yes">Listeria</italic> agar (ALOA, Biolife) for the enumeration of <italic toggle="yes">Listeria monocytogenes</italic> after 48 h of incubation at 37&#176;C. Moreover, an aliquot of each microbial suspension was heat-treated for 20 min at 90&#176;C, plated on a plate count agar (PCA, Difco) and incubated for 24 h at 30&#176;C for spore-forming bacteria (SFB) counts. LAB, AMB, yeasts, molds, and <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae</italic> counts were used as indicators of the overall microbiological quality of samples, while SFB, <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Ls. monocytogenes</italic> were also considered as potential pathogens and indicators of the product microbiological safety (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Each sample was tested in triplicate.</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of Polyphenolic Extracts From Grape Pomace</title><p>Polyphenols were extracted in triplicate from 500 mg (DW, dry weight) GP, SIL, and SIL+ after silos opening (T0), macerated with 50 mL extraction solvent (70% acetone + 0.01% TFA), at 4&#176;C, over-night. After centrifugation of the slurry (10 min at 2,000 &#215; <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>) the supernatant was collected, further 10 mL of extraction solvent were added to the pellet, and the extraction was repeated on a rotary shaker for 1 h. Pooled supernatants were evaporated <italic toggle="yes">in vacuo</italic> at 32&#176;C using a model R-205 B&#252;chi rotavapor (B&#252;chi Labortechnik AG, Switzerland) and re-suspended in acidified water (0.01% trifluoracetic acid) (TFA) at known volume. Extracts were filtered on 0.45 &#956;m CA syringe filter (Filtres Fioroni, France), portioned and stored at &#8722;20&#176;C until analysis. The extraction experiments were performed twice, with each triplicated extraction considered for HPLC injection.</p></sec><sec><title>Identification and Quantification of Polyphenolic Compounds</title><p>The HPLC separation, identification, and quantification of polyphenols in GP, SIL, and SIL+ extracts were performed using the same chromatographic method and column as already reported (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). The polyphenolic compounds were identified by comparing their peak retention times and UV-visible spectra with those of commercial standards, where available. Spiking experiments using sample solutions and standards as well as comparisons to any relevant published grape pomace analytical characterization were used to verify peak identities (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>).</p><p>The identified phenolic compounds were quantified by the external standard method using a six-points calibration curve of oenin (1.25&#8211;250 mg/L), gallic acid (1&#8211;100 mg/L), syringic acid (0.5&#8211;100 mg/L), catechin (1&#8211;100 mg/L), and rutin (0.5&#8211;100 mg/L). When reference standard compounds were not available, the quantification was done using the calibration curve of the most structurally related substance, including a molecular correction factor (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Phenols and Hydrophilic Antioxidant Capacity</title><p>The polyphenolic extracts were assessed for total phenol content and reducing capacity by the Folin-Ciocalteu (F-C) assay, as well as their antioxidant capacity using the ABTS assay (Trolox-equivalent antioxidant capacity - TEAC) and the oxygen radical absorbance capacity (ORAC) assay (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). A rapid microplate methodology, using a microplate reader (Infinite M-200, Tecan Group Ltd, M&#228;nnedorf, Switzerland) and 96-well plates (Costar, 96-well clear round bottom plate, Corning) was used.</p><p>Two independent plates (at least) were performed for each sample, which was tested in triplicate for each dilution (four dilutions of each extract).</p></sec><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> Rumen Digestion</title><p>All the operations of rumen fluid sampling were performed at the slaughterhouse, suddenly after animal slaughtering. Rumen fluid was obtained by a total of 24 animals (Limousine steers, aged 12 months, reared in the same farm). All animals were fed <italic toggle="yes">ad libitum</italic> with the same feed ratio (86.7% of dry matter, 15.9% of crude protein, 9.2% of crude fiber, 25.6% of NDF, 10.1% of ADF, and 2.6% of ADL). Samples of ruminal contents (filtered through eight layers of gauze cloth) were collected in thermos flasks (previously filled with distilled water at 39&#176;C to avoid thermal shock to the rumen fluid), insufflating CO<sub>2</sub> into the headspace to ensure the environment remained anaerobic and taken within 30 min to the laboratory. After transport, the top layer of ruminal contents was discarded, and the remaining portion was mixed and blended under a CO<sub>2</sub> headspace for 1 min to remove any additional particles and/or attached organisms. The combined fluid and contents were strained through 6 layers of cheesecloth to form the inoculum for the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> fermentation (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>).</p><p><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> fermentation was conducted for 48 h using the Daisy II incubator system (ANKOM Tech., Fairport, NY), as described by Maggiolino et al. (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). The unit consisted of four incubation vessels with a capacity of 2 L for each. Each vessel contained 1.6 L of buffer solution, 400 mL of rumen liquor, and 25 nylon filter bags (ANKOM F57, ANKOM Tech., Fairport, NY). The buffer solution consisted of 1.33 L buffer A (KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 10.0 g/L; MgSO<sub>4</sub> H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.5 g/L; NaCl, 0.5 g/L; CaCl<sub>2</sub> H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.1 g/L; and urea, 0.5 g/L) and 266 mL of buffer B (Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>, 15.0 g/L and Na<sub>2</sub>S<sub>7</sub>H<sub>2</sub>O, 1.0 g/L), mixed in each digestion vessel and the pH was adjusted to 6.8, as reported by the method of Marten and Barnes (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Each digestion trial for each sample was performed in duplicate. Bags were rinsed in acetone and allowed to air dry before drying at 100&#176;C for 24 h, after recording dry bag weight. They were used and filled with a total of 500 mg each GP, SIL, and SIL+ (all samples were stored at &#8722;20&#176;C before analysis). All samples had been previously ground until the particle size reached 2 mm screen using a hammer mill (Pullerisette 19, Fritsch GmbH, Laborgeratebau, Germany). Twenty-five bags were put in each incubation vessel. After digestion, all bags were weighed again. All analysis for nutrient parameters was performed after digestion and percentage of disappearance for each parameter was calculated as: (PB-PA)/PB, where PB is the quantity (g/kg) of parameter in the samples before the digestion and PA is the quantity (g/kg) of the parameter after digestion. Results were expressed as percentage.</p></sec><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> Gas Production and Analysis</title><p>For gas and volatile fatty acid analysis, an automated pressure transducer system (Ankom Technology, Macedon, NY) was used as described by Maggiolino et al. (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). It was equipped with 8 different 250 mL bottles. The same buffer solutions for the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> digestion section were used. Each vessel received 133.3 mL of Buffer A and 26.7 mL of Buffer B. Then, 40 mL of rumen fluid was added. The GP, SIL, and SIL+ (500 mg) were pre-weighed into each vessel. The head space of each vessel was insufflated with CO<sub>2</sub> for 2 min to ensure anaerobic conditions.</p><p>Vessels were put in an oscillating water bath (39&#176;C with an oscillating frequency of 45/min), to reproduce movements similar to those found in the rumen, and digestion was simulated for a 48-h fermentation period. After this period, vessels were removed from the water bath and placed into an ice bath while gas samples were drawn into evacuated test tubes, as described by Trotta et al. (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Gas samples were analyzed for methane production with gas chromatography (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA) by using the total gas volume at standard temperature and pressure (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Flasks were opened, pH measured, and 1 mL aliquot of the fermentation medium was combined in a 1.5 mL centrifuge tube with 0.1 mL of 500 g/L metaphosphoric acid and 0.1 mL of 85 mM of 2-ethyl butyrate. Samples were centrifuged at 39,000 &#215; <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>, at 23&#176;C for 15 min. Afterward, they were processed for volatile fatty acid (VFA) concentrations (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>) using a gas chromatograph with FID (Agilent Technologies, Inc., Santa Clara, CA) equipped with a 2 m &#215;3 mm packed column (45.60 Carboxen 1000, Supelco, Inc., Bellefonte, PA). For determination of ammonia nitrogen, 2 mL fluid and 2 mL trichloro-acetic acid solution (10%, w/v) were mixed to deproteinize the samples and then centrifuged for 5 min at 1,500 &#215; <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>. The supernatant (2 mL) was processed in order to measure the ammonia nitrogen concentration according to a spectrophotometric method (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was performed to differentiate among the treatments (GP, SIL, and SIL+), the phenolic content, the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> digestion data, and gas emission results. The ANOVA was performed using the general linear model (GLM) by SAS software (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>), according to the following model:</p><disp-formula id="E2"><mml:math id="M2" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="right center left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>y</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ij</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#956;</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#945;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>G</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>j</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#949;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ijk</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where y<sub>ij</sub> represents all the previous cited patterns as dependent variables; &#956; is the overall mean; &#945;<sub>i</sub> is the silo random effect; G was the effect of the jth group (GP, SIL, and SIL+) (j = 1, &#8230;3) and &#949;<sub>ijk</sub> was the error term.</p><p>The microbial data after ensiling were subject to a multifactorial ANOVA according to the following model:</p><disp-formula id="E3"><mml:math id="M3" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="right center left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>y</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ijk</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#956;</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#945;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>G</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>j</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>T</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>k</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>G</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#215;</mml:mo><mml:mo>T</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>jk</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#949;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ijkl</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>where y<sub>ij</sub> represents all the microbial patterns as dependent variables; &#956; is the overall mean; &#945;<sub>i</sub> is the silo random effect; G was the effect of the jth group (SIL and SIL+) (j = 1, 2); T represents the effect of the kth time after desilation (k = 1, &#8230;4); G &#215; T represents the effect of the binary interaction of the jth group and kth time (1,&#8230;,8) and &#949;<sub>ijk</sub> was the error term. When not significant, the binary interaction was dropped from the model. A Tukey test was applied to evaluate the differences according to time.</p><p>The significance was set at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, and the results were expressed as means and standard error of the means.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Chemical Composition and Microbiological Analyses</title><p>The chemical composition of GP, SIL, and SIL+ is shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. There are no differences after ensiling with or without <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG in DM, CP, EE, NDF, ADF, and ash (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05), although ME showed the highest values in SIL+ (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01) and lower in SIL compared to GP (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). NFC content was lower in SIL+ than GP and SIL (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). Moreover, ensiling (both SIL and SIL+) showed lower pH compared to the GP (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and WSC disappeared (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Impact of ensiling with or without <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG on chemical composition and pH of grape pomace.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>GP</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SIL</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SIL+</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>MSE</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DM (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.211</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0422</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP, % of DM</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.078</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1699</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EE, % of DM</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2258</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ash, % of DM</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.081</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2882</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDF, % of DM</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.237</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3885</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADF, % of DM</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.117</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6221</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NFC, % of DM</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.6<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.4<sup>C</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.323</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WSC, % of DM</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.82<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.52<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.49<sup>C</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ME, Mj/kg DM</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.91<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.67<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.10<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0411</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">DM, dry matter; CP, crude protein; EE, ether extract; NDF, neutral detergent fiber; ADF, acid detergent fiber; NFC, non-fiber carbohydrate; WSC, water soluble carbohydrates; ME, metabolizable energy; GP, grape pomace; SIL, grape pomace after silage; SIL+, grape pomace after silage with L. plantarum 5BG; MSE, mean standard error</italic>.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Different letters correspond to statistical differences. A, B, C = P &lt;0.01; a, b, c = P &lt;0.05</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The results of GP microbiological analyses, before ensiling, are shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. Total AMB and LAB loads were 6.22 &#177; 0.07 log cfu/g and 5.96 &#177; 0.13 log cfu/g, respectively. Yeast load was 7.39 &#177; 0.08 log cfu/g, while the cell densities of SFB, <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> were 2.94, 2.26, and 0.8 log cfu/g, respectively.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Microbiological characteristics of grape pomace (GP). The microbial loads (log cfu/g) of total aerobic mesophilic bacteria (AMB), lactic acid bacteria (LAB), yeasts, spore-forming bacteria (SFB), <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> are reported as means and standard deviation (error bars).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-808293-g0001.jpg"/></fig><p>In SIL (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>) the AMB counts did not vary significantly over time, while in SIL+ the values were significantly lower at the opening of the silage (0 h) (5 &#177; 0.04 log cfu/g) than at 144 h (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). However, after 6 d (144 h) both silages presented equal values (6.3 log cfu/g). SIL+ showed LAB population ranging from 5.60 &#177; 0.15 log cfu/g (0 h) to 6.17 &#177; 0.15 log cfu/g (144 h) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05), and both silages did not show significant differences at the same times.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Microbiological characteristics of the silage with (SIL+) or without (SIL) <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG inoculation. The microbial loads (log cfu/g) of total aerobic mesophilic bacteria (AMB), lactic acid bacteria (LAB), and spore-forming bacteria (SFB) and yeasts are reported. Values of each time point are the means of three replicates &#177; standard error (error bars). Different letters of the same color show statistical differences among time (A, B = <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01; a, b = <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05); *, ** show statistical differences between groups at the same time (*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05; **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-808293-g0002.jpg"/></fig><p>At the opening of the silages and in all experimental times, SFB showed no differences between SIL and SIL+ (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05); however, they increased in SIL (P &lt;0.01) and SIL+ (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) after 48 h and then remained constant in both experimental trials.</p><p>After opening, the SIL yeast population was higher than SIL+ (5.66 &#177; 0.1 log cfu/g) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), but after 6 d yeasts increased in SIL+ reaching values (6.5 &#177; 0.19 log cfu/g) higher than SIL (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01).</p><p>Moreover, enterobacteria and <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> were present in GP, but both were absent in silage; while molds and <italic toggle="yes">Ls. monocytogenes</italic> were absent in both GP and silages.</p></sec><sec><title>Identification and Quantification of Phenolic Compounds and Antioxidant Activity</title><p>The chromatographic profiles of GP extract at &#955; = 520, 280, and 350 nm are shown in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref> and the identified compounds are listed in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The analytical profile of SIL and SIL+ extracts was comparable to that one of GP, only quantitative differences occurred.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>HPLC separation of phenolic compounds in GP extract (<italic toggle="yes">V. vinifera</italic> L., cv Nero di Troia), at &#955; = 520, 280, and 350 nm. For peak assignment, see <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-808293-g0003.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Peaks assignment of phenolic compounds extracted from grape pomace (<italic toggle="yes">V. vinifera</italic> L., cv Nero di Troia).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>No</bold>.</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Compound</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>RT (min)</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gallic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catechin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epicatechin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delphinidin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syringic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyanidin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Petunidin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peonidin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malvidin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rutin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quercetin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malvidin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-coumaroylglucoside <italic toggle="yes">(t)</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quercetin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">RT, Retention Time</italic>.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">(t), Tentatively identified compound</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The targeted HPLC analysis of GP extracts at &#955; = 520 nm revealed the presence of anthocyanins, with the typical five peaks of the monoglycosilated anthocyanins present in grape, according to the order delphinidin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside, cyanidin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside, petunidin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside, peonidin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside, and the predominant malvidin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside, which were identified by comparison with reference compounds. Additionally, some peaks were detected with retention time higher than that of malvidin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside, representing acylated anthocyanins, which were not assigned to specific structures, exclusively based on the UV-Vis spectra, except for the peak at RT= 36.5 being tentatively identified as malvidin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-coumaroylglucoside (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).</p><p>Phenolic profile content of GP, SIL, and SIL+ is reported in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. GP showed a total anthocyanins content higher than SIL (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) and SIL+ (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). SIL showed monoglycosilated anthocyanins, rutin, and epicatechin content lower than GP (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01) and the highest content of syringic acid (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). SIL+ showed the lowest content of gallic acid, monoglycosilated anthocyanins, rutin, catechin, and epicatechin (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01) and the highest content of acylated anthocyanins (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01) and quercetin (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Moreover, SIL+ showed a catechin and epicatechin contents lower than SIL (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) and GP (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Phenolic profile content (mg/g dry weight) in grape pomace (GP), after silage with (SIL+) or without (SIL) <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG inoculation, quantified by HPLC analysis (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Phenolic structure</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Phenolic compounds</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>GP</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SIL</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SIL+</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SEM</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-flavonoids</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hydroxybenzoic acids</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gallic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0006</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Syringic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0013</td></tr><tr style="border-top: thin solid #000000;"><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavonoids</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthocyanins</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monoglycosilated</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23<sup>C</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acylated</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0034</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.32<sup>Aa</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.72<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.63<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0092</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavonols (as rutin eq.)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rutin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02<sup>C</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quercetin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27 <sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0442</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flavanols (as catechin eq.)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catechin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66<sup>Aa</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13<sup>Bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0048</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Epicatechin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12<sup>C</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">Different letters in the same line show statistical differences: A, B, C = P &lt;0.01; a, b, c = P &lt;0.05</italic>.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">GP, grape pomace; SIL, grape pomace after silage; SIL+, grape pomace after silage with L. plantarum 5BG; SEM, mean standard error</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p><xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> reports the total phenol content (TPC) and the antioxidant activity of GP, SIL, and SIL+. The TPC in SIL+ was lower than SIL (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). The lowest ORAC activity was measured in SIL+ (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01), although no statistical differences were observed between GP, SIL, and SIL+ about TEAC activity (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Total phenol content (TPC) and antioxidant activity (by TEAC and ORAC assays) in grape pomace (GP), and after silage with (SIL+) or without (SIL) <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG (per g dry weight).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>GP</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SIL</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SIL+</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SEM</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPC (mg GAE/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.99<sup>AB</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.88<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.60<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0063</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TEAC (&#956;mol TE/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140.82</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.85</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121.92</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4248</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ORAC (&#956;mol TE/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219.97<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">218.36<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154.23<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.78</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0062</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">Different letters in the same line show statistical differences: A, B = P &lt;0.01</italic>.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">GP, grape pomace; SIL, grape pomace after silage; SIL+, grape pomace after silage with L. plantarum 5BG; SEM, mean standard error</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> Digestion and Gas Production</title><p><xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref> reports the results of apparent percentage of disappearance after <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> digestion. SIL+ showed the highest DM, OM, NDF, CP, EE, and NFC disappearance (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01). Moreover, SIL showed higher DM, OM, NDF, CP, EE, and NFC percentage of disappearance compared to GP (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Percentage of disappearance after <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> digestion in grape pomace (GP), after silage with (SIL+) or without (SIL) <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>GP</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SIL</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SIL+</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SEM</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DM (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.5<sup>C</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.1<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OM (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.2<sup>C</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.3<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.8<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDF (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.2<sup>C</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.7<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.83</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADF (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.8<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.3<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.5<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EE (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.5<sup>C</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.9<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NFC (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.8<sup>C</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.1<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.67</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">Different letters in the same line show statistical differences: A, B, C = P &lt;0.01</italic>.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">DM, dry matter; OM, organic matter; NDF, neutral detergent fiber; ADF, acid detergent fiber; CP, crude protein; EE, ether extract; NFC, non-fiber carbohydrate; GP, grape pomace; SIL, grape pomace after silage; SIL+, grape pomace after silage with L. plantarum 5BG; SEM, mean standard error</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> gas production results are reported in <xref rid="T6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>. SIL+ showed the lowest propionic (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01) <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> production and the highest butyric, methane (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01) and nitrogen (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> production, although the total gas production and the total VFA production did not show differences among treatments (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> gas production in grape pomace (GP), after silage with (SIL+) or without (SIL) <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>GP</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SIL</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SIL+</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SEM</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total gas production (mL)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2002</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total VFA (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3621</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetic (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4052</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propionic (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.3<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.0<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.9<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0254</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Butyric (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.3<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.8<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.7<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methane (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7<sup>B</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.1<sup>A</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogen (NH<sub>3</sub>-N) (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.9<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.0<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0182</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">Different letters in the same line show statistical differences: A, B = P &lt;0.01; a, b = P &lt;0.05</italic>.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">VFA, volatile fatty acids; GP, grape pomace; SIL, grape pomace after silage; SIL+, grape pomace after silage with L. plantarum 5BG; SEM, mean standard error</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Chemical Composition Characterization and Ensiling Effects</title><p>Feed digestibility is an important factor in the nutritional efficiency assessment of a ration. Among the three experimental treatments (GP, SIL, and SIL+), DM, OM, CP, EE, ash, NDF, ADF, and NFC values are often not consistent with those reported in the literature. For example, Spanghero et al. (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>) observed slightly higher content of DM in Italian red and white grape pomace, but lower in the Californian red one. On the other hand, in both grape pomaces investigated, they observed similar values of OM and CP, higher values of EE and ADF and lower values of NDF. Massaro Junior et al. (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), studying South African red grape pomace, observed lower DM content, similar OM and NDF content, and higher EE, CP, and ADF content. Nevertheless, the high variability in the GP chemical composition depends on different factors such as the type of grape, grape maturity, wine production methods, components proportions (seeds and pulp), harvest methods (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). For these reasons it is difficult to compare values and results among different studies. Some authors stated that grape pomace DM should be &gt;250 g/kg to obtain a good quality silage; some others defined an interval between 280 and 400 g/kg of DM to avoid high nutrient losses (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). The GP used in our experiment for ensiling showed a suitable DM content and the nutrient losses were almost null. Similarly, some authors observed no change in DM, CP, and ash after anaerobic storage (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). It can be supposed that this lack of differences can be due to the short storage time (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>), and that ensiling both with and without <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG addition had no great effect on grape pomace nutritional composition. Results showed that pH decreased with ensiling, and it decreased even more when <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG was added. There are different approaches to the suitability of pH values for silage: some authors defined pH value 4.2 as the upper threshold for a positive assessment of a silage, while other researchers stated that the final pH is not important; what matters is the decreasing rate, as this parameter is more important in inhibiting a secondary fermentation occurrence (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). The decrease of pH values during the ensiling process can be related to fermentation activities involving NFC consumption (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>) but also WSC (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>).</p><p>The results of the present work are consistent with this knowledge. LAB fermentation activities lead to the organic acid production with consequent pH reduction (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Probably, the strain addition improved the fermentation processes inducing a lower concentration of NFC and WSC, and lower pH values. This result could be due to an efficient homofermentative lactic acid production promoted by the LAB strain (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p><p>The ensiling process reduced the grape pomace ME, but the <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG addition seemed to enhance it. Similarly, Alipour and Rouzbehan (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) reported that ensiling reduced the grape pomace ME, probably due to a reduction of some nutrient availability and the incapacity of this storage process to reduce all the tannins and their negative effects on digestibility. Probably, the <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG was able to increase grape pomace ME throughout a greater reduction of phenolic substances and consequently higher digestibility.</p></sec><sec><title>Microbiological Quality</title><p>Plant-associated microbiota is composed of bacteria, including LAB, <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus</italic> sp., <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium</italic> sp., and coliform bacteria, as well as yeasts and molds. In general, a LAB number is considered a fundamental factor in predicting the suitability for the silage fermentation and in evaluating the need to apply the bacterial inoculants at ensiling. In fact, when the LAB number exceeds 5 log cfu/g, the silage can be well preserved. On the contrary, the low LAB number and the high number of harmful microorganisms could indicate the need to control the fermentation of the silage by LAB inoculation (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). The proliferation of undesirable microorganisms can cause direct DM and nutrients losses, but also indirect issues, due to reduced palatability and the risk of negative effects on the animal performance and health (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). In this current work, the epiphytic microbiota in GP was evaluated, and decided to proceed with the inoculation with <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG, although high LAB counts were observed (ca. 5.9 log cfu/g). During ensiling, the role of LAB is to decrease pH by converting carbohydrates into organic acids which help to preserve the silage. Moreover, LAB inhibits the growth of undesirable microorganisms by competing for nutrients and synthesizing antimicrobial and antifungal agents (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Different LAB species synthesize some metabolites, such as bacteriocins, hydrogen peroxide, and organic acids that inhibit the growth of pathogenic and spoilage bacteria, yeast, and molds (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG, used in our study as a grape pomace inoculant, was able to produce antimicrobial compounds and organic acids responsible for antifungal properties (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>).</p><p>The results of the current work showed that the LAB number present in both silages (SIL and SIL+) can guarantee the quality of the silage. In fact, <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacteriaceae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> were absent in the silages and SFB were in low number. After ensiling, both LAB and yeast populations were still high in number probably due to the carbon source quantities in GP that were suitable in supporting microbial growth. As observed in this study (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), after ensiling, NCF decreased significantly probably due to their use by microorganisms. Furthermore, after ensiling, the tannin precursors decreased; therefore, a reduction of their inhibitory effect on the bacterial population could be hypothesized (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>).</p><p>Yeast counts in GP were higher than the reported values in other silage crops (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>) and similar to those found in grape marc at the beginning of storage (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>), while, after opening, yeasts were lower in SIL+ than in untreated and acidified marc studied by Maragkoudakis et al. (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Probably, the yeast number decreased as results of pH reduction and antifungal activity of <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). During air exposure, yeast population remained substantially stable, however, as it is known, yeasts can cause aerobic deterioration and reduce the nutritional value of the silage (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Therefore, further research is needed to improve yeast control.</p></sec><sec><title>HPLC Analysis: Anthocyanins and Other Phenolic Compounds</title><p>While the silages, with or without the <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG addition, did not show effects on the anthocyanins chromatographic profile (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>), it revealed evidence of change in the anthocyanins concentration. In fact, ensiling decreased total anthocyanins content by 12%, whereas monoglycosylated anthocyanins content decreased much more (by 20%). Ensiling with <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG addition led to a more significant reduction of monoglycosilated anthocyanins content than GP (reduction of 52%); comparing the two silage techniques, a 40% reduction occurred with LAB strain inoculation than without any supplement. The acylated anthocyanins content increased only in SIL+, reaching values of almost 20 and 25% higher than GP and SIL, respectively.</p><p>All these results point to the conclusion that the silage processes (with or without LAB strain inoculation) lead to an overall decreasing trend in the total anthocyanins content. On the other hand, acylated anthocyanins increased, exclusively with the addition of <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG. Thus, it can be hypothesized that, during silage with inoculated LAB strain, monoglycosilated anthocyanins undergo acylation by acyltransferases of bacterial origin (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>).</p><p>The total amount of anthocyanins found in GP (cv Nero di Troia) was within the range reported in other research (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>), or to grape skin of the same cultivar Nero di Troia, limited to monoglycosilated anthocyanins (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>).</p><p>The represented phenolic acids in the samples were the hydroxybenzoic acids, i.e., gallic and syringic acids. Gallic acid content did not change during silage (SIL) but decreased in SIL+. Syringic acid content was higher in SIL. As grape pomace is a highly oxidized product, syringic acid is supposed to be formed through oxidative degradation of malvidin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). The value we found in GP was consistent with previous reports for different grape cultivar pomace (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). With silage, a degradative oxidation of (monoglycosilated) anthocyanins occurred (with a 20% decrease), producing syringic acid from the degradation of malvidin 3-<italic toggle="yes">O</italic>-glucoside, possibly also from microbiological intervention. When GP was silaged with the addition of <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG, monoglycosilated anthocyanins were further degraded (more than 50%) compared to GP sample, as oxidation of phenolic compounds can be supported by laccase from LAB origin (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). Conversely, syringic acid content did not change; the intervention of the strain 5BG could lead to a different metabolic fate of syringic acid.</p><p>Among flavonols, in GP rutin was predominant, followed by quercetin. In SIL samples, rutin content dropped (72% decrease), as well as in SIL+ samples (94% decrease). Moreover, the reduction in SIL+ was remarkable (78% reduction), even when compared to SIL. On the contrary, quercetin tended to increase in SIL+, being concomitant with the rutin decrease. This result was expected as quercetin is the aglycone which is released after rutin hydrolysis.</p><p>Catechin and epicatechin amounts occurred in GP samples after anthocyanins. The total flavanol content (catechin and epicatechin) was in the same range as reported in grape by-products from different red grape varieties (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). The catechin was predominant over epicatechin, as usually reported, except in a few grape cultivars (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>).</p><p>Flavanols (catechin and epicatechin) content in SIL and SIL+ decreased by ~36% and ~80% of the value in GP, respectively. The reduction of flavanol content could be a positive aspect, as catechin and epicatechin are the precursor compounds of condensed tannins, which, as described in the published literature, tend to influence the digestibility of the feeding ration (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>). When GP has been used for feeding purposes (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), the reported content of epicatechin was 0.11 mg g<sup>&#8722;1</sup>, comparable to the content found in our experiments after ensiling with <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG addition.</p><p>It has been reported already that the anaerobic storage of a plant matrix leads to a decrease of polyphenolic content (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). In ensiled grape pomace in particular, Alipour and Rouzbehan (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) found a reduction of total phenols and tannins. Moreover, it has been shown that storage increased the polymerization of existing tannins into higher oligomers (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). Thus, it can be hypothesized that polymerization occurs at the expenses of tannins precursors (flavanols). <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> could be more efficient to promote polymerization than the existing microorganisms in the silage.</p></sec><sec><title>Hydrophilic Antioxidants: Phenols and Antioxidant Capacity</title><p>The phenols content in GP (cv Nero di Troia) was in the same range as in past publications, both in different Italian red grape cultivars (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>), and international cultivars (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>), also used for feeding cows (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>).</p><p>With ensiling, the phenol content was statistically lower in SIL+. The same trend was shown for the antioxidant capacity: silage, with or without <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG addition, reduced the total phenol content and, consequently, the antioxidant capacity of the samples.</p><p>The antioxidant capacity in GP, assessed by TEAC assay, was similar to that reported by Gonz&#225;lez-Param&#225;s et al. (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>), but lower than Rockenbach et al. (<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>). The ORAC value in our experiments revealed the same trend reported by Yilmaz and Toledo (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>) in international grape varieties, even if they used &#946;-phycoerithrin as fluorescent marker instead of fluorescein.</p></sec><sec><title>Apparent Percentage of Disappearance After <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> Digestion and Gas Production</title><p>Rumen digestibility represents an important factor to define feeds nutrients productive efficiency and animals' environmental impact. Therefore, the evaluation of the inclusion of innovative food on rumen digestibility plays a key role for in field application (<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>). Ensiling did not affect most of the chemical constituents, both with and without <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG inclusion, but a more significant effect on <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> digestibility was found. Ensiling increased the DM, OM, NDF, CP, EE, and NFC percentage of disappearance, and these results were even improved by <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG inoculation. Past publications reported that ensiling GP released secondary compounds as tannins (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>) and that they may negatively affect digestibility, particularly because they can bind crude proteins, minerals, and carbohydrates (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>, <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>). The current study showed that ensiling reduced the GP flavanols (tannins precursors) content and that the <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG addition reduced even more their concentration. Similarly, other researchers reported that anaerobic storage like ensiling can be used to reduce tannins content of grape pomace (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>). It is known that <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> is a LAB species able to degrade phenolic compounds, but the metabolic pathways of their degradation in LAB have not been completely described (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Furthermore, many factors can influence the results of a LAB addition, such as the characteristics of raw materials, epiphytic microbiota, and the silage management. A recent work (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) investigated the biotransformation of phenolic compounds in sainfoin silage inoculated with <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> and observed the reduction of flavanols (catechin and epicatechin). The flavanols content reduction can explain digestibility differences found in this study among SIL, SIL+, and GP (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>). The antioxidant activity of these secondary compounds (tannins, anthocyanins, etc.) can be exerted also on the rumen microbial activity reducing and/or inhibiting some of them and, consequently, reducing the digestive capability. It is well known that <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> addition, apart from accelerating lactic acid production and inhibiting detrimental microorganisms' growth, may also further control microorganism population conferring antimicrobial properties to silage and outcompeting them for free sugars (<xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>, <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>). On the other hand, it is inferred that <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> addition improves digestibility likely throughout the reduction of all phenolic compounds that may inhibit microbial activity (<xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>, <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>). Total gas production values for GP were similar to those reported by other authors (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>), and they increased in SIL+. Differently from what was reported by some authors (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), the reduction in flavanols content in SIL+ could be the main cause of the increase in gas production during digestion. The total volatile fatty acids production did not change, but there was an increase in butyric acid and a slightly decrease in propionic acid in SIL+ compared to both GP and SIL.</p><p>The substrate for the production of butyric acid is dietary fiber, which undergoes different metabolic pathways as a result of bacterial fermentation, starting from glucose and, consequently, carbohydrates availability (<xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>). Ensiling reduced the NFC content, likely because the latter represent the first suitable substrate for the growth of the microbiota, as also confirmed by the <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG addition. Moreover, NFC digestibility increased with ensiling probably due to the lower total phenol content and flavanols (condensed tannins precursors), resulting in a higher and faster butyric acid production and thus a lower and slower propionic acid production.</p><p>Ammonia nitrogen represents one of the major sources for microbial growth and microbial protein synthesis in the rumen (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>) and its production rate is strictly linked to the dietary rumen protein degradation (<xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>). The increased ammonia nitrogen values observed in <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic>-added silage probably could be due to the increased protein digestibility, considering that high antioxidant component inclusion in feed tends to reduce the ammonia nitrogen concentration (<xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>). This result shows how ensiling processes can give more nitrogen availability and digestibility with a consequent higher nutrient availability for microbial populations. In fact, some authors reported that ammonia concentration, a key metabolite for nitrogen production, decreased due to a lower protein degradation in the feed and a lower microbial protein synthesis (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>).</p><p>The CH<sub>4</sub> production tended to be higher in the SIL+ compared to the other treatments. It seems that ensiling with <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG increased its production. Methane production depends not only on the available fermentable substrate amount but also to the proportion of VFA produced during the fermentation (<xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>). Also condensed tannins content has been reported to correlate negatively with CH<sub>4</sub> production (<xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>). Tannins have both the ability to reduce protein and carbohydrate availability for rumen microorganism fermentation, complexing them (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>), and the capacity to inhibit bacteria, protozoas, and archeans, activity (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>). Furthermore, tannins may inhibit the growth or activity of rumen methanogen and protozoa through bactericidal or bacteriostatic activities (<xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>), most likely through binding proteins and enzymes of the microbial cells (<xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>). Although the lower content of NFC, the lower phenols content in the SIL+ probably had a synergic effect combining more substrate availability for fermentation and lower phenols inhibition of fermentation.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The results of this study suggested GP as an alternative ingredient in animal feeding. The nutrient content of GP did not show important changes with ensiling, except for the reduction of NFC content, probably because of its role in fermentation kinetics. In addition, the level of condensed tannins precursors (flavanols) was reduced by the ensiling process. This was more effective if the <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG was added to the silage. Moreover, total phenol content and antioxidant activity were both reduced by strain 5BG addition. These combined observations are consistent with the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> digestibility of the ensiled grape pomace, particularly when <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG was added. In fact, all parameters investigated show increased percentage of disappearance, confirming a better <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> digestibility of GP if ensiled with <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG. Furthermore, ensiling with <italic toggle="yes">L. plantarum</italic> 5BG addition was able to affect <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> rumen fermentation patterns and methane <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> production. Although total volatile fatty acids production did not show differences, butyric acid and methane production slightly increased. In conclusion, ensiled grape pomace can represent an important source of digestible nutrient for ruminants and SIL+ may be an alternative feed. However, additional research demonstrating the <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> utilization, or at least further advanced <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> techniques are needed.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be made available by the authors, without undue reservation.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by Ethics Committee for Animal Testing&#8211;CESA (process number 2-X/17) of the Department of Veterinary Medicine of the University of Bari.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>PDB: investigation, formal analysis, writing-original draft, and writing-review and editing. AM: conceptualization, investigation, data curation, formal analysis, writing-original draft, and writing-review and editing. CA: investigation. PDP: conceptualization, investigation, funding acquisition, resources, project administration, and writing-review and editing. FB: investigation, visualization, supervision, writing-original draft, and writing-review and editing. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="s9"><title>Funding</title><p>This research was funded in part by the CNR-DiSBA project NutrAge (FOE-2019, DSB.AD004.271).</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s10"><title>Publisher's Note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors would like to thank Stella Lisa Lonigro, Leone D'Amico, Giovanna Calzaretti, and Francesco Giannico for their technical assistance. We are grateful to the winery Crifo (Ruvo di Puglia, BA, Italy) for providing grape pomace. The authors are also grateful to Ludovico Varallo for the English revision of the manuscript. The authors thank the Regional Project Rete di Laboratori per l'Innovazione degli Alimenti Funzionali (LAIFF) (PO Puglia FESR 2007-2013 Asse I, Linea 1.2 - PO Puglia FSE 2007-2013 Asse IV) which allowed the spectrofluorimeter Infinite M-200 (Tecan Group Ltd., M&#228;nnedorf, Switzerland) purchasing.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salami</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valenti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'grady</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kerry</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattioli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Licitra</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of dietary cardoon meal on growth performance and selected meat quality parameters of lambs, and the antioxidant potential of cardoon extract in ovine muscle homogenates</article-title>. <source>Meat Sci</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>153</volume>:<fpage>126</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2019.03.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30927684</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moate</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hixson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deighton</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hannah</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of feeding either red or white grape marc on milk production and methane emissions from early-lactation dairy cows</article-title>. <source>Animals.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>976</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani10060976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32512732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7341285</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>SRO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berrisford</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moate</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynard</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Reducing methane on-farm by feeding diets high in fat may not always reduce life cycle greenhouse gas emissions</article-title>. <source>Int J Life Cycle Assess.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>78</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11367-013-0619-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cieslak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szumacher-Strabel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stochmal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oleszek</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Plant components with specific activities against rumen methanogens</article-title>. <source>Animal.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>253</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1751731113000852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23739468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brenes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Viveros</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chamorro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arija</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Use of polyphenol-rich grape by-products in monogastric nutrition. A review</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>211</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2015.09.016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vallini</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fava</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Michelini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Recovery of polyphenols from red grape pomace and assessment of their antioxidant and anti-cholesterol activities</article-title>. <source>N Biotechnol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>338</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nbt.2015.12.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26705904</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmedna</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Functional components of grape pomace: their composition, biological properties and potential <italic toggle="yes">applications</italic></article-title>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>37</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2621.2012.03197.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Basalan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gungor</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>FN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yalcinkaya</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nutrient content and in vitro digestibility of Turkish grape pomaces</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>169</volume>:<fpage>194</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2011.07.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ringseis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eder</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dusel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Determination of polyphenol and crude nutrient content and nutrient digestibility of dried and ensiled white and red grape pomace cultivars</article-title>. <source>Arch Anim Nutr.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>200</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1745039X.2015.1039751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25963744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schogor</surname><given-names>ALB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Marchi</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grande</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Citrus pulp as a dietary source of antioxidants for lactating holstein cows fed highly polyunsaturated fatty acid diets</article-title>. <source>Asian-australas J Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1104</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5713/ajas.2013.13836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25083104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4109866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moate</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>SRO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torok</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hannah</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribaux</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tavendale</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Grape marc reduces methane emissions when fed to dairy cows</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>97</volume>:<fpage>5073</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>87</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2013-7588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24952778</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manso</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallardo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salv&#225;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerra-Rivas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mantec&#243;n</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lav&#237;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of dietary grape pomace combined with linseed oil on fatty acid profile and milk composition</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>1111</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2015-9981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26709181</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ianni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Maio</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pittia</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grotta</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perpetuini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tofalo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Chemical-;nutritional quality and oxidative stability of milk and dairy products obtained from Friesian cows fed with a dietary supplementation of dried grape pomace</article-title>. <source>J Sci Food Agric.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>3635</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.9584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30629293</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alipour</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rouzbehan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of ensiling grape pomace and addition of polyethylene glycol on in vitro gas production and microbial biomass yield</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>137</volume>:<fpage>138</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>49</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2006.09.020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabacco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Revello-Chion</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borreani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of Lactobacillus buchneri LN4637 and Lactobacillus buchneri LN40177 on the aerobic stability, fermentation products, and microbial populations of corn silage under farm conditions</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>5589</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>98</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2011-4286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22032382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borreani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabacco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muck</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Silage review: factors affecting dry matter and quality losses in silages</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>101</volume>:<fpage>3952</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>79</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2017-13837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29685272</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muck</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadeau</surname><given-names>EMG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mcallister</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Contreras-Govea</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kung</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Silage review: Recent advances and future uses of silage additives</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>101</volume>:<fpage>3980</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4000</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2017-13839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29685273</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of lactic acid bacteria and molasses additives on the microbial community and fermentation quality of soybean silage</article-title>. <source>Bioresour Technol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>238</volume>:<fpage>706</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2017.04.055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28501002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> additive and temperature on the ensiling quality and microbial community dynamics of cauliflower leaf silages</article-title>. <source>Bioresour Technol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>307</volume>:<fpage>123238</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2020.123238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32247271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of the microbial community, metabolome and biotransformation of phenolic compounds of sainfoin (<italic toggle="yes">Onobrychis viciifolia</italic>) silage ensiled with or without inoculation of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus plantarum</italic></article-title>. <source>Bioresour Technol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>316</volume>:<fpage>123910</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2020.123910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32750640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodr&#237;guez</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Curiel</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Landete</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Las Rivas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Felipe</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#243;mez-Cordov&#233;s</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Food phenolics and lactic acid bacteria</article-title>. <source>Int J Food Microbiol.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>132</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2009.03.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19419788</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wittouck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salvetti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franz</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mattarelli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A taxonomic note on the genus Lactobacillus: Description of 23 novel genera, emended description of the genus Lactobacillus Beijerinck 1901, and union of Lactobacillaceae and Leuconostocaceae</article-title>. <source>Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>2782</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>858</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijsem.0.004107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32293557</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavermicocca</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Angiolillo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lonigro</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valerio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bevilacqua</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perricone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Lactobacillus plantarum 5BG survives during refrigerated storage bio-preserving packaged spanish-style table olives (cv. <italic toggle="yes">Bella di Cerignola</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>889</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.00889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29867802</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5949355</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>AOAC</collab></person-group>. <source>Official Methods of Analysis</source>. <publisher-loc>Gathersburg, MD</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>AOAC</publisher-name> (<year>2005</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Soest</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Methods for dietary fiber, neutral detergent fiber, and nonstarch polysaccharides in relation to animal nutrition</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>1991</year>) <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>3583</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>97</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(91)78551-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1660498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Givens</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Getachew</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of NRC, UC Davis and ADAS approaches to estimate the metabolizable energy values of feeds at maintenance energy intake from equations utilizing chemical assays and in vitro determinations</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>114</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2003.12.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mcdonald</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>The Biochemistry of Silage</source>. <publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Chalcombe Publications</publisher-name> (<year>1991</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>&#193;vila</surname><given-names>CLS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Silage fermentation&#8212;updates focusing on the performance of micro-organisms</article-title>. <source>J Appl Microbiol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>128</volume>:<fpage>966</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.14450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31519038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerardi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calabriso</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carluccio</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Durante</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mita</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Techno-functional properties of tomato puree fortified with anthocyanin pigments</article-title>. <source>Food Chem.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>240</volume>:<fpage>1184</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2017.08.057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28946241</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aleixandre-Tudo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du Toit</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of UV-Visible spectroscopy for phenolic compounds quantification in winemaking</article-title>. In: <source>Frontiers and New Trends in the Science of Fermented Food and Beverages</source>. London, UK: IntechOpen (<year>2019</year>). Available online at: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5772/intechopen.79550</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rana</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Separation, identification, quantification, and method validation of anthocyanins in botanical supplement raw materials by HPLC and HPLC&#8211;MS</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>3515</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf010389p</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11513621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maggiolino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lorenzo</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qui&#241;ones</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Latorre</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blando</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Centoducati</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of dietary supplementation with Pinus taeda hydrolyzed lignin on in vivo performances, <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> nutrient apparent digestibility, and gas emission in beef steers</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>255</volume>:<fpage>114217</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2019.114217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marten</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prediction of energy digestibility of forages with rumen fermentation and fungal enzyme systems. In: Pigden CBW, Graham M, editors</article-title>. <source>Standardization of Analytical Methodology for Feeds Workshop</source>. <publisher-loc>Ottawa, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Development Research Centre</publisher-name> (<year>1980</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trotta</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klotz</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harmon</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of source and level of dietary energy supplementation on <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> digestibility and methane production from tall fescue-based diets</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>242</volume>:<fpage>41</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2018.05.010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rinker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mcleod</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harmon</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Yucca schidigera extract decreases in vitro methane production in a variety of forages and diets</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>159</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2010.05.005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naziroglu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuce</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of vitamin e on ruminal fermentation in vitro</article-title>. <source>J Vet Med A Physiol Pathol Clin Med.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>251</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1439-0442.2002.00418.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12126139</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>SAS</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>SAS</article-title>. In: Ra G, editor. <source>The SAS System for Windows</source><publisher-loc>Cary, NC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SAS</publisher-name> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spanghero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salem</surname><given-names>AZM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chemical composition, including secondary metabolites, and rumen fermentability of seeds and pulp of Californian (USA) and Italian grape pomaces</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>152</volume>:<fpage>243</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2009.04.015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Massaro Junior</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bumbieris Junior</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zanin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Da Silva</surname><given-names>LDDF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galbeiro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of storage time and use of additives on the quality of grape pomace silages</article-title>. <source>J Food Process Preserv.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>e14373</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jfpp.14373</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laufenberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nystroem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Transformation of vegetable waste into value added products:: (A) the upgrading concept; (B) practical implementations</article-title>. <source>Bioresour Technol.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>87</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>98</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-8524(02)00167-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12765356</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baumg&#228;rtel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kluth</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Epperlein</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodehutscord</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A note on digestibility and energy value for sheep of different grape pomace</article-title>. <source>Small Ruminant Research.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>302</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smallrumres.2005.11.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruberto</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Renda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amico</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tringali</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Volatile components of grape pomaces from different cultivars of Sicilian Vitis vinifera L</article-title>. <source>Bioresour Technol.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>260</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2006.12.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17321134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ben Salem</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saghrouni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nefzaoui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Attempts to deactivate tannins in fodder shrubs with physical and chemical treatments</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>122</volume>:<fpage>109</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2005.04.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jobim</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nussio</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Avan&#231;os metodol&#243;gicos na avalia&#231;&#227;o da qualidade da forragem conservada</article-title>. <source>J Revista Brasileira de Zootecnia.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>101</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>19</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1516-35982007001000013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of cultivar, wilting and storage period on fermentation and the clostridial community of alfalfa silage</article-title>. <source>Ital J Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>336</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1828051X.2017.1364984</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schn&#252;rer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Magnusson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antifungal lactic acid bacteria as biopreservatives</article-title>. <source>Trends Food Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>70</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tifs.2004.02.014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valerio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Biase</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lattanzio</surname><given-names>VMT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavermicocca</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Improvement of the antifungal activity of lactic acid bacteria by addition to the growth medium of phenylpyruvic acid, a precursor of phenyllactic acid</article-title>. <source>Int J Food Microbiol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>222</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2016.01.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26827290</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolci</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabacco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cocolin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borreani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Microbial dynamics during aerobic exposure of corn silage stored under oxygen barrier or polyethylene films</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>7499</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>507</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.05050-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21821764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3209159</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maragkoudakis</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nardi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bovo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D'andrea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giacomini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Biodiversity, dynamics and ecology of bacterial community during grape marc storage for the production of grappa</article-title>. <source>Int J Food Microbiol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>162</volume>:<fpage>143</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2013.01.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23416549</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>N-N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Q-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Anthocyanins and their variation in red wines i. monomeric anthocyanins and their color expression</article-title>. <source>Molecules.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1571</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>601</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules17021571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22314380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6268338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kammerer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Claus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schieber</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Polyphenol Screening of pomace from red and white grape varieties (<italic toggle="yes">Vitis vinifera</italic> L</article-title>.) by HPLC-DAD-MS/MS. <source>J Agric Food Chem.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>4360</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf049613b</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15237937</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rockenbach</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzaga</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rizelio</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gon&#231;alves</surname><given-names>AEDSS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Genovese</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fett</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Phenolic compounds and antioxidant activity of seed and skin extracts of red grape (<italic toggle="yes">Vitis vinifera</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Vitis labrusca</italic>) pomace from Brazilian winemaking</article-title>. <source>Food Res Int.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>897</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>901</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2011.01.049</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sri Harsha</surname><given-names>PSC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simonetti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spigno</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavelli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of phenolics, <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> reducing capacity and anti-glycation activity of red grape skins recovered from winemaking by-products</article-title>. <source>Bioresour Technol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>140</volume>:<fpage>263</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2013.04.092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23707914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicoletti</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bello</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Rossi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corradini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification and quantification of phenolic compounds in grapes by HPLC-PDA-ESI-MS on a semimicro separation scale</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>8801</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf801411m</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18781764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saucier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teissedre</surname><given-names>P-L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monti</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glories</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anthocyanone A: A quinone methide derivative resulting from malvidin 3-O-glucoside degradation</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>2698</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>704</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf062875o</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17338545</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Melo</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Massarioli</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Denny</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dos Santos</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franchin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Winery by-products: Extraction optimization, phenolic composition and cytotoxic evaluation to act as a new source of scavenging of reactive oxygen species</article-title>. <source>Food Chem.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>181</volume>:<fpage>160</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2015.02.087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25794735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Claus</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mojsov</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Enzymes for wine fermentation: current and perspective applications</article-title>. <source>Fermentation</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/fermentation4030052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez-Param&#225;s</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esteban-Ruano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos-Buelga</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Pascual-Teresa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivas-Gonzalo</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Flavanol content and antioxidant activity in winery byproducts</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>234</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf0348727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14733501</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodr&#237;guez Montealegre</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romero Peces</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chac&#243;n Vozmediano</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;nez Gascue&#241;a</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garc&#237;a Romero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Phenolic compounds in skins and seeds of ten grape Vitis vinifera varieties grown in a warm climate</article-title>. <source>J Food Compos Anal.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>687</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jfca.2005.05.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bekhit</surname><given-names>AE-DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mcconnell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mros</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of extraction solvent, waste fraction and grape variety on the antimicrobial and antioxidant activities of extracts from wine residue from cool climate</article-title>. <source>Food Chem.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>134</volume>:<fpage>474</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2012.02.103</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jayanegara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wina</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soliva</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marquardt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreuzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leiber</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dependence of forage quality and methanogenic potential of tropical plants on their phenolic fractions as determined by principal component analysis</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>163</volume>:<fpage>231</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2010.11.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Min</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solaiman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shange</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eun</surname><given-names>J-S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Gastrointestinal bacterial and methanogenic archaea diversity dynamics associated with condensed tannin-containing pine bark diet in goats using 16S rDNA amplicon pyrosequencing</article-title>. <source>Int J Microbiol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>2014</volume>:<fpage>141909</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/141909</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24669219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3941959</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Makkar</surname><given-names>HPS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of storage and urea addition on detannification and in sacco dry matter digestibility of mature oak (<italic toggle="yes">Quercus incana</italic>) leaves</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>1993</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>247</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0377-8401(93)90017-E</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toledo</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Oxygen radical absorbance capacities of grape/wine industry byproducts and effect of solvent type on extraction of grape seed polyphenols</article-title>. <source>J Food Compos Anal.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>41</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jfca.2004.10.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rockenbach</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzaga</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caliari</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Genovese</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gon&#231;alves</surname><given-names>AEDSS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phenolic compounds content and antioxidant activity in pomace from selected red grapes (<italic toggle="yes">Vitis vinifera</italic> L. <italic toggle="yes">and Vitis labrusca L</italic>) widely produced in Brazil</article-title>. <source>Food Chem.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>127</volume>:<fpage>174</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2010.12.137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olivo</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>GTD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#205;tavo</surname><given-names>LCV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva Junior</surname><given-names>RCD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prado</surname><given-names>RMD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessing the nutritional value of agroindustrial co-products and feed through chemical composition, <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> digestibility, and gas production technique %J Acta Scientiarum</article-title>. <source>Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>289</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4025/actascianimsci.v39i3.34024</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mcsweeney</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mcneill</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Microbial interactions with tannins: nutritional consequences for ruminants</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>91</volume>:<fpage>83</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0377-8401(01)00232-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Makkar</surname><given-names>HPS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects and fate of tannins in ruminant animals, adaptation to tannins, and strategies to overcome detrimental effects of feeding tannin-rich feeds</article-title>. <source>Small Ruminant Res.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>241</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0921-4488(03)00142-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayrhuber</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus buchneri</italic> in forage preservation</article-title>. <source>Trends Biotechnol.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>282</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0167-7799(03)00106-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12788549</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gollop</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zakin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>ZG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antibacterial activity of lactic acid bacteria included in inoculants for silage and in silages treated with these inoculants</article-title>. <source>J Appl Microbiol.</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>662</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2004.02504.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15715869</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salvador</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sm&#226;nia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sm&#226;nia</surname><given-names>EFA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maraschin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>SRS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial activity and composition profile of grape (<italic toggle="yes">Vitis vinifera</italic>) pomace extracts obtained by supercritical fluids</article-title>. <source>J Biotechnol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>164</volume>:<fpage>423</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2012.09.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23036924</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bueno</surname><given-names>ICS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brandi</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fagundes</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benetel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muir</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of condensed tannins in the in vitro rumen fermentation kinetics in ruminant species: feeding type involved?</article-title><source>Animals</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>635</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani10040635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32272600</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7222832</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zubair</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Metagenomic analysis of community, enzymes and metabolic pathways during corn straw fermentation with rumen microorganisms for volatile fatty acid production</article-title>. <source>Bioresour Technol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>342</volume>:<fpage>126004</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2021.126004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34583109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahoo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhat</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> screening of plant extracts to enhance the efficiency of utilization of energy and nitrogen in ruminant diets</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>145</volume>:<fpage>229</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2007.05.036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of polyphenolic extract from Eucommia ulmoides Oliver leaf on growth performance, digestibility, rumen fermentation and antioxidant status of fattening lambs</article-title>. <source>Anim Sci J.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>888</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/asj.12998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29575598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merry</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Theodorou</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An automated system for measuring gas production from forages inoculated with rumen fluid and its use in determining the effect of enzymes on grass silage</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>83</volume>:<fpage>205</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0377-8401(99)00138-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><label>77.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patra</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Meta-analyses of effects of phytochemicals on digestibility and rumen fermentation characteristics associated with methanogenesis</article-title>. <source>J Sci Food Agric.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>2700</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.4143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20740549</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><label>78.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anantasook</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wanapat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cherdthong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunun</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of plants containing secondary compounds with palm oil on feed intake, digestibility, microbial protein synthesis and microbial population in dairy cows</article-title>. <source>Asian Australas J Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>820</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5713/ajas.2012.12689</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25049855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4093251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><label>79.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Supapong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cherdthong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seankamsorn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khonkhaeng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wanapat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunun</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of Delonix regia seed meal supplementation in Thai native beef cattle on feed intake, rumen fermentation characteristics and methane production</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>232</volume>:<fpage>40</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2017.08.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>