<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8258120</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8258120.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8258120</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8258120</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34239912</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.681202</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Metabolome-Microbiome Responses of Growing Pigs Induced by Time-Restricted Feeding</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="H">Hongyu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1267387/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names initials="P">Pengke</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1364013/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhiyang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1364740/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/238317/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names initials="W">Weiyun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/265399/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Laboratory of Gastrointestinal Microbiology, Jiangsu Key Laboratory of Gastrointestinal Nutrition and Animal Health, College of Animal Science and Technology, Nanjing Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Nanjing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>National Center for International Research on Animal Gut Nutrition, Nanjing Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Nanjing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Claudio Forte, University of Turin, Italy</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Padraig Strappe, Central Queensland University, Australia; Congying Chen, Jiangxi Agricultural University, China</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Yong Su <email>yong.su@njau.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Animal Nutrition and Metabolism, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">374996</issue-id><elocation-id>681202</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>07</day><month>07</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-04 21:25:16.313"><day>04</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2021 Wang, Xia, Lu, Su and Zhu.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wang, Xia, Lu, Su and Zhu</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-08-681202.pdf"/><abstract><p>Time-restricted feeding (TRF) mode is a potential strategy in improving the health and production of farm animals. However, the effect of TRF on microbiota and their metabolism in the large intestine of the host remains unclear. Therefore, the present study aimed to investigate the responses of microbiome and metabolome induced by TRF based on a growing-pig model. Twelve crossbred growing barrows were randomly allotted into two groups with six replicates (1 pig/pen), namely, the free-access feeding group (FA) and TRF group. Pigs in the FA group were fed free access while the TRF group were fed free access within a regular time three times per day at 07:00&#8211;08:00, 12:00&#8211;13:00, and 18:00&#8211;19:00, respectively. Results showed that the concentrations of NH4-N, putrescine, cadaverine, spermidine, spermine, total biogenic amines, isobutyrate, butyrate, isovalerate, total SCFA, and lactate were increased while the pH value in the colonic digesta and the concentration of acetate was decreased in the TRF group. The Shannon index was significantly increased in the TRF group; however, no significant effects were found in the Fisher index, Simpson index, ACE index, Chao1 index, and observed species between the two groups. In the TRF group, the relative abundances of <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella 1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Eubacterium ruminantium group</italic> were significantly increased while the relative abundances of <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium sensu sticto 1, Lactobacillus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Eubacterium coprostanoligenes group</italic> were decreased compared with the FA group. PLS-DA analysis revealed an obvious and regular variation between the FA and TRF groups, further pathway enrichment analysis showed that these differential features were mainly enriched in pyrimidine metabolism, nicotinate and nicotinamide metabolism, glycerolipid metabolism, and fructose and mannose metabolism. In addition, Pearson's correlation analysis indicated that the changes in the microbial genera were correlated with the colonic metabolites. In conclusion, these results together indicated that although the overall microbial composition in the colon was not changed, TRF induced the gradient changes of the nutrients and metabolites which were correlated with certain microbial genera including <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus, Eubacterium_ruminantium</italic> group, <italic toggle="yes">Eubacterium coprostanoligenes</italic> group, <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> 1, and <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium</italic> sensu sticto 1. However, more studies are needed to understand the impacts of TRF on the health and metabolism of growing pigs.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>growing pigs</kwd><kwd>metabolome</kwd><kwd>microbiome</kwd><kwd>time-restricted feeding</kwd><kwd>microbial metabolites</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="7"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="57"/><page-count count="12"/><word-count count="7589"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Recently, a considerable amount of reference highlighted the contributions of the type, quantity, and composition of nutrients intake to host health and metabolism both on animals and human beings (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). By contrast, there are fewer studies concerning the effects of feeding patterns on health and metabolism. However, to date, limited literature has already indicated that changes in feeding patterns may also affect the metabolism, health, and production of animals (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Specifically, Rothschild et al. (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) reviewed that TRF trends to reduce the body weight, total cholesterol, and concentrations of triglycerides, glucose, insulin, interleukin, and tumor necrosis factor-&#945; with improving insulin sensitivity (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Consistently, TRF was reported to ameliorate the serum lipid and liver profiles of the individuals and increased the richness of the gut microbiota on human beings (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Zarrinpar et al. (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) reported that compared with the FA group, TRF has changed the dynamics both in the relative abundance and compositions of gut microflora on mice as well as liver metabolism. These studies concerning mice and human beings together indicated that TRF has profound effects on the host metabolism and may be a potential remedy for the prevention of metabolic diseases and promoting a profitable and safe swine production. However, the mechanisms underpinning the beneficial effects of TRF on metabolic health remain largely unknown.</p><p>In recent years, more and more evidence has indicated that the microbiota plays a crucial role in host metabolism and health (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Vice versa, factors including diet composition (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), nutritional concentrations (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), and diet types (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) were found to shape the microbial communities. Therefore, we hypothesized that TRF changed the concentration gradient of nutrients, thus, preferentially stimulating the proliferation of certain microorganisms in the intestine and further exerting its beneficial effects on host health and metabolism. As obesity has become a global concern and has a close relationship with food taking, related studies mostly focus on indicators such as glucose and lipid metabolism, which are mostly performed on mice. More studies concerning the effects of TRF on gut microbiota and relevant metabolome are needed. Hence, the present study aimed to explore the metabolome-microbiome responses of growing pigs induced by a time-restricted feeding and to study the relationships between the gut microbiota, gut environment, and metabolites. Specifically, the feeding pattern used in the present study was similar to the three-meal pattern in modern society. Considering the high similarity in anatomy, physiology, polyphagy, habits, metabolism, and gut microbiota between pigs and human beings (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), findings from this study will provide information on the applications of TRF on human beings as well.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>This study was approved by the Nanjing Agricultural University Animal Care and Use Committee (Nanjing, Jiangsu Province, China) (SYXK2019-0066). All animal care procedures in the experiment were operated according to the standard of Experimental Animal Care and Use Guidelines of China (EACUGC2018-01).</p></sec><sec><title>Animals, Housing, and Sample</title><p>Twelve 105-day growing crossbred barrows (Duroc &#215; Landrace &#215; Large White, average bodyweight = 56.29 &#177; 1.38 kg) were randomly allotted into two groups with six replicates (1 pig/pen) per group, namely, the free-access feeding group (FA) and TRF group. Pigs in the FA group were fed free-access to feed while the TRF group were fed free-access within a regular time three times per day at 07:00&#8211;08:00, 12:00&#8211;13:00, and 18:00&#8211;19:00, respectively. All pigs were fed with the same commercial pellet feed for growing pigs and <italic toggle="yes">ad libitum</italic> access to water throughout the experiment period. After a 14-day <italic toggle="yes">ad libitum</italic> feeding during the pre-experiment period, the trial started and lasted for 21 days. All pigs were slaughtered and colonic digesta samples were collected on the 21st day. After measuring the pH using a portable pH meter (Hanna Instruments, Villafranca, Italy), all samples were stored under &#8722;80&#176;C for microbiota, microbial metabolites, and metabolome analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>DNA Extraction, 16S rRNA Gene Amplification, and Sequencing</title><p>Total DNA from colonic digesta was extracted using the cetrimonium bromide (CTAB) method according to a previous method (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). The sequencing was finished by Shanghai Biozeron Biotechnology Co., Ltd (Shanghai, China). Shortly, the V3&#8211;V4 regions of the bacterial 16S rRNA gene were amplified using a universal primer with the barcode [forward primer (5&#8242;-ACTC CTRCGGGAGGCAGCAG-3&#8242;) and a reverse primer (5&#8242;-GGACTACCVGGGTATCTAAT-3&#8242;)] (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Then, sequencing libraries were generated using the NEB Next&#174;Ultra&#8482;DNA Library Prep Kit for Illumina (NEB, USA) following the manufacturer's recommendations, and index codes were added. At last, the library was sequenced on an Illumina MiSeq platform and 250/300 bp paired-end reads were generated.</p><p>QIIME (version 1.17) was used to demultiplex and quality-filter the raw sequence. Reads that were shorter than 50 bp and those that could not be assembled were discarded. Reads with an exact barcode matching and two nucleotide mismatches in primer matching, or containing ambiguous characters, were removed. According to the overlap sequence, only sequences that overlap longer than 10 bp were assembled according to their overlap sequence. Reads which could not be assembled were discarded. Operational taxonomic units (OTUs) were clustered with a 97% similarity cutoff standard using UPARSE (version 7.1, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://drive5.com/uparse/">http://drive5.com/uparse/</ext-link>), and chimeric sequences were identified and removed using UCHIME. The phylogenetic affiliation of each 16S rRNA gene sequence was analyzed by the RDP Classifier (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rdp.cme.msu.edu/">http://rdp.cme.msu.edu/</ext-link>) against the silva (SSU115). Rarefaction curve, Shannon and Simpson diversity indices, and Ace and Chao richness estimators were assessed using an online website (MicrobiomeAnalyst, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.microbiomeanalyst.ca/">https://www.microbiomeanalyst.ca/</ext-link>). The principal coordinate analysis (PCoA) was conducted based on the Bray&#8211;Curtis distance. EdgeR algorithms were used for performing a differential abundance analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Metabolome Analysis and Data Processing</title><p>Metabolome analyses were finished by a commercial company named BioCluster (Shanghai, China). Briefly, 50 mg of the colonic sample was extracted with 800 &#956;L of 80% methanol. A total of 200 &#956;L of supernatant was added with 5 &#956;L of internal standard (140 &#956;g/mL, DL-o-Chlorophenylalanine), then transferred to a vial for LC-MS analysis. LC-MS Analysis was finished using the analysis of the LC-MS platform (Thermo, Ultimate 3000LC, Q Exactive) under the following setups: Column: Hyper gold C18 (100 &#215; 2.1 mm 1.9 &#956;m); Chromatographic separation conditions: Column temperature: 40&#176;C; Flow rate: 0.3 mL/min; Mobile phase A: water +5% acetonitrile +0.1% formic acid; Mobile phase B: acetonitrile +0.1% formic acid; Injection volume: 4 &#956;L; Automatic injector temperature: 4&#176;C; ESI+: Heater Temp 300&#176;C; Sheath Gas Flow rate, 45 arb; Aux Gas Flow Rate, 15 arb; Sweep Gas Flow Rate, 1 arb; spray voltage, 3.0 KV; Capillary Temp, 350&#176;C; S-Lens RF Level, 30%. ESI-: Heater Temp 300&#176;C, Sheath Gas Flow rate, 45 arb; Aux Gas Flow Rate, 15 arb; Sweep Gas Flow Rate, 1 arb; spray voltage, 3.2 KV; Capillary Temp, 350&#176;C; S-Lens RF Level, 60%.</p><p>All statistical analyses of the metabolites were done based on the different function modules of a powerful tool, which is available online (version 5.0,) (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Features with &gt;30% missing values were removed, and the missing values of the remaining features will be replaced by a very small value (half of the minimum positive value found in the data set) by default. No missing values were detected with the criterion. The data then underwent logarithmic transformation and normalization of auto-scaling. Fold change analysis and <italic toggle="yes">T</italic>-test were conducted to determine the fold change and statistical significance of each metabolite from the colonic samples of growing pigs from the TRF group compared with the FA group. PLS-DA was employed to picture the overall difference between the TRF and FA groups, and to explore the differential metabolites. The metabolites with variable importance projection (VIP) values above 1.0, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 were selected as differential metabolites. The differential metabolites were used to execute an enrichment analysis to explore the main pathway changed by the TRF.</p></sec><sec><title>Short-Chain Fatty Acids (SCFAs)</title><p>The concentrations of SCFAs (acetate, propionate, isobutyrate, butyrate, isovalerate, valerate) were measured by the gas chronograph method according to Wang et al. (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Shortly, 0.25 g of colonic digesta samples was suspended in 1.5 mL distilled water. After vortex-mixing, the suspension was centrifuged at 12,000 &#215; rmp for 10 min at 4&#176;C. A total of 1 mL of the supernatant was taken and mixed with 0.2 mL of 25% (w/v) metaphosphoric acid. The mixture was frozen at 20&#176;C overnight. After thawing, the mixture was centrifuged at 12,000 &#215; rmp for 20 min at 4&#176;C, then 0.5 mL of the supernatant was taken and mixed with an isovolumic ether. Shaking of the mixture was performed to extract the SCFA in the aqueous phase. The organic phase was taken for further analysis using an Agilent 7890A gas chromatograph (Agilent Technologies, Wilmington, DE) equipped with the flame ionization detector (FID), splitless injection port. Standard curves are established using the gradient mixed standards to calculate the concentration of the measured SCFA. The total SCFAs were calculated by adding the six SCFAs measured.</p></sec><sec><title>Lactate</title><p>The concentration of lactate was measured by the colorimetric method using the reagent kit (PN: A019-2-1, Nanjing Jiancheng Institute of Biological Engineering, China) following the instructions in the specification.</p></sec><sec><title>Ammonia-N</title><p>The concentration of Ammonia-N in the colonic digesta was analyzed by the colorimetric method according to Shen et al. (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Specifically, 0.1 g of colonic digesta were weighed and suspended in 1.5 mL of 0.2 M HCl. Following vortex-mixing, the suspension was centrifuged at 14,000 &#215; g for 20 min at 4&#176;C. A total of 0.5 mL of the supernatant was taken and mixed with 0.5 mL of 0.08% (w/v) sodium nitroprusside-sodium salicylate and 0.5 mL of sodium hypochlorite-sodium hydroxide solution. The mixture was vortex mixed and left to stand for 10 min. Absorbance at 700 nm was recorded. Gradient ammonium chloride solutions were used to establish a robust standard curve to calculate the concentration of Ammonia-N.</p></sec><sec><title>Biogenic Amines</title><p>Biogenic amines including methylamine, tryptamine, putrescine, cadaverine, tyramine, spermidine, and spermine in the colonic digesta were detected by a high-performance liquid chromatography method according to Yang et al. (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Gradient mixed standards were also analyzed as the samples to establish a robust curve to calculate the concentrations of the biogenic amines.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>The significance of pH, NH4-N, biogenic amines, SCFAs, the differential microbiota, and metabolites between the two groups were analyzed using the unpaired two-tail <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test (IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, Version 21.0). Pearson correlation was analyzed to evaluate the correlation between the differential microorganisms, microbial metabolites, and the features identified from the metabolome. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered to represent a significant difference. Data visualization was completed using the GraphPad Prism (version 8.0.1, GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA) and R software (version 4.0.4).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Bacterial Community Composition in Colonic Digesta of Growing Pigs Under Different Feeding Modes</title><p>A total of 517,362 clean sequences were obtained after data filtering under a normal quality control system. Using the standard of 97% similarity level, these clean sequences were clustered into 784 OTUs. The rarefaction curves were gradually flattened out with the increasing sampling quantity (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>). The &#945;-diversity indexes of the colonic bacterial community were shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>. To a large extent, TRF had no significant effects on the Fisher index, Simpson index, ACE index, Chao1 index, and Observed species (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05). However, the Shannon index was significantly higher in the TRF group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.040). Also, the Principal coordinate analysis indicated that TRF could not distinguish the panorama of the colonic bacterial community (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>). Whereas, at the family level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>), the relative abundances of Prevotellaceae (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.023), Campylobacteraceae (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.010), Tannerellaceae (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.012), and Anaeroplasmataceae (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.021) were significantly higher in the TRF group compared to those in the FA group, while the relative abundances of Lactobacillaceae (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0014) in the FA group were significantly higher than the TRF group. Meanwhile, at the genus level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>), the relative abundances of <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> 1 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0029) and <italic toggle="yes">Eubacterium ruminantium</italic> group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.017) were significantly higher in the TRF group, and the relative abundances of <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium sensu sticto</italic> 1 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.022), <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.002), and <italic toggle="yes">Eubacterium coprostanoligenes group</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0036) were lower compared with the FA group.</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Differences in the colonic bacterial &#945;-diversity index of growing pigs between the FA and TRF groups. FA, free access group; TRF, time-restricted feeding group. *Indicates a significant difference between the two groups; ns represents no significant difference.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-681202-g0001.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The relative abundance of bacteria in colonic digesta of growing pigs at the family level. FA, free access group; TRF, time-restricted feeding group. **Indicates a significant difference between the FA and TRF groups with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01; while *indicates a significant difference with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-681202-g0002.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The relative abundances of bacteria in colonic digesta of growing pigs at the genus level. FA, free access group; TRF, time-restricted feeding group. **Indicates a significant difference between the FA and TRF groups with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01; while *indicates a significant difference with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-681202-g0003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>The pH, Bacterial Metabolites, and the Metabolome in Colonic Digesta of Growing Pigs</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, TRF significantly increased the concentrations of NH4-N (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), putrescine (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.003), cadaverine (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.010), spermidine (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), spermine (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.014), total biogenic amines (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), isobutyrate (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001), butyrate (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.005), isovalerate (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.001), total SCFA (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.008), and lactate (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.024), while it decreased the pH value and the concentration of acetate (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.002) in colonic digesta. TRF had a trend to increase the concentration of methylamine (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.083) and tended to decrease the concentration of tyramine (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.063). Using the LC-MS metabolomic technique, a total of 258 metabolites in the ESI+ mode and 123 metabolites in the ESI- mode were identified. According to the characteristics of the detected metabolites in each ion mode, one of the repeated metabolites detected in both ESI+ and ESI- modes were eliminated, the remaining 332 metabolites were combined for further analysis. These metabolites mainly included amino acids and their derivatives, organic acids, amines, nucleoside, flavonoid, fatty acids, peptides, etc. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>, the PLS-DA analysis revealed an obvious and regular variation between the FA and TRF groups. Based on the standards of VIP &gt; 1.0 and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, a total of 22 significant differential features were identified (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Results of pathway enrichment analysis showed that these differential features were mainly enriched in pyrimidine metabolism, nicotinate and nicotinamide metabolism, glycerolipid metabolism, and fructose and mannose metabolism (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The pH value and concentrations of lactic acid, NH4-N, biogenic amines, and SCFAs in colonic digesta of growing pigs.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Items</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>FA<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TRF<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.49 &#177; 0.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.26 &#177; 0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NH4-N (mg/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">332.79 &#177; 5.68</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">376.6 &#177; 6.78</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methylamine (&#956;mol/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.85 &#177; 3.75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.2 &#177; 0.97</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tryptamine (&#956;mol/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.07 &#177; 6.26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.81 &#177; 6.81</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.163</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putrescine (&#956;mol/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.77 &#177; 6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.99 &#177; 3.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cadaverine (&#956;mol/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.08 &#177; 3.75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.44 &#177; 4.67</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tyramine (&#956;mol/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.33 &#177; 4.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.44 &#177; 2.78</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spermidine (&#956;mol/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">173.99 &#177; 14.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">312.13 &#177; 17.93</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spermine (&#956;mol/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.04 &#177; 4.45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.61 &#177; 9.54</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total biogenic amines (&#956;mol/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">415.12 &#177; 19.33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">635.62 &#177; 28.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetate (&#956;mol/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.56 &#177; 0.53</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.11 &#177; 0.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propionate (&#956;mol/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.67 &#177; 0.45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.02 &#177; 0.45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.300</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isobutyrate (&#956;mol/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.19 &#177; 0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47 &#177; 0.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Butyrate (&#956;mol/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.38 &#177; 0.26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.03 &#177; 0.15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isovalerate (&#956;mol/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60 &#177; 0.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.99 &#177; 0.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valerate (&#956;mol/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.36 &#177; 0.18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.48 &#177; 0.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.310</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total SCFA (&#956;mol/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.3 &#177; 0.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.55 &#177; 0.62</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lactate (&#956;mol/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20 &#177; 0.36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.68 &#177; 0.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><label>a</label><p><italic toggle="yes">FA, free access group; TRF, time-restricted feeding group</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Partial least squares discriminant analysis (PLS-DA) score plot of colonic metabolites (both ESI+ and ESI-) of growing pigs in the FA and TRF groups. FA, free access group; TRF, time-restricted feeding group; QC, quality control. The ellipse represents the 95% confidence interval of each group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-681202-g0004.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Identification of significant differential features in colonic digesta of growing pigs.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NO</bold>.</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Feature</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>FC<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>log<sub><bold>2</bold></sub>(FC)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>VIP<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup><bold>b</bold></sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mode</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hexadecanedioic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53477</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.90302</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2162</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">dTMP</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9032</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5376</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2006</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glycylleucine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55638</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.84587</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1357</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methyl-beta-galactopyranoside</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36016</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.4733</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0248</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fructose 1-phosphate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7772</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9593</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0098</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hippuric acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43986</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.1849</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.416</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urobilin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53018</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.91544</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0603</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16-Hydroxyhexadecanoic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65938</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.60082</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1402</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thymidine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5709</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65161</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5147</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lysophosphatidylethanolamine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6385</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71238</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3816</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serinyl-Leucine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52303</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.93502</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0933</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thymidine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7536</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81031</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2584</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adenosine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7304</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79107</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0149</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-Methyladenosine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0063</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0046</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1544</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monoglyceride</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9224</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94294</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0194</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D-2-Aminobutyric acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5904</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.76023</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9605</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asparaginyl-glutamic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6256</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70102</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2668</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DL-pipecolic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.8771</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5246</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N6, N6, N6-Trimethyl-L-lysine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8283</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87054</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4042</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niacinamide</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53713</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.89665</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4031</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytidine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6513</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72356</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3731</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI+</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dihydroartemisinin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8634</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89791</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3595</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESI+</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN2"><label>a</label><p><italic toggle="yes">FC, fold change</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN3"><label>b</label><p><italic toggle="yes">VIP, variable importance in the projection</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Pathway enrichment of these significant differential metabolites identified between the FA and TRF groups. The x-axis marks the pathway impact and the y-axis represents the pathway enrichment. Each node marks a pathway, with larger sizes and darker colors representing higher pathway enrichment and pathway impact values.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-681202-g0005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Correlations Between the Bacterial Genera, Bacterial Metabolites, and Differential Features in Colonic Digesta of Growing Pigs</title><p>Based on the Pearson correlation analysis, the differential microbiota at the genus level showed a significant correlation with bacterial metabolites in colonic digesta (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>). Specifically, <italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae XPB1014 group</italic> was negatively correlated with methylamine (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.86, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001) and total SCFA (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.58, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.047), while it was positively correlated with pH (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.70, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.01). <italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae NK3A20 group</italic> was negatively correlated with propionate (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.66, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.020), while it was positively correlated with lactate (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.63, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.029), isobutyrate (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.64, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.025), and butyrate (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.58, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.046). <italic toggle="yes">Mitsuokella</italic> was positively correlated with NH4-N (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.59, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.045), lactate (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.72, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0082), and isovalerate (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.58, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.049). <italic toggle="yes">Coprococcus 2</italic> was negatively correlated with pH (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.69, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.010), while it was positively correlated with <italic toggle="yes">spermidine</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.58, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.046), spermine (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.69, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.012), total biogenic amines (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.66, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.020), acetate (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.64, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.024), and total SCFA (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.66, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.020). <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium sensu stricto 1</italic> was negatively correlated with methylamine (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.64, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.026) and butyrate (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.58, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.049). <italic toggle="yes">Eubacterium ruminantium group</italic> was negatively correlated with pH (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.74, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0055), while it was positively correlated with spermine (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.59, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.045), total biogenic amines (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.64, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.026), acetate (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.66, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.018), butyrate (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.60, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.040), and total SCFA (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.62, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.030). <italic toggle="yes">Turicibacter</italic> was negatively correlated with butyrate (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.63, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.028). <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> was negatively correlated with putrescine (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.67, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.017) and cadaverine (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.69, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.013), while it was positively correlated with tyramine (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.69, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.013).</p><fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Correlations between the differential microbiota at the genus level with bacterial metabolites in colonic digesta of growing pigs. Each row in the graph represents a pH value and bacterial metabolite (including SCFAs, biogenic amines, lactate, and NH4-N), each column represents a genus, each square represents a Pearson correlation coefficient between a genus and a bacterial metabolite (or pH), while the area of each square represents the size of each correlation coefficient. Red color represents a negative correlation, while blue color represents a positive correlation. ***Indicates a significant difference between the free access group and time-restricted feeding group with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001; while **, *indicates significant difference with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 respectively.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-681202-g0006.jpg"/></fig><p>Based on the Pearson correlation analysis, the differential microbiota at the genus level showed a significant correlation with the significant differential features in colonic digesta (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>). Specifically, <italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae XPB1014</italic> group was negatively correlated with cytidine (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.70, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.011), dihydroartemisinin (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.61, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.033), asparaginylglutamic acid (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.80, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.017), and monoglyceride (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.69, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.014), while it was positively correlated with serinyl-leucine (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.80, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0019), glycylleucine (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.68, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.014), and methyl-&#946;-galactopyranoside (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.64, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.025). <italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae NK3A20</italic> group was positively correlated with DL-pipecolic acid (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.78, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0029). <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.74, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0056), <italic toggle="yes">Prevotellaceae NK3B31 group</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.74, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0060), <italic toggle="yes">Parabacteroides</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.61, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0034), <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella 1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.64, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0024), and <italic toggle="yes">Prevotellaceae UCG 001</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.73, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0070) were negatively correlated with D-2-aminobutyric acid. <italic toggle="yes">Mitsuokella</italic> was positively correlated with 1-methyladenosine (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.79, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0020), N6,N6,N6-trimethyl-L-lysine (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.66, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.020), DL-pipecolic acid (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.58, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.047), dTMP (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.67, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.018), fructose-1-phosphate (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.67, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.018), and Lysophosphatidylethanolamine (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.61, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.034), while it was negatively correlated with serinyl-leucine (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.60, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.038) and glycylleucine (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.67, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.018). Turicibacter was positively correlated with urobilin (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.62, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.030). <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium sensu stricto 1</italic> was negatively correlated with monoglyceride (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.60, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.040). <italic toggle="yes">Eubacterium ruminantium group</italic> was positively correlated with monoglyceride (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.64, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.024), while it was negatively correlated with hexadecanedioic acid (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.58, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.046). <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> was negatively correlated with 1-methyladenosine (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.70, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.011), adenosine (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.61, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.036), thymidine (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.71, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.010), and dTMP (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = &#8722;0.74, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0056), while it was positively correlated with niacinamide (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.76, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.004) and D-2-aminobutyric acid (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> = 0.65, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.02).</p><fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Correlation analysis between the differential microbiota at the genus level with the differential features identified from the LC-MS metabolome in colonic digesta of growing pigs. Each row in the graph represents the differential features, each column represents a genus, each square represents a Pearson correlation coefficient between a genus and a differential feature, while the area of each square represents the size of each correlation coefficient. Red color represents a negative correlation, while blue color represents a positive correlation. **Indicates a significant difference between the free access group and the time-restricted feeding group with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01; while *indicates a significant difference with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-681202-g0007.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Growing evidence suggests that the nutrients (including fatty acids, amino acids, and saccharides) and the luminal environment (e.g., pH) shapes the microbiota community (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). In the present study, the overall composition of the colonic microbiota communities was not changed between the two groups, the most likely reason is that all pigs in both groups were fed with the same commercial feed. However, the Shannon index was significantly increased in the present study indicating that the TRF group improved the evenness of the microbial community. As reported, metabolite cross-feeding promotes a suboptimal community growth and shapes the species diversity in the gut microbiota (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Therefore, the results may be contributed to the nutritional variations in the colonic lumen along with the different feeding rhythms. Under the free-access mode, a growing pig eats about seven times per day with an average feed intake of 260 g (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). However, our research found that the phased feed intake of growing pigs in a day underwent diurnal rhythmicity and peaked at 12:00&#8211;16:00 (unpublished data), which means that a fluctuation in nutrients may exist in the colonic lumen. By contrast, pigs in the TRF group were fed access to feed at identical intervals which may lead to a relative evenness of the nutrients, thus, affecting the microbiota community meanwhile.</p><p>A plethora of studies has reported that the bidirectional interactions between the host and the intestinal microbiota are tightly regulated to maintain health and homeostasis (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Gut microbiota plays pivotal roles in maintaining metabolic hemostasis including the metabolism of amino acids, carbohydrates, lipid, nucleotide, and vitamins (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Vice versa, nutrients in the intestine taking by the host could domesticate the gut microbes meanwhile (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Although the overall microbial composition was not considerably different, the TRF group significantly altered the relative abundance of certain taxa like <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> at the genus level. Surprisingly, we found that the TRF group has decreased the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic>, however, the decrease did not reduce the content of lactate. These results were inconsistent with those reported previously (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Zhang et al. (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) have reported that the oral administration of the <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> strain has increased the production of lactate. The following reasons may explain these results. Firstly, <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic>, as well as <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic>, could produce lactate (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Thus, in line with Zhang et al. (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), we found that the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> was not directly correlated with the concentration of lactate. Secondly, as a secondary metabolite, the lactate produced was possibly consumed simultaneously by yeasts or other aerobic bacteria in the FA group (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Besides, the production efficiency of lactate during fermentation by different strains of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> was not identical, especially with different substrates (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Researchers have found that <italic toggle="yes">Mitsuokella</italic> had a positive effect on the serum free amino acids in weaned piglets (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), while in the present study, we found that <italic toggle="yes">Mitsuokella</italic> had a negative correlation with serinyl-leucine and glycylleucine. <italic toggle="yes">Eubacterium coprostanoligenes</italic> group has been reported to have a function of bio-transforming cholesterol to coprostanol which could further influence the fat metabolism of the host (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Cholesterol has been shown to exert crucial physiological effects on animals (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). While in the present study, TRF has significantly reduced the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Eubacterium coprostanoligenes</italic> group which possibly indicates that more cholesterol was utilized in the TRF group. Consistently, differential metabolites were enriched in fat-related metabolism pathways. <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> has been reported to associate with the increase of host feed intake (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). However, the feed intake was not affected by TRF in the present study (unpublished data). The possible reason was that although the relative abundance of Prevotellaceae at the family level was increased by TRF, it did not change the relative abundance of Prevotella at the genus level, but increased the relative abundance of Prevotella 1. Despite relating to several diseases (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), several members of Prevotellaceae were reported to produce succinate and could improve the glucose homeostasis status by activating intestinal gluconeogenesis (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Thus, through promoting host health or energy metabolism, Prevotellaceae was reported to increase the feed efficacy in pigs (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Herein, we found that TRF has significantly increased the relative abundance of Prevotellaceae at the family level which suggests that TRF would probably improve the production efficacy of swine production. As an evidence, the FCR was indeed improved by TRF in the present study (unpublished data).</p><p>Microbial metabolic products, mainly including SCFAs and biogenic amines, are thought to mediate the beneficial health effects of the intestinal microbial community (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). SCFAs were the main end-products of microorganisms fermenting carbohydrates, which are generally believed to have a benefit to host health (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). Specifically, butyrate, as one of the most important SCFAs, has extensive effects on improving immunity and intestinal health and promoting host metabolism (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). In the present study, we found that TRF has increased the concentration of butyrate which indirectly reflected that TRF could improve host metabolism. Accordingly, the <italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae NK3A20</italic> group, which was positively correlated with butyrate, was found to be increased by TRF treatment (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Besides, we also found that D2-aminobutyric acid, an unnatural chiral &#945;-amino acid, in colonic digesta of growing pigs had excessive correlations with the differential bacterial genera. Unfortunately, there are currently few studies concerning the physiological function of D2-aminobutyric acid, thus, further research is still needed. Biogenic amines are produced by intestinal microbiota through the decarboxylation of aromatic or cationic amino acids (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). In the present study, we found that the TRF mode had a trend to decrease the concentration of tyramine. Furthermore, we found that <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> had a tight correlation with tyramine. Research has found that <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> can deaminate proteins (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). Moreover, researchers have found that 28% of the <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> produced tyramine (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). In the present study, TRF has increased the concentration of putrescine, spermidine, and spermine. Putrescine was reported to stimulate the synthesis of epithelial DNA and RNA (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). In line with this notion, pathway analysis indicates that TRF has increased the progress of pyrimidine metabolism. Furthermore, putrescine could mitigate intestinal atrophy by suppressing inflammatory responses in weanling piglets (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). Spermidine and spermine were reported to promote adipogenesis (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>), while cadaverine exerts protective effects on epithelial cells (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Consistently, researchers have found that <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> was negatively correlated with cadaverine (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). The decreased production of biogenic amines may be contributed to the inhibitory effects of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> on the growth of amine-positive bacteria (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). However, some genera of amine positive lactic acid bacteria strains, including <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus plantarum</italic> (FI8595) and <italic toggle="yes">Lactococcus lactis subsp. cremoris</italic> (MG 1363), had a crucial role on the increase of cadaverine and accumulation of putrescine (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). However, the biogenic amines function probably depends on the dose and physiological state of the host (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In conclusion, the overall composition of gut microbiota community between the two groups was not influenced. However, TRF treatment significantly altered the relative abundance of certain families and genera including <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus, Eubacterium ruminantium</italic> group, <italic toggle="yes">Eubacterium coprostanoligenes</italic> group, <italic toggle="yes">Prevotella</italic> 1, and <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium sensu sticto</italic> 1. Furthermore, TRF treatment induced the gradient changes of metabolites in colonic digesta. Interestingly, the correlation results suggested that gradients of metabolites induced by TRF were correlated with the differential microbial genera indicating that the metabolites might mediate the effect of TFR on the gut microbiota. However, more research is needed to understand the benefits and risks of TRF on the health and metabolism of growing pigs.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The data presented in the study are deposited in the repository of Sequence Read Archive, accession number: PRJNA715648.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by Nanjing Agricultural University Animal Care and Use Committee (Nanjing, Jiangsu Province, China) (SYXK2019-0066).</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>YS and WZ conceived and designed the experiments. HW, PX, ZL, and YS performed the experiments and analyzed the data. HW and YS wrote the paper. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work was supported by grants from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31872362 and 32072688).</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s9"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2021.681202/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2021.681202/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Figure 1</label><caption><p>Rarefaction curve comparing the number of OTUs found in the 16S rDNA gene libraries from microbiota in the colon.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.PDF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Figure 2</label><caption><p>Principal coordinate analysis (PcoA) of the colonic bacterial community of the growing pigs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6). FA, free access group; TRF, time-restricted feeding group.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.PDF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Batson</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calder&#243;n</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tokach</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodworth</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodband</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dritz</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of coarse wheat bran and crude protein level in nursery pig diets without pharmacological levels of zinc oxide</article-title>. <source>Kansas Agr Exp Station.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4148/2378-5977.7985</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petry</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huntley</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedford</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patience</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Xylanase increased the energetic contribution of fiber and improved the oxidative status, gut barrier integrity, and growth performance of growing pigs fed insoluble corn-based fiber</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>233</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jas/skaa233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32687554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7392531</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dynamic changes in serum metabolomic profiles of growing pigs induced by intravenous infusion of sodium butyrate</article-title>. <source>Metabolites.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>20</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/metabo10010020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31906303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7023161</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhuo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Gut microbial metabolism of dietary fibre protects against high energy feeding induced ovarian follicular atresia in a pig model</article-title>. <source>Br J Nutr.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>125</volume>:<fpage>38</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>49</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007114520002378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32600501</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>iTRAQ-based proteomic analysis reveals alterations in the liver induced by restricted meal frequency in a pig model</article-title>. <source>Nutrition.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>871</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nut.2016.01.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27106395</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hepatic lipid metabolism is affected by a daily 3-meal pattern with varying dietary crude protein with a pig model</article-title>. <source>Anim Nutr.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aninu.2019.11.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32211524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7082684</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothschild</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoddy</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jambazian</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varady</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Time-restricted feeding and risk of metabolic disease: a review of human and animal studies</article-title>. <source>Nutr Rev.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>72</volume>:<fpage>308</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nure.12104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24739093</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeb</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fatima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Time-restricted feeding is associated with changes in human gut microbiota related to nutrient intake</article-title>. <source>Nutrition.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>78</volume>:<fpage>110797</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nut.2020.110797</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32540674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zarrinpar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaix</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yooseph</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Diet and feeding pattern affect the diurnal dynamics of the gut microbiome</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1006</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2014.11.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25470548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4255146</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardiner</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Metzler-Zebeli</surname><given-names>BU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawlor</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of intestinal microbiota on growth and feed efficiency in pigs: a review</article-title>. <source>Microorganisms.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1886</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms8121886</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33260665</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7761281</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tremaroli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>B&#228;ckhed</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Functional interactions between the gut microbiota and host metabolism</article-title>. <source>Nature.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>489</volume>:<fpage>242</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22972297</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of the dietary protein level on the microbial composition and metabolomic profile in the hindgut of the pig</article-title>. <source>Anaerobe.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anaerobe.2015.12.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26723572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Undernutrition shapes the gut microbiota and bile acid profile in association with altered gut-liver FXR signaling in weaning pigs</article-title>. <source>J Agr Food Chem.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>3691</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>701</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.9b01332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30864445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of fermented feed on growth performance, holistic metabolism and fecal microbiota in weanling piglets</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>266</volume>:<fpage>114505</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2020.114505</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prather</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Advancing swine models for human health and diseases</article-title>. <source>Mo Med.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>110</volume>:<fpage>212</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23829105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6179855</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Estelle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiilerich</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramayo-Caldas</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A reference gene catalogue of the pig gut microbiome</article-title>. <source>Nat Microbiol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmicrobiol.2016.161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27643971</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>ZL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Utilization of amino acids by bacteria from the pig small intestine</article-title>. <source>Amino Acids.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>1201</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00726-010-0556-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20300787</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Caecal infusion of the short-chain fatty acid propionate affects the microbiota and expression of inflammatory cytokines in the colon in a fistula pig model</article-title>. <source>Microb Biotechnol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>859</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>68</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1751-7915.13282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29856120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6116746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Using microbiome analyst for comprehensive statistical, functional, and meta-analysis of microbiome data</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>799</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>821</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41596-019-0264-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31942082</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of the gynosaponin on methane production and microbe numbers in a fungus-methanogen co-culture</article-title>. <source>J Anim Feed Sci.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>272</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22358/jafs/66184/2011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Monensin and nisin affect rumen fermentation and microbiota differently in vitro</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1111</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.01111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28670304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5472720</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Determination of biogenic amines in digesta by high performance liquid chromatography with precolumn dansylation</article-title>. <source>Anal Lett.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>1290</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00032719.2013.871550</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Agans</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez-Burillo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rufi&#225;n-Henares</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paliy</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary fatty acids sustain the growth of the human gut microbiota</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>84</volume>:<fpage>e0152518</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01525-18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30242004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6193386</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nutrients mediate intestinal bacteria&#8211;mucosal immune crosstalk</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2018.00005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29416535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5787545</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rong</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Microbiome-metabolomics analysis investigating the impacts of dietary starch types on the composition and metabolism of colonic microbiota in finishing pigs</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1143</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.01143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31191480</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6549541</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phalak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Suboptimal community growth mediated through metabolite crossfeeding promotes species diversity in the gut microbiota</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>e1006558</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30376571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6226200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKeith</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Feed intake pattern of group-housed growing-finishing pigs monitored using a computerized feed intake recording system</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci.</source> (<year>1997</year>) <volume>75</volume>:<fpage>1443</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/1997.7561443x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9250503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bogere</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Won</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Beneficial roles of probiotics on the modulation of gut microbiota and immune response in pigs</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>e0220843</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0220843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31461453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6713323</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Weaning alters intestinal gene expression involved in nutrient metabolism by shaping gut microbiota in pigs</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>694</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2020.00694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32362884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7181064</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Combination of lactobacillus plantarum and Saccharomyces cerevisiae DV10 as starter culture to produce mango slurry: microbiological, chemical parameters and antioxidant activity</article-title>. <source>Molecules.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>4349</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules24234349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31795169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6930673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in ileal microbial composition and microbial metabolism by an early-life galacto-oligosaccharides intervention in a neonatal porcine model</article-title>. <source>Nutrients.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1753</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu11081753</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31366090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6723927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Fecal microbiota and its correlation with fatty acids and free amino acids metabolism in piglets after a Lactobacillus strain oral administration</article-title>. <source>Front microbiol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>785</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.00785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31040835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6476935</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Einarsson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lidbeck</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orrhage</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nord</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of lactic acid producing bacteria on the human intestinal microflora during ampicillin treatment</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis.</source> (<year>1991</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>247</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>54</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/00365549109023408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1906634</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>FY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Aerobic stability and effects of yeasts during deterioration of non-fermented and fermented total mixed ration with different moisture levels</article-title>. <source>Asian-australas J Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>816</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5713/ajas.14.0837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25925059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4412978</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Othman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ariff</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rios-Solis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Extractive fermentation of lactic acid in lactic acid bacteria cultivation: a review</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>2285</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.02285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29209295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5701932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freier</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beitz</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartman</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of eubacterium coprostanoligenes sp. nov., a cholesterol-reducing anaerobe</article-title>. <source>Int J Syst Evol Microbiol.</source> (<year>1994</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00207713-44-1-137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8123557</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#225;iz-Vazquez</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Puente-Mart&#237;nez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ubillos-Landa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pacheco-Bonrostro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santab&#225;rbara</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cholesterol and Alzheimer's disease risk: a meta-meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Brain Sci</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>386</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/brainsci10060386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32570800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7349210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluating the profound effect of gut microbiome on host appetite in pigs</article-title>. <source>BMC Microbiol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-018-1364-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30547751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6295093</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brinkman</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hildebrand</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kubica</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goosens</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Favero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Declercq</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Caspase deficiency alters the murine gut microbiome</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Dis.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>e220</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cddis.2011.101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22012254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3219086</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Vadder</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kovatcheva-Datchary</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zitoun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duchampt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Backhed</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mithieux</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Microbiota-produced succinate improves glucose homeostasis via intestinal gluconeogenesis</article-title>. <source>Cell Metab.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2016.06.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27411015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Exploring the fecal microbial composition and metagenomic functional capacities associated with feed efficiency in commercial DLY pigs</article-title>. <source>Front microbiol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.00052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30761104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6361760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Den Besten</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Eunen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Groen</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Venema</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reijngoud</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of short-chain fatty acids in the interplay between diet, gut microbiota, and host energy metabolism</article-title>. <source>J Lipid Res.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>2325</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1194/jlr.R036012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23821742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3735932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in cecal microbiota community of suckling piglets infected with porcine epidemic diarrhea virus</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>e0219868</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0219868</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31310635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6634403</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedford</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Implications of butyrate and its derivatives for gut health and animal production</article-title>. <source>Anim Nutr.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aninu.2017.08.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30140754</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6104520</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>&#946;-sitosterol attenuates high grain diet-induced inflammatory stress and modifies rumen fermentation and microbiota in sheep</article-title>. <source>Animals.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>171</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani10010171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31963945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7022687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kabouridis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lasrado</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCallum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chng</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snippert</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clevers</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The gut microbiota keeps enteric glial cells on the move; prospective roles of the gut epithelium and immune system</article-title>. <source>Gut Microbes.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>398</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>403</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/19490976.2015.1109767</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26558327</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4826126</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cayr&#233;</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vignolo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garro</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Modeling lactic acid bacteria growth in vacuum-packaged cooked meat emulsions stored at three temperatures</article-title>. <source>Food Microbiol.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>561</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0740-0020(02)00154-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Curiel</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz-Capillas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Las Rivas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrascosa</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jim&#233;nez-Colmenero</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mu&#241;oz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Production of biogenic amines by lactic acid bacteria and enterobacteria isolated from fresh pork sausages packaged in different atmospheres and kept under refrigeration</article-title>. <source>Meat Sci.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>368</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meatsci.2011.01.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21316866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Girdhar</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barta</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santoyo</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary putrescine (1, 4-diaminobutane) influences recovery of turkey poults challenged with a mixed coccidial infection</article-title>. <source>J Nutr.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>136</volume>:<fpage>2319</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jn/136.9.2319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16920848</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Putrescine mitigates intestinal atrophy through suppressing inflammatory response in weanling piglets</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci Biotechno.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40104-019-0379-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31516701</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6734277</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyv&#246;nen</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koponen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weisell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pietil&#228;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khomutov</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Veps&#228;l&#228;inen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Spermidine promotes adipogenesis of 3T3-L1 cells by preventing interaction of ANP32 with HuR and PP2A</article-title>. <source>Biochem</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>453</volume>:<fpage>467</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BJ20130263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23672317</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Soybean antigen proteins and their intestinal sensitization activities</article-title>. <source>Curr Protein Pept Sci.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>613</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1389203716666150630134602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26122781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCormick</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siber</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maurelli</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Inhibition of Shigella flexneri-induced transepithelial migration of polymorphonuclear leucocytes by cadaverine</article-title>. <source>Cell Microbiol.</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>143</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1462-5822.1999.00014.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11207548</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The inhibition of cell-free supernatant of Lactobacillus plantarum on production of putrescine and cadaverine by four amine-positive bacteria <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic></article-title>. <source>LWT-Food Sci Techno.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>106</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lwt.2015.11.028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuley</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balikci</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#214;zogul</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>G&#246;kdogan S, &#214;zogul F. Stimulation of cadaverine production by foodborne pathogens in the presence of Lactobacillus, Lactococcus, Streptococcus spp</article-title>. <source>J Food Sci.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>M650</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1750-3841.2012.02825.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22853653</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amendola</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cervelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fratini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polticelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sallustio</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mariottini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Spermine metabolism and anticancer therapy</article-title>. <source>Curr Cancer Drug Targets.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>118</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/156800909787580935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19275753</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Development of monoclonal antibodies and a competitive ELISA detection method for glycinin, an allergen in soybean</article-title>. <source>Food Chem.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>121</volume>:<fpage>546</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2009.12.045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>