<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8057350</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8057350.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8057350</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8057350</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33889603</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.613203</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Acute Host-Response of Turkeys Colonized With <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter coli</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sylte</surname><given-names initials="MJ">Matthew J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>&#8224;</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1088768/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sivasankaran</surname><given-names initials="SK">Sathesh K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trachsel</surname><given-names initials="J">Julian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/533357/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zuowei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/182038/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names initials="TA">Timothy A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn003"><sup>&#8224;</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/581595/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names initials="LC">Lawrance C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn004"><sup>&#8224;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qijing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/16831/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Looft</surname><given-names initials="T">Torey</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/134927/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Food Safety and Enteric Pathogens Research Unit, National Animal Disease Center, Agricultural Research Services, U.S. Department of Agriculture</institution>, <addr-line>Ames, IA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Genome Informatics Facility, Iowa State University</institution>, <addr-line>Ames, IA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Veterinary Diagnostic Laboratory, Iowa State University</institution>, <addr-line>Ames, IA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Department of Veterinary Microbiology and Preventive Medicine, Iowa State University</institution>, <addr-line>Ames, IA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Guillermo Tellez, University of Arkansas, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Khaled Abdelaziz, Ceva Animal Health LLC, United States; Saeed El-Ashram, Foshan University, China</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Torey Looft <email>torey.looft@usda.gov</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Veterinary Infectious Diseases, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn><fn fn-type="present-address" id="fn002"><p>&#8224;Present address: Matthew J. Sylte, Center for Veterinary Biologics, Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service, United States Department of Agriculture, Ames, IA, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="present-address" id="fn003"><p>Timothy A. Johnson, Department of Animal Sciences, Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="present-address" id="fn004"><p>Lawrance C. Chandra, Department Clinical Sciences, Oklahoma State University, Stillwater, OK, United States</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>4</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">374996</issue-id><elocation-id>613203</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>10</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>21</day><month>04</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-04-01 19:25:14.540"><day>01</day><month>04</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2021 Sylte, Sivasankaran, Trachsel, Sato, Wu, Johnson, Chandra, Zhang and Looft.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sylte, Sivasankaran, Trachsel, Sato, Wu, Johnson, Chandra, Zhang and Looft</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-08-613203.pdf"/><abstract><p>Consumption of contaminated poultry products is one of the main sources of human campylobacteriosis, of which <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic> subsp. <italic toggle="yes">jejuni</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">C. jejuni</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> are responsible for ~98% of the cases. In turkeys, the ceca are an important anatomical site where <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> asymptomatically colonizes. We previously demonstrated that commercial turkey poults colonized by <italic toggle="yes">C. jejuni</italic> showed acute changes in cytokine gene expression profiles, and histological intestinal lesions at 2 days post-inoculation (dpi). Cecal tonsils (CT) are an important part of the gastrointestinal-associated lymphoid tissue that surveil material passing in and out of the ceca, and generate immune responses against intestinal pathogens. The CT immune response toward <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> remains unknown. In this study, we generated a kanamycin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> construct (CcK) to facilitate its enumeration from cecal contents after experimental challenge. <italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> analysis of CcK demonstrated no changes in motility when compared to the parent isolate. Poults were inoculated by oral gavage with CcK (5 &#215; 10<sup>7</sup> colony forming units) or sterile-media (mock-colonized), and euthanized at 1 and 3 dpi. At both time points, CcK was recovered from cecal contents, but not from the mock-colonized group. As a marker of acute inflammation, serum alpha-1 acid glycoprotein was significantly elevated at 3 dpi in CcK inoculated poults compared to mock-infected samples. Significant histological lesions were detected in cecal and CT tissues of CcK colonized poults at 1 and 3 dpi, respectively. RNAseq analysis identified 250 differentially expressed genes (DEG) in CT from CcK colonized poults at 3 dpi, of which 194 were upregulated and 56 were downregulated. From the DEG, 9 significantly enriched biological pathways were identified, including platelet aggregation, response to oxidative stress and negative regulation of oxidative stress-induced intrinsic apoptotic signaling pathway. These data suggest that <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> induced an acute inflammatory response in the intestinal tract of poults, and that platelet aggregation and oxidative stress in the CT may affect the turkey's ability to resist <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> colonization. These findings will help to develop and test <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> mitigation strategies to promote food safety in commercial turkeys.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Meleagris gallopavo</italic> (Turkey)</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter coli</italic></kwd><kwd>cecal tonsil</kwd><kwd>RNAseq analysis</kwd><kwd>acute phase protein</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="61"/><page-count count="11"/><word-count count="8829"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="disclaimer"><p>Mention of trade names or commercial products in this article is solely for the purpose of providing specific information and does not imply recommendations or endorsement by the U.S. Department of Agriculture. USDA is an equal opportunity provider and employer.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Campylobacteriosis is the most prevalent bacterial foodborne disease in humans worldwide (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Thermophillic <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic> subsp. <italic toggle="yes">jejuni</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">C. jejuni)</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> are responsible for almost 100% of cases in humans, of which up to 70% of human cases (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) are caused by ingesting or handling contaminated poultry products (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). As intestinal commensals, thermophilic campylobacters asymptomatically persistently colonize the cecum of chickens (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) and turkeys (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Acutely after colonization, some strains of <italic toggle="yes">C. jejuni</italic> have been shown to induce an upregulation of pro-inflammatory cytokines and chemokines genes in the cecum of chickens (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) or turkeys (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), as well as mild histological changes were detected in the cecum of turkeys post-colonization (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). In turkeys, expression of pro-inflammatory genes and histologic lesions resolved by day 7 post-colonization to levels detected in mock-colonized age-matched poults (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Similar kinetics in the expression of pro-inflammatory cytokine interferon-gamma (IFN&#947;) were detected in cecal tissue of chickens colonized by <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). It appears that <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> can modulate the cecal immune response shortly after colonization, but the mechanism is unknown. Studying the acute host-response may help design mitigation strategies to diminish <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> colonization in turkeys.</p><p>Both chickens and turkeys lack intestinal lymph nodes, but have a diverse complement of gastrointestinal-associated lymphoid tissues (GALT) populating the mucosal surface of the intestinal tract, and include the bursa of Fabricius, cecal tonsils (CT), Peyer's patches, Meckel's diverticulum, and discreet lymphocyte aggregates located in the intestinal lamina propria. Poultry have two ceca, each with an accompanying CT. Anatomically, CT are uniquely situated at the base of each cecum, where immune cells sample intestinal contents entering and leaving each cecum. Intestinal contents are propelled in between the ceca and colon of poultry in a process of peristalsis and antiperistalsis, which is controlled by the enteric nervous system (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">C. jejuni</italic> heavily colonizes the cecum of turkeys with &#8805;10<sup>8</sup> cfu/g of cecal contents after experimental inoculation (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). The CT are large lymphoid aggregates in the poultry GALT, and are important to control infectious diseases or respond to vaccines in the distal intestinal tract (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). The cellular composition of chicken CT are rich in B and T cells (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), and IgA secreting cells (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) and CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) in turkeys. Initially, CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells populate the chicken CT, and are slowly replaced in time by B cells and IgM/IgA secreting plasma cells (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). In spite of repeated exposure of <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> to cells of CT, little is known about the role of CT immune response to <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic>, especially <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic>. Germ-free chicks mono-associated with <italic toggle="yes">C. jejuni</italic> demonstrated an influx of B and T cells to the CT (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Differences in the expression of pro-inflammatory cytokines and chemokines were detected in chicken CT tissue following oral gavage with a <italic toggle="yes">C. jejuni</italic> lysate, with or without different adjuvants (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">C. jejuni</italic> outer membrane proteins can stimulate an inflammatory response after directly interacting with CT cells (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). In this study, turkeys were acutely colonized with <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> and we sought to characterize the host-response in intestinal tissues, focusing on the CT. We hypothesized that changes in gene expression in the CT of <italic toggle="yes">C. Coli</italic> colonized poults may help explain why poults fail to clear <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> after inoculation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Generation of <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter coli</italic> Antibiotic Resistant Construct</title><p>The <italic toggle="yes">CmeF</italic> locus was selected as insertion site of kanamycin (Kan) antibiotic resistant cassette into wild-type <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter coli</italic> strain 80-102 (ATCC 43481), which was originally isolated from turkey feces in Colorado. This locus was previously used to transform wild-type <italic toggle="yes">C. jejuni</italic> strain NCTC 11168 with chloramphenicol or kanamycin resistance cassettes to create antibiotic resistant constructs (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Briefly, two sets of primers were designed to amplify both ends of the <italic toggle="yes">CmeF</italic> gene and were used as the flanking sequences to help integrate the Kan resistance cassette into the <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> chromosome by homogenous recombination (Pair one: Cme-1F: 5&#8242;-CCTAAGGAAAGATCATTCACTCCAGCTGTG-3&#8242;, Cme-1R:5&#8242;-GATATATTGATAAGCGGGATCCGCGTGCAGGCATTGATGATCCCG-3&#8242;; Pair two: Cme-2F:5&#8242;-GTCTTAGCATTATCCTGCAGTTCGCAGCTTGTAAAGGCGGAT-3&#8242;, Cme-2R: 5&#8242;-GAACTTAGCAATCTTCGCATAAAAACAGGAG-3&#8242;). The Kan resistance cassette was amplified from pMW10 (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) by the following primers: kanF 5&#8242;-CGCGGATCCCGCTTATCAATATATCTATAGAATGG-3&#8242;, kanR 5&#8242;-GAACTGCAGGATAATGCTAAGACAATCACTAAAG-3&#8242;. An overlap PCR was performed to get a three-fragment-ligated product (CmeF-part1_Kan_CmeF-part2). The CmeF-Kan resistance cassette fragments were introduced into <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> isolate 80-102 using an electroporator (Gene Pulser Xcell System; Bio-Rad Laboratories, Richmond, CA, USA), and incubated onn Muller Hinton agar (MH; Neogen Corporation, Lansing, MI) for 5 h. Transformants (<italic toggle="yes">CmeF</italic>::<italic toggle="yes">Kan</italic>) were selected on MH agar containing kanamycin (30 &#956;g/L) cultured at 42&#176;C in a microaerophilic gas environment (5% O<sub>2</sub>, 10% CO<sub>2</sub> and 85% N<sub>2</sub> gas) for 48 h, and individual colonies were tested using PCR to ensure the Kan resistance cassette was inserted into the <italic toggle="yes">cmeF</italic> gene. The resistance of different <italic toggle="yes">CmeF</italic>::<italic toggle="yes">Kan</italic> transformants was determined by culturing individual colonies were on Campy Line agar (CLA) (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>) containing different concentration of kanamycin (25, 50 or 100 &#956;g/mL) at 42&#176;C in a microaerpohillic gas environment. <italic toggle="yes">CmeF</italic>::<italic toggle="yes">Kan</italic> transformants (herein named CcK) were considered kanamycin resistant if they grew on CLA containing at least 100 &#956;g/mL kanamycin. Once antibiotic resistance was determined, aliquots of the strain were stored at &#8722;80&#176;C in MH broth containing 10% (v/v) sterile glycerol.</p></sec><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> Motility and Growth Curves</title><p>The motility of wild type <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> or kanamycin-resistant construct CcK used in these studies were assessed each time it was used. Briefly, cryopreserved <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> were inoculated onto a CLA plate, with or without kanamycin (100 &#956;g/mL), and were cultured in a microaerophilic gas incubator at 42&#176;C for 18 h. Up to 5 colony forming units (cfu) of each strain were used to inoculate Bolton's broth base (Neogen Corporation), and was incubated shaking (100 rpm) in a miroaerophillic gas environment at 42&#176;C for 18 h. Ten microliter of each broth culture was microscopically visualized at 400X magnification using a Nikon Eclipse Ni dark-field microscope (Nikon Instruments Inc., Melville, NY). Motility was visually assessed. Strains were considered motile if they had a positive motility agar test or had at least 90% of the organisms actively moving. If motility wasn't detected in the agar stab, or &lt;90% were motile by microscopic observation, the inoculum was not used.</p><p>Preparation of the growth curve inocula were performed by static culture of CcK and its parent strain at 42&#176;C in the broth phase of biphasic MH broth and agar (2% w/v) in a microaerophilic gas environment (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Growth curves were performed in octuplet using instrument-specific microplates in a Bioscreen C plate reader (Growth Curves USA, Piscataway, NJ), measuring OD<sub>600</sub> every 2 h for 48 h. To limit aggregation, which may impact optical density values, microplates were shaken for 30 s prior to each OD<sub>600</sub> reading. For each replicate of each isolate, MH broth culture volumes were 200 &#956;L, and were incubated at 42&#176;C in a microaerophilic gas chamber. Uninoculated media served as a control to subtract OD<sub>600</sub> background. The logistical area under the curve, growth rate and generation time were determined by analyzing growth curve data using the R package growthcurver (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Animal Experimental Design</title><p>This animal experiment was conducted according to the regulations established by the NADC Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee. Day of hatch Hybrid jake poults (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 45) were obtained from a commercial breeder and co-housed in a single ABSL-2 room. Throughout the study, poults were fed a turkey poult starter ration and had water available <italic toggle="yes">ad libitum</italic>. The <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> status of experimental poults was determined at day 15 of age by randomly selecting and euthanizing <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5 poults. Necropsy was performed to harvest 1 g of cecal contents, which was cultured by enrichment in 10 mL of Bolton's broth base containing <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> selection supplement (Neogen Corporation) for 48 h in a microaerophilic gas environment at 42&#176;C (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Afterward, 100 &#956;L was cultured for 48 h at 42&#176;C in a microaerophilic environment on Campy Line agar containing 25 &#956;g/mL sulfamethoxazole (CLA-S) (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Poults were considered free of <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> colonization if no colonies resembling pure cultures of <italic toggle="yes">C. jejuni</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> were recovered after enrichment. After co-housing for 20 days, the remaining (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 40) poults were evenly distributed into two ABSL-2 rooms for challenge (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 20/room). Room temperature, humidity and lighting cycle were approximately the same for the ABSL-2 rooms. Preparation of <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> CcK inoculum was performed by subculturing at least 5 colonies from a pure culture of CcK on CLA-S agar supplemented with 100 &#956;g/mL kanamycin (CLA-S-K) into 100 mL of MH broth and cultured in a microaerophilic gas environment at 42&#176;C shaking at 100 rpm for 48 h. On the day of challenge, the OD<sub>600</sub> value was adjusted to 0.4 in sterile MH broth. The cfu/mL of each inocula was enumerated using serial dilation CLA-S agar supplemented with 100 &#956;g/mL kanamycin, and motility was assessed using dark-field microscopy, as described above. At 21 days old, all poults (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 20) within a room were individually inoculated by orally gavage with either 1 mL of MH broth containing approximately 5 &#215; 10<sup>7</sup> cfu of CcK, or mock inoculated with 1 mL of sterile MH broth. At 1- and 3-days post-inoculation (dpi), <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 10 poults from the CcK or mock-inoculated rooms were randomly selected, bled from their brachial vein and euthanized by intravenous barbiturate overdose. Necropsy was performed to harvest cecal contents for enumeration of CcK from each animal. Intestinal tissues, including ileum, CT and colon were fixed in buffered neutral formalin for histological analysis and the remaining CT was preserved in RNALater for isolation of total RNA.</p></sec><sec><title>Enumeration of <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> From Intestinal Samples</title><p>Cecal contents were stored on ice and transported to the laboratory for culture. From each animal, 1 g of cecal contents was diluted in 9 mL of sterile PBS, vortexed for 5 s and serially diluted up to 10<sup>&#8722;6</sup>. Enumeration was performed utilizing the track-plating dilution method (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>), where 10 &#956;L of each dilution was plated in duplicate on CLA-S-K and incubated at 42&#176;C in a microaerophilic environment for 48 h. Colony forming units resembling those from pure cultures of <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> isolate 80-102 were enumerated. For statistical purposes, if no colonies resembling <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> grew, the sample was assigned the culture limit of detection value of 10<sup>3</sup> cfu/g of contents. Poults were considered positive for <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> colonization if at least one colony was cultured on CLS-S-K media.</p></sec><sec><title>Histological Analysis</title><p>At necropsy, colon, ileum, cecum and a CT were immersed in 10% buffered neutral formalin, and fixed for 48 h. Tissues were transferred and stored in 70% ethanol before cutting into histology cassettes and embedding in paraffin for thin sectioning (5 &#956;m), and stained with hematoxalin and eosin. Slides were single-blinded analyzed and scored by a poultry pathologist (YS) for lesions. Because <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> are commensals of the poultry intestinal microbiota, and severe lesions are not observed in experimentally colonized poults (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), a unique scoring system was used to evaluate changes of the intestinal histomorphology. The following criteria were scored from ten random fields per tissue at 400X magnification: (1) Heterophils in lamina propria; score (&lt;3, 0; &#8805;3&#8211;5, 1; &#8805;5&#8211;10, 2; &#8805;10, 3), (2) Heterophil margination in epithelium; score (&lt;10%, 0; &#8805;10&#8211;25%, 1; &#8805;25&#8211;75%, 2; &#8805;75%, 3), (3) Edema in lamina propria; score (&lt;10%, 0; &#8805;10&#8211;25, 1; &#8805;25&#8211;75, 2; &#8805;75, 3), (4) Goblet cell hyperplasia; score (&lt;10%, 0; &#8805;10&#8211;25%, 1; &#8805;=25&#8211;75%, 2; &#8805;75%, 3). (5) Crypt ectasia (small) &lt;100 &#956;m; score (&lt;3, 1; &#8805;3&#8211;5, 2; &gt;5, 3), (6) Crypt ectasia (large); &#8805;100 = 400 &#956;m, add 2 to score from crypt ectasia (small); &#8805;400 &#956;m, add 3 to score), (7) Apoptotic/necrotic cells in lamina propria; score (&lt;10%, 0; &#8805;10&#8211;25%, 1; &#8805;25&#8211;75%, 2; &#8805;75%, 3) and (8) Blunting &#177; fusion of epithelium; score (no lesions, 0; mild blunting, 1; moderate to marked blunting, 2; severe blunting and fusion &#177; blebbing, 3). For each group, the final scores were averaged. The minimal and maximal scores were 0 and 24, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Alpha-1 Acid Glycoprotein ELISA</title><p>Prior to euthanasia, ~3 mL of blood was sampled from the brachial vein and clotted by incubating at 37&#176;C for 4 h. Afterwards, blood was centrifuged at 1,200 &#215; g for 10 min at 4&#176;C, serum was removed and stored at &#8722;20&#176;C. Serum alpha-1 acid glycoprotein (AGP) levels were measured, performed in triplicate for each serum sample, using a commercially available turkey-specific AGP ELISA (Life Diagnostics Inc.; West Chester, PA). Following the manufacturer's protocol, serum samples were diluted and absorbance at 405 nm was measured using a Synergy HT spectrophotometer (BioTek; Wintooski, VT). Per the manufacturer's recommendation, the AGP concentration (ng/mL) was extrapolated from an AGP standard curve, using BioTek Gen 5 software.</p></sec><sec><title>RNA Preservation, Total RNA Extraction, and RNAseq Library Preparation</title><p>Total RNA from the remaining CT from each poult was preserved by immersing the tissue in 5 mL of RNALater stabilizer solution (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA), and were incubated at 4&#176;C for 24 h (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). The CT was snap frozen by placing it in an internally threaded cryovial and fully immersing in liquid nitrogen for 1 min. Cryovials were then stored indefinitely in a &#8722;80&#176;C freezer. For total RNA isolation, up to 150 mg of CT was placed into a gentleMACS M tube (Miltenyi Biotec Inc., San Diego, CA) containing 1 mL of TRIZOL reagent (Life Technologies). Tissue was homogenized using a gentleMACS Octo Dissociator (Miltenyi Biotec Inc.) using the gentleMACS program RNA_02. The homogenate was centrifuged in the M tube for 30 s at 800 &#215; g at room temperature, and supernatant was transferred to nuclease-free 1.5 mL microfuge tubes. Two hundred microliter of chloroform was added and up to 300 &#956;L of the aqueous phase was harvested after centrifugation for 15 min at 12,000 &#215; g at 4&#176;C. The aqueous phase was further processed using mirVana miRNA isolation kit without phenol, per the manufacturer's protocol (Ambion, Carlsbad, CA). The quantity of eluted total RNA was spectrophotometrically estimated using a NanoDrop-2000 instrument (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA). Per the manufacturer's protocol, up to 500 ng of total RNA was evaluated for RNA integrity using an RNA ScreenTape and 2200 TapeStation instrument (Agilent Technologies Inc., Santa Clara, CA). Total RNA was stored at &#8722;80&#176;C in nuclease free tubes until used to prepare RNAseq libraries. All samples had RNA integrity number equivalent (RINe) values &#8805; 8, indicating the high quality of total RNA isolated from CT samples. Up to 100 ng of total RNA was used to generate sequencing libraries using TruSeq stranded mRNA library kit (Illumina; San Diego, CA).</p></sec><sec><title>RNAseq Analysis</title><p>Eight library samples per lane were randomly assigned across 4 lanes of a HiSeq 3000 (Illumina), and paired end 100 bp sequencing was performed. The quality of the sequenced reads was analyzed using FastQC (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/">https://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/</ext-link>). Reads were aligned to the turkey reference genome (UMD 5.0, NCBI Annotation 101) and read counts were quantified using the STAR algorithm v2.5.2b (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Genes that had raw read count &lt;10 in all samples were considered as a low signal and removed from the differential gene expression analysis. The gene counts for each sample were transformed and normalized using the Bioconductor package DESeq2 v1.24.0 (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) in R v3.5.0. Principle Component Analysis (PCA) was performed to determine any expression outliers based on overall gene expression counts. Linear regression models within DESeq2 were used to test differentially expressed genes between case and control groups. The effect of known covariates between case-control status including RNA quality (e.g., RNA integrity number) and sequencing slide differences was tested using Student's <italic toggle="yes">T</italic>-test (R software). In addition, to account for the underlying unmeasured confounding factors in the RNA-Seq data, we used SVAseq (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) with default parameters to estimate surrogate variables (SVs). None of the estimated SVs differed significantly between case-control status in both 1 and 3 dpi, so we did not include them in the differential gene expression analysis model. We considered fold change &#8805;1.5 (&#8805;0.58 log<sub>2</sub>FC) with FDR &lt; 0.05 as a significantly differentially expressed gene (DEG). To identify functional groups from the DEG, we tested gene sets of Gene Ontology Biological Processes (GO:BP) terms using DAVID (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>) online tool with default parameters. The GO terms with FDR &lt; 0.1 were considered as enriched. Raw sequenced reads and processed data have been deposited in NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus database and are available under accession <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-geo" xlink:href="GSE158639"><ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="GSE158639">GSE158639</ext-link></ext-link> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE158639">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE158639</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Data for <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> enumeration were analyzed using an unpaired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test with Welch's correction using Prism statistical software v8.1.2 (Graph Pad Software Inc., San Diego, CA) to detect differences between time points. Data for serum alpha-1 acid glycoprotein concentration and histological scoring were analyzed for significant differences between groups or treatment days using a one-way ANOVA followed by Tukey <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> multiple comparisons test using Prism. Growth curve data were analyzed for logistical area under the curve, generation time and growth rate using the R package growthcurver (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/cran/growthcurver">https://github.com/cran/growthcurver</ext-link>) (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Results were considered significant at values of <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &#8804; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> Growth and Motility of Wild-Type <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> and Kanamycin-Resistant Construct CcK</title><p>In order to more easily enumerate <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> from cecal contents, a kanamycin-resistant construct (CcK) was generated by inserting the kanamycin-resistance cassette into <italic toggle="yes">CmeF</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">CmeF:</italic>:<italic toggle="yes">Kan</italic>) in the chromosome of <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> parent strain ATCC 80-102. The same locus was previously used to generate antibiotic resistant constructs of <italic toggle="yes">C. jejuni</italic> (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). The parent strain was killed by addition of 10 &#956;g /mL of kanamycin into CLA-S agar, whereas CcK grew on CLA-S containing 25, 50 or 100 &#956;g/mL of kanamycin. Analysis of growth between the parent strain and CcK (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>) demonstrated significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the logistical area under curve, doubling time and growth rate (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>). Motility is essential for <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> colonization in turkeys (Sylte, 2018). No difference in motility was detected between CcK and its parent strain. Overall, these data demonstrate that CcK construct didn't affect motility, but <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> growth of CcK was significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) than its parent strain. While the purpose of this study was not to compare the wild type and the antibiotic-resistant construct, it is important to acknowledge that these genetic changes could potentially affect colonization <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. For example, the acquisition of antibiotic resistance, particularly chromosomal mutations, comes at a biological cost, in the absence of antibiotic selective pressure. This may result in a decreased fitness such as a reduced <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> growth rate or a decrease in ability to persist in the host (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). As such, we cannot exclude the possibility that an altered <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> fitness may affect the host response compared to a wild-type <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> isolate.</p></sec><sec><title>Cecal Colonization of Turkey Poults With CcK</title><p>Poults used in this study were free of detectable <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> prior to experimental inoculation, based on lack of <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> recovery after enrichment of cecal contents. At 1 dpi, all sampled poults (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 10) in the CcK group were positive for colonization with 3.32 &#215; 10<sup>7</sup> &#177; 4.4 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup> cfu/g of cecal contents (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> and <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). By 3 dpi, 8/10 poults (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) in the CcK group were positive for colonization with significantly less (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0021) CcK recovered (7.63 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup> &#177; 5.52 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup> cfu/g of cecal contents) that at 1 dpi. Mock-colonized poults remained free of detectable CcK contamination throughout the study (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The 1 and 3 dpi CcK cecal colonization data are similar to levels seen 2 dpi in turkeys infected with chloramphenicol- or kanamycin-resistant constructs of <italic toggle="yes">C. jejuni</italic> (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). In the absence of kanamycin, a loss of fitness may explain the significant decrease in CcK cecal colonization between 1 and 3 dpi. However, we were concerned about the detrimental effects on the intestinal microbiota, and didn't administer kanamycin to poults after inoculation. Diminished fitness of <italic toggle="yes">C. jejuni</italic> in the absence of a positive selection antibiotic is supported by previous work where erythromycin resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. jejuni</italic> was less ecologically fit than the erythromycin sensitive parent strains, and failed to transmit to chickens already colonized by erythromycin sensitive <italic toggle="yes">C. jejuni</italic> (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>).We think a decrease in CcK fitness would be minimized by the acute design of this study, but should be considered for animal studies longer designed to achieve <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> persistence.</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Enumeration of antibiotic resistant construct CcK from cecal contents of turkey poults. Data represent the mean CcK cfu/g of cecal contents from each poult and the mean (solid bar) &#177; SEM at 1 and 3 dpi. Statistical differences in the number of enumerated CcK cfu/g of cecal contents was determined using an unpaired <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test with Welch's correction. Significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) between different time points are represented by an asterisk (*).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-613203-g0001.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of CcK direct plate enumeration and post-culture validation from cecal samples 1 and 3 dpi.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Days post- inoculation</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Inoculation</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> colonization</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Cecal colonization</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Direct plating culture positive</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> qPCR positive</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcK</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mock</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>#</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/10</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CcK</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mock</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>#</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/10</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><label>#</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Below limit of detection (10<sup>3</sup> cfu/g of contents)</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Host-Response to CcK Colonization</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> mainly colonize the distal intestinal of turkey poults (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), and produce a temporal change in expression of pro-inflammatory genes in the cecum and intestinal histological lesions (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), but it was unknown whether the inflammatory response extended beyond the intestinal tract. Alpha-1 acid glycoprotein (AGP; also known as orosomucoid 1) is a positive acute phase protein produced in poultry. The only commercially available, turkey-specific reagent to test production of acute phase proteins is for AGP. It is best characterized in chickens, and increases in response to bacterial, viral or other inflammatory stimuli (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>), and may modulate phagocytosis and bacterial killing by heterophils (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Less is known about the biology of AGP in turkeys, especially if <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> colonization affects serum AGP levels. At 3 dpi, serum AGP levels were significantly elevated (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001) in CcK-colonized poults (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). These data indicate that inflammation from CcK colonization induced a systemic response. Because of the acute nature of this study, we were unable to follow the kinetics of serum AGP levels after CcK colonization. However, our data are similar to those in layer hens orally inoculated with <italic toggle="yes">S. enterica</italic> serovar Enteritidis, which induced a significant increase in serum AGP concentration (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). Production of AGP is temporal in chickens (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>), and is likely the same in turkeys after CcK colonization. Pro-inflammatory cytokines IL-1&#946;, TNF&#945; or IL-6 induce AGP expression from the liver (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>), the main tissue producing APG in chickens (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). Our previous work demonstrated elevated cecal <italic toggle="yes">il6</italic> expression 2 dpi in <italic toggle="yes">C. jejuni</italic> inoculated poults (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). We did not test for cytokine gene expression in cecal tissue in this study, but cecal IL-6 or other pro-inflammatory cytokines may be the cause of elevated serum AGP at 3 dpi.</p><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Serum alpha-1 acid glycoprotein (AGP) concentration in CcK- or mock-colonized turkey poults. Data represent the mean AGP (ng/mL) from CcK- or mock-colonized poults and the mean (solid bar) &#177; SEM at 1 and 3 dpi. Statistical differences between means were determined using one-way ANOVA followed by a <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> multiple comparisons test (Tukey). Significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) different time points and treatments are represented by different letters.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-613203-g0002.jpg"/></fig><p>To further assess the host-response to CcK colonization, single blinded histological scoring of intestinal tissues (e.g., cecum, cecal tonsil, colon, and ileum) from mock- and CcK-inoculated poults at 1 and 3 dpi was performed. At 1 and 3 dpi, CcK inoculated intestinal tissues had significantly higher (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.03) mean histological scores (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>). Scores for cecum and cecal tonsil tissues were analyzed, and significant lesion scores (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.0001) were noted at 1 dpi, but not 3 dpi, in the cecum of CcK-colonized poults (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>). Significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.0001) in histological scoring was detected at 3 dpi, but not 1 dpi, in the cecal tonsil of CcK-colonized poults (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3C</xref>). Representative images for the intestinal tissue comparisons show areas of necrotic or dilated crypts with intralesional bacteria (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">Supplementary Figures 3&#8211;5</xref>). These results are similar to previous work where significant histological lesion scoring was detected acutely in intestinal tissues of turkeys inoculated by <italic toggle="yes">C. jejuni</italic> at 2 dpi, but not at 7 or 14 dpi (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Common lesions in CcK inoculated cecum at 1 dpi were severe blunting of cecal villi and necrotic crypts, and degenerate heterophils in the cecal tonsils at 3 dpi.</p><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Histological scoring of intestinal tissues. A grading score was used to evaluate the following changes of the intestinal histomorphology in CcK- or mock-colonized poults at 1 and 3 dpi: (1) number of heterophils in the epithelium, lamina propria, and submucosa/muscularis as a possible indicator of inflammation and immune activation, (2) presence of small granulomas within the lamina propria, (3) crypt ectasia with or without heterophilic accumulation, (4) presence of apoptotic cells in the lamina propria, (5) areas with attenuated epithelium. Intermediate scores for each category (1&#8211;5) was obtained for all intestinal sections (ileum, cecal tonsils, ceca, and colon) for each bird. The final histological score of one poult was the sum of each intermediate scores. For each group, the final scores were averaged for <bold>(A)</bold> all intestinal tissues, <bold>(B)</bold> cecum only and <bold>(C)</bold> CT only and differences between means were determined using one-way ANOVA followed by a <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> multiple comparisons test (Tukey). Significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) within time points are represented by an asterisk (*).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-613203-g0003.jpg"/></fig><p>Previously, we've demonstrated expression of pro-inflammatory genes, including IFN&#947; in the cecum, and histological lesions in the distal intestinal tract of poults 2 dpi <italic toggle="yes">C. jejuni</italic> colonization (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Similar kinetics in the expression of pro-inflammatory cytokine IFN&#947; were detected in cecal tissue of chickens colonized by <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic>, and it's hypothesized that impairing <italic toggle="yes">ifng</italic> expression may be responsible for <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> colonization (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). The rapid decrease in expression of pro-inflammatory genes in the cecum shortly after <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> colonization represents an important opportunity to improve <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> mitigation strategies. We sought to examine the acute host-response in the cecal tonsil of CcK and mock-colonized poults at 1 and 3 dpi and used RNAseq-based approaches to globally identify the transcriptional changes in the CT samples. To our knowledge, this is the first description of transcriptional changes in the CT of poultry after <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> colonization. All CcK- and mock-inoculated samples used in this study are detailed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM7">Supplementary Table 1</xref>. RNA integrity ranged from 9.3 to 10 for the 32 samples. At both 1 and 3 dpi, mock colonized (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8) and CcK colonized (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8) RNA samples from CT were subject to RNAseq. Using PCA analysis, 3 outliers were identified from the CcK colonized 1 dpi samples, and removed and 29 of 32 samples were processed for differential gene (DEG) expression analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM6">Supplementary Figure 6</xref>). The total number of reads produced for each library ranged from 24 to 92 million with the median of 46.5 million paired-end reads per library. Approximately, 82% of sequenced reads were successfully mapped uniquely to the reference genome (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM7">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). Approximately, 13% of mapped reads failed to align due to short read length or poor read quality. A small percentage of reads were (4.4%) aligned to multiple location in the genome which were removed from the downstream analysis.</p><p>Using the criteria of fold change &#8805; 1.5 and FDR &lt; 0.05, a total of 273 DEG were identified in the acute phase (3 dpi) after CcK colonization (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM8">Supplementary Tables 2, 3</xref>), and none of the DEG were passed our filtering criteria at 1 dpi, Of the 273 DEG, 149 genes were significantly up-regulated and 124 were down-regulated. Identification of DEG at 3 dpi in CT samples agrees with CT histological lesion scores (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3C</xref>). The top 10 significantly up- and down-regulated DEG are summarized in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Mal T cell differentiation protein like (MALL), was significantly downregulated at 3 dpi in CT, and functions in T cell differentiation (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Downregulating <italic toggle="yes">Mall</italic> may impair the development of antigen-specific T cells, and promote colonization by <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic>. In poultry, food-borne pathogens, such as <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic>, may induce immunological tolerance (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>), which may explain why they fail to clear these bacteria. Development of regulatory T cells (Tregs) may explain how poultry become immunologically tolerant to food-borne pathogens. More cells resembling a Treg phenotype (CD4<sup>+</sup>, CD25<sup>hi</sup>, and IL-10<sup>+</sup>) were isolated from cecal tonsils (CT) of chickens colonized with <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium, than control chickens (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Although we found no significant differences in expression of <italic toggle="yes">il10</italic> or other putative Treg markers in poultry (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">ctla4, lag3</italic>, and others) (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), development of Tregs by the end of this study (3 dpi) was unlikely. <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Pullorum modulated CT host immunity to a Th2 response by downregulating expression of <italic toggle="yes">ifng</italic> and upregulating <italic toggle="yes">il13</italic> (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). These data, and ours, suggest that food-borne pathogens in poultry, modulate the immune response in the intestinal tract, including the cecal tonsil, of to avoid their clearance. Examining transcriptional changes at later time points may be useful to test the development of immunotolerance in the CT of <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> colonized turkeys. <italic toggle="yes">In ovo</italic> treatment of chicken embryos with a probiotic, <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus salvarius</italic>, modulated the expression of CT immune genes after hatch (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Although not attempted, it would be interesting to see whether imprinting CT gene expression with a probiotic could prevent foodborne pathogen colonization, or enhance gut health.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Summary of upregulated and downregulated differently expressed genes at 3 dpi in cecal tonsil of CcK-colonized poults.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gene symbol</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Fold change (log2)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>FDR <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Genbank</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Predicted gene function</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC100540260</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04579</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XM_010708497">XM_010708497</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tyrosine phosphatase receptor type transcript</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC100545456</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03510</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XM_010725015">XM_010725015</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Receptor accessory protein transcript variant</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC104917316</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02443</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XM_010728501">XM_010728501</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homeobox protein SIX2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC104912995</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03187</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XR_795065">XR_795065</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized protein</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC100546239</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03249</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XM_010707354">XM_010707354</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LEG1 homolog-like</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC104916149</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04231</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XM_010727130">XM_010727130</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homeobox protein SIX2-like</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC104914158</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01238</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XR_002119998">XR_002119998</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized protein</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC104911266</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01908</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XM_010712037">XM_010712037</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iodothyronine deiodinase 3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC100544663</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03367</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XM_003209101">XM_003209101</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apolipoprotein D</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC100540834</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01898</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XM_010715727">XM_010715727</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative dimethylaniline monooxygenase [N-oxide-forming] 6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC104916315</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00257</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XM_010727366">XM_010727366</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EGF-like domain-containing protein</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC104914637</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01804</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XM_010724747">XM_010724747</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fibrillin-1-like</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC104912630</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01013</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XM_010716658">XM_010716658</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Collagen alpha-3(IV) chain-like</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC104913148</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04840</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XM_019611809">XM_019611809</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ovostatin-like</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC100543592</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04453</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XM_003213848">XM_003213848</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleoredoxin-like transcript</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC104914991</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01589</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XR_002109873">XR_002109873</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized protein</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC109364129</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01178</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XR_002110156">XR_002110156</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized protein</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC104914821</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02927</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XM_019610345">XM_019610345</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDZ domain-containing protein 2-like</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC104912792</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00001</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XM_019619432">XM_019619432</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E3 ubiquitin-protein ligase HERC1-like</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC104915991</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00008</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XR_002121382">XR_002121382</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized protein</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LOC104916559</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.69</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00035</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XR_796609">XR_796609</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uncharacterized protein</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>To predict the downstream effects of the 3 dpi DEG, pathway analysis was performed using GO:BP terms using DAVID software. Using the turkey gene symbols from the list of DEG, we identified 9 BP terms (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>) significantly altered in 3 dpi CcK samples (FDR &lt; 0.1). A more lenient FDR was used to maximize GO:BP terms for pathway identification, and this technique has been used to identify pathways in data sets with smaller numbers of DEG (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). Of the identified BP terms relating to inflammation, platelet aggregation has the most significant BP terms (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.008). Platelets aggregate during hemostasis as well as during thrombosis. Histological analysis of CcK colonized tissues revealed no evidence of hemorrhage or thrombosis. Mammalian platelets are known to express pro-inflammatory cytokines, chemokines and activate inflammatory cells, but may also diminish inflammation (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). It is unknown whether <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> interacts with platelets in the CT, or affects inflammation. Negative regulation of vascular permeability (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.052) was also identified. The DEG involved in this may function to limit the formation of edema in CT after <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> colonization, as well limit as an influx of inflammatory cells (e.g., heterophils). Oxidative stress and apoptosis were another common BP terms, including response to oxidative stress (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.033), negative regulation of oxidative stress-induced intrinsic apoptotic signaling pathway (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.044), and negative regulation of release of cytochrome C from mitochondria (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.092). The intrinsic pathway of apoptosis is initiated by stressors such as UV radiation, oxidant stress and involves activation of caspase-9 via the release of mitochondrial cytochrome C into the cytoplasm of affected cells (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). It is unclear if these BP terms are functioning as a result of a stressor in the CT. How <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> activate oxidant stress in the CT of colonized poults is unknown. Methionine is a key limiting amino acid in poultry, and its deficiency produced oxidant stress in CT of chickens (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> are fastidious and some strains (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">C. jejuni</italic> NCTC 11168) require methionine for growth in a minimal medium (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>), and rapidly consume it from medium (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). It's not known whether the CcK isolate is similar and rapidly consumes methionine. Based on these observations, CcK may consume dietary methionine and create a deficiency in the CT to produce oxidant stress. Supplementation of dietary methionine may prevent oxidant stress in the CT after <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> colonization and affect the functionality of the CT immune response.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Pathway analysis: significantly enriched gene ontology (GO) biological process (BP) terms.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Go term ID</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>BP term</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>FDR <italic toggle="yes">p-</italic>value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0070527</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platelet aggregation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01465</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0051450</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myoblast proliferation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03088</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:2001214</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive regulation of vasculogenesis</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04095</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0043116</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative regulation of vascular permeability</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0509</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006979</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response to oxidative stress</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05896</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:1902176</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative regulation of oxidative stress-induced intrinsic apoptotic signaling pathway</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06081</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0006412</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Translation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07213</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0008299</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isoprenoid biosynthetic process</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08983</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0090201</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative regulation of release of cytochrome c from mitochondria</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08983</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GO:0048741</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skeletal muscle fiber development</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09931</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>In conclusion, the results from these studies are the first to describe the host-response of the turkey CT to <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> colonization. Using a <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> kanamycin resistant construct CcK for ease of enumeration from cecal contents, poults were orally colonized and the acute host response was evaluated. Significant histological lesions were noted in the cecum at 1 dpi and in CT at 3 dpi, and transcriptome analysis of CT gene expression demonstrated DEG at 3 dpi. Genes involved in regulating immune function were downregulated, and pathway analysis of the DEG identified platelet aggregation, downregulation of apoptosis and decreased vascular permeability. Evaluation of gene expression at additional timepoints after colonization, with different wild type stains, would likely provide additional understanding of the dynamic responses after infection. Results from this study provide insight into host-response of the turkey CT to <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> colonization. These findings will help to develop and test <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> mitigation strategies to promote food safety in commercial turkeys.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s4"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The datasets presented in this study can be found in online repositories. The names of the repository/repositories and accession number(s) can be found in the article/<xref ref-type="sec" rid="s7">Supplementary Material</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by National Animal Disease Center Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>MS designed the experiment. MS, TJ, LC, and TL were involved in acquisition of the experimental data. ZW and QZ generated the antibiotic-resistant <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> construct. MS, JT, SS, and YS performed data analysis and interpretation. The manuscript was drafted and revised for important intellectual content by MS, JT, SS, YS, ZW, TL, TJ, LC, and QZ, as well as, final approval of the version to be published with agreement to be accountable for all aspects of the work in ensuring that questions related to the accuracy or integrity of any part of the work are appropriately investigated and resolved. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors are greatly appreciative of the outstanding technical support of Matt H. Inbody, Ella L. Meyer, Lisa X. Lai, Dalene Whitney, and Brian Conrad. The authors thank Dr. David Alt and Darrell Bales for assistance with the ISU DNA sequencing facility.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This research was supported by USDA, ARS appropriated CRIS funds.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s7"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2021.613203/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2021.613203/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Figure 1</label><caption><p>Growth characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> wild-type (parent strain) NCTC 80-102, and kanamycin-resistant construct (CcK). Growth curves were performed in Mueller Hinton broth for 48 h at 42&#176;C in a microaerophilic environment (5% O<sub>2</sub>, 10% CO<sub>2</sub>, and 85% N<sub>2</sub>). Data represent the mean &#177; SEM OD<sub>600</sub> of 8 cultures in Bolton's broth measured every 2 h for a total of 48 h with the background value of unincolated media subtracted.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Image_1.TIF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Figure 2</label><caption><p>Analysis of logistical area under the curve, growth rate and generation time of <italic toggle="yes">C. coli</italic> wild-type (parent) NCTC 80-102, and kanamycin-resistant construct (CcK). Growth curves were performed in Mueller Hinton broth for 48 h at 42&#176;C in a microaerophilic environment (5% O<sub>2</sub>, 10% CO<sub>2</sub>, and 85% N<sub>2</sub>). Data represent the mean &#177; SEM logistical area under the curve, growth rate and doubling time of 8 replicate cultures in either broth. Statistical differences in the each variable were determined using the R package growthcurver followed by a <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> multiple comparisons test (Tukey). Significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) between different organisms are represented by different letters.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Image_2.TIF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Figure 3</label><caption><p>Representative Histological of ileal tissues. Representative comparisons are shown for <bold>(A)</bold> an ileum from a mock-colonized bird and <bold>(B)</bold> ileum from a CcK-colonized bird, with heterophilic ileitis marked with an arrow.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Image_3.TIFF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Figure 4</label><caption><p>Representative Histological of cecal tonsil tissues. Representative comparisons are shown for <bold>(A)</bold> a cecal tonsil from a mock-colonized bird and <bold>(B)</bold> cecal tonsil from a CcK-colonized bird, with necrotic cecal crypts with intralesional bacteria marked with a star.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Image_4.TIFF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Figure 5</label><caption><p>Representative Histological of colonic tissues. Representative comparisons are shown for <bold>(A)</bold> a colonic tissue from a mock-colonized bird and <bold>(B)</bold> colonic tissue from a CcK-colonized bird, with crypt dilatation/ectasia marked with star.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Image_5.TIFF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Figure 6</label><caption><p>PCA analysis of RNAseq samples.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Image_6.TIFF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Table 1</label><caption><p>CcK infected and mock turkey cecal tonsil RNAseq samples description and sequencing statistics.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_1.XLSX" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Table 2</label><caption><p>List of differentially expressed genes in 1 dpi.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_2.XLSX" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Table 3</label><caption><p>List of differentially expressed genes in 3 dpi.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_3.XLSX" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tauxe</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Emerging foodborne pathogens</article-title>. <source>Int J Food Microbiol.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>78</volume>:<fpage>31</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-1605(02)00232-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12222636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Epps</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hume</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nisbet</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Foodborne <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic>: infections, metabolism, pathogenesis and reservoirs</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>6292</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>304</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph10126292</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24287853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3881114</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corcoran</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dooley</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fanning</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Campylobacter</article-title>. <source>Vet Res</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>351</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/vetres:2005012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15845230</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beery</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hugdahl</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Colonization of gastrointestinal tracts of chicks by <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. (<year>1988</year>) <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>2365</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.54.10.2365-2370.1988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3060015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC204261</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sylte</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inbody</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Looft</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Line</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of different <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic> isolates to colonize the intestinal tract of commercial turkey poults and selective media for enumeration</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>97</volume>:<fpage>1689</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>98</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pex384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29514291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sylte</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inbody</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trachsel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Looft</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Intestinal colonization and acute immune response in commercial turkeys following inoculation with <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic> constructs encoding antibiotic-resistance markers</article-title>. <source>Vet Immunol Immunopathol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>210</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetimm.2019.02.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30947981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abuoun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cawthraw</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothwell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> colonization of the chicken induces a proinflammatory response in mucosal tissues</article-title>. <source>FEMS Immunol Med Microbiol.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>114</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-695X.2008.00458.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18647351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaughnessy</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meade</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cahalane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reiman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callanan</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Innate immune gene expression differentiates the early avian intestinal response between <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic></article-title>. <source>Vet Immunol Immunopathol</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>132</volume>:<fpage>191</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetimm.2009.06.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19632728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swaggerty</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kogut</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>H-I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Genovese</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Gene expression profiling of the local cecal response of genetic chicken lines that differ in their susceptibility to <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic> colonization</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e11827</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0011827</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20676366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2911375</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swaggerty</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kogut</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Genovese</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Caecal transcriptome analysis of colonized and non-colonized chickens within two genetic lines that differ in caecal colonization by <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>Anim Genet</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>491</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>500</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2052.2010.02168.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21906100</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Close</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaloner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacharme-Lora</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothwell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cytokine responses in birds challenged with the human food-borne pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic> implies a Th17 response</article-title>. <source>R Soc Open Sci.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>150541</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsos.150541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27069644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4821255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Awad</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Re-thinking the chicken-<italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic> interaction: a review</article-title>. <source>Avian Pathol</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>352</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03079457.2018.1475724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29764197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Connerton</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lafontaine</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'kane</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghaffar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of the timing of exposure to <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic> on the gut microbiome and inflammatory responses of broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Microbiome.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>88</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40168-018-0477-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29753324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5948730</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hodgkiss</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Peristalsis and antiperistalsis in the chicken caecum are myogenic</article-title>. <source>Q J Exp Physiol.</source> (<year>1984</year>) <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/expphysiol.1984.sp002777</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6718680</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heidari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fitzgerald</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Immune responses in cecal tonsils of Marek's disease virus-infected chickens</article-title>. <source>Avian Dis.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>213</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1637/10950-093014-Reg.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26473671</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fasina</surname><given-names>YO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of intestinal immune response to <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens i</italic>nfection in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>188</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>98</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pey390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30239962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6347130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trout</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Avian gut-associated lymphoid tissues and intestinal immune responses to <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> parasites</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev.</source> (<year>1996</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>349</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.9.3.349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8809465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC172898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naqi</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Distribution of immunoglobulin-bearing cells in the gut-associated lymphoid tissues of the turkey: effect of oral treatment with intestinal microflora</article-title>. <source>Am J Vet Res.</source> (<year>1984</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>2193</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6388437</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shanmugasundaram</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selvaraj</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Regulatory T cell properties of chicken CD4+CD25+ cells</article-title>. <source>J Immunol.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>186</volume>:<fpage>1997</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2002</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1002040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21242520</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Moral</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fonfr&#237;a</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jim&#233;nez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zapata</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Appearance and development of lymphoid cells in the chicken (<italic toggle="yes">Gallus gallus</italic>) caecal tonsil</article-title>. <source>Anatom Rec.</source> (<year>1998</year>) <volume>250</volume>:<fpage>182</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0185(199802)250:2&amp;#x0003c;182::AID-AR8&amp;#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9489779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pielsticker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rychlik</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Velge</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of the gut microbiota composition on <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic> colonization in chickens</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>85</volume>:<fpage>e00380</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.00380-17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28808158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5649013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taha-Abdelaziz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alkie</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hodgins</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yitbarek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shojadoost</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharif</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Gene expression profiling of chicken cecal tonsils and ileum following oral exposure to soluble and PLGA-encapsulated CpG ODN, and lysate of <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>Vet Microbiol</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>212</volume>:<fpage>67</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2017.11.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29173590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taha-Abdelaziz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Astill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shojadoost</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borrelli</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Campylobacter-derived ligands induce cytokine and chemokine expression in chicken macrophages and cecal tonsil mononuclear cells</article-title>. <source>Vet Microbiol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>246</volume>:<fpage>108732</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2020.108732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32605752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akiba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>Y-W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Interaction of CmeABC and CmeDEF in conferring antimicrobial resistance and maintaining cell viability in <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic></article-title>. <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dki419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16303882</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>W&#246;sten</surname><given-names>MMSM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boeve</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koot</surname><given-names>MGA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Nuenen</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Der Zeijst</surname><given-names>BAM</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Identification of <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic> promoter sequences</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol.</source><volume>180</volume>, <fpage>594</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>599</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.180.3.594-599.1998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9457862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC106926</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Line</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Development of a selective differential agar for isolation and enumeration of Campylobacter spp</article-title>. <source>J Food Protect.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>1711</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4315/0362-028X-64.11.1711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11726148</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sprouffske</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Growthcurver: an R package for obtaining interpretable metrics from microbial growth curves</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinform.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>172</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-016-1016-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27094401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4837600</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolton</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A selective medium for isolating <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni/coli</italic></article-title>. <source>J Clin Pathol</source>. (<year>1982</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>462</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jcp.35.4.462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7042765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC497682</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abeyta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Isolation of <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> species from food and water</article-title>. In: <source>Bacteriological Analytical Manual</source>, <edition>8th ed</edition>. <publisher-name>AOAC International</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Gaithersburg, Md</publisher-loc>. (<year>1998</year>). <fpage>p. 7.01</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7.24</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Line</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berrang</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Addition of sulfamethoxazole to selective media aids in the recovery of <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic> spp. from broiler rinses</article-title>. <source>J Rapid Methods Automat Microbiol.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1745-4581.2008.00111.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jett</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatter</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huycke</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilmore</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Simplified agar plate method for quantifying viable bacteria</article-title>. <source>Biotechniques.</source> (<year>1997</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>648</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2144/97234bm22</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9343684</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schlesinger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drenkow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaleski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>STAR: ultrafast universal RNA-seq aligner</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23104886</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3530905</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Love</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>550</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-014-0550-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4302049</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leek</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>svaseq: removing batch effects and other unwanted noise from sequencing data</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>e161</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25294822</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4245966</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang Da</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lempicki</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Systematic and integrative analysis of large gene lists using DAVID bioinformatics resources</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>57</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2008.211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19131956</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The biological cost of antibiotic resistance</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Microbiol.</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>489</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1369-5274(99)00005-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10508723</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bjorkholm</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sjolund</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falk</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Engstrand</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mutation frequency and biological cost of antibiotic resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Helicobacter pylori</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>. (<year>2001</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>14607</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.241517298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11717398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC64729</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luangtongkum</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seng</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Impaired fitness and transmission of macrolide-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic> in its natural host</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>1300</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.05516-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22183170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3294946</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanimura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of the effects of infectious bronchitis and infectious laryngotracheitis on the chicken respiratory tract</article-title>. <source>J Compar Pathol.</source> (<year>1996</year>) <volume>114</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0021-9975(96)80058-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8729076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitarai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshioka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koizumi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shibahara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Serum levels of interleukin-6, alpha1-acid glycoprotein, and corticosterone in two-week-old chickens inoculated with <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> lipopolysaccharide</article-title>. <source>Poultry Sci.</source> (<year>1998</year>) <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>908</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ps/77.6.908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9628544</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyake</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akiba</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in plasma alpha 1-acid glycoprotein concentration and selected immune response in broiler chickens injected with <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> lipopolysaccharide</article-title>. <source>Br. Poultry Sci.</source> (<year>1998</year>) <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>152</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00071669889547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9568314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klasing</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The kinetics of hemopexin and &#945;1-acid glycoprotein levels induced by injection of inflammatory agents in chickens</article-title>. <source>Avian Dis.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>289</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1592967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11417807</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gast</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of the effects of infection with <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> Enteritidis, in combination with an induced molt, on serum levels of the acute phase protein, alpha1 acid glycoprotein, in hens</article-title>. <source>Poultry Sci.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>81</volume>:<fpage>1295</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>300</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ps/81.9.1295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12269607</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sylte</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suarez</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Vaccination and acute phase mediator production in chickens challenged with low pathogenic avian influenza virus; novel markers for vaccine efficacy?</article-title><source>Vaccine.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>3097</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>105</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2012.02.055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22394994</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lecchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scarafoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bronzo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martino</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavallini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sartorelli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Alpha(1)-acid glycoprotein modulates phagocytosis and killing of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> by bovine polymorphonuclear leucocytes and monocytes</article-title>. <source>Vet J.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>196</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tvjl.2012.07.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22909957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Orosomucoid, an acute response protein with multiple modulating activities</article-title>. <source>J Physiol Biochem.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>71</volume>:<fpage>329</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13105-015-0389-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25711902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lecchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grilli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giudice</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ceciliani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Widespread extrahepatic expression of acute-phase proteins in healthy chicken (<italic toggle="yes">Gallus gallus</italic>) tissues</article-title>. <source>Vet Immunol Immunopathol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>190</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetimm.2017.06.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28778317</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>cDNA cloning and sequence of MAL, a hydrophobic protein associated with human T-cell differentiation</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA.</source> (<year>1987</year>) <volume>84</volume>:<fpage>1997</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2001</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.84.7.1997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3494249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC304570</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kogut</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swaggerty</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Byrd</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selvaraj</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arsenault</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chicken-specific kinome array reveals that <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enterica</italic> Serovar Enteritidis modulates host immune signaling pathways in the cecum to establish a persistence infection</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1207</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms17081207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27472318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5000605</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kogut</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arsenault</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Immunometabolic phenotype alterations associated with the induction of disease tolerance and persistent asymptomatic infection of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> in the chicken intestine</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>372</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2017.00372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28421074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5378774</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shanmugasundaram</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kogut</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arsenault</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swaggerty</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddish</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> infection on cecal tonsil regulatory T cell properties in chickens</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>1828</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pev161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26049799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barrow</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Model of persistent salmonella infection: <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar pullorum modulates the immune response of the chicken from a Th17-type response towards a Th2-type response</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>e00307</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.00307-18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29760212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6056865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunislawska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slawinska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bednarczyk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siwek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Transcriptome modulation by <italic toggle="yes">in ovo</italic> delivered <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus synbiotics</italic> in a range of chicken tissues</article-title>. <source>Gene.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>698</volume>:<fpage>27</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2019.02.068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30831211</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reimand</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isserlin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Voisin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kucera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tannus-Lopes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rostamianfar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pathway enrichment analysis of &#8220;omics&#8221; data</article-title>. <source>bioRxiv.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <fpage>232835</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/232835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6607905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30664679</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Margraf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zarbock</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Platelets in inflammation and resolution</article-title>. <source>J Immunol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>203</volume>:<fpage>2357</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1900899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31636134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elmore</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Apoptosis: a review of programmed cell death</article-title>. <source>Toxicol. Pathol.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>495</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>516</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01926230701320337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17562483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2117903</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyu</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Oxidative stress, apoptosis and abnormal expression of apoptotic protein and gene and cell cycle arrest in the cecal tonsil of broilers induces by dietary methionine deficiency</article-title>. <source>Res Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>121</volume>:<fpage>65</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>75</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rvsc.2018.10.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30359813</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alazzam</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonnassie-Rouxin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dufour</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ermel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>MCLMAN, a new minimal medium for <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic> NCTC 11168</article-title>. <source>Res Microbiol.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>162</volume>:<fpage>173</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.resmic.2010.09.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21144899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Der Hooft</surname><given-names>JJJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alghefari</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Everest</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>KEV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Unexpected differential metabolic responses of <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic> to the abundant presence of glutamate and fucose</article-title>. <source>Metabolomics.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>144</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11306-018-1438-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30830405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6208705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The G Protein-coupled receptor FFAR2 promotes internalization during influenza A virus entry</article-title>. <source>J Virol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <fpage>94</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.01707-19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6955252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31694949</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kotarsky</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Owman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olde</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of a free fatty acid receptor, FFA2R, expressed on leukocytes and activated by short-chain fatty acids</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>303</volume>:<fpage>1047</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-291X(03)00488-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12684041</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>