<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8460904</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8460904.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8460904</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8460904</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34568471</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.689212</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Suitability of Nasal and Deep Nasopharyngeal Swab Sampling of Calves in the <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> Control Program</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pohjanvirta</surname><given-names initials="T">Tarja</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1192398/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>V&#228;h&#228;nikkil&#228;</surname><given-names initials="N">Nella</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Talvitie</surname><given-names initials="V">Vera</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pelkonen</surname><given-names initials="S">Sinikka</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Autio</surname><given-names initials="T">Tiina</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1113496/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Veterinary Bacteriology and Pathology, Finnish Food Authority</institution>, <addr-line>Kuopio</addr-line>, <country>Finland</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Production Animal Medicine, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Helsinki</institution>, <addr-line>Saarentaus</addr-line>, <country>Finland</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Animal Health Ettry</institution>, <addr-line>Sein&#228;joki</addr-line>, <country>Finland</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Inge Santman-Berends, Royal GD, Netherlands</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Annegret Tautenhahn, Freie Universit&#228;t Berlin, Germany; Racem Ben Romdhane, Free University of Berlin, Germany</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Tarja Pohjanvirta <email>tarja.pohjanvirta@foodauthority.fi</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Veterinary Epidemiology and Economics, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>9</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">374996</issue-id><elocation-id>689212</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>8</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>25</day><month>09</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-06 19:25:14.163"><day>06</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2021 Pohjanvirta, V&#228;h&#228;nikkil&#228;, Talvitie, Pelkonen and Autio.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Pohjanvirta, V&#228;h&#228;nikkil&#228;, Talvitie, Pelkonen and Autio</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-08-689212.pdf"/><abstract><p><italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> is an important cattle pathogen affecting animal health, welfare, and productivity. The main disease syndromes are mastitis, pneumonia, and otitis media in young stock, as well as arthritis. Response to antibiotic treatment is poor and no effective vaccine is available. Asymptomatic carriers are common and usually harbor the organism in the airways or mammary glands. Purchase of carrier animals is a major risk for the introduction of infection into naive herds. Following the detection of <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in Finland in 2012, a voluntary control program was established. It aims to prevent the spread of the infection and to help farms attain certification of a low <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> risk. Among the diagnostic tools in the program, nasal swabs (NS) from young calves have been tested for <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> to indicate the infection status of the herd. In this study, we assessed the suitability of this test method. We analyzed the effectiveness of NS and deep nasopharyngeal swabs (NP) to detect <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in pneumonic and healthy calves in dairy herds recently infected with <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic>. In pneumonic calves, NP sampling followed by culture and real-time PCR demonstrated a proportion of positive agreement (PPA) of 0.91 compared with bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL), whereas NS showed only 0.5 PPA compared with BAL. Among healthy dairy calves, overall <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> prevalence in NS was 29.6%. The highest rate of shedding (43%) occurred in calves 31&#8211;60 days old. At the calf level, <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> prevalence in NP samples was 47% compared with 33% in NS samples among the 284 studied calves. However, at the herd level, NS sampling classified 51 out of 54 herds with a positive infection status as infected, whereas in NP sampling, the respective figure was 43 out of 54 herds (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.061). In conclusion, NS sampling from calves under 6 months of age and analyzed by real-time PCR is a cost-efficient method for a control program to detect <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in dairy herds, even if no <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> mastitis has been detected in the herd. For pneumonic calves, we recommend only NP or BAL sampling.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic></kwd><kwd>diagnostics</kwd><kwd>nasal swab</kwd><kwd>deep nasopharyngeal swab</kwd><kwd>control program</kwd><kwd>calves</kwd><kwd>cattle</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="5"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="32"/><page-count count="8"/><word-count count="6317"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> is increasingly recognized as a significant disease-causing agent in various age groups of cattle. The infection presents itself with different signs, such as pneumonia, which mainly occurs in young animals, mastitis, arthritis, otitis media, and rarely keratoconjunctivitis or reproductive tract problems (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> infections tend to be chronic and the response to antibiotic therapy is often poor (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). There is increasing resistance to the antibiotics commonly used to treat pneumonia in calves in Europe (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), and no effective commercial vaccine is available (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> infections have a debilitating effect on animal welfare and can be costly to farmers. There is a critical need to develop preventive measures to reduce the effects of <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> infections in the cattle industry. One such a preventive measure could be a control program aiming to reduce the risk of introducing <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> into naive herds through animal trade. <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> was detected in Finland for the first time at the end of 2012 (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). During 2013, a voluntary control program was established by Animal Health ETT and the cattle industry. The aim of the program is to ensure that dairy and suckler cow herds in the highest level of the program are free of <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic>, and thus prevent the spread of the agent between herds when live animals are purchased. This also relieves the <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> infection pressure and reduces the use of antimicrobials in specialized calf-rearing farms, as their calves originate from dairy farms.</p><p>Several methods need to continuously be applied to ensure that a dairy herd is free of <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic>. The main elements in the Finnish <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> control program are regular herd health visits, clinical monitoring, and sampling of suspected cases, such as calf pneumonia, routine testing of mastitis samples, nasal swab sampling of healthy calves, and the control of animal trade and movement. The main manifestation of <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in cows is mastitis. In Finland, individual clinical and subclinical mastitis milk samples are extensively tested. Almost all milk samples are tested using a multiplex PCR assay. In this test, specific primers to detect <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> have been in use since the beginning of 2012. However, in some dairy herds, <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> can cause pneumonia in calves without causing mastitis in cows, or only in few cows, which may remain undetected (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Consequently, even rigorous mastitis milk sample testing to detect <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> does not guarantee that a herd is free of the agent. Testing for <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> antibodies was not regarded as a useful tool in the control program because of the low sensitivity and specificity of the ELISA tests previously available (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Thus, we could not confidently rely on serological testing of herds to detect subclinical infections.</p><p>Different anatomical sites for the detection of <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in carrier animals have been studied, but no site has been found that could be consistently used. In an earlier study by Bennet and Jasper (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> was significantly more often found in the nasal secretions of healthy young calves in herds with <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> mastitis compared with non-infected herds. Based on this finding, nasal swabs (NS) taken from calves up to 6 months of age and analyzed by real-time PCR for <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> were included in the program. NS are affordable and practical to use in the field, as swabbing of young calves is relatively easy and quick. Another more cumbersome and more expensive technique would be deep nasopharyngeal swabs (NP) to sample pharyngeal lymphoid tissue. It has previously been shown that in young calves, <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> can colonize the tonsils without nasal shedding (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). However, to our knowledge, the suitability of NP to detect <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in pharyngeal lymphoid tissue in healthy dairy calves has not been investigated.</p><p>The objective of this study was to (1) determine the overall apparent prevalence of nasal shedding in calves in dairy herds with recently confirmed <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> infection, (2) study the apparent <italic toggle="yes">M</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">bovis</italic> prevalence in nasal swabs (NS) in different age groups of calves under one year of age, (3) assess the suitability of NS and NP sampling at the herd level to detect carrier calves, and (4) compare different sampling and analytical methods to detect <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in calves with acute respiratory disease.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Calves With Acute Respiratory Disease</title><p>Two veterinarians clinically evaluated 62 non-vaccinated calves aged 3&#8211;22 weeks with acute respiratory disease signs in two calf-rearing farms with endemic <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic>. The veterinarians took NS, NP, and bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) samples from each calf. These calves had not been medicated with antibiotics during the month before sampling.</p></sec><sec><title>Calves in Dairy Farms Recently Infected With <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic></title><p>Clinically healthy calves aged from 3 to 348 days in 30 <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic>&#8211;infected dairy herds were included in the study. Herds 1 to 19 and their <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> infection status were described in V&#228;h&#228;nikkil&#228; et al. (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). These herds were sampled by a veterinarian four times at approximately 6-month intervals. Two more dairy herds (herds 20 and 21) were sampled twice with a 6-month interval, and nine herds (herds 22&#8211;30) were sampled once. During each visit, the veterinarian took NS from a maximum of 20 (range 6&#8211;23, depending on the herd size) of the youngest calves on the farm. In addition, NP samples were also collected from five calves per herd and per visit. The number of cows in the study herds varied from 18 to 315, the mean being 91 cows, and 9/30 herds had 100 or more cows (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). We included in this analysis the results from the first visit to each farm, and thereafter the results from the visits where at least one positive NS or NP was found in the herd, meaning that the infection status of the herd was then positive.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Agreement between bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) and nasal swab (NS) or deep nasopharyngeal swab (NP) in detecting <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in 62 calves with acute respiratory disease.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sample</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Detection method</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>Number of calves with each combination</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Proportion of positive</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Kappa (95% CI)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> (kappa)</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>of results (BAL/compared method)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>agreement</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>+/+</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>+/&#8211;</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#8211;/+</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#8211;/&#8211;</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Culture</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 (0.34, 0.72)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Real-time PCR</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 (0.31, 0.69)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NP</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Culture</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.7, 0.97)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>As soon as possible after <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> diagnosis, farmers were given advice to apply measures aiming to prevent the spread of infection, described in detail in Haapala et al. (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Briefly, the farmers were advised to separate newborn calves from the dam immediately after birth into a clean pen in a space separate from older animals. Unpasteurized colostrum was fed to all calves, followed by milk replacer or raw milk from healthy cows. None of the farms bought colostrum from another farm.</p></sec><sec><title>Sampling Techniques</title><p>Nasal swabs (Transystems, Copan, Brescia, Italy) were taken prior to NP and BAL. The nostrils were cleaned with a paper towel and the swab was inserted into a nostril to a depth of ~13 cm. Two nasal swabs, one for PCR and one for mycoplasma culture, were simultaneously collected from calves with acute respiratory disease and one NS was taken from healthy calves in dairy herds. NP swabs were taken with 27-cm-long guarded swabs (Medical Wire Equipment Ltd, Corsham, England). The sheathed swab was inserted into the ventral nasal cavity approximately 1 cm rostral to the medial canthus of the eye, and the swab was advanced a few centimeters to the nasopharynx area and rotated. The swab was withdrawn into the sheath before removal. BAL samples were collected using a self-made double-guarded plastic catheter inserted through the nose into the trachea. Then, the inner catheter was pushed out and advanced until it wedged in a bronchus. Thirty to forty milliliters of sterile 0.9% saline was injected and immediately aspirated back into the syringe (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). The swabs intended for mycoplasma culture were soaked in D broth (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) and 0.5 ml of the BAL sample was transferred into D broth. The samples were transported to the laboratory within 24 h in styrofoam boxes with a freezer pack.</p></sec><sec><title>M. bovis Culture</title><p>A 10-fold dilution from D broth to F broth (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) was made, and tightly closed tubes were incubated at 37 &#176;C for 3&#8211;5 days to enrich <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic>, followed by identification of <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> using real-time PCR (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> Real-Time PCR</title><p>DNA was extracted from nasal swabs according to Sachse et al. (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Real-time PCR was performed as described (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). The cut-off value for <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic>&#8211;positive real-time PCR results was set to C<sub>t</sub> 37.0.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>We evaluated the agreement among sampling and detection methods by calculating the proportion of positive agreement (PPA), the kappa coefficient, and the corresponding <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value for kappa using Epitools Epidemiological Calculators (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). The kappa coefficient was interpreted according to McHugh (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>): 0&#8211;0.20 no agreement, 0.21&#8211;0.39 minimal, 0.40&#8211;0.59 weak, 0.60&#8211;0.79 moderate, 0.80&#8211;0.90 strong, and above 0.90 almost perfect agreement. To determine whether NS and NP sampling differed significantly in the ability to assess a herd visit as positive, McNemar's &#967;<sup>2</sup> test was conducted (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Significance was set at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Detection of <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in Calves With Acute Respiratory Disease</title><p><italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> was detected in 29/62 (47%), 24/62 (38.7%), 15/62 (24.2%), and 14/62 (22.6%) of BAL, NP, NS (culture), and NS (real-time PCR) samples, respectively. The proportion of positive agreement of NP compared with BAL was 0.91 and the kappa coefficient was 0.84 (strong), whereas the proportion of positive agreement of NS (real-time PCR) compared with BAL (culture) was 0.65 and the kappa coefficient was 0.50 (weak) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Nasal swabs analyzed by culture only yielded one more positive sample compared with PCR from swabs (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). NS (real-time PCR) proportion of positive agreement compared with NP culture was 0.68 and kappa coefficient was 0.53 (weak) (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Agreement between deep nasopharyngeal swab (NP) culture and nasal swab (NS) PCR in detecting <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in dairy herd calves (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 284) and calves with respiratory disease (BRD, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 62).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sample</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Detection method</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>Number of calves with each combination</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Proportion of positive</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Kappa (95% CI)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> (kappa)</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>of results (NP culture/NS real-time PCR)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>agreement</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>+/+</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>+/&#8211;</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#8211;/+</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#8211;/&#8211;</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS (dairy)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Real-time PCR</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 (0.38, 0.58)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS (BRD)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Real-time PCR</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56 (0.35, 0.77)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Calves in Dairy Herds Recently Infected With <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic></title><p>The total number of NS taken from 3- to 348-day-old calves was 1,037. The overall apparent <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> prevalence in nasal swabs was 29.5%. The highest prevalence of 43% was detected in calves aged 31 to 60 days. Thereafter, shedding decreased and was 13.7% in 150- to 180-day-old calves (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Large variation from zero to 75% was seen between the herds in the apparent prevalence of nasal shedding. Both NS and NP samples were taken from 284 calves. <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> was detected in 93/284 (32.7%) and in 133/284 (46.8%) of NS and NP samples, respectively. Proportion of positive agreement of NS compared with NP samples in these calves was 0.68 and the kappa coefficient was 0.48 (weak) (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Number of nasal swabs (NS) sampled from 30 dairy herds and number (%) of <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> PCR-positive swabs per age group (<italic toggle="yes">d</italic> = age in days).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Age (<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Number sampled</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Number (%) of PCR-positive NS</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0&#8211;30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">259</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (25.9)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31&#8211;60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">260</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112 (43.1)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61&#8211;90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (31.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91&#8211;120</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (22.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121&#8211;150</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (21.0)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151&#8211;180</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (13.7)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">181&#8211;348</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (21.7)</td></tr><tr style="border-top: thin solid #000000;"><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,037</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">306 (29.5)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Effectiveness of NS and NP Samples in Indicating the Infection Status of Dairy Herds</title><p>Altogether, there were 54 herd visits with a positive infection status in which at least one positive NS or NP was found in the herd (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Tables 4</xref>, <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). All samples from two herds were already negative at the first visit, and during one visit, only NS samples were taken from herd D (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Out of the 54 herd visits with a positive infection status, 51/54 (94.4%) would have been classified as infection status positive if only NS had been analyzed, and 43/54 (79.6%) as infection status positive if only NP samples had been analyzed (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Tables 4</xref>, <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). This difference was not statistically significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.061).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> detected in nasal (NS) and deep nasopharyngeal (NP) swabs in 30 dairy farms during the first visit after the index case.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Herd ID</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Number of cows</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Index case<xref rid="TN1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref></bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Days from index case to first sampling</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>No. positive/total</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>NS</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>DNP</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">183</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">268</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17/50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ND</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">315</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/5</td></tr><tr style="border-top: thin solid #000000;"><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180/529 (34%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79/145 (54.5%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><label>*</label><p><italic toggle="yes">M, mastitis; CP, calf pneumonia; NS, nasal swabs taken to join the M. bovis control program; ND, not done</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in nasal (NS) and deep nasopharyngeal (DNP) swabs during visits 2&#8211;4 to farms with a positive infection status.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>Visit 2</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>Visit 3</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>Visit 4</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>No. positive/total</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>No. positive/total</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>No. positive/total</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Herd ID</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>NS</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>DNP</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>NS</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>DNP</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>NS</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>DNP</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14/25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10/21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="TN2" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="TN2" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="TN2" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="TN2" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="TN2" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="TN2" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="TN2" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="TN2" ref-type="table-fn">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66/223</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26/61</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34/172</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21/50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26/113</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/29</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">&#8211; Infection status of the farm negative, all NS and NP negative</italic>.</p><fn id="TN2"><label>*</label><p><italic toggle="yes">No visit</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>We assessed the suitability of nasal swab (NS) and deep nasopharyngeal swab (NP) sampling of young calves for use in the <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> control program. We observed an apparent overall <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> prevalence of 29.5% in NS sampling, with the highest prevalence of 43% in 31- to 60-day-old calves. At an individual level, NP sampling was the most sensitive sampling method for detecting <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in healthy calves under 6 months of age. However, at the herd level, NS sampling was slightly more efficient than NP sampling in healthy young stock. Real-time PCR from NS correctly classified 51/54 herd visits with a positive infection status as positive, in contrast to NP sampling, which classified only 43/54 visits correctly. However, the difference only approached statistical significance (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.061). The reason for this difference is related to the sampling protocol, as we took NS from the 20 youngest calves in the herd during the visits and only five NP samples. Guarded NP swabs are expensive compared with simple bacteriological swabs used in nasal swabbing, and an assistant is needed to restrain the calf's head when a NP sample is taken. By taking several NS samples from young calves, the sensitivity of the sampling method increases, which allows its use as a cost-efficient method in the <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> control program.</p><p>There have only been a few reports on the prevalence of nasal shedding of <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in dairy calves. Bennet and Jasper (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) observed that approximately 34% of calves in herds with <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> mastitis shed <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in nasal secretions compared with 6% of calves in non-mastitis herds. In our study, the overall prevalence of nasal shedding in dairy herd calves during the first visit after a confirmed <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> index case was the same as in the study of Bennet and Jasper (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), namely, 34%. Interestingly Bennet and Jasper (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) found that in <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic>&#8211;infected herds, the highest prevalence of nasal shedding occurred in calves at around 5 weeks of age, and in general in various age groups, nasal shedding was highest at between 1 and 4 months of age. In our study, the highest prevalence of 43% was detected in calves aged 4 to 8 weeks, and thereafter the prevalence declined, being only slight under 14% in 22- to 26-week-old calves. However, in our study, only a small fraction of nasal swabs was taken from calves older than 5 months. Therefore, some caution is necessary regarding the prevalence in older calves. Other studies have reported a substantially lower nasal prevalence. In Denmark, Feenstra et al. (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) determined that 18% of nasal swabs from 0 to 6-month-old calves in herds with <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> mastitis were positive compared to 11% from non-mastitis herds. Recently, in Australia, Hazelton et al. (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) followed 450 heifer calves in eight herds, seven of which were <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> mastitis herds, and found that at weaning, only 2.4% of the calves were shedding <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> into nasal secretions.</p><p>Several factors might affect the observed nasal shedding prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic>. One is the detection method. All previous studies (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) have used a plate culture method, whereas we used real-time PCR. Our <italic toggle="yes">oppD</italic> real-time PCR and culture method both displayed an analytical sensitivity of 10<sup>2</sup> cfu/ml <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in BAL fluid (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). In this study, we also compared real-time PCR and culture results from nasal swabs taken simultaneously from pneumonic calves. The culture method detected only one more positive sample compared with real-time PCR. However, PCR analysis is available in many laboratories, whereas mycoplasma culture is demanding and only available in specialized laboratories, thus making PCR a more useful method in a control program. Another factor that affects the <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> prevalence in calves is the housing conditions. If newborn calves are isolated from older, presumably infected animals in another building or outside hutches, and cows with <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> mastitis are culled, it is likely that the calves will display no nasal shedding of <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>).</p><p>Previously, Maunsell et al. (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) have demonstrated that after oral inoculation of <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic>, both palatine and pharyngeal tonsils were the main site of <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> colonization. However, despite heavy colonization of the tonsils, only two out of eight calves in the experiment were found to shed <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> into nasal secretions. Thus, the tonsils, rather than the epithelium of the nasal passages, may be the main upper respiratory tract colonization site, and tonsil swabs may be the best sampling method to detect <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> colonization. Data supporting this were also reported following a study by Haapala et al. (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>), in which the tonsils of 4 out 20 clinically healthy bovines were colonized. NP swabbing samples the respiratory and associated lymphoid epithelium of the nasopharynx. We therefore compared <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> detection from NS and NP taken from 284 calves under 6 months of age in our study herds. At the individual level, NP sampling detected more positive calves (133/284) than NS (93/284). This suggests that tonsillar (in this case pharyngeal tonsillar area) swabs are indeed more sensitive than nasal swabs in detecting <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> colonization. This finding was recently confirmed by Buckle et al. (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) in New Zealand. They analyzed palatine tonsillar swabs taken at slaughter from healthy 3- to 5-month-old calves from a <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> seropositive herd. Real-time PCR detected <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in almost 93% of the tonsillar swabs, whereas only 12% of tracheal swabs were positive. In the studies of both Maunsell et al. (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) and Buckle et al. (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), tonsillar swabs were taken <italic toggle="yes">post mortem</italic>. Swabs from the tonsil crypts are difficult to take from live animals, and the most comparable technique is NP sampling.</p><p>A high tonsil colonization rate of calves can be expected in herds in which <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> mastitis milk or contaminated colostrum is fed to calves (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Studies on the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in colostrum are scarce and the topic has not been investigated in Finland. Gille et al. (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) examined colostrum samples from 17 herds recently infected with <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> using PCR detection. In only four herds out of 17, <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> DNA was detected in 1.9% of colostrum samples. In some samples, borderline C<sub>t</sub> values were recorded, and it is unclear whether these colostrum samples contained enough bacteria to infect the calf. Timonen et al. (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) estimated the <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> prevalence in colostrum to be 1.7&#8211;4.7% in four very large Estonian dairy herds in which <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> mastitis cows were not always culled. In Finland, colostrum is given to calves unpasteurized. It is possible that some of the calves in our study herds became colonized through colostrum. Approximately 170,000 individual clinical and subclinical mastitis quarter milk samples are tested annually in Finland (there are approximately 260,000 dairy cows in the country). Cows with <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> mastitis are segregated from the milk herd and are usually rapidly culled or slaughtered (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). The feeding of mastitis milk to calves in our study herds was highly unlikely, as the farmers were strictly advised not to give any mastitis milk to calves. Thus, pharyngeal colonization observed in our study is more likely to be characteristic of <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> infection in young calves rather than a result of feeding contaminated milk to calves.</p><p>The classification of a herd as <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> positive or negative is difficult and requires different sampling strategies and tools for different animal groups. The average herd size of dairy herds in Finland is 50 cows (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). As nicely demonstrated in the study by Humphry et al. (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>), an imperfect test applied to a small herd is problematic. Testing of clinical mastitis and respiratory disease cases in calves is an essential part of the control program. Testing of <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> antibodies has demonstrated that the infection spreads rapidly in the herd and high antibody levels persist in cows for a long time (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Thus, testing of antibodies is not suitable to detect active infection. Moreover, previous studies have demonstrated that during an initial outbreak of <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> mastitis, colonization and shedding are not consistently associated with a particular anatomical site and shedding rapidly decreases in cows (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Thus, NS sampling of cows is not efficient for a control program. However, in calves, <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> is more prevalent in the upper respiratory tract, and NS sampling should be targeted at calves. The number of swabs taken from a control program herd during each sampling should be based on the average number of calves available for sampling and should aim to keep laboratory analysis costs reasonable. In our program, the herd health veterinarian visits each herd biannually and sampling is included in these visits. Biannual sampling allows targeting at calves younger than 6 months old in which <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> prevalence is at its highest.</p><p>We compared different sampling and detection methods in pneumonic calves to determine the most cost-effective method to sample clinical cases in herds in the control program. In pneumonic calves, NP had a strong agreement with BAL sampling in detecting <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic>. Recently, Doyle et al. (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) examined the agreement among four sampling methods in the detection of different bovine respiratory disease pathogens. They compared the agreement of NS and NP with transtracheal wash in pneumonic dairy calves aged 31&#8211;74 days. Plate culture and PCR identification was used to detect <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic>. Their study yielded a very good positive agreement of 91 and 92% and a kappa value of 0.82 and 0.83, respectively, when NS and NP were compared with transtracheal wash results. The authors concluded that regarding <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> diagnostics, both NS and guarded NP can be efficiently used in pneumonic calves. Our findings are consistent with theirs when considering NP: we obtained a proportion of positive agreement of 0.91 and a kappa coefficient of 0.84 when we compared NP with BAL in pneumonic calves. Van Driessche et al. (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>) investigated the agreement of NP with BAL sampling in young veal and beef calves, and the kappa coefficient was 0.58 when direct culture of the samples was used. However, in NP they used a similar unguarded swab to that which we used in our NS. We obtained quite a similar kappa coefficient of 0.53 when NS culture results were compared with BAL results in pneumonic calves. Previously, Thomas et al. (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) compared NS with BAL in calves under 1 year of age and found that NS had a sensitivity of only 21%. Thus, NS was not predictive of <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in the lower respiratory tract. Our results agree with those of van Driessche et al. (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>) and Thomas et al. (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), suggesting that NS is not a sensitive sampling method to detect <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in calves suffering from respiratory disease.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Guarded NP at the group level is a sensitive and practical method to detect <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in pneumonic calves. NS taken from young calves and analyzed by real-time PCR is a cost-efficient method to detect <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> in dairy herds, even if no <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> mastitis has been detected in the herd. We recommend that only calves under 6 months of age are sampled because in older calves, the prevalence of nasal shedding substantially decreases, although further study is needed to confirm this. Small herds in the control program are problematic because a reliable number of samples cannot be obtained. The suitability of new antibody ELISA tests in the Finnish control program should be evaluated. In the future, the effect of NS pooling on the sensitivity of PCR needs to be studied, as this would cost-efficiently allow a larger number of NS to be taken per herd. Finally, NP swabs appear to detect calves carrying <italic toggle="yes">M. bovis</italic> with a higher sensitivity than NS. Further studies are needed to verify this and determine the optimal use of these methods in the control program.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/supplementary material, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author/s.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>Ethical review and approval was not required for the animal study because in this study normal sampling methods used routinely in bovine respiratory disease sampling was used and no ethical approval was thus required. Written informed consent was obtained from the owners for the participation of their animals in this study.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>TP participated in the experimental design and method validation, analyzed the data, and wrote the article. NV was responsible for laboratory analyses and data management. VT conducted most of the sampling of recently infected dairy herds. SP was responsible for acquiring funding and project supervision and participated in experimental design. TA participated in the experimental design, method validation, data analysis, and project supervision. All authors contributed to revising the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="s9"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was funded by grant number 1876/312/2013 from the Ministry of Agriculture and Forestry of Finland.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s10"><title>Publisher's Note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors would like to sincerely thank the farmers who contributed to the study. Aino Wainio DVM and Milla Hiekkaranta DVM are acknowledged for skillful sampling of the BRD calves. We are grateful to laboratory technicians in the Kuopio Laboratory of Veterinary Bacteriology and Pathology for excellent technical assistance.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dudek</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholas</surname><given-names>RAJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szacawa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bednarek</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> infections occurrence, diagnosis and control</article-title>. <source>Pathogens.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>640</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/pathogens9080640</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32781697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7459460</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maunsell</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woolums</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Francoz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenbusch</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Step</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> infections in cattle</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>772</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>83</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-1676.2011.0750.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21745245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayling</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosales</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barden</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gosney</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in antimicrobial susceptibility of <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> isolates from Great Britain</article-title>. <source>Vet Rec.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>175</volume>:<fpage>486</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/vr.102303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25185107</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heuvelink</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reugebrink</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mars</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial susceptibility of <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> isolates from veal calves and dairy cattle in the Netherlands</article-title>. <source>Vet Microbiol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>189</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2016.04.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27259820</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gautier-Bouchardon</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferr&#233;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Grand</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paoli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gay</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poumarat</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Overall decrease in the susceptibility of <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> to antimicrobials over the past 30 years in France</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e87672</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24503775</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3913625</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perez-Casal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prysliak</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maina</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suleman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jimbo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Status of the development of a vaccine against <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic></article-title>. <source>Vaccine</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>2902</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2017.03.095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28433326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>V&#228;h&#228;nikkil&#228;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pohjanvirta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haapala</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simojoki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soveri</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of the course of <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> infection in naturally infected dairy herds</article-title>. <source>Vet Microbiol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>231</volume>:<fpage>107</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2019.03.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30955796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wawegama</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Markham</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kanci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schibrowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oswin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of an IgG enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay as a serological assay for detection of <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> infection in feedlot cattle</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>1269</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>75</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.02492-15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26912757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4844740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jasper</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nasal prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> and IHA titers in young dairy animals</article-title>. <source>Cornell Vet.</source> (<year>1977</year>) <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>361</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">872593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maunsell</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Powe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woolard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Love</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Oral inoculation of young dairy calves with <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> results in colonization of tonsils, development of otitis media and local immunity</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e44523</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0044523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22970240</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3435275</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haapala</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>V&#228;h&#228;nikkil&#228;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kulkas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuunainen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pohjanvirta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Autio</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> infection in dairy herds&#8212;risk factors and effect of control measures</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2020-18814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33309344</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Autio</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pohjanvirta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holopainen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rikula</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pentik&#228;inen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huovilainen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Etiology of respiratory disease in non-vaccinated, non-medicated calves in rearing herds</article-title>. <source>Vet Microbiol.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>119</volume>:<fpage>256</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>265</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.200610.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17084565</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7130506</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friis</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Isolation of mycoplasmas from Danish cattle</article-title>. <source>Nord Vet Med.</source> (<year>1983</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>74</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6348700</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>B&#246;lske</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Survey of mycoplasma infections in cell cultures and a comparison of detection methods</article-title>. <source>Zentralbl Bakteriol Mikrobiol Hyg.</source> (<year>1988</year>) <volume>269</volume>:<fpage>331</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0176-6724(88)80176-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3146169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sachse</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salam</surname><given-names>HSH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hotzel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Use of a novel real-time PCR technique to monitor and quantitate <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> infection in cattle herds with mastitis and respiratory disease</article-title>. <source>Vet J.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>186</volume>:<fpage>299</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>303</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.016/j.tvjl.2009.10.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19926318</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sergeant</surname><given-names>ESG</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Epitools Epidemiological Calculators, Ausvet</source>. (<year>2018</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://epitools.ausvet.com.au" ext-link-type="uri">http://epitools.ausvet.com.au</ext-link> (accessed July 5, 2021).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McHugh</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Interrater reliability: the kappa statistic</article-title>. <source>Biochem Med.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>276</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3900052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23092060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feenstra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bisgaard Madsen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friis</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meyling</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahrens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A field study of <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> infection in cattle</article-title>. <source>Zentralbl Veterinarmed B.</source> (<year>1991</year>) <volume>(3)</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>202</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1439-0450.1991.tb00861.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1858457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hazelton</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosward</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheehy</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dwyer</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> and other Mollicutes in replacement dairy heifers from <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic>-infected and uninfected herds: a 2-year longitudinal study</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>103</volume>:<fpage>11844</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2020</pub-id>&#8211;18921<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32981720</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wisselink</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smid</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plater</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ridley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asp&#225;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A European interlaboratory trial to evaluate the performance of different PCR methods for Mycoplasma bovis diagnosis</article-title>. <source>BMC Vet Res.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>86</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12917-019-1819-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30866933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6417145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haapala</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pohjanvirta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Syrj&#228;l&#228;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soveri</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simojoki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Detection of <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> carrier animals using tonsil samples&#8212;preliminary results. In: Chalker V, Spiller B, editors</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the European Mycoplasma Conference London</source>. London, UK (<year>2019</year>). p. <fpage>70</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buckle</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castillo-Alcala</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Begg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bingham</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>First report of the use of mucosal swabs of the palatine tonsillar crypt for detection of <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> in naturally infected calves</article-title>. <source>N Z Vet J.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>309</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00480169.2020.1765892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32422083</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gille</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evrard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Supr&#233;</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gr&#233;goire</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The presence of <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> in colostrum</article-title>. <source>Vet Res.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13567-020-00778-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32299498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7164199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Timonen</surname><given-names>AAE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Autio</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pohjanvirta</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#228;kkinen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katholm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Within-herd prevalence of intramammary infection caused by <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> and associations between cow udder health, milk yield, and composition</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>6554</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2016-12267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28601455</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>International Committee for Animal Recording (ICAR)</collab></person-group>. <source>The Global Standard for Livestock Data, Statistics</source>. (<year>2021</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://my.icar.org/stats/list" ext-link-type="uri">https://my.icar.org/stats/list</ext-link> (accessed February 15, 2021).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Humphry</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunn</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A practical approach to calculate sample size for herd prevalence surveys</article-title>. <source>Prev Vet Med.</source>(<year>2004</year>) <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>173</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>188</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.prevetmed.2004.07.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15488269</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#248;ller Pedersen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenbaum Nielsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Field experience of antibody testing against <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> in adult cows in commercial Danish dairy cattle herds</article-title>. <source>Pathogens.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>637</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/pathogens9080637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32781506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7460496</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Punyapornwithaya</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gay</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allredge</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Association between an outbreak strain causing <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> mastitis and its asymptomatic carriage in the herd: a case study from Idaho, USA</article-title>. <source>Prev Vet Med.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>93</volume>:<fpage>66</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/prevetmed2009.08.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19880206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hazelton</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheehy</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bosward, KL, Parker AM, Morton JM, Dwyer CJ, et al. Shedding of <italic toggle="yes">Mycoplasma bovis</italic> and antibody responses in cows recently diagnosed with clinical infection</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>101</volume>:<fpage>584</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2017-13512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29055548</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Credille</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lehenbauer</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berghaus</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Champagne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Agreement among 4 sampling methods to identify respiratory pathogens in dairy calves with acute bovine respiratory disease</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>954</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.14683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28295570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5434980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Driessche</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valgaeren</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gille</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ducatelle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haesebrouck</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nasopharyngeal swab versus nonendoscopic bronchoalveolar lavage for isolation of bacterial pathogens from preweaned calves with respiratory disease</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>946</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.14668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28425146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5435039</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dizier</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trolin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mainil</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Isolation of mycoplasma species from the lower respiratory tract of healthy cattle and cattle with respiratory disease in Belgium</article-title>. <source>Vet Rec</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>151</volume>:<fpage>472</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/vr.151.16.472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12418530</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>