<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8200825</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8200825.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8200825</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8200825</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34136557</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.680742</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Dietary <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus coagulans</italic> Supplementation Modulates Intestinal Immunity and Microbiota of Broiler Chickens Challenged by <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names initials="S">Shuangshuang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>&#8224;</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/470447/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>&#8224;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yi</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="T">Tao</given-names></name><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/366731/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names initials="D">Di</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhengfan</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names initials="B">Binying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff><institution>Hubei Key Laboratory of Animal Nutrition and Feed Science, School of Animal Science and Nutrition Engineering, Wuhan Polytechnic University</institution>, <addr-line>Wuhan</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Amlan Kumar Patra, West Bengal University of Animal and Fishery Sciences, India</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Bingkun Zhang, China Agricultural University, China; Shad Mahfuz, Sylhet Agricultural University, Bangladesh</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Binying Ding <email>dbying7471@126.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Animal Nutrition and Metabolism, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>&#8224;These authors have contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>5</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">374996</issue-id><elocation-id>680742</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>4</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>15</day><month>06</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-01-07 21:25:23.617"><day>07</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2021 Guo, Xi, Xia, Wu, Zhao, Zhang and Ding.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Guo, Xi, Xia, Wu, Zhao, Zhang and Ding</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-08-680742.pdf"/><abstract><p>Preventative effects of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus coagulans</italic> against <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic> infection in broilers have been well-demonstrated. The present study was conducted to investigate the modulation of these two probiotics on intestinal immunity and microbiota of <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>-challenged birds. The 336 one-day-old broilers were assigned to four groups with six replicates in each group. Birds in the control were unchallenged and fed a basal diet, and birds in the three challenged groups were dietary supplemented with nothing (Cp group), 1 &#215; 10<sup>9</sup> CFU/kg of <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> (Lf_Cp group), or 1 &#215; 10<sup>10</sup> CFU/kg of <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> (Bc_Cp group). Challenge was performed from days 14 to 20, and samples were collected on days 21 and 28. Challenge upregulated interleukin (IL)-1&#946; and transforming growth factor (TGF)-&#946;4 mRNA expression in jejunum on day 21, which was downregulated by <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic>, respectively (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Both probiotic groups upregulated jejunal IL-1&#946;, interferon (IFN)-&#947;, IL-17, and TGF-&#946;4 on day 28 as well as IFN-&#947; on day 21 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The Bc_Cp group increased CD3<sup>+</sup> T cell counts in the jejunal crypt on day 21 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Challenge decreased the ileal ACE index on day 21 and cecal microbial richness on day 28, which were increased by probiotic treatments, and ileal bacterial richness decreased in the Bc_Cp group on day 28 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Only ileal microbiota on day 21 was distinctly affected with an R-value at 0.3116 by ANOSIM analysis (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Compared with the control, ileal <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> increased on day 21, and ileal <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> and cecal <italic toggle="yes">Proteobacteria</italic> decreased on day 28 in challenged groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Challenge increased <italic toggle="yes">Romboutsia</italic> spp. in the ileum as well as unclassified f_<italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Ruminococcus_torques</italic> group in the cecum, and decreased <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> spp. in the ileum on day 21, which were all conversely modulated by <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Challenge increased amino acid metabolism of ileal microbiota and membrane transport of cecal microbiota, and decreased amino acid metabolism of cecal microbiota on day 21, which were conversely regulated by both probiotics (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). In conclusion, <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> attenuated the intestinal inflammation and microbial dysbiosis soon after <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> challenge.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic></kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Bacillus coagulans</italic></kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic></kwd><kwd>immunity</kwd><kwd>gut microbiota</kwd><kwd>broiler chicken</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="4"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="49"/><page-count count="13"/><word-count count="8733"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Necrotic enteritis (NE) is one of the most important enteric diseases in poultry and causes huge economic losses to the industry worldwide (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Clinical NE is characterized by diarrhea, intestinal necrotic lesions, severe morbidity and mortality, and lower growth rate and feed efficiency, while the subclinical form presents as poor growth performance without mortality (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic>, the etiological agent of NE, is a spore-forming Gram-positive bacterium and commonly exists in environments such as soil, sewage, litter, feces of chickens, and the intestines of humans and animals (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> population is normally &lt; 10<sup>2</sup> to 10<sup>4</sup> colony-forming units (CFU) per gram of intestinal contents in the small intestine of healthy chickens compared to 10<sup>7</sup> to 10<sup>9</sup> CFU/g in NE birds (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p><p>Traditional NE mitigation strategies included antibiotic growth promoters and ionophores. With the increasing pressure to reduce antibiotic use in poultry production, the incidence of NE has been increasing in recent years (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) and alternative nutritional strategies are in urgent need. Probiotics, such as lactic acid bacteria, <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus, Bifidobacteria</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic>, are potentially alternative strategies to prevent or mitigate NE in birds (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Probiotics exhibit protective effects by producing antimicrobial compounds, competitive excluding, enhancing the intestinal barrier, and stimulating host immunity (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). It has been reported that daily oral administration of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic> 1.2029 reduced the severity of NE lesions and ameliorated inflammation by upregulating interleukin (IL)-10 mRNA expression and downregulating interferon (IFN)-&#947; and toll-like receptor (TLR) 2 expression in the ileum of <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>-challenged broiler chickens (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Dietary supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus coagulans</italic> decreased gut lesion scores as well as cecal population and hepatic translocation of <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>, and increased mRNA expression of fowlicidin-2, an antimicrobial peptide, in the jejunum of NE birds (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>).</p><p>In recent years, high-throughput sequencing technologies have been used to analyze the bacterial communities in different intestinal segments of chickens (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Using this technology, Li et al. (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) reported that dietary addition with <italic toggle="yes">L. acidophilus</italic> decreased the Shannon index of ileal microbiota and restored the intestinal microbial community in <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>-challenged broiler chickens by increasing relative abundance of beneficial bacteria such as <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> and decreasing abundance of pathogens such as <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia-Shigella</italic>. The NE birds' diet supplemented with <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> DSM 32315 had an intestinal microbiota with diversity and composition more similar to that of healthy counterparts reflected by the reduction of opportunistic pathogens and protein-fermentative bacteria (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). However, the effects of <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> on the intestinal microbial profiles of NE birds are largely unknown. Therefore, the present study was conducted to investigate the influence of <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> on the intestinal immunity and microbiota of broiler chickens infected with <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Experimental Design and Bird Management</title><p>All animal procedures used in the present study were performed in compliance with Hubei Provincial Regulations for Laboratory Animals (011043145-029-2013-000009), and were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Wuhan Polytechnic University. A total of 336 one-day-old sex-mixed broiler chicks were randomly assigned to four groups, each with six replicates of 14 birds. Birds in the control group were fed a corn-soybean meal basal diet and unchallenged by <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>. Birds infected with <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> were considered as positive control (Cp group). Challenged birds in the Lf_Cp and Bc_Cp groups were fed basal diets supplemented with 1 &#215; 10<sup>9</sup> CFU/kg of <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> and 1 &#215; 10<sup>10</sup> CFU/kg of <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic>, respectively. The <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> (CGMCC No. 1.2029) was obtained from China General Microbiological Culture Collection Center (CGMCC, Beijing, China) and cultured in Mann-Rogosa-Sharpe broth. The overnight culture of <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> was absorbed by nano silicon dioxide and probiotic concentration was 1 &#215; 10<sup>9</sup> CFU/g of powder. The product of <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> (1 &#215; 10<sup>10</sup> CFU/g) was obtained from Hubei Horwath Biotechnology Co. Ltd. (Wuhan, China). Both <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> powder was mixed in the diet at a dose of 0.1%. The basal diet was formulated according to the nutritional requirements of the National Research Council (1994). The composition and nutrient levels of the basal diet are presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>. The trial lasted for 28 days. Birds were raised in wire cages in an environmentally controlled room with 23 h of light and were allowed <italic toggle="yes">ad libitum</italic> access to water and mashed diets throughout the trial.</p></sec><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic> Challenge</title><p>The avian <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> type A field strain (CVCC2030) was obtained from China Veterinary Culture Collection Center (Beijing, China). The NE model was established as Du et al. (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) described with modification. The <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> was cultured in cooked meat medium and incubated anaerobically overnight at 37&#176;C. The organism was counted using tryptose-sulfite-cycloserine agar plates. From days 14 to 20, challenged birds were orally gavaged with 1 mL of actively growing culture of <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> (1 &#215; 10<sup>8</sup> CFU/mL) once per day. Birds in the control group were gavaged with equal volumes of sterile meat medium.</p></sec><sec><title>Sample Collection</title><p>On days 21 and 28, two birds per replicate (12 birds per group) were randomly selected and euthanized by cervical dislocation. Jejunal mucosa was scraped from about 10 cm of the jejunal segment and stored at &#8722;80&#176;C for total RNA isolation. Approximately 1 cm of the mid-jejunum was sampled and immediately fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde for immunohistochemical analysis. Digesta from the ileum and cecum was collected and stored at &#8722;80&#176;C for DNA extraction.</p></sec><sec><title>RNA Isolation and Quantitative Real-Time PCR</title><p>Total RNA of jejunal samples was isolated using Trizol reagent (Invitrogen Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA) according to the manufacturer's protocol. The concentration and purity of total RNA was quantified by measuring its optical density at 260 and 280 nm with a NanoDrop&#174; ND-2000 UV-VIS spectrophotometer (Thermo Scientific, Wilmington, DE, USA). RNA integrity was verified by agarose gel electrophoresis. One microgram of total RNA was reverse transcribed by the PrimeScript&#174; RT reagent Kit with gDNA Eraser [Takara Biotechnology (Dalian) Co., Ltd., Dalian, China] according to the manufacturer's instructions. The quantitative real-time PCR assay was performed with the 7500 fluorescence detection system (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA) according to optimized PCR protocols using the SYBR Premix Ex TaqTM kit [Takara Biotechnology (Dalian) Co., Ltd.]. The primer pairs for the amplification of genes encoding IL-1&#946;, INF-&#947;, IL-13, IL-17, and transforming growth factor (TGF)-&#946;4 are presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Table 2</xref>. &#946;-actin served as an endogenous reference gene. The PCR conditions were an initial denaturation step at 95&#176;C for 30 s, 40 cycles at 95&#176;C for 5 s, annealing and extension temperature at 60&#176;C for 34 s. Each biological sample was run in triplicate. To confirm amplification specificity, the PCR products from each primer pair were subjected to a melting curve analysis and subsequent agarose gel electrophoresis. Gene expression was quantified using the comparative threshold cycle method and the data were expressed as the relative values to the control group.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunohistochemical Analysis</title><p>The number of CD3<sup>+</sup> intraepithelial T cells in the jejunal villus and crypt was determined by immunohistochemical (IHC) analysis as R&#246;he et al. (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) described with modifications. Briefly, the fixed jejunal tissue was dehydrated and embedded with paraffin wax. The paraffin blocks were consecutively cut at 5 &#956;m and the obtained sections were mounted on glass slides. The indirect immunohistochemical method was used for IHC analysis following the manufacturer's instructions (Boster Biological Technology Co., Ltd., Wuhan, China). After blocking, the jejunal sections were incubated with primary antibody (1:100 dilution) against CD3 T cell receptors overnight at 4&#176;C using humidity chambers. A rat anti-human CD3 antibody, which cross-reacts with the chicken CD3 complex, was used as the primary antibody. Then, tissue sections were incubated with secondary antibody conjugated with horseradish peroxidase (HRP) and CD3<sup>+</sup> T cells were visualized using a chromogenic dye. Additionally, slides were counterstained with hematoxylin. One of the images of stained slides is presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>. Finally, the CD3<sup>+</sup> T cells were quantified using a light microscope (Olympus, Tokyo, Japan), which was equipped with a digital camera (Olympus, Tokyo, Japan) and an image analysis program (ProRes CapturePro software, Jenoptik, Jena, Germany). The data were presented as the number of CD3<sup>+</sup> T cells per 1,000 &#956;m<sup>2</sup> in the villus and crypt regions, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>DNA Extraction</title><p>Bacterial DNA from the ileal and cecal digesta was extracted using a QIAamp DNA Stool Mini Kit (Qiagen Inc., Valencia, CA, USA). The DNA concentration was measured with a NanoDrop&#174; ND-2000 UV-VIS spectrophotometer (Thermo Scientific, Wilmington, DE, USA), and the DNA quality was determined by agarose gel electrophoresis. Some samples were pooled together before DNA extraction. Therefore, eight and seven DNA samples in each group were enrolled for high-throughput sequencing on days 21 and 28, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Amplification and 16S rRNA Gene Sequencing</title><p>The DNA extracted from samples collected on day 21 was amplified and sequenced as Wu et al. (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) described. Briefly, the V3-V4 region of the 16S rRNA gene was amplified by two-stage PCR. The first stage of PCR was performed using the HiFi HotStart ReadyMix kit (Kapa Biosystems, Wilmington, MA, USA) with the forward primer (5&#8242;-TCGTCGGCAGCGTCAGATGTGTATAAGAGACAGCCTACGGGNGGCWGCAG-3&#8242;) and the reverse primer (5&#8242;-GTCTCGTGGGCTCGGAGATGTGTATAAGAGACAGCACTACHVGGGTATCTAATCC-3&#8242;). The second stage of index PCR was processed using the Nexteta XT Index kit (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA), in which the dual indices and Illumina sequencing adapters were attached. Then, PCR products were purified with the Agencourt AMPure XP purification system (Beckman, Brea, CA, USA) and quantified by the SpectraMax i3X Multi-mode detection platform (Molecular Devices, San Jose, CA, USA). The purified amplicons were sequenced using the Illumina MiSeq platform (San Diego, CA, USA).</p><p>Due to technical issues, the DNA amplification and bacterial 16S rRNA gene sequencing for samples collected on day 28 was performed by Shanghai Majorbio Bio-Pharm Technology Co., Ltd. (Shanghai, China). The V3-V4 variable region of 16S RNA gene was amplified with barcoded primer pair 338F/806R (338F: 5&#8242;-ACTCCTACGGGAGGCAGCAG-3&#8242;; 806R: GGACTACHVGGGTWTCTAAT-3&#8242;). The amplicons were then extracted from 2% agarose gels and purified using the AxyPrep DNA Gel Extraction Kit (Axygen Biosciences, Union City, CA, USA) and quantified by a Quantus<sup>TM</sup> Fluorometer (Promega Corporation, Madison, WI, USA). Purified amplicons were pooled in equimolar amounts and pair-end sequenced (2 &#215; 300) on an Illumina MiSeq platform (San Diego, CA, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>Bioinformatics Analysis</title><p>Bioinformatics analysis was performed using the Majorbio Cloud Platform (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.majorbio.com">http://www.majorbio.com</ext-link>). Raw sequencing reads were demultiplexed and quality-filtered by Trimmomatic software (version 0.36) and then merged by FLASH software (version 1.2.7). Operational taxonomic units (OTUs) were clustered with the 97% similarity cut-off using UPARSE software (version 7.1). The taxonomy of each OTU representative sequence was analyzed using the RDP Classifier (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rdp.cme.msu.edu/">http://rdp.cme.msu.edu/</ext-link>) against the SILVA rRNA database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arb-silva.de">http://www.arb-silva.de</ext-link>) with a confidence threshold of 70%. After the elimination of interference sequence, a rarefaction curve and Venn diagram were created using R software (version 2.15.3). Analysis of alpha diversity was performed using Mothur software (version 1.30.1). Beta diversity was evaluated by the unweighted Unifrac principal co-ordinates analysis (PCoA) and the significance of bacterial separation among groups was reflected by ANOSIM analysis. Both analyses were conducted using R software. The top 10 differentially abundant bacteria at the genus level in the control vs. Cp group, Cp vs. Lf_Cp group, and Cp vs. Bc_Cp group were analyzed with Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test and a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value threshold of 0.05 was used. PICRUSt analysis was conducted to predict the potential function of microbiota. The OTUs were normalized by copy number and metagenome prediction was categorized into the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) at level 2 (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>The data of intestinal immune indices, bacterial alpha diversity, top 4 phyla, and top 5 predicted KEGG pathways were analyzed by one-way ANOVA using SPSS version 21.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). When significant differences were observed, individual group means were compared using Duncan's multiple comparison. If data did not comply with normal distribution, which was analyzed by a Kolmogorov-Smirnov test, a non-parameter test and pairwise comparisons were used to analyze the data. Data in figures are presented as mean and SE, while data in tables are given as mean and pooled SEM. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Jejunal Cytokine Gene Expression</title><p>The mRNA expression of cytokines in the jejunum is revealed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>. At 21 days of age, compared with the control group, the Cp group upregulated the mRNA expression of IL-1&#946; and TGF-&#946;4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). However, compared with the Cp group, the Bc_Cp and Lf_Cp groups downregulated the IL-1&#946; and TGF-&#946;4 mRNA expression, respectively (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The gene expression of IL-13 and IL-17 was not significantly affected (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). At 28 days of age, compared with the control and Cp groups, the Lf_Cp and Bc_Cp groups significantly upregulated the mRNA expression of IL-1&#946;, INF-&#947;, IL-17, and TGF-&#946;4 in the jejunum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The mRNA level of IL-13 was not influenced by challenge and dietary treatments (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The cytokine mRNA expression in jejunal mucosa of <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic>-challenged broiler chickens fed diets supplemented with <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus coagulans</italic> on days 21 <bold>(A)</bold> and 28 <bold>(B)</bold>. Data were expressed as mean and SE from 12 chickens. Control, unchallenged group; Cp, <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>-challenged group; Lf_Cp, challenged group with dietary supplementation of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic>; Bc_Cp, challenged group with dietary supplementation of <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus coagulans</italic>. IL, interleukin; IFN, interferon; TGF, transforming growth factor.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-680742-g0001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Jejunal CD3<sup>+</sup> T Cell Counts in Jejunum</title><p>The CD3<sup>+</sup> T cell counts in the villus and crypts of the jejunum are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. At 21 days of age, the Lf_Cp group tended to increase the villus CD3<sup>+</sup> T cell counts in contrast to the Cp group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.059). The Bc_Cp group had higher crypt CD3<sup>+</sup> T cell counts than that of the other three groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), among which the cell count did not significantly differ (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05). At 28 days of age, the jejunal CD3<sup>+</sup> cell counts were not significantly affected by treatments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05). The Lf_Cp group tended to have a higher CD3<sup>+</sup> T cell number in the crypt of the jejunum than that of the Cp and Bc_Cp groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.087).</p><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The CD3<sup>+</sup> T cell counts in villus and crypt of jejunum of <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic>-challenged broiler chickens fed diets supplemented with <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus coagulans</italic> on days 21 <bold>(A)</bold> and 28 <bold>(B)</bold>. Data were expressed as mean and SE from 12 chickens. Control, unchallenged group; Cp, <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>-challenged group; Lf_Cp, challenged group with dietary supplementation of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic>; Bc_Cp, challenged group with dietary supplementation of <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus coagulans</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-680742-g0002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Quality of Sequencing Data and Venn Diagram</title><p>The sequencing of ileal and cecal samples collected on days 21 and 28 generated a total of 3,215,602, 4,590,839, 1,482,180, and 1,624,227 effective sequences, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Tables 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">4</xref>). The median read length for these samples was 451, 449, 433, and 433 base pairs, respectively. The Good's coverage (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Tables 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">4</xref>) and rarefaction curves (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>) showed that sufficient sequencing coverage for all samples was achieved. All treatments shared 270 and 400 OTUs in ileal and cecal microbial communities at 21 days of age, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM4">Supplementary Figures 3A,C</xref>). At 28 days of age, there were 226 and 406 common OTUs in ileal and cecal microbiota of the four groups, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM4">Supplementary Figures 3B,D</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Alpha Diversity of Microbiota in Ileum and Cecum</title><p>As seen in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, at 21 days of age, compared with the control group, the Cp group tended to decrease Sobs (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.087) and Chao1 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.096) indices and significantly reduced the ACE index of ileal microbiota (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Meanwhile, the Bc_Cp group had comparable Sobs and ACE indices to the control. The alpha diversity of cecal microbiota was not significantly affected by treatments on day 21. At 28 days of age, the Bc_Cp group had lower richness indices (Sobs, Chao1, and ACE) than those of the other three groups in ileal microbiota (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Compared with the Cp group, the Lf_Cp group tended to increase the Shannon index (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.055) and decrease the Simpson index of ileal microbiota (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.087). In the cecum, the Cp group decreased in richness indices (Chao1 and ACE) in contrast to the control and Bc_Cp groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The Cp group tended to have lower Sobs (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.075) and Shannon (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.058) indices of cecal microbiota than those in the other three groups.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The alpha diversity of ileal and cecal microbiota in broiler chickens<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>1</sup></xref>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Item</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Shannon</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Simpson</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sobs</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Chao 1</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ACE</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ileum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.59</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233.38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">276.68</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">289.09<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Cp</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158.75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">193.15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">191.64<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Lf_Cp</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">187.88</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">230.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">236.10<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Bc_Cp</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.55</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228.13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">263.77</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">270.76<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;SEM</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.62</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.122</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.192</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.087</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cecum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">297.50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">367.41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">371.15</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Cp</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">286.50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">362.88</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">363.66</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Lf_Cp</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">314.88</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">384.51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">381.43</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Bc_Cp</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">276.38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">344.71</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">336.79</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;SEM</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.32</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.447</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.578</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.390</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.164</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ileum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">281.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">307.65<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">308.70<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Cp</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">248.64<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261.43<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Lf_Cp</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.44</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229.71<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247.86<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">248.96<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Bc_Cp</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138.36<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147.88<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;SEM</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.63</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.84</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.087</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cecum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">347.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">372.62<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">367.82<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Cp</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">263.29<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">289.83<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">285.92<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Lf_Cp</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">321.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">341.32<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">336.98<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Bc_Cp</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">349.14<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">370.23<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">366.51<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;SEM</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.99</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.44</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.058</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.268</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><label>1</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Data are expressed as mean and pooled SEM from 8 and 7 chickens on days 21 and 28, respectively</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN2"><label>a, b</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Values within a row with different superscripts differ significantly at P &lt; 0.05. Control, unchallenged group; Cp, Clostridium perfringens-challenged group; Lf_Cp, challenged group with dietary supplementation of Lactobacillus fermentum; Bc_Cp, challenged group with dietary supplementation of Bacillus coagulans</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Beta Diversity of Microbiota in Ileum and Cecum</title><p>Beta diversity illustrated via PCoA is presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>. At 21 days of age, the Lf_Cp group had distinct ileal microbiota compared with the other three groups, with a slight similarity with the control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>). Meanwhile, ileal microbiota on day 21 in the Cp group was much similar to that in the Bc_Cp group. Cecal microbiota on day 21 as well as ileal and cecal microbiota on day 28 was not notably differentiated by treatments. However, the positive R-values in ANOSIM analysis suggested that the inter-group difference of microbial communities in both the ileum and cecum at two time points was greater than the intra-group difference (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The PCoA plots of intestinal microbiota of <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic>-challenged broiler chickens fed diets supplemented with <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus coagulans</italic> on days 21 <bold>(A,C)</bold> and 28 <bold>(B,D)</bold>. Data were derived from 8 and 7 chickens on days 21 and 28, respectively. Control, unchallenged group; Cp, <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>-challenged group; Lf_Cp, challenged group with dietary supplementation of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic>; Bc_Cp, challenged group with dietary supplementation of <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus coagulans</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-680742-g0003.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Similarities of bacterial composition among groups by ANOSIM analysis<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3"><sup>a</sup></xref>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Item</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">R</italic>-value</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d 21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Ileum</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3116</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Cecum</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1085</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d 28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Ileum</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1516</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Cecum</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1539</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN3"><label>a</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Data are derived from 8 and 7 chickens on days 21 and 28, respectively</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Bacterial Composition at Phylum Level in Ileum and Cecum</title><p>The ileal and cecal bacterial composition at the phylum level is shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">Supplementary Figure 4</xref>. The top four phyla in each intestinal segment and at each time point are presented in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. At 21 days of age, compared with the control, the Cp and Lf_Cp groups increased the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> in the ileum (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The bacterial compositions at the phylum level in the cecum were not significantly affected by treatments (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05). At 28 days of age, compared with the control, the Cp and Bc_Cp groups decreased in ileal <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> abundance, and all other groups reduced in cecal <italic toggle="yes">Proteobacteria</italic> abundance (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The top 4 phyla in the ileal and cecal microbiota of broiler chickens<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN4"><sup>1</sup></xref>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Item</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Control</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cp</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Lf_Cp</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Bc_Cp</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SEM</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ileum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.66<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.87<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.61</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.62</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.79</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.232</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">Proteobacteria</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.80</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.55</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">Cyanobacteria</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.74</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.34</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.612</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cecum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.79</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.94</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.74</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.775</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.85</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.78</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.74</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.830</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">Verrucomicrobia</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.740</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">Proteobacteria</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.719</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ileum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.923</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">Cyanobacteria</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.79</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.727</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">Proteobacteria</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.78</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.44</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.329</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.47<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.76<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cecum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.58</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.86</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.83</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.860</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.35</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.70</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.62</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.879</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">Proteobacteria</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.47<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.86<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.61<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN5"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;<italic toggle="yes">Tenericutes</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.285</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN4"><label>1</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Data are expressed as mean and pooled SEM from 8 and 7 chickens on days 21 and 28, respectively</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN5"><label>a, b</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Values within a row with different superscripts differ significantly at P &lt; 0.05. Control, unchallenged group; Cp, Clostridium perfringens-challenged group; Lf_Cp, challenged group with dietary supplementation of Lactobacillus fermentum; Bc_Cp, challenged group with dietary supplementation of Bacillus coagulans</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Top 10 Differentially Abundant Bacteria at Genus level in Ileum and Cecum</title><p>The top 10 differentially abundant genera in selected groups are seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4</xref>&#8211;<bold>6</bold>.</p><fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The top 10 differentially abundant bacteria at genus level in control vs. Cp groups. Ileal and cecal microflora on days 21 <bold>(A,C)</bold> and 28 <bold>(B,D)</bold> was analyzed. Data were derived from 8 and 7 chickens on days 21 and 28, respectively. Control, unchallenged group; Cp, <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>-challenged group. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-680742-g0004.jpg"/></fig><p>At 21 days of age, compared with the control, the Cp group increased the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Romboutsia</italic> spp. and decreased in <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> spp. abundance in the ileum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Compared with the Cp group, the Lf_Cp group decreased the relative contents of <italic toggle="yes">Romboutsia</italic> spp. and unclassified f_<italic toggle="yes">Peptostreptococcaceae</italic>, and increased the <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> spp. abundance in the ileum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5A</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The Bc_Cp group had a higher ileal <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroides</italic> spp. content than that of the Cp group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6A</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). In contrast to the control, the Cp group increased unclassified f_<italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Ruminococcus_torques</italic> group abundance in the cecum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4C</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), both of which was decreased in the Lf_Cp group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5C</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Compared with the Cp group, the Bc_Cp group decreased cecal unclassified f_<italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae</italic> content (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6C</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>The top 10 differentially abundant bacteria at genus level in Cp vs. Lf_Cp groups. Ileal and cecal microflora on days 21 <bold>(A,C)</bold> and 28 <bold>(B,D)</bold> was analyzed. Data were derived from 8 and 7 chickens on days 21 and 28, respectively. Cp, <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>-challenged group; Lf_Cp, challenged group with dietary supplementation of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic>. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, ***<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-680742-g0005.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>The top 10 differentially abundant bacteria at genus level in Cp vs. Bc_Cp groups. Ileal and cecal microflora on days 21 <bold>(A,C)</bold> and 28 <bold>(B,D)</bold> was analyzed. Data were derived from 8 and 7 chickens on days 21 and 28, respectively. Cp, <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>-challenged group; Bc_Cp, challenged group with dietary supplementation of <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus coagulans</italic>. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-680742-g0006.jpg"/></fig><p>At 28 days of age, <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> challenge did not induce significant changes in ileal microbiota (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4B</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05). Compared with the Cp group, the Lf_Cp group decreased in the relative abundance of unclassified f_<italic toggle="yes">Peptostreptococcaceae</italic> in the ileum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5B</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Meanwhile, the Bc_Cp group increased ileal <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus</italic> spp. content (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6B</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). In the cecum, <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> challenge decreased the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia-Shigella</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4D</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Compared with the Cp group, the Lf_Cp group reduced the relative content of <italic toggle="yes">Faecalibacterium</italic> spp. and increased <italic toggle="yes">Ruminococcus</italic>_torques group content in the cecum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5D</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The Bc_Cp group increased the relative abundance of both <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia-Shigella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Ruminococcus</italic>_torques group in the cecum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6D</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></sec><sec><title>Predicted Functional Potentials of OTUs in Ileum and Cecum</title><p>The top five presumptive functions of microbiota at level 2 of the KEGG pathways are illustrated in <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. At 21 days of age, the Lf_Cp group had a higher abundance of the replication and repair pathway and translation pathway than that of the other three groups in the ileum (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Compared with the control, the Cp group increased ileal abundance of amino acid metabolism, but the Lf_Cp group decreased this pathway abundance (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). In contrast to the control, the Cp group increased the abundance of the membrane transport pathway, but decreased amino acid metabolism in the cecum (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Both probiotic-supplemented groups exhibited opposite changes to the Cp group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) and did not significantly differ from the control (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05). The Lf_Cp group had higher abundance of the replication and repair pathway than that of the control in the cecum (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). At 28 days of age, compared with the control and Cp groups, the Bc_Cp and Lf_Cp groups increased the abundance of ileal membrane transport and cecal carbohydrate metabolism, respectively (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>The top 5 abundant microbial pathway grouped into level 2 functional categories using PICRUSt<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN6"><sup>1</sup></xref>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Item</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Control</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cp</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Lf_Cp</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Bc_Cp</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SEM</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ileum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Membrane transport</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.81</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.722</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Carbohydrate metabolism</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.789</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Replication and repair</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.86<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.71<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.65<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Amino acid metabolism</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.74<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.55<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.34<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.36<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Translation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.44<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.28<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.81<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.31<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cecum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Membrane transport</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.40<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.82<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.61<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.74<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Carbohydrate metabolism</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.89</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.82</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.83</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.689</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Amino acid metabolism</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.75<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.55<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.73<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.71<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Replication and repair</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.78<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.62<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.94<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.80<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Energy metabolism</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.82</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.91</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.097</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ileum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Membrane transport</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.69<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.79<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.16<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.91<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Carbohydrate metabolism</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.79</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.253</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Amino acid metabolism</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.97</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.85</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Replication and repair</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.853</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Energy metabolism</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.803</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cecum</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Membrane transport</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.35</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.72</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.71</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.487</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Carbohydrate metabolism</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.88<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.25<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.06<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN7"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Amino acid metabolism</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.58</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.81</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.57</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Replication and repair</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.94</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.77</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.526</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;Energy metabolism</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.79</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.84</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.86</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.81</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.688</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN6"><label>*</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Data are expressed as mean and pooled SEM from 8 and 7 chickens on days 21 and 28, respectively</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN7"><label>a&#8722;c</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Values within a row with different superscripts differ significantly at P &lt; 0.05. Control, unchallenged group; Cp, Clostridium perfringens-challenged group; Lf_Cp, challenged group with dietary supplementation of Lactobacillus fermentum; Bc_Cp, challenged group with dietary supplementation of Bacillus coagulans</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The previously reported results from the current study showed that the <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> challenge-induced NE model was successful, evidenced by decreased averaged feed intake and increased jejunal lesion score as well as elevated <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> counts in the ileum and cecum (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Furthermore, both <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> addition inhibited intestinal pathogen colonization and <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> exhibited superior effects in alleviating intestinal injury (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Therefore, the intestinal immunity and microbiota of <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>-challenged birds fed <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic>-supplemented diets were further investigated in the present study.</p><p>The <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> studies have demonstrated that <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> challenge evoked intense intestinal inflammatory responses <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> TLRs or nucleotide-binding oligomerization domains triggered the nuclear factor kappa B signaling pathway in broilers (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). This signaling cascade resulted in the activation of macrophages and/or dendritic cells, which in turn led to the differentiation of na&#239;ve T helper (Th) cells into mature effector Th1, Th2, Th17, and Treg cells, which characteristically produced IL-1, INF-&#947;, IL-13, IL-17, and TGF-&#946;, respectively (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Fasina and Lillehoj (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) reported that <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> infection induced intestinal inflammation via the activation of Th2 and Th17 cells and inhibition of Treg cells, proven by the upregulation of IL-13 and IL-17 and downregulation of TGF-&#946;4. In the present study, <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> challenge upregulated jejunal IL-1&#946; and TGF-&#946;4 expression, which was downregulated by <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic>, respectively, soon after the infection (day 21). However, both probiotics increased the mRNA expression of IL-1&#946;, INF-&#947;, IL-13, IL-17, and TGF-&#946; in the jejunum at seven days post infection (day 28). This suggested that probiotics showed inhibitory and stimulatory effects on cytokine expression of Th cells in the acute and recovery phase of <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> challenge, respectively. Meanwhile, they mainly modulated the functions of Th1, Th17, and Treg cells. However, Emami et al. (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) reported that <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus licheniformis</italic> alone or combined with prebiotic and essential oil downregulated the IFN-&#947;, IL-10, and IL-17 mRNA abundance in the jejunum of broilers with subclinical NE, indicating a inhibition of Th2, Th17, and Treg cell function.</p><p>Intraepithelial lymphocytes (IEL), consisting of natural killer cells, T cells, and B cells, are an important component in gut-associated lymphoid tissue, which is one of the major immunological systems in chickens (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Increase of the general T cell (CD3<sup>+</sup>) population within the intestinal epithelium indicates a strong local immune system with increased resistance to enteric diseases (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). In the present study, <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> tended to increase CD3<sup>+</sup> T cell density in the villus on day 21 and in the crypt on day 28, and <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> significantly elevated crypt CD3<sup>+</sup> T cell population in the jejunum of <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>-challenged broilers. This suggested that <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> addition might induce intestinal T cell responses to fight against <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> infection in broiler chickens. Consistently, Bai et al. (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) observed that <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> JS combined with <italic toggle="yes">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> stimulated the intestinal T cell immune system by increasing the subpopulations of IEL CD3<sup>+</sup>, CD4<sup>+</sup>, and CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells in the jejunum of broiler chickens. It was reported that <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> spores as adjuvants with inactivated H9N2 enhanced CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T cell responses in White Leghorn chickens against avian influenza H9N2 (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>).</p><p>It has been demonstrated that the diversity of microbial community contributed to the homeostasis of intestinal microbiota and the resistance to pathogens (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). In the present study, <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> challenge decreased the richness (Sobs, Chao1, and ACE indices) and diversity (Shannon index) of cecal microbiota at 28 days of age, and both probiotic groups had comparable alpha diversity to the control. The same change of ACE index was seen in the ileal microbiota at 21 days of age. This indicated that the impaired intestinal microbial richness and diversity was restored by probiotic addition. Partly consistent with our findings, Li et al. (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) reported that <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> infection decreased the richness of ileal bacterial community of broiler chickens and dietary <italic toggle="yes">L. acidophilus</italic> addition reduced its diversity, but both challenge and probiotic supplementation increased the richness and diversity of cecal microbiota. Furthermore, we found that <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> significantly decreased ileal bacterial richness at 28 days of age. In a non-challenged model, broilers fed <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> TBC169 had higher diversity of jejunal microbiota than that of the control on day 21, but lower diversity on day 42, although both of which did not achieve statistical significance (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>).</p><p>In the current study, beta diversity analysis indicated only ileal microbiota at 21 days of age was markedly altered by treatments with the highest R-value (0.3116) by ANOSIM analysis. The unchallenged and challenged birds without probiotic addition had distinct microbiota only in the ileum on day 21. Compared with the <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>-challenged group, <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> alone and both probiotics altered intestinal microbiota on days 21 and 28, respectively. Necrotic enteritis in broilers was caused by <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> proliferation and manifested by lesions in the small intestine (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Moreover, the exogenous <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> administration could not totally colonize in the intestine and they might be gradually excreted after challenge. This was evidenced by our previous observation that the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> in ileal and cecal contents quantified by qPCR in the challenged group without probiotic supplementation was much higher than that in the control on day 21 and no significant <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> abundance was seen on day 28 (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). The influence of probiotic addition on the intestinal microbiota of birds challenged by <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> might be disclosed in the following description.</p><p>It has been reported that <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes, Cyanobacteria, Proteobacteria</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> were the four predominant bacterial phyla in ileal microbiota (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), and <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes, Proteobacteria, Bacteroidetes, Tenericutes</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Verrucomicrobia</italic> were the predominant phyla in cecal microbiota (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). This was consistent with our findings. Meanwhile, challenged birds in the Cp and Lf_Cp groups had higher relative abundance of ileal <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> than that of birds in the control group on day 21, and challenged birds had lower ileal <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> and cecal <italic toggle="yes">Proteobacteria</italic> abundance on day 28. Contrary to our observation, Xu et al. (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) demonstrated that NE severity was related to a decrease of <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> and an increase of <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Proteobacteria</italic>. Moreover, Zhang et al. (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) observed that <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> challenge significantly decreased ileal <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> abundance in broilers. The increase of <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> population could suppress <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> and restore intestinal homeostasis (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). It was speculated that the increase of <italic toggle="yes">Firmicutes</italic> abundance in the Cp and Lf_Cp groups might be a strategy for the host to maintain ileal microbial homeostasis. The increase of <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> was associated with a decrease of nutrient absorption (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">Proteobacteria</italic> contain a wide variety of pathogens such as <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli, Salmonella</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Shigella</italic>, which can colonize in the intestine of chickens (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). The decrease of <italic toggle="yes">Proteobacteria</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> in challenged birds on day 28 might indicate that a healthy bacterial community was achieved in the recovery phase post challenge.</p><p>At 21 days of age, <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> challenge increased <italic toggle="yes">Romboutsia</italic> spp. in the ileum as well as unclassified f_<italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Ruminococcus_torques</italic> group in the cecum, and decreased <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> spp. in the ileum, which were all conversely modulated by dietary <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> addition. <italic toggle="yes">Romboutsia</italic> spp. was reported to be associated with less severe immune responses accompanied with decreasing levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines in plasma (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). It was predominant in the feces of nursing home residents with <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium difficile</italic> colonization (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). Therefore, the decrease of <italic toggle="yes">Romboutsia</italic> spp. abundance in challenged birds fed <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic>-supplemented diet might benefit microbial homeostasis and alleviate inflammation. In a NE challenge model of broilers, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> DSM 32315 decreased the <italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae</italic> members in the cecum (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), this was consistent with our findings that both <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> reduced the cecal <italic toggle="yes">Lachnospiraceae</italic> abundance. <italic toggle="yes">Ruminococcus</italic> spp. could produce lantibiotics that enhanced sterilization activity against some clostridia and bifidobacteria species (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>), and the increase of <italic toggle="yes">Ruminococcus</italic> spp. was associated with mucin glycans (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Xu et al. (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) reported that higher <italic toggle="yes">Ruminococcus</italic> spp. and <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroides</italic> spp. abundance was observed in the ileum of NE birds, which was decreased by <italic toggle="yes">B. licheniformis</italic> supplementation. Dietary <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> decreased <italic toggle="yes">Ruminococcus</italic> spp. in the cecum, but <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> increased <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroides</italic> spp. in the ileum of <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>-challenged birds. <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroides</italic> spp. can evolve into a pathogenic form and will increase when the gut is pathologically impaired (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). In the current study, <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> significantly increased <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> spp. in the ileum on day 21 and decreased <italic toggle="yes">Faecalibacterium</italic> spp. in the cecum on day 28. <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> spp. is a well-known beneficial genus in the gut and functions by maintaining intestinal bacterial community, improving immunity and gut integrity, and facilitating nutrition absorption (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). Complying with our findings, Li et al. (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) reported that <italic toggle="yes">L. acidophilus</italic> supplementation increased <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> spp. and suppressed <italic toggle="yes">Faecalibacterium</italic> spp., a potentially pathogenic flora.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Peptostreptococcaceae</italic> was one of the dominant families in the ileum of broilers (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). In a broiler NE model established by <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria maxima</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> co-infection, challenged birds had higher ileal <italic toggle="yes">Peptostreptococcaceae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus</italic> spp. abundance as compared to counterparts fed <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus</italic> direct-fed microbials (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Similarly, <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> decreased unclassified f_<italic toggle="yes">Peptostreptococcaceae</italic> in the ileum of <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>-challenged birds on both days 21 and 28. However, <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> increased <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus</italic> spp. in the ileum on day 28. It has been indicated that there was a positive correlation between the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia-Shigella</italic> with NE occurrence in broilers (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Numerous studies evidenced that <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> challenge increased the <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia-Shigella</italic> abundance in the ileum, and probiotic supplementation significantly or numerically decreased it (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). However, in the present study, <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> challenge decreased <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia-Shigella</italic> in the cecum on day 28, which was increased by <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic>. These data suggested that <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> exerted a negative effect on intestinal microbiota at 7 days post challenge.</p><p>Membrane transport, carbohydrate metabolism, amino acid metabolism, replication and repair, and energy metabolism were the dominant functions of microbiota, which was confirmed by Zhang et al. (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Membrane transport pathways are essential to cell viability and growth and are thereby crucial for the survival of bacteria in the gut ecosystem (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). Zhang et al. (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) reported that <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> challenge decreased the abundance of the membrane transport function of ileal microbiota. In contrast, we found <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> infection increased the membrane transport of cecal microbiota on day 21, which was decreased by probiotic addition. Meanwhile, challenged birds fed <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic>-supplemented diet had higher membrane transport abundance in the ileum on day 28. This indicated that the activities of ileal and cecal microbiota showed different responses to challenge and probiotic addition. It has been demonstrated that decreased carbohydrate metabolism and increased amino acid metabolism was observed in inflamed mucosal microbiota of ulcerative colitis patients (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). In the present study, <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> challenge increased amino acid metabolism of ileal microbiota, but decreased it in cecal microbiota on day 21, which were conversely changed by probiotic addition. This might be attributed to the mucolytic characteristic and ileal colonization of <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Dietary <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> affected the bacterial function by changing the microbial composition. Furthermore, challenged birds supplemented with <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> had higher abundance of the replication and repair of ileal and cecal microbiota as well as translation of ileal microbiota on day 21. Consistently, Cui et al. (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>) reported that dietary addition with <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium butyricum</italic> increased the replication and repair of jejunal microbiota in broilers, which improved the renewal and vigorous vitality of bacteria.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p><italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> challenge induced inflammatory responses and intestinal microbial dysbiosis soon after challenge and these impairments diminished at 7 days post challenge. Dietary <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic> supplementation attenuated inflammation by modulating Th cell function and T cell responses, and restored intestinal microflora by enriching beneficial bacteria and suppressing harmful flora. <italic toggle="yes">L. fermentum</italic> exhibited superior microbial modulatory effects to <italic toggle="yes">B. coagulans</italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The sequencing data presented in the study are deposited in the Sequence Read Archive of the NCBI, accession number <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="SPR304801">SPR304801</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Wuhan Polytechnic University.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>SG, YiX, and BD conceived and designed the experiment. SG, YiX, and TW performed the experiment. SG, YuX, TW, and DZ analyzed the data. SG, YuX, ZZ, and BD wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This research was funded by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 31702130), the Hubei Provincial Key Project for Scientific and Technical Innovation (2018ABA110), the Open Project of Hubei Key Laboratory of Animal Nutrition and Feed Science (DKXY2020014), and the Launching Research Fund from Wuhan Polytechnic University (2019RZ03).</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s9"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2021.680742/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2021.680742/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Image_1.TIFF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Image_2.TIF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Image_3.TIF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Image_4.TIF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shojadoost</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vince</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prescott</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The successful experimental induction of necrotic enteritis in chickens by <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic>: a critical review</article-title>. <source>Vet Res.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>74</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1297-9716-43-74</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23101966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3546943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaldhusdal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hofshagen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Barley inclusion and avoparcin supplementation in broiler diets. 2. Clinical, pathological, and bacteriological findings in a mild form of necrotic enteritis</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>1992</year>) <volume>71</volume>:<fpage>1145</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.0711145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1641378</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Songer</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Clostridial enteric diseases of domestic animals</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev.</source> (<year>1996</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>216</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.9.2.216-234.1996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8964036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC172891</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>In vitro lecithinase activity and sensitivity to 22 antimicrobial agents of <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic> isolated from necrotic enteritis of broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Res Vet Sci.</source> (<year>1988</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>337</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2905509</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Songer</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Necrotic enteritis in chickens: a paradigm of enteric infection by <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic> type A</article-title>. <source>Anaerobe.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anaerobe.2009.01.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19186215</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalique</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoaib</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qing</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajput</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Probiotics mitigating subclinical necrotic enteritis (SNE) as potential alternatives to antibiotics in poultry</article-title>. <source>AMB Express.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13568-020-00989-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32172398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7072080</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>La Ragione</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Competitive exclusion by <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> spores of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enterica</italic> serotype Enteritidis and <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic> in young chickens</article-title>. <source>Vet Microbiol.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>245</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-1135(03)00077-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12814892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Two <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> species inhibit the growth and alpha-toxin production of <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic> and induced proinflammatory factors in chicken intestinal epithelial cells <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic></article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>2081</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.02081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29118744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5661052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pretreatment with probiotic <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecium</italic> NCIMB 11181 ameliorates necrotic enteritis-induced intestinal barrier injury in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>10256</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-46578-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31311959</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6635415</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Reduced lesions in chickens with <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic>-induced necrotic enteritis by <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic> 1</article-title>.2029. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>91</volume>:<fpage>3065</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.2012-02548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23155014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus coagulans</italic> supplementation on the growth performance and gut health of broiler chickens with <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic>-induced necrotic enteritis</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci Biotechnol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40104-017-0220-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29416856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5784659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borda-Molina</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Camarinha-Silva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Current perspectives of the chicken gastrointestinal tract and its microbiome</article-title>. <source>Comput Struct Biotechnol J.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.csbj.2018.03.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30026889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6047366</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus acidophilus</italic> on gut microbiota composition in broilers challenged with <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e0188634</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0188634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29190649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5708699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bortoluzzi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Serpa Vieira</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Paula Dorigam</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menconi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sokale</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doranalli</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> DSM 32315 supplementation attenuates the effects of <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic> challenge on the growth performance and intestinal microbiota of broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Microorganisms.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms7030071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30841654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6463140</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doranalli</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rinttil&#228;</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vienola</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jurgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Apajalahti</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> DSM 32315 on the pathology, performance, and intestinal microbiome of broiler chickens in a necrotic enteritis challenge</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>3450</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pey500</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30452717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6698186</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>In vitro antibacterial activity of thymol and carvacrol and their effetcs on broiler chickens challenged with <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic></article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci Biotechnol</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>58</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40104-015-0055-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26705471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4690362</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>R&#246;he</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gobel</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goodarzi Boroojeni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zentek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of feeding soybean meal and differently processed peas on the gut mucosal immune system of broilers</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>2064</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pew491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28339726</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of N-acetylcysteine on the gut microbiota in the piglets infected with porcine epidemic diarrhea virus</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>582338</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2020.582338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33511162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7835392</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary L-arginine supplementation alleviates the intestinal injury and modulates the gut microbiota in broiler chickens challenged by <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic></article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1716</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.01716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30108569</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6080643</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus coagulans</italic> on the growth performance and gut health of broilers challenged with <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic></article-title>. <source>China Anim Husbandry Vet Med</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>2927</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.16431/j.cnki.1671-7236.2019.10.013</pub-id> (Abstract in English)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Inflammatory responses to a <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic> type A strain and alpha-toxin in primary intestinal epithelial cells of chicken embryos</article-title>. <source>Avian Pathol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03079457.2015.1005573</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25584964</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cosmi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maggi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santarlasci</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liotta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Annunziato</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>T helper cells plasticity in inflammation</article-title>. <source>Cytometry Part A.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>85</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cyto.a.22348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24009159</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of host genetic factors and host immunity in necrotic enteritis</article-title>. <source>Avian Pathol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>313</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03079457.2016.1154503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26957203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fasina</surname><given-names>YO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of intestinal immune response to <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic> infection in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>188</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>98</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pey390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30239962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6347130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emami</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimminau</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalloul</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of probiotics and multi-component feed additives on microbiota, gut barrier and immune responses in broiler chickens during subclinical necrotic enteritis</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>572142</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2020.572142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33324697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7725796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Intestinal immune responses to coccidiosis</article-title>. <source>Dev Comp Immunol.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>303</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0145-305x(99)00080-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10717295</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalloul</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shellem</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doerr</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of vitamin A deficiency on host intestinal immune response to <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria acervulina</italic> in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>81</volume>:<fpage>1509</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ps/81.10.1509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12412917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of probiotic-supplemented diets on growth performance and intestinal immune characteristics of broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>663</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.2012-02813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23436517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kye</surname><given-names>Y-C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S-M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>B-S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> spores as adjuvants against avian influenza H9N2 induce antigen-specific antibody and T cell responses in White Leghorn chickens</article-title>. <source>Vet Res.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>68</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13567-020-00788-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32448402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7245620</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Konstantinov</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Favier</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kl&#252;ss</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Souffrant</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Microbial diversity studies of the porcine gastrointestinal ecosystem during weaning transition</article-title>. <source>Anim Res.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>317</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/animres:2004019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C-L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S-G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>Q-R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C-B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Intestinal morphologic and microbiota responses to dietary <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus</italic> spp. in a broiler chicken model</article-title>. <source>Front Physiol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1968</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2018.01968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30705639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6344408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Kluyveromyces marxianus</italic> supplementation on immune responses, intestinal structure and microbiota in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e0180884</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0180884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28700666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5507273</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Differential effects of bacitracin methylene disalicylate (BMD) on the distal colon and cecal microbiota of young broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>114</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2019.00114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31058171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6478705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Bacillus licheniformis</italic> normalize the ileum microbiota of chickens infected with necrotic enteritis</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1744</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-20059-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29379124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5789067</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fasina</surname><given-names>YO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stough</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liles</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic> infection and antibiotic administration on microbiota in the small intestine of broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>95</volume>:<fpage>247</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pev329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26567176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jumpertz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turnbaugh</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trinidad</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bogardus</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Energy-balance studies reveal associations between gut microbes, caloric load, and nutrient absorption in humans</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>58</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3945/ajcn.110.010132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21543530</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3127503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mora</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mamani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#243;pez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Recent emergence of clonal group O25b:K1:H4-B2-ST131 <italic toggle="yes">ibeA</italic> strains among <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> poultry isolates, including CTX-M-9-producing strains, and comparison with clinical human isolates</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>76</volume>:<fpage>6991</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01112-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20817805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2976257</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malmuthuge</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stothard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Griebel</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Transcriptome analysis reveals regional and temporal differences in mucosal immune system development in the small intestine of neonatal calves</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>602</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-016-2957-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27515123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4981982</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Araos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andreatos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ugalde</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mylonakis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D'agata</surname><given-names>EMC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fecal microbiome among nursing home residents with advanced dementia and <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium difficile</italic></article-title>. <source>Digest Dis Sci</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>1525</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10620-018-5030-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29594967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6434537</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dabard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bridonneau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Phillipe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anglade</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Molle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nardi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Ruminococcin A, a new lantibiotic produced by a <italic toggle="yes">Ruminococcus gnavus</italic> strain isolated from human feces</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>4111</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.67.9.4111-4118.2001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11526013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC93137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crost</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tailford</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Gall</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fons</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henrissat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juge</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Utilisation of mucin glycans by the human gut symbiont <italic toggle="yes">Ruminococcus gnavus</italic> is strain-dependent</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e76341</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0076341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24204617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3808388</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ferritin-like family proteins in the anaerobe Bacteroides fragilis: when an oxygen storm is coming, take your iron to the shelter</article-title>. <source>Biometals.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>577</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10534-013-9650-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23842847</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3815548</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bermudez-Brito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plaza-D&#237;az</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mu&#241;oz-Quezada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#243;mez-Llorente</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Probiotic mechanisms of action</article-title>. <source>Ann Nutr Metab.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>160</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000342079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23037511</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez-Patlan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solis-Cruz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pontin</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez-Velasco</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Merino-Guzman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of a <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus</italic> direct-fed microbial on growth performance, intestinal barrier integrity, necrotic enteritis lesions, and ileal microbiota in broiler chickens using a laboratory challenge model</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>108</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2019.00108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31106209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6492466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>C-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of gut microbiota and the effect of lauric acid against necrotic enteritis in <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> side-by-side challenge model</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>e0205784</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0205784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31150394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6544216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crumlish</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Phylogenetic and functional characterization of the distal intestinal microbiome of rainbow trout <italic toggle="yes">Oncorhynchus mykissfrom</italic> both farm and aquarium settings</article-title>. <source>J Appl Microbiol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>122</volume>:<fpage>347</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.13347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27860093</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davenport</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poles</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abidi</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ullman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Metabolic alterations to the mucosal microbiota in inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>Inflamm Bowel Dis.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>723</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MIB.0000000000000011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24583479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4158619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Xylanase supplementation to a wheat-based diet alleviated the intestinal mucosal barrier impairment of broiler chickens challenged by <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic></article-title>. <source>Avian Pathol</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>291</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03079457.2012.684089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22702457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>High-throughput sequencing-based analysis of the intestinal microbiota of broiler chickens fed with compound small peptides of Chinese medicine</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>100897</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2020.11.066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33518313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7936118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>