<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8358326</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8358326.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8358326</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8358326</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34395579</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.712942</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evidence of Sex Differentiation Based on Morphological Traits During the Early Development Stage of Mud Crab <italic toggle="yes">Scylla paramamosain</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names initials="W">Wenxiao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names initials="S">Shaobin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names initials="L">Ligang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names initials="F">Fei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="Q">Qingyang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names initials="H">Huaiping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/456468/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="S">Shengkang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/445361/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yueling</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/426598/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikhwanuddin</surname><given-names initials="M">Mhd</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/276545/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names initials="H">Hongyu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/634312/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Marine Biotechnology, Shantou University</institution>, <addr-line>Shantou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Shantou University- Universiti Malaysia Terengganu, Joint Shellfish Research Laboratory, Shantou University</institution>, <addr-line>Shantou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Institute of Tropical Aquaculture and Fisheries, Universiti Malaysia Terengganu</institution>, <addr-line>Kuala Terengganu</addr-line>, <country>Malaysia</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Beide Fu, Institute of Hydrobiology, Chinese Academy of Sciences (CAS), China</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Huan Wang, Ningbo University, China; Zhiyi Bai, Shanghai Ocean University, China</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Hongyu Ma <email>mahy@stu.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Livestock Genomics, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>7</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">374996</issue-id><elocation-id>712942</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>13</day><month>08</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-05 19:25:14.360"><day>05</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2021 Cui, Fang, Lv, Huang, Lin, Wu, Zheng, Li, Zhang, Ikhwanuddin and Ma.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Cui, Fang, Lv, Huang, Lin, Wu, Zheng, Li, Zhang, Ikhwanuddin and Ma</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-08-712942.pdf"/><abstract><p>In order to uncover the sexual difference in morphology and how early they appear during the development stage of mud crab <italic toggle="yes">Scylla paramamosain</italic>, we measured, observed, and biostatistically analyzed morphological traits related to sex. For unveiling the morphological differences between sexes, morphological traits involving abdomen width (AW), carapace length (CL), and carapace width (CW) were first measured during the crablet development stage of <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic> in the present study. The correlation analyses and path analyses exhibited that sexual dimorphism in the third abdomen width (AW3) and fourth abdomen width (AW4) could be used for sex identification from stage C VI (stage VI of crablet). Based on the stepwise discriminant analysis and standardized traits, a sex discriminant equation was constructed, which is capable for sex identification in crablets from stage C VI. Observations for secondary sexual traits and abdomen morphology (shape and pleopods) using a dissecting microscope or scanning electron microscope indicated that sexes are easily identified at stage C VIII according to the abdomen shape; meanwhile, at stage C II based on pleopod difference, and at stage C I by the presence or absence of gonopores. The findings in this study contribute greatly to the accuracy of sex identification of <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic> during the early development stage, which promotes the understanding of the morphological differentiation mechanism of sex.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Scylla paramamosain</italic></kwd><kwd>morphological differences</kwd><kwd>sex identification</kwd><kwd>development stages</kwd><kwd>biostatistical analysis</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="5"/><equation-count count="1"/><ref-count count="34"/><page-count count="11"/><word-count count="5978"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Sexual dimorphism deriving from sex differentiation of animals is always one of the critical propositions in life science, which makes life more complex and wonderful (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). The significant sexual differences in morphology and physiology are known as secondary sexual traits, which encompass a suite of traits from the external genitalia, to courtship behaviors, to any other sex-specific morphological, behavioral, or physiological traits (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). These different traits allow each sex to better adapt to the environment and occupy a favorable ecological niche (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Sexual dimorphism is quite prevalent in the animal kingdom and has attracted researchers' attention (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). However, knowledge about the morphological difference between sexes of crablets remains lacking.</p><p>The mud crab <italic toggle="yes">Scylla paramamosain</italic> belongs to the genus <italic toggle="yes">Scylla</italic> and exhibits significant sexual dimorphism concerning growth rate, body size, and abdomen morphology (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Apart from that, females have higher economic and nutritional values than males (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). As one of the traditional and prevalent marine crabs, the output of <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic> has reached the leading position among marine commercial crabs in China (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Due to the demand fueled by increasing standards of living in the major consumer countries and preference for sexually mature female crabs with high nutritional value and better taste, the price of females is often two to three times higher than that of males (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Therefore, it is significant for sex-biased breeding with the help of sex identification in morphology during the immature stage, and, monosexual breeding can be an effective solution to meet the ever-increasing market demand for females.</p><p>It is commonly accepted that the sexual differences of mud crab in morphology at the mature stage are mainly in the following aspects: (1) Four pairs of double-branched (biramous) pleopods are in the wide and rounded female abdomen. Contrary to the females, there is only one pair of uniramous gonopods in the narrow and straight male abdomen. Additionally, one pair of gonopores is in the third thoracic segment of the female, and no gonopore was found at the same position in the males (2) The females keep a faster growth rate and a bigger body size than the males except for the cheliped size (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Apart from that, several studies have been implemented about morphological differences between the sexes of crabs. A clear sexual dimorphism in crab size was found in <italic toggle="yes">Loxopagurus loxochelis</italic>, with males reaching larger dimensions than females, mainly in terms of the major (i.e., left) chela size (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). In the male of <italic toggle="yes">Eriocheir japonica</italic>, ambulatory legs are relatively longer than females (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Sexual dimorphism was evident in terms of claw size and coloration of the symbiotic pea crab <italic toggle="yes">Austinixa aidae</italic>. Males have larger claws than females, which gives them the favor in male&#8211;male competition. In addition, the body coloration of males was more similar to the sand grains of the beach than that of females (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Furthermore, there were highly significant differences by sex in carapace length, carapace width, carapace height, and body weight for adult Chinese mitten crab (<italic toggle="yes">Eriocheir sinensis</italic>) (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Besides, female adults had wider abdominal segments and a thicker body compared with males of the leucosiid crab <italic toggle="yes">Pyrhila pisum</italic> (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Although several studies focused on the morphological differences in the mature crab were done, the study about the immature crab was still lacking. Especially in the <italic toggle="yes">Scylla</italic>, the sex of the immature mud crab is hard to identify, and the time of sexual differentiation in morphology has not been determined yet.</p><p>In crustaceans, females are identified by unique sexual morphological features dedicated to mating and breeding, which developed gradually before or at puberty but are hard to characterize in the early development stage (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). As far as we know, only several studies have been devoted exclusively to understand the specific time for sex identification of crablets by morphology. To find out the specific time for sex identification, Shi et al. (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) constructed a discriminant function equation based on growth traits of the juvenile mud crabs, which will provide great help for further research on the time of sex differentiation of the <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic>. In the histological and morphological study of the crab <italic toggle="yes">E. japonicus</italic>, Lee et al. (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) found that sex differentiation first occurred in the gonoducts, and sexual dimorphism is visible in the abdomen at the fifth crab stage. In addition, there may be differences in some morphological traits between sexes during the development from crablet to adult in the Chinese mitten crab <italic toggle="yes">Eriocheir sinensis</italic> (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). As the secondary sexual characteristics, the female leucosiidae crab <italic toggle="yes">Pyrhila pisum</italic> gradually developed their abdomen during the juvenile stage and drastically enlarged their width and thickness by a puberty molt from juvenile to adult (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Although some studies have been conducted, the information applied for sex identification in specific stages based on the morphological differences during the development of the <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic> crablets is still lacking. Additionally, the previous study has revealed that the external morphological differentiation of <italic toggle="yes">Scylla serrata</italic> is earlier than gonadal differentiation (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p><p>In which stage can the mud crab be distinguished in males and females by sexual morphology? Also, at which stage does morphological sexual differentiation begin? In this study, we attempt to answer these questions in mud crab <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic>. Hence, the morphological differences between sexes during the early development of mud crab <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic> were studied to determine the differentiation time. Also, a discriminant function equation was constructed, by which the specific stages of sex differentiation in morphology is further determined. Exploring the critical period of morphological sex differentiation can provide the basis for sex control technology and the development of monosexual crab breeding techniques. It can also promote a deep understanding of the mechanism underlying the sexual differentiation of mud crab and other crabs.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Larvae and Crablet Culture and Sampling</title><p>The <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic> larvae were hatched in circular fiberglass tanks (0.9 m in diameter, 1.0 m in height) at a local aquaculture farm (Guangdong Province, China), and then they were transferred to concrete rearing tanks (5.8 &#215; 4.8 &#215; 1.8 m). Culture conditions were ambient temperature, natural photoperiod, and salinity of ~28 ppt. The molting times were recorded, and the crablets at each stage were randomly sampled from a family. The molting and sampling time of the crablets at the eight stages are described in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Sampling time increased with molting time. A total of 72 crablets at each stage were sampled, of which 42 were for sex identification and morphological observation, and 30 were for observing by scanning electron microscope and dissecting microscope.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The molting and sampling time at the different stages of the <italic toggle="yes">Scylla paramamosain</italic> crablets.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Stage</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>C I</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>C II</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>C III</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>C IV</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>C V</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>C VI</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>C VII</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>C VIII</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Molting time</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PJ3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PJ6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PJ10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PJ14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PJ19</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PJ24</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PJ31</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sampling time</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PJ1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PJ3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PJ6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PJ10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PJ14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PJ19</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PJ24</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PJ31</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">C I-VIII, crablet stage I-VIII; PJ, postjuvenile crab</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Morphological Trait Measurement and Observation</title><p>The first abdomen width (AW1), second abdomen width (AW2), third abdomen width (AW3), fourth abdomen width (AW4), and fifth abdomen width (AW5) were measured to the nearest 0.01 mm by standard vernier calipers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). The carapace length (CL) and carapace width (CW) were measured using the methods of Gao et al. (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Measurement indexes of the <italic toggle="yes">Scylla paramamosain</italic> crablet. CL, carapace length; CW, carapace width; AW1, first abdomen width; AW2, second abdomen width; AW3, third abdomen width; AW4, fourth abdomen width; AW5, fifth abdomen width.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-712942-g0001.jpg"/></fig><p>To study the abdominal differences between sexes in terms of morphology and secondary sex characters, we observed the abdomen shape, pleopods, and gonopore of the crablets using a dissecting microscope and scanning electron microscope.</p></sec><sec><title>Identification of Genetic Sex</title><p>The genetic sex of the <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic> crablets was identified following the method designed previously by our laboratory (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). A pair of female-specific primers, designed based on the sex-specific SNP markers, were used to amplify the sex-specific SNP locus, and the female-specific band was checked on agarose gel.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>All data were analyzed with Microsoft Excel 2010 and IBM SPSS 20.0. Results are expressed as mean values with the standard error mean (SEM). Before the statistical analysis, data normality and homoscedasticity test were carried out using the Shapiro&#8211;Wilk test. One-way ANOVA and Tukey's multiple range tests were conducted to distinguish significant differences with statistical significance at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 and high significance at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01. The coefficient of variation (CV) of each trait was estimated using the formula of CV = (standard deviation/mean) &#215; 100%.</p><p>The correlation analysis between morphological traits with sex was performed using Pearson coefficient (two-tailed, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value). The multiple regression equation was constructed, and the determination coefficient was calculated as described by Jiang et al. (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). For the construction of the discriminant function equation, the values of six traits (except CW) were normalized to CW and subsequently subjected to stepwise discriminant analysis by SPSS 20.0.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Difference in Morphological Traits Between Sexes and Their Correlation With Sex</title><p>The crablets of the <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic> were collected at the first day after each molting from stage C I to stage C VIII. The sample size and morphological traits at different stages are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">Supplementary Table 1</xref>. The change in these traits at the successive stages showed the morphological difference between sexes and morphological change during the developmental process. Of the seven morphological traits measured, all indexes increased gradually with the crablets growth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). Apart from that, AW1 and AW2 values exhibited significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01) differences between sexes at stage C VIII. The AW3 and AW4 values of the females were significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01) higher than those of the males from stage C VI. The values of CL, CW, and AW5 showed no differences between sexes.</p><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The size of the <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic> at different stages. C I, C II, C III, C IV, C V, C VI, C VII, and C VIII represent crablets of stages I, II, III, IV, V, VI, VII, and VIII.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-712942-g0002.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Changes and differences of seven traits between females and males during the development of the <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic> crablets. ** represents significant differences at 0.01 level. C I, C II, C III, C IV, C V, C VI, C VII, and C VIII represent crablets of stages I, II, III, IV, V, VI, VII, and VIII. AW1, first abdomen width; AW2, second abdomen width; AW3, third abdomen width; AW4, fourth abdomen width; AW5, fifth abdomen width.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-712942-g0003.jpg"/></fig><p>The genetic sex of 336 crablets (42 crablets per stage) was successfully identified (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref> and <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Although the number of male and female crablets was diverse at different stages, the female:male sex ratio of all crablets was 1:1. Besides, the sex ratio is close to or equal to 1:1 from stage C V to stage C VIII. Correlation analysis indicated that, from stage C I to C V, there was no significant correlation between the seven morphological traits and sex (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). At stage C VI, AW3 and AW4 were highly and significantly correlated with sex (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01), and AW2 was significantly correlated with sex (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). For stage C VII, both AW3 and AW4 were significantly correlated with sex with the correlation coefficient &#8722;0.514 and &#8722;0.609 (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). At stage C VIII, AW1, AW2, AW3, and AW4 were highly and significantly correlated with sex (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Statistics of genetic sex at different development stages of <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic> crablets.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Stage</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Number</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Female</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Male</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Ratio (female/male)</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C I</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C II</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C III</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C IV</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C V</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C VI</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C VII</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C VIII</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">336</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Correlation coefficients between morphological traits and sex at the different development stages.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Stage</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CW</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CL</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AW1</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AW2</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AW3</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AW4</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>AW5</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C I</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.129</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.097</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.180</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.180</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.067</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.067</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.238</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C II</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.035</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.167</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.278</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.132</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.041</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.201</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C III</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.173</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.246</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.282</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.103</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.111</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.219</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C IV</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.199</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.067</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.098</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.162</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.196</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.254</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.054</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C V</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.062</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.205</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.093</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.071</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.170</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.087</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C VI</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.073</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.261</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.071</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.306<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.442<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.426<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.170</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C VII</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.124</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.067</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.301</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.248</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.514<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.609<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.053</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C VIII</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.086</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.100</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.446<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.598<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.804<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.754<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>**</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.068</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><p><italic toggle="yes"><sup>**</sup> and <sup>*</sup> represent significant differences at 0.01 and 0.05 level, respectively</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Determination of Coefficients and Path Coefficients</title><p>Multiple regression analysis and path analysis demonstrated that the seven morphological traits have no significant effects on sex identification from stage C I to stage C V, and the AW1, AW3, and AW4 have significant effects on sex identification from stage C VI to stage C VIII (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01) (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Additionally, AW4 has a more direct impact on sex identification compared with AW1 and AW3. Besides that, CW and AW4 at stage C VII, and CW and AW3 at stage C VIII exhibited significant effects on sex identification (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01). Moreover, the raising determination coefficient indicated that the effects of morphological traits on sex identification were increasing.</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Multiple stepwise regression analysis between the morphological traits and sex at three developmental stages.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Stage</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Trait</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Coefficient</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Direct effect</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Indirect effect</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Determination coefficient (R<sup><bold>2</bold></sup>)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic></bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Multiple regression equation</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C VI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AW1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AW3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.334</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AW1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.071</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.547</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.618</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y = 1.815X<sub>1</sub> &#8211; 1.410X<sub>2</sub> + 2.637</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AW3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.442</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.843</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.401</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C VII</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CW</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AW4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.684</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CW</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.124</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.895</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y = 0.295X<sub>4</sub> &#8211; 1.240X<sub>3</sub> + 0.256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AW4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.609</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;1.306</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.698</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C VIII</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CW</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AW3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.765</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CW</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.086</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.391</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.477</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y = 0.140X<sub>4</sub> &#8211; 1.146X<sub>2</sub> + 2.218</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AW3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.804</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.992</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.188</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">X<sub>1</sub>, the first abdomen width; X<sub>2</sub>, the third abdomen width; X<sub>3</sub>, the fourth abdomen width; X<sub>4</sub>, carapace width; y, sex</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Construction of Discriminant Equations and Their Application</title><p>Given that the morphological traits were significantly related to sex only from stages C VI to C VIII, the values of morphological traits from these stages were used to construct discriminant equations. Five standardized morphological traits (AW1/CW, AW2/CW, AW3/CW, AW4/CW, and AW5/CW) were identified as contributors to Fischer's linear discriminant function of sex identification based on stepwise discriminant analysis. Discriminant equations were established as follows:</p><disp-formula id="E1"><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>138</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>964</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#160;AW</mml:mtext><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CW&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>627</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>625</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#160;AW</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CW</mml:mtext></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>161</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>378</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#160;AW</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CW&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>583</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>418</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#160;AW</mml:mtext><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CW</mml:mtext></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>283</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>938</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#160;AW</mml:mtext><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CW&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>93</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>230</mml:mn><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>277</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>494</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#160;AW</mml:mtext><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CW&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>522</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>555</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#160;AW</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CW</mml:mtext></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>301</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#160;AW</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CW&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>456</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>279</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#160;AW</mml:mtext><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CW</mml:mtext></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>323</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>078</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#160;AW</mml:mtext><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mtext>CW&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>81</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>634</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>If F1 &gt; F2, the candidate was estimated to be female; otherwise, it was male. The reliability assessment of the discriminant equations was conducted using 336 individuals from eight development stages (<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). By comparison with the genetic sex, more than 85% accuracy was detected from stages C VI to C VIII while low accuracy from stages C I to C V, which indicated that the discriminant equations are suitable only from stages C VI to C VIII.</p><table-wrap id="T5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>The accuracy of sex identification at different stages of the <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">paramamosain</italic> crablets.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Stage</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Genetic sex</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Number</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>Predicted</bold>
<bold>sex</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Identification accuracy (%)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total discriminant accuracy (%)</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Female</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Male</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C VIII</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.48</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C VII</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.91</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.71</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C VI</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.95</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.71</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C V</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.91</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.14</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C IV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.14</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.62</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.86</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.61</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Sexual Difference of Secondary Sexual Traits and Abdomen Shape</title><p>According to the genetic sex, the crablets were distinguished to male and female. Secondary sexual traits and their abdomen morphology were observed; as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>, the females shared the triangle-like shape of the abdomen with the males. However, the edges of the female abdomen start converting to a straight line at stage C VI; the counterpart of the male still maintains the original concave features. At stage C VIII, the edges of the female abdomen converted to a convex type line. With this feature, it is easy to distinguish sexes.</p><fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The external morphology of the abdomen at different development stages of male and female <italic toggle="yes">S</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">paramamosain</italic> crablets. F, female; M, male. The black arrows represent the segment where the shape was changed.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-712942-g0004.jpg"/></fig><p>Transformation of pleopods during the development was observed with the scanning electron microscope (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). At stage C I, the female crablet has four pairs of slender uniramous pleopods that vary in length (P1 &gt; P2 &gt; P3 &gt; P4), as well as the males. Secondary sexual characteristics begin to appear at stage C II, in which the slender uniramous pleopods of the female crablets were shortened and transformed to the biramous. In male crablets, P1 and P2 were shortened and metamorphosed into clublike gonopods, while P3 and P4 degenerated and disappeared at stage C II. In the developmental stages from stages C III to C VIII, the pleopods were ever-growing with a constant length ratio in both sexes (P1 &gt; P2 &gt; P3 &gt; P4 for the females and P1 &gt; P2 for the males), and the P2 of the males was metamorphosed finally into the mating organ.</p><fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>The secondary sexual characteristics of the <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic> crablets. C I, C II, C III, C IV, C V, C VI, C VII, and C VIII represent crablets of stages I, II, III, IV, V, VI, VII, and VIII. F, female; M, male; G1 and G2 represent gonopods 1 and 2; P1, P2, P3, and P4 represent pleopods 1, 2, 3, and 4.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-712942-g0005.jpg"/></fig><p>Through the observation of the secondary sex character, a comparative analysis of the gonopores was carried out (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>). The results showed that a pair of gonopores, which were located on the third thoracic segments and near the central axis, were enclosed by the thin cuticle at all stages (from stages C I to C VIII) of the females. Conversely, no gonopore was found at the same position in the males.</p><fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>The gonopore characteristics of the <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic> crablets. F, female; M, male; GP, gonopores. C I, C II, C III, C IV, C V, C VI, C VII, and C VIII represent crablets of stages I, II, III, IV, V, VI, VII, and VIII. 1&#8211;5, first&#8211;fifth thoracic segment.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-712942-g0006.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>In the <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic>, the adult females possess a wider and more rounded abdomen, which covers four pairs of biramous pleopods, compared with the adult males. This pattern of sexual dimorphism in abdomen morphology is in accord with previous observations of other <italic toggle="yes">Scylla</italic> crabs (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). However, the first sign of sexual differentiation in morphology, represented by the beginning of abdominal morphological differentiation and development, is still unclear. The specific time of the sex differentiation in abdominal morphology was herein explored based on the observation and measurement of morphological traits of crablets. The results will provide a simple and effective method to distinguish the sex of mud crab in early development from the external morphology. First, the abdominal morphology of the males and the females was compared and analyzed from stages C I to C VIII. The results demonstrated that the sex of crablets could be first distinguished according to AW3 and AW4 from stage C VI in addition to AW1 and AW2 from stage C VIII. By quantifying the abdominal morphology of crablets, the correlation between abdominal morphology and sex was analyzed by one-way ANOVA. The abdomens of females were significantly rounder than that of males as they grow, with the sexual differences of AW3 and AW4 from stage VI, suggesting that the two morphological traits are significantly correlated with sex (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). The finding in the present study is consistent with the previous research to a certain extent, in which the abdominal segments corresponding to AW3 and AW4 were applied to distinguish sexes (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Significant correlations were found between sex and AW1, AW2, AW3, and AW4, but AW3 and AW4 are the most appropriate morphological traits for sex identification based on the comparison between sexes and one-way ANOVA. Besides, traits AW1, AW3, and AW4 have a significant direct effect on sex identification, which were found from stage C VI to C VIII based on path analysis, suggesting that it is feasible to discriminate sex with the resort to these abdominal morphologies from stage C VI. Our findings here are in accordance with the report by Flores et al. (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>), in which the morphological difference of the abdomen can be used to determine sex when the crablets grow up to a certain stage. Combined with the results of path analysis, stage C VI, which could be adopted to distinguish the sex of crablets, was further determined.</p><p>To ensure the high accuracy of sex identification, the data-based discriminant equations and path analysis were performed to derive the predicting models for estimating the magnitude and significance of causal connections between traits and sex identification (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). In the present study, the sex discriminant equations, applicable to the crablets from stage C VI, were constructed based on standardized morphological traits. Path analysis indicated that the morphological traits AW3 and AW4 have direct impacts on sex identification. In the earlier studies, morphological traits were considered as the key factors affecting body weight in the <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic> crablets and were standardized to establish a reliable and immediate equation for sex identification (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). In conclusion, our study indicated that the morphological traits AW3 and AW4 could be used to identify the sex of crablets from stage C VI.</p><p>The traits directly related to reproduction are frequently observed in many species and have been used as an effective method for sexing (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Gonopore, a reproductive aperture or pore of certain insects and worms, is the reproductive organ that is the remarkable evidence for the sex identification of mud crab in addition to gonopods (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). The results of this study demonstrated that the sex of crablets would be distinguished based on the presence of gonopores or not at stage C I and gonopods at stage C II. This finding is consistent with the research on other decapods. Lee et al. (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) reported that in the crab <italic toggle="yes">Eriocheir japonicus</italic>, the gonopores of the females were visible at stage C I, while the different gonopods in sexes were discerned at stage C III. Sex identification can be implemented at stage C II when the sex differences regarding gonopores and gonopods were observed on <italic toggle="yes">Callinectes sapidus, Rhizocephalan harrisii</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Menippe mercenaria</italic> (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). In summary, the differentiation time of external sexual characteristics of decapods is diverse among different species (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>).</p><p>Although it happened at different stages, the sex-related variation in morphological traits on crablets caters for the need for reproduction of the females who needs to carry their eggs beneath their abdomens until hatching (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Generally, the morphological traits AW3 and AW4 can be regarded as the indicators for sex determination from stage C VI. The sex of crablets could be distinguished based on the presence of gonopores or not at stage C I and gonopod traits at stage C II using a dissecting microscope or scanning electron microscope. Hence, under the circumstance of keeping unstressed and uninjured aquatic animals, the combination of observation and biostatistical analysis will be a powerful method to examine the relationships between a dependent variable (like sex or bodyweight) and two or more independent variables (morphological characteristics).</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In the present study, seven morphological traits were measured during the crablet development stage of the <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic> to research the sexual difference in morphology and morphological change. The correlation analyses between sex and morphological traits indicated that AW3 and AW4 could be implemented to identify sex from stage C VI. A sex discriminant equation was constructed based on the stepwise discriminant analysis and standardized traits, providing a possibility in sex identification of crablets from stage C VI. Path analysis showed that sex identification can be put into practice following the arisen difference of AW3 and AW4 between sexes from stage C VI. Sexes are easily distinguished at stage C VIII according to the abdomen shape, at stage C II based on pleopod difference, and at stage C I based on the presence of gonopores or not.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s9">Supplementary Material</xref>, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author/s.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>WC participated in the experimental design, investigations, data analyses, interpretation, and drafted the manuscript. SF participated in the experimental design and data analysis. LL, ZH, FL, and QW participated in the investigations. HZ, SL, YZ, and MI participated in the manuscript modification. HM participated in the experimental design and provided all materials and reagents. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s8"><title>Publisher's Note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Nos. 31772837 and 42076133), the Leading Talent Project of Special Support Plan of Guangdong Province (No. 2019TX05N067), the Special Projects in Key Fields of Colleges and Universities in Guangdong Province (No. 2020ZDZX1001), the Program of Agricultural and Rural Department of Guangdong Province (No. Yuenong2019B4), and the STU Scientific Research Foundation for Talents (No. NTF17006).</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s9"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2021.712942/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2021.712942/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Figure 1</label><caption><p>Genetic sex identification of some individuals at the different development stages of the <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic> crablets. M, maker, C I, C II, C III, C IV, C V, C VI, C VII, and C VIII represent crablet of stage I, II, III, IV, V, VI, VII, and VIII.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_1.DOCX" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Supplementary Table 1</label><caption><p>Statistics of growth traits in different development stage of the juvenile <italic toggle="yes">S. paramamosain</italic>.</p></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Image_1.TIF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gui</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic basis and biotechnological manipulation of sexual dimorphism and sex determination in fish</article-title>. <source>Sci China Life Sci.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>124</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11427-014-4797-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25563981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farhadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikhwanuddin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The regulatory mechanism of sexual development in decapod crustaceans</article-title>. <source>Front Mar Sci</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>679687</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmars.2021.679687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farhadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikhwanuddin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The significant sex-biased expression pattern of Sp-Wnt4 provides novel insights into the ovarian development of mud crab (Scylla paramamosain)</article-title>. <source>Int J Biol Macromol</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>183</volume>:<fpage>490</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>501</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2021.04.186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33957197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bear</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Both cell-autonomous mechanisms and hormones contribute to sexual development in vertebrates and insects</article-title>. <source>Bioessays.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>725</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bies.201300009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23804281</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prakash</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular mechanisms of secondary sexual trait development in insects</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Insect Sci.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>40</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cois.2016.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27720072</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Waiho</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fazhan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Gonadal microRNA expression profiles and their potential role in sex differentiation and gonadal maturation of mud crab <italic toggle="yes">Scylla paramamosain</italic></article-title>. <source>Mar Biotechnol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>320</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10126-019-09882-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30835008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Waiho</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fazhan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>High-density genetic linkage maps provide novel insights into ZW/ZZ sex determination system and growth performance in mud crab (<italic toggle="yes">Scylla paramamosain</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Front Genet</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>298</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fgene.2019.00298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31024620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6459939</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikhwanuddin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative transcriptome analysis provides insights into differentially expressed genes and long non-coding RNAs between ovary and testis of the mud crab (Scylla paramamosain)</article-title>. <source>Mar Biotechnol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>20</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10126-017-9784-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29152671</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waiho</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Growth performance and biochemical composition dynamics of ovary, hepatopancreas and muscle tissues at different ovarian maturation stages of female mud crab, <italic toggle="yes">Scylla paramamosain</italic></article-title>. <source>Aquaculture</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>515</volume>:<fpage>734560</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquaculture.2019.734560</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waiho</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikhwanuddin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Female-specific SNP markers provide insights into a WZ/ZZ sex determination system for mud crabs <italic toggle="yes">Scylla paramamosain, S tranquebarica</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">S serrata</italic> with a rapid method for genetic sex identification</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>981</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-018-5380-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30594128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6311006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Different biochemical composition and nutritional value attribute to salinity and rearing period in male and female mud crab <italic toggle="yes">Scylla paramamosain</italic></article-title>. <source>Aquaculture</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>513</volume>:<fpage>734417</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquaculture.2019.734417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farhadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Integrative transcriptome sequencing reveals the molecular difference of maturation process of ovary and testis in mud crab <italic toggle="yes">Scylla paramamosain</italic></article-title>. <source>Front Mar Sci</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>658091</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmars.2021.658091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Waiho</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fazhan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quinitio</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baylon</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujaya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Azmie</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Larval rearing of mud crab (Scylla): what lies ahead</article-title>. <source>Aquaculture.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>493</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquaculture.2018.04.047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waiho</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aweya</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fazhan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative analysis of growth performance between female and male mud crab <italic toggle="yes">Scylla paramamosain</italic> crablets: evidences from a four-month successive growth experiment</article-title>. <source>Aquaculture.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>505</volume>:<fpage>351</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquaculture.2019.02.062</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mantelatto</surname><given-names>FLM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinell</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Relative growth and sexual dimorphism of the South Atlantic hermit crab Loxopagurus loxochelis (Anomura, Diogenidae) from Ubatuba, Brazil</article-title>. <source>J Nat Hist.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>429</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>37</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/002229301300009621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Satake</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Difference in body size and sexual dimorphism in the Ogasawara mitten crab, Eriocheir ogasawaraensis, and the Japanese mitten crab, Eriocheir japonica</article-title>. <source>Pac Sci.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>71</volume>:<fpage>171</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>88</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2984/71.2.6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peir,&#243;</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baeza</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mantelatto</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Host-use pattern and sexual dimorphism reveals the mating system of the symbiotic pea crab Austinixa aidae (Crustacea: Brachyura: Pinnotheridae)</article-title>. <source>J Mar Biol Assoc UK.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>93</volume>:<fpage>715</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0025315412000720</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>ZG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Morphological attributes and quality parameters of different sexes of <italic toggle="yes">Eriocheir sinensis</italic> cultured in a pond</article-title>. <source>Prog Fish Sci.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>114</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.19663/j.issn2095-9869.20180914001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Archdale</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sexual traits and reproductive strategy of the leucosiid crab <italic toggle="yes">Pyrhila pisum</italic></article-title>. <source>J Mar Biol Assoc UK</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0025315420000776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Charniaux-Cotton</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sex differentiation</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walterman</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group> editor. <source>The Physiology of Crustacea</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY, London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name> (<year>1960</year>). p. <fpage>411</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>47</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamauchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamauchi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sex differentiation in the crab <italic toggle="yes">Eriocheir japonicus</italic> (Decapoda, Grapsidae)</article-title>. <source>Invertebr Reprod Dev.</source> (<year>1994</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>37</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07924259.1994.9672377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Preliminary studies on sexual differentiation of larval Scylla serrata</article-title>. <source>J Oceanogra Taiwan Strait.</source> (<year>1994</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>284</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>BQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>FY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The relationship between morphometric characters and body weight of Portunus trituberculatus</article-title>. <source>Mar Fish Res.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4238/TWHX.0.1994-03-010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>ZG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Characteristics of growth traits and their effects on baby weight of G1 individuals in the mud crab (Scylla paramamosain)</article-title>. <source>Genet Mol Res.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>6050</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4238/2014.August.7.19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25117362</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Differences in External Morphology and Population Dynamics Among the Megalopae of Four Scylla Species</source>. <publisher-loc>Taiwan</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>NSYSU</publisher-name> (<year>2002</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keenan</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lavery</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davie</surname><given-names>PJF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Genetics and morphology distinguish three species of mud crab, genus <italic toggle="yes">Scylla</italic></article-title>. In: <source>Proceedings 2nd World Fisheries Congress</source>, Brisbane. (<year>1996</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tongdee</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Size distribution, sex ratio and size at maturity of mud crab (Scylla spp) in Ranong Province, Thailand</article-title>. <source>Asian Fish Sci.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4238/10021917986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>AAV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>FPL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Negreiros-Fransozo</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Postlarval stages and growth patterns of the spider crab Pyromaia Tuberculata (Brachyura, Majidae) from laboratory-reared material</article-title>. <source>J Crustac Biol.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>314</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1163/20021975-99990238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasriel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swanson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Interactive Path Analysis</source>. United States Patent Application (<year>2003</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malison</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Held</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaatz</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sex determination of yellow perch by external morphology</article-title>. <source>N Am J Aquacult.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>73</volume>:<fpage>285</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15222055.2011.601983</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taketomi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwamasa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Iwanaga</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Androgenic gland and external sexual characteristics of the intersexual male of the freshwater crab <italic toggle="yes">Geothelphusa dehaani</italic></article-title>. <source>Crusta Res</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18353/crustacea.36.0_15</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Payen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Morphology, histology, ultrastructure, and organogenesis of the androgenic glands in crustacea</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group>, editor. <source>Recent Advances in Comparative Arthropod Morphology, Physiology and Development.</source><volume>Vol. 2.</volume><publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Rutgers University Press</publisher-name> (<year>1990</year>). p. <fpage>439</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>72</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Morphological variation of freshwater crabs zilchiopsis collastinensis and trichodactylus borellianus (Decapoda, Trichodactylidae) among localities from the middle paran&#225; river basin during different hydrological periods</article-title>. <source>ZooKeys.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>457</volume>:<fpage>171</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>86</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zookeys.457.6726</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4283370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25561836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Baeza</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spadaro</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Behringer</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sexual dimorphism, allometry, and size at first maturity of the Caribbean king crab, Mithrax spinosissimus, in the Florida Keys</article-title>. <source>J Shellfish Res.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>909</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2983/035.031.0401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>