<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8520915</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8520915.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8520915</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8520915</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34671662</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.746809</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Antibacterial Properties of Canine Platelet-Rich Plasma and Other Non-Transfusional Hemo-Components: An <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> Study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Attili</surname><given-names initials="AR">Anna-Rita</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/517858/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iacoucci</surname><given-names initials="C">Cristina</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Serri</surname><given-names initials="E">Evelina</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuteri</surname><given-names initials="V">Vincenzo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/472710/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cantalamessa</surname><given-names initials="A">Andrea</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Linardi</surname><given-names initials="M">Martina</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rifici</surname><given-names initials="C">Claudia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazzullo</surname><given-names initials="G">Giuseppe</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names initials="G">Giacomo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/659184/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galosi</surname><given-names initials="L">Livio</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1068782/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tambella</surname><given-names initials="AM">Adolfo Maria</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/999331/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Laboratory of Medical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, School of Biosciences and Veterinary Medicine, University of Camerino</institution>, <addr-line>Matelica</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Veterinary Teaching Hospital, School of Biosciences and Veterinary Medicine, University of Camerino</institution>, <addr-line>Matelica</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Pathology Laboratory, Department of Veterinary Sciences, University of Messina</institution>, <addr-line>Messina</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Pathology Laboratory, School of Biosciences and Veterinary Medicine, University of Camerino</institution>, <addr-line>Matelica</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Roberta Perego, University of Milan, Italy</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Piera Anna Martino, University of Milan, Italy; Livia Camargo Garbin, The University of the West Indies St. Augustine, Trinidad and Tobago</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Adolfo Maria Tambella <email>adolfomaria.tambella@unicam.it</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Comparative and Clinical Medicine, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn002"><p>&#8224;These authors have contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>04</day><month>10</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">374996</issue-id><elocation-id>746809</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>8</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>19</day><month>10</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-01-11 05:25:15.280"><day>11</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2021 Attili, Iacoucci, Serri, Cuteri, Cantalamessa, Linardi, Rifici, Mazzullo, Rossi, Galosi and Tambella.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Attili, Iacoucci, Serri, Cuteri, Cantalamessa, Linardi, Rifici, Mazzullo, Rossi, Galosi and Tambella</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-08-746809.pdf"/><abstract><p>This <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> study was carried out to evaluate the potential antibacterial properties of canine non-transfusional hemo-components. Therapeutic formulations commonly used for regenerative medicine purposes (platelet-rich plasma, platelet gel, platelet lysate, fibrin glue), considering both leukocyte-rich and leukocyte-poor formulations, but also platelet-poor plasma and activating substances (thrombin, calcium gluconate), were tested to detect elements with potential antimicrobial properties. The antibacterial effect was tested on different bacterial strains (<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> subspecies <italic toggle="yes">aureus, Staphylococcus cohnii</italic> subspecies <italic toggle="yes">cohnii, Escherichia coli, Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> subspecies <italic toggle="yes">pneumoniae</italic>) isolated from canine wounds and classified as susceptible, multidrug-, extensively, and pandrug-resistant bacteria toward a known panel of human and veterinary antibiotics. The evaluation was carried out by agar gel diffusion method (Kirby&#8211;Bauer) and micro-inhibition in broth using microplates and spectrophotometer reading. The study findings confirmed the hypothesized antibacterial properties of canine non-transfusional hemo-components. A more effective bacteriostatic effect was found against Gram-negative bacteria, drug-resistant too. The presence of leukocytes or platelets does not appear to be essential for the antibacterial effect. Further studies should be conducted to evaluate the exact mechanism of action of the antimicrobial activity. However, non-transfusional hemo-components could be a useful natural aid in controlling bacterial infections in dogs.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>platelet-rich plasma</kwd><kwd>platelet-poor plasma</kwd><kwd>platelet lysate</kwd><kwd>platelet concentrates</kwd><kwd>leucocytes</kwd><kwd>antibacterial effect</kwd><kwd>dogs</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001"><institution-wrap><institution>Universit&#224; degli Studi di Camerino</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100010739</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="8"/><table-count count="5"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="89"/><page-count count="15"/><word-count count="11356"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Antimicrobial resistance (AMR) is a multifaceted topic at the interface of human, animal, and plant health, food hygiene, and environmental sciences, resulting to be a major global public health issue of the 21st century (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>).</p><p>To counter this increasing phenomenon, both in human and in veterinary medicine, more and more scientists are looking for molecules that can assist or replace the action of antibiotics. The topical use of non-transfusional hemo-components or autologous platelet concentrates (PCs), including platelet-rich plasma (PRP), platelet gel (PG), platelet lysate (PL), and fibrin glue (FG), has gained great popularity during the past 20 years; thus, they have been used, mainly for their regenerative properties, in a variety of human medical fields such as orthopedics (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), wound healing (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), ophthalmology (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), and dentistry (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Despite a recent growing interest, fewer <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> studies in dogs have been published (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>).</p><p>While the potential regenerative effect of PCs has been extensively studied, fewer studies have investigated the possible relationship with bacterial growth. Some authors have empirically supposed that PCs could promote infections, associating them with microbiological culture media and acting as a substrate for the growth of bacteria (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). More recently, on the contrary to this theory, some evidence would attribute to PCs an inhibitory effect on bacterial growth, although the results cannot be considered definitive yet (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). The antibacterial properties of PCs are supported by some <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> studies conducted mostly in humans (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>), but also in horses (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>) and rabbits (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Systematic reviews of current literature considering <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>, preclinical, and clinical studies have shown that PCs may have antibacterial properties (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>).</p><p>The antibacterial effect of PCs has also been recently highlighted in <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> studies on surgical wounds (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>), sternotomy wounds (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>, <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>), osteomyelitis (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>), spinal infections (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>), and bacterial cystitis (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>), while another <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> study showed controversial results (<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>). Since infection control is a prerequisite for the wound healing process and for avoiding the chronicization event, recently, in a small controlled clinical trial performed in dogs, MRSA-infected skin wounds treated with PRP showed an accelerated healing process with rapid re-epithelialization and granulation tissue formation, reduction of inflammation, and decrease of bacterial loads (<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>).</p><p>Until now, the components of the PCs that control antimicrobial activity have not been fully understood, so the mechanisms of PC interaction with bacteria need further investigation.</p><p>In order to detect any elements potentially endowed with antimicrobial properties, we explored the antimicrobial activity of PCs (PRP, PG, PL, FG) against susceptible (S), multidrug-resistant (MDR) extensively drug-resistant (XDR), and pandrug-resistant (PDR) Gram-positive and Gram-negative microorganisms isolated from canine wounds. In this set of <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> investigations, leukocyte-rich (L-PRP, L-PG) and leukocyte-poor formulations (P-PRP, P-PG), but also platelet-poor plasma (L-PPP, P-PPP) and intermediate elements of the PC production process (thrombin, calcium gluconate), were evaluated.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Animals and Blood Collection</title><p>The study was performed complying with the Animal Welfare Body of the University of Camerino (protocol number E81AC.10/A) according to the National Legislative Decree n. 26/2014, implementation of EU Directive 2010/63/EU. Blood was collected from five owned dogs at the Veterinary Teaching Hospital, School of Biosciences and Veterinary Medicine, University of Camerino. The owner's informed consent was obtained for participation in the study. All animals were between 1 and 10 years of age, had a minimum body weight of 15 kg, and belonged to different dog breeds (three mixed breed, one Labrador retriever, one English setter). They had no noteworthy medical problems or medical history, except for degenerative joint disease, and did not take any medications. An articular infiltration of autologous PRP was practiced in each dog for the management of degenerative joint disease; an aliquot of whole blood in excess of the amount needed for PRP preparation was used for the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> investigations of the present study. Each dog, upon admission, had a complete physical examination, complete blood count, and serum biochemical profile. No animals had platelet disorders or took anticoagulant and antibiotic drugs.</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of Hemo-Components</title><p>In each dog, fresh autologous whole blood (50 ml) was collected from the jugular vein using a 60-ml syringe containing anticoagulant citrate dextrose solution A (ACD-A: SALF SpA, Cenate Sotto, Bergamo, Italy) in a ratio of 1:9. Blood collection and preparation procedures were performed as described by Tambella and collaborators (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) in aseptic conditions through a laminar flow cabin (Bicasa, Bernareggio, MB, Italy) and following the Good Laboratory Practices. The hemo-components were obtained from a pool of fresh canine whole blood. Prior to preparation of each hemo-component, an aliquot was used to determine the blood cell count.</p><sec><title>Autologous Thrombin</title><p>The thrombin-rich solution was obtained from autologous whole blood which was centrifuged (Rotina 46R, Hettich, Milan, Italy) at 650 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 10 min. The plasma supernatant fraction was mixed with 10% calcium gluconate (B. Braun, Melsungen, Germany) in a ratio of 5:1 and incubated (cooled incubator IL 23R, VWR Incu-Line, Milan, Italy) at 37&#176;C for 30 min. The resulting clot was crushed, and the final supernatant, the thrombin-rich solution, was collected for PRP activation.</p></sec><sec><title>Leukocyte-Rich -PPP, -PRP, and -PG</title><p>As described by Tambella et al. (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), leukocyte-rich platelet-poor plasma (L-PPP), leukocyte PRP (L-PRP), and leukocyte PG (L-PG) were obtained by a double-spin technique. Whole blood was centrifuged (Rotina 46R, Hettich, Milan, Italy) at 180 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 20 min. To stratify the concentrated platelet pellet in the bottom layer, and platelet poor plasma (L-PPP) in the supernatant layer, the plasma with the buffy coat layer was centrifuged at 650 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 15 min. A half amount of L-PPP was picked up and used for the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> study. By resuspending the PCs in the residual part of PPP, the L-PRP was obtained. A half amount of L-PRP was used for the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> study; to obtain L-PG, the residual L-PRP was transferred in sterile glass Petri dishes and mixed with the thrombin-rich solution and the calcium gluconate in a volumetric ratio of 8:1:0.5. The L-PG production was achieved at room temperature in 5 min.</p></sec><sec><title>Leukocyte-Poor (Pure) -PPP, -PRP, and -PG</title><p>Pure platelet-poor plasma (P-PPP), pure platelet-rich plasma (P-PRP), and pure platelet gel (P-PG) were obtained by a double-spin technique. In order to reduce the leukocyte concentration as much as possible, the first centrifugation of whole blood was performed at 500 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 20 min using tubes (VF108SAS Venosafe, Terumo Europe NV, Leuven, Belgium) containing a gel enabling the separation of the different blood components. The plasma fraction was then centrifuged at 2,000 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 10 min to achieve separation of P-PPP (the supernatant half-fraction) from P-PRP (the residual half-fraction). Similarly, P-PG was obtained by mixing P-PRP with the autologous thrombin-rich solution and calcium gluconate.</p></sec><sec><title>FG</title><p>Fibrinogen concentrate, the precursor of FG, was obtained following the method proposed by Tarantino et al. (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>). This method is characterized by physical separation (centrifugation) and the presence of a special membrane, capable of concentrating fibrinogen. After centrifugation of whole blood (2,000 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 10 min), the plasma fraction obtained without buffy coat was transferred in special tubes (Amicon Ultra 15, Merck Millipore Ltd, Tullagreen, Carrigtwohill, Co Cork, Ireland) with a 100,000 MWCO (molecular weight cutoff) porosity filter. Then, tubes were centrifuged at 3,600 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 45 min and the fibrinogen concentrate above the filter was obtained.</p></sec><sec><title>PL</title><p>PL was produced as reported in previous studies with some modifications (<xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>, <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>). Using a two-step centrifugation protocol (180 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 20 minutes and 1,500 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 10 minutes), packed PC was produced from whole blood with ACD-A. To remove platelet membranes and other cellular debris and obtain the PL, three repeated cycles of freezing (at &#8722;20&#176;C) and thawing (at room temperature) followed by centrifugation at 2,500 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 20 min were undergone obtaining the PL as supernatant.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Evaluation of Antibacterial Activity</title><sec><title>Bacterial Strains and Their Antibiotic Susceptibility Evaluation</title><p>To compare the antibacterial effect of each hemo-component, strains isolated from canine wounds were selected from the bacterial collection of the Laboratory of Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, School of Bioscience and Veterinary Medicine, University of Camerino, based on their ability to cause also infections in the surgical setting.</p><p>Three different frozen strains of <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> subspecies <italic toggle="yes">aureus</italic>, one <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus cohnii</italic> subspecies <italic toggle="yes">cohnii</italic>, three <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> subspecies <italic toggle="yes">pneumoniae</italic>, two <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, and three <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> strains were thawed and reconstituted. In addition, <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> subspecies <italic toggle="yes">aureus</italic> ATCC&#174; 43300<sup>&#8482;</sup> strain was used as control. After pre-enrichment in Tryptic Soy Broth (TSB) (Liofilchem, Roseto degli Abruzzi, Italy) and incubation at 37&#176;C for 6 h in aerobic condition, a loop was shown on Columbia Blood Agar (Liofilchem, Italy), Mannitol Salt Agar (Liofilchem, Italy), MacConkey Agar (Liofilchem, Italy), and Pseudomonas Cetrimide Agar (Liofilchem, Italy) and incubated aerobically at 37&#176;C for 24 h. Colonies were identified and confirmed by MALDI-TOF MS (Bruker Daltonics, Hamburg, Germany).</p><p>In order to determine their antibiotic susceptibility profile and classify the strains as susceptible, MDR, XDR, and PDR (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>), antimicrobial susceptibility testing toward 16 commercial human and veterinary antibiotics, belonging to eight different classes, was performed according to the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute and EUCAST guidelines (<xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>, <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>).The standard disk diffusion method (Kirby&#8211;Bauer test) was used to test amoxicillin and clavulanic acid (AUG 30 &#956;g), penicillin (P 1 UI), oxacillin (OX 1 &#956;g), cefadroxil (CDX 30 &#956;g), cefoxitin (CFX 30 &#956;g), cefquinome (CEQ 30 &#956;g), enrofloxacin (ENR 5 &#956;g), gentamicin (CN 10 &#956;g), sulfamethoxazole and trimethoprim (SXT 25 &#956;g), tetracycline (TE 30 &#956;g), amikacin (AK 30 &#956;g), streptomycin (S 300 &#956;g), metronidazole (M 50 &#956;g), and polymyxin B (PB 300 &#956;g). The E-test method was used for <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus</italic> strains to determine the MICs against vancomycin (VA), and teicoplanin (TEC), as described by the manufacturer (MIC Test Strip, Liofilchem, Italy).</p></sec><sec><title>Antibacterial <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> Evaluation of Hemo-Components</title><p>To evaluate the antibacterial effect of different hemo-components and activating agents (PL, FG, thrombin, L-PPP, P-PPP, L-PRP with calcium gluconate, P-PRP with calcium gluconate, L-PRP with thrombin, P-PRP with thrombin, L-PG 35 &#956;l, P-PG 35 &#956;l, L-PG 500 &#956;l, and P-PG 500 &#956;l), the Kirby&#8211;Bauer disk diffusion method and the broth inhibition by microtiter method were performed.</p><sec><title>Kirby&#8211;Bauer Disk Diffusion Method</title><p>Following the CLSI (2018) recommendations (<xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>), each microorganism was suspended in sterile saline solution (Thermo Fisher, Milan, Italy) to obtain an optical density equal to 0.5 McFarland (1 &#215; 10<sup>8</sup> CFU/ml), verified at 550 nm by a spectrophotometer (Jenway, Genova Nano, Bibby Scientific, Staffordshire, UK). A sterile cotton swab was dipped into the inoculum suspension and the excess fluid removed by turning the swab against the inside of the tube to avoid over-inoculation of plates. The inoculum was spread evenly over the entire surface of the Mueller Hinton II agar plate (MH; Liofilchem, Italy) by swabbing in three directions. Each hemo-component was placed by a micropipette (PIPETMAN L P20L 2&#8211;20 &#956;l, Gilson, Milan, Italy) on the surface of the media, in contact with the microorganisms to reduce as much as possible the variables that could influence their actions against bacteria. Specifically, four different Petri dishes were used to test hemo-components with and without leukocytes against each microorganism.</p><p>The amount of each liquid hemo-component was 8 &#956;l, except for PG, tested at 35 and 500 &#956;k, in the pre-jellification phase. Positive controls were performed inoculating the microbial suspension (McFarland 0.5) on MH (Liofilchem, Italy) alone, whereas the same media inoculated with saline solution or hemo-components, with and without leukocytes only, represented the negative controls. The assay was conducted in duplicate and repeated twice. All plates were incubated at 37&#176;C aerobically and evaluated after 4, 8, and 24 h. For each strain, areas (mm) with bacterial inhibition or areas with few bacterial colonies were compared to the respective positive control.</p></sec><sec><title>Broth Inhibition by Microtiter Method</title><p>The antibacterial activity was determined using the broth inhibition by microtiter method. Bacterial strains have been grown in Tryptic Soy Broth (Liofilchem, Italy) at 37&#176;C for 6 h, aerobically. The final inoculum concentration was adjusted using a spectrophotometer (Jenway, Genova Nano, Bibby Scientific, Staffordshire, UK) to 1 &#215; 10<sup>4</sup> CFU/ml (OD<sub>540nm</sub>), and 20 &#956;l of each bacterial suspension was inoculated into a 96-well microtiter plate (Sero-Wel&#174;, Bibby Sterilin Ltd., UK) containing 10 &#956;l of each hemo-component (PL, FG, L-PRP, P-PRP, L-PRP plus thrombin, P-PRP plus thrombin, L-PRP plus calcium gluconate, P-PRP plus calcium gluconate, L-PPP, P-PPP) and 170 &#956;l of sterile TSB. Quantities of 10, 20, 40, and 180 &#956;l were used for pre-jellification L-PG and P-PG to test the antimicrobial activity toward 20 &#956;l of each bacterial suspension. Each well was tested with the respective negative control represented by the same quantities of the hemo-components only. Positive controls with 20 &#956;l of each bacterial suspension in 170 &#956;l of sterile TSB were considered. As a blank negative control, an amount of 170 &#956;l of sterile TSB was placed in the first and last wells of each plate. In addition, wells containing only each hemo-component were used as negative controls. No 0.01% acetic acid was added to prevent peptide aggregation and release of platelet contents. The microtiter plates were incubated at 37&#176;C aerobically under slow and continuous agitation (300 g/minute) (Asal 715, Milano, Italy) and evaluated after 4, 18, and 24 h of incubation. A visual assessment (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>) was conducted after 4 h, while at 18 and 24 h the observations were read using a spectrophotometer (Multiskan Ascent, Thermo Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA), at a wavelength of 540 nm. The test was repeated twice.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>All experiments were performed in duplicate. Statistical differences between quantitative variables (mean OD<sub>540nm</sub>) were evaluated with Student's <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test. To determine the antimicrobial activity, the mean optical density (OD<sub>540nm</sub>) value recorded for each microorganism and the hemo-component, less the OD<sub>540nm</sub> value recorded for each hemo-component, was compared to the respective positive controls recorded at the same time. Mean OD values for the different bacteria (susceptible or drug-resistant Gram-positive and Gram-negative strains) and recorded at different times (18&#8211;24 h) were analyzed with and without the leukocyte component.</p><p>Finally, the mean OD values of bacterial concentrations in the presence of hemo-components with leukocytes were compared with the mean OD values observed in the presence of hemo-components without leukocytes. STATA version 13.0 (STATA Corporation, College Station, TX, USA) was used to conduct the statistical analysis. A <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value less than 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Preparation of Hemo-Components and Whole Blood and Hemo-Component Cell Counts</title><p>No technical problems occurred during the preparation of non-transfusional hemo-components. Each hemo-component was easily produced using common laboratory tools and was ready for use in this <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> study. Cell concentrations were appropriate for the specific characteristics requested for each hemo-component.</p><p>In L-PRP and L-PG, platelet concentrations increased by 4.3-fold and leukocyte concentrations increased 2.1-fold compared with whole blood (WB) baseline values.</p><p>In L-PPP, platelet count decreased approximately 142-fold compared with L-PRP and leukocytes decreased approximately 45-fold.</p><p>As expected, the pure formulations (P-PRP, P-PG, and P-PPP) were leukocyte-depleted. Platelet concentrations in P-PRP and P-PG increased 2.2-fold from WB.</p><p>Both platelet and leukocyte concentrations were very low in P-PPP and FG.</p><p>There were no detectable blood cells in PL.</p><p>The mean number of platelets and white blood cells obtained by blood count analysis from the WB pool and the different hemo-components are reported in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Leukocyte and platelet concentrations obtained from whole blood (pool of 250 ml from five dogs) and each hemo-component.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="9" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>Cell count evaluation</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>WB</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>L-PRP/L-PG</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>L-PPP</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>P-PRP/P-PG</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>P-PPP</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>FG</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>PL</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>T</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>WBC</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.71</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>PLT</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1139</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">583</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">WBC = number of leukocytes &#215;10<sup>3</sup>/&#956;l; PLT = number of platelets &#215;10<sup>3</sup>/&#956;l; WB, whole blood (pool of 250 ml); L-PRP, leukocyte platelet-rich plasma; L-PG, leukocyte platelet gel; L-PPP, leukocyte platelet-poor plasma (L-PPP); P-PRP, pure platelet-rich plasma; P-PG, pure platelet gel; P-PPP, pure platelet-poor plasma; FG, fibrin glue; PL, platelet lysate; T, thrombin-rich solution; nd, not detectable</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Bacterial Strains and Their Antibiotic Susceptibility Evaluation</title><p>Among the selected Gram-positive and Gram-negative microorganisms, different susceptibility profiles were observed and classified (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) (<xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>). One strain of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> subspecies <italic toggle="yes">aureus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. cohnii</italic> subspecies <italic toggle="yes">cohnii</italic>, one strain of <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> subspecies <italic toggle="yes">pneumoniae</italic>, and one strain of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> resulted to be susceptible to the panel of antibiotics, and one strain of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> subspecies <italic toggle="yes">aureus, P. aeruginosa, K. pneumoniae</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">pneumoniae</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> were MDR, while one strain of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> subspecies <italic toggle="yes">aureus, K. pneumoniae</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">pneumoniae</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> resulted to be extensively drug-resistant. Only one strain of <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> was PDR.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Antimicrobial resistance profiles of microorganisms selected and identified by MALDI-TOF MS from canine wounds.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Bacterial species</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Resistance profiles</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>S</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>MDR</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>XDR</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>PDR</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">aureus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ENR-TE</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">S. cohnii</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">cohnii</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUG-P-OX</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">pneumoniae</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SXT-M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">aureus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-ENR-SXT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">pneumoniae</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUG-P-TE-M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SXT-TE-M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ENR-SXT-TE-M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">aureus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUG-OX-P-CDX-CFX- ENR-SXT-TE-S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">pneumoniae</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUG-P-CDX-CFX- ENR-SXT-TE-S-M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUG-P-CDX-CFX-CEQ-ENR-SXT-TE-S-M</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AUG-P-CDX-CFX-CEQ-ENR-CN-SXT-TE-AK-S-M-PB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">MALDI-TOF MS, matrix-assisted laser desorption ionization-time-of-flight mass spectrometry; S, susceptible; MDR, multidrug-resistant; XDR, extensively drug-resistant; PDR, pandrug-resistant; AUG 30 &#956;g, amoxicillin and clavulanic acid; OX 1 &#956;g, oxacillin; P 1 UI, penicillin G; CDX 30 &#956;g, cefadroxil; CFX 30 &#956;g, cefoxitin; CEQ 30 &#956;g, cefquinome; ENR 5 &#956;g, enrofloxacin; CN 10 &#956;g, gentamicin; SXT 25 &#956;g, sulfamethoxazole and trimethoprim; TE 30 &#956;g, tetracycline; AK 30 &#956;g, amikacin; S 300 &#956;g, streptomycin; M 50 &#956;g, metronidazole; PB 300 &#956;g, polymyxin B; MIC VA, vancomycin; MIC TEC, teicoplanin</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Antibacterial Effect Evaluation of the Hemo-Components</title><sec><title>Kirby&#8211;Bauer Method</title><p>After 4 h of incubation at 37&#176;C under aerobic conditions, no inhibition zones were observed for Gram-positive bacteria. Among Gram-negative microorganisms, some inhibition zones were observed for susceptible <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> strains cultured with P-PG and L-PG. In particular, increased mean inhibition zones of 2.5 &#215; 4.5 mm, 7.5 &#215; 10 mm, and 8.5 &#215; 50 mm were recorded for P-PG 35 &#956;l, P-PG 500 &#956;l, and L-PG 500 &#956;l, respectively (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>L-PG 500 &#956;l effect against susceptible <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">pneumoniae</italic> strain after 4 h at 37&#176;C aerobically.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-746809-g0001.jpg"/></fig><p>The MDR <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">pneumoniae</italic> strain showed a zone of inhibition to all hemo-components, except for calcium gluconate, and P-PRP plus calcium and thrombin (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). PG showed a greater antibacterial effect, although non-significant differences were recorded between hemo-components both with and without leukocytes.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Inhibition zones recorded by each hemo-component for multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">pneumoniae</italic> after 4 h of incubation using the Kirby&#8211;Bauer method.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Hemo-components</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Inhibition zone (mm)</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platelet lysate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 &#215; 10</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fibrin glue</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 &#215; 12</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PRP</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 &#215; 9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-PRP</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 &#215; 9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PRP plus thrombin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5 &#215; 9.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-PRP plus thrombin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 &#215; 9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PRP plus calcium gluconate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 &#215; 10</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PPP</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5 &#215; 10</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-PPP</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 &#215; 9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PG 35 &#956;l</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 &#215; 20</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-PG 35 &#956;l</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 &#215; 18</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PG 500 &#956;l</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 &#215; 45</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-PG 500 &#956;l</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 &#215; 64</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">L-PRP, leukocyte platelet-rich plasma; P-PRP, pure platelet-rich plasma; L-PPP, leukocyte platelet-poor plasma; P-PPP, pure platelet-poor plasma: L-PG, leukocyte platelet gel; P-PG: pure platelet gel</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">pneumoniae</italic> inhibition zones by leukocyte-formulations after 4 h at 37&#176;C aerobically. 1: platelet lysate; 2: thrombin; 3: L-PRP; 4: L-PRP plus thrombin; 5: L-PRP plus calcium gluconate; 6: L-PPP; in the center of the plate: L-PG.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-746809-g0002.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">pneumoniae</italic> inhibition zones by pure formulations after 4 h at 37&#176;C aerobically. 1: fibrin glue; 2: calcium gluconate; 3: P-PRP; 4: P-PRP plus thrombin; 5: P-PRP plus calcium gluconate; 6: P-PPP; in the center of the plate: P-PG.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-746809-g0003.jpg"/></fig><p>For extensively drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">pneumoniae</italic> strains, inhibition zones of 2 &#215; 3.5 mm, 4.5 &#215; 37.5 mm, and 5 &#215; 38 mm were observed for P-PG 35 &#956;l, P-PG 500 &#956;l, and L-PG 500 &#956;l, respectively.</p><p>The L-PG 500 &#956;l showed an antibacterial effect against the pan drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> by recording an inhibition zone of 16.5 &#215; 43 mm. Moreover, all the hemo-components gave areas of bacterial inhibition, except for thrombin and L-PRP with calcium gluconate against the extensively drug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strain, while P-PPP and P-PG 35 &#956;l, P-PG 500 &#956;l, and L-PG 500 &#956;l inhibited the growth of MDR and susceptible <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>.</p><p>The spectrophotometer reading after 18 h confirmed what was recorded after 4 h of incubation and revealed more defined inhibition zones. In particular, compared to the respective bacterial positive control, significantly reduced areas of bacterial growth (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) were observed for the hemo-components against Gram-negative strains (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>, <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Leukocyte-formulations against the extensively resistant <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> after 18 h at 37&#176;C aerobically. 1: platelet lysate; 2: thrombin; 3: L-PRP; 4: L-PRP plus thrombin; 5: L-PRP plus calcium gluconate; 6: L-PPP; 7: L-PG.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-746809-g0004.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Inhibition zones (mm) recorded for Gram-negative bacteria after 18 h of incubation using the Kirby&#8211;Bauer method.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Hemo-components</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="6" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>Inhibition zones (mm)</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">
<bold>K. pneumoniae</bold>
</italic>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">
<bold>E. coli</bold>
</italic>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">
<bold>P. aeruginosa</bold>
</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>MDR</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>XDR</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>MDR</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>XDR</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>MDR</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>PDR</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platelet lysate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 &#215; 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 &#215; 9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 &#215; 4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 &#215; 6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fibrin glue</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 &#215; 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 &#215; 10</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thrombin</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 &#215; 8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 &#215; 5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PRP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 &#215; 8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 &#215; 10.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5 &#215; 7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 &#215; 9.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-PRP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 &#215; 9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 &#215; 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PRP plus thrombin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 &#215; 9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 &#215; 12.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 &#215; 6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 &#215; 7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-PRP plus thrombin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 &#215; 9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 &#215; 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-PRP plus calcium gluconate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 &#215; 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PRP plus calcium gluconate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 &#215; 9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 &#215; 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 &#215; 4.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 &#215; 7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PPP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 &#215; 9.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 &#215; 10.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 &#215; 7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 &#215; 9.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-PPP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 &#215; 9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 &#215; 10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 &#215; 8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PG 35 &#956;l</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 &#215; 20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 &#215; 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 &#215; 10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5 &#215; 18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 &#215; 12</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-PG 35 &#956;l</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 &#215; 18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PG 500 &#956;l</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 &#215; 45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 &#215; 20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5 &#215; 10.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 &#215; 10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.5 &#215; 20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 &#215; 22</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-PG 500 &#956;l</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 &#215; 64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">L-PRP, leukocyte platelet-rich plasma; P-PRP, pure platelet-rich plasma; L-PPP, leukocyte platelet-poor plasma; P-PPP, pure platelet-poor plasma; L-PG, leukocyte platelet gel; P-PG, pure platelet gel</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>After 18 h of incubation, L-PG 35 &#956;l, L-PG 500 &#956;l, and P-PG 500 &#956;l also showed a significant antibacterial effect (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) against Gram-positive bacteria. Inhibition zones of 4 &#215; 10 mm, 19 &#215; 26 mm, and 50 &#215; 22 mm were recorded for susceptible <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">aureus</italic> in the presence of L-PG 35 &#956;l, L-PG 500 &#956;l, and P-PG 500 &#956;l, respectively. <italic toggle="yes">S. cohnii</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">cohnii</italic> susceptible to the panel of antibiotics tested resulted to be inhibited by P-PG 500 &#956;l (4 &#215; 17.5 mm).</p><p>At 24 h, the size of each inhibition zones was confirmed.</p></sec><sec><title>Antibacterial Evaluation by Broth Inhibition by Microtiter Method</title><p>Reductions in bacterial growth (mean OD<sub>540nm</sub> values) were also recorded with the microtiter method, as early as 4 h for Gram-negative microorganisms. This was confirmed by reading at 18 and 24 h. In relation to Gram affinity, different hemo-components induced a significant decrease in the growth of Gram-negative (0.897 vs. 1.604, t = 3.537 <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.001) and resistant bacteria (0.742 vs. 1.908, t = 4.506 <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0005) compared with the corresponding bacterial growth in the absence of the hemo-component. At 18 h, thrombin significantly reduced the MDR <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> growth (1.845 vs. 2.258, t = 41.094 <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0001). The presence of leukocytes inhibited the bacterial growth more, but not statistically significant, compared with hemo-components without leukocytes. Significant differences were observed for MDR, XDR <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae, E. coli</italic>, XDR, and PDR <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> (<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>OD<sub>540nm</sub> reductions in Gram-negative bacteria (mean OD<sub>540nm</sub> bacterium plus hemo-component vs. mean OD<sub>540nm</sub> bacterial control) recorded after 18 and 24 h of incubation by the broth microdilution method.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Hemo-components</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Time (h)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="6" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>OD</bold>
<sub>
<bold>540nm</bold>
</sub>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">
<bold>K. pneumoniae</bold>
</italic>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">
<bold>E. coli</bold>
</italic>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">
<bold>P. aeruginosa</bold>
</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>MDR</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>XDR</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>MDR</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>XDR</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>MDR</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>PDR</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Bacterial controls without hemo-components</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.195</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.300</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.432</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.568</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.258</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.641</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.413</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.440</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.512</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.338</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.340</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.653</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fibrin glue</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.366</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.932 <xref rid="TN21" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*1</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thrombin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.845 <xref rid="TN1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*2</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.633 <xref rid="TN22" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*3</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PRP</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.290</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.498</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.230 <xref rid="TN4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*4</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.978 <sup>*5</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.116 <xref rid="TN24" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*6</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-PRP</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.268</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PRP plus thrombin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.123</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.448</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.200</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.640</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.220</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-PRP plus thrombin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.104</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.398</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.300</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.400</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PRP plus calcium gluconate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.901</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.400</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.188</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.500</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.290</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.480</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.200</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.512</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-PRP plus calcium gluconate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.369</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.408</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PPP</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.124</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023 <xref rid="TN3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*7</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.061 <xref rid="TN4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*8</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.019 <xref rid="TN25" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*9</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-PPP</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.180</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035 <xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*10</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.014</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.260 <xref rid="TN6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*11</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.282 <xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*12</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PG 10 &#956;l</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-PG 10 &#956;l</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PG 20 &#956;l</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.101<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*13</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-PG 20 &#956;l</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PG 40 &#956;l</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.911</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.144</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.103 <xref rid="TN8" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*14</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.134</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.568</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.104 <xref rid="TN27" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*15</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.970 <xref rid="TN28" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*16</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-PG 40 &#956;l</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.969</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.099 <xref rid="TN8" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*17</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.328 <xref rid="TN10" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*18</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.176 <xref rid="TN29" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*19</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.236 <sup>*20</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-PG 180 &#956;l</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.449 <xref rid="TN11" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*21</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.068 <xref rid="TN12" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*22</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.345 <xref rid="TN13" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*23</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.265 <xref rid="TN14" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*24</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.196 <xref rid="TN15" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*25</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.357 <xref rid="TN16" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*26</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.480 <xref rid="TN31" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*27</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.350 <xref rid="TN32" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*28</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.272 <xref rid="TN33" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*29</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.926 <xref rid="TN34" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*30</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.029 <xref rid="TN35" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*31</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P-PG 180 &#956;l</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.505 <xref rid="TN17" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*32</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085 <xref rid="TN18" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*33</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12 <xref rid="TN19" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*34</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.643 <xref rid="TN20" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*35</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.466 <xref rid="TN36" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*36</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.006 <xref rid="TN37" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*37</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003 <xref rid="TN38" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*38</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063 <xref rid="TN39" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*39</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.007 <xref rid="TN40" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*40</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.355 <xref rid="TN41" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*41</sup></xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic toggle="yes">At 18 h:</italic>
</p><fn id="TN1"><label>*2</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 41.094 p = 0.001)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN2"><label>*4</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 30.398 p = 0.011)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN3"><label>*7</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 23.895 p = 0.003)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN4"><label>*8</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 27.730 p = 0.013)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN5"><label>*10</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 7.001 p = 0.020)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN6"><label>*11</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 27. 586 p = 0.001)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN7"><label>*13</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 151.101 p &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN8"><label>*14</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 122.002 p = 0.0001)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN9"><label>*17</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 22.985 p = 0.0023)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN10"><label>*18</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 22.265 p = 0.002)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN11"><label>*21</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 222.563 p &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN12"><label>*22</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 9.283 p = 0.011)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN13"><label>*23</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 165.210 p &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN14"><label>*24</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 267.991 p &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN15"><label>*25</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 166.877 p &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN16"><label>*26</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 156.681 p &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN17"><label>*32</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 7.192 p = 0.019)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN18"><label>*33</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 23.895 p = 0.002)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN19"><label>*34</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 22.237 p = 0.002)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN20"><label>*35</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 31.988 p = 0.001)</italic>.</p></fn><p>
<italic toggle="yes">At 24 h:</italic>
</p><fn id="TN21"><label>*1</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 34.203 p = 0.001)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN22"><label>*3</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 175.258 p &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN23"><label>5</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 42.135 p = 0.001)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN24"><label>*6</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 339.621 p &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN25"><label>*9</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 351.950 p &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN26"><label>*12</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 17.645 p = 0.003)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN27"><label>*15</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 226.595 p &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN28"><label>*16</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 116.373 p = 0.0001)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN29"><label>*19</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 186.653 p &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN30"><label>*20</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 168.233 p &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN31"><label>*27</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 452.334 p &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN32"><label>*28</label><p>
<italic toggle="yes">(t = 734.907 p &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>)</italic>
</p></fn><fn id="TN33"><label>*29</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 139.973 p = 0.0001)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN34"><label>*30</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 48.647 p = 0.0004)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN35"><label>*31</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 765.556 p &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN36"><label>*36</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 130.081 p = 0.0001)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN37"><label>*37</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 142.865 p &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN38"><label>*38</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 65.491 p = 0.0002)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN39"><label>*39</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 39.049 p = 0.001)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN40"><label>*40</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 32.126 p = 0.001)</italic>;</p></fn><fn id="TN41"><label>*41</label><p><italic toggle="yes">(t = 181.383 p &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>)</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>No significant bacterial reductions were observed when P-PRP, L-PRP, and P-PRP with thrombin, L-PRP and P-PRP with calcium gluconate, and L-PG 10 &#956;l and P-PG 10 &#956;l were applied for 18 and 24 h.</p><p>For Gram-positive bacteria, OD<sub>540nm</sub> reductions were observed at 18 h for all <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">aureus</italic> strains in the presence of FG (1.025 vs. 1.439, t = 114.969 <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0001) and 24 h (1.153 vs. 1.553, t = 222.159 <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>) in comparison to the positive controls.</p><p>L-PG 10 &#956;l reduced MDR <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">aureus</italic>, both at 18 h (1.15 vs. 1.481, t = 160.803 <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>) and at 24 h (0.665 vs. 0.9765, t = 278.611 <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>). L-PG 20 &#956;l (0.622 vs. 0.955, t = 7.8347 <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0159), L-PG 180 &#956;l (&#8722;0.018 vs. 0.955, t = 46.344 <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.0005), and P-PG 180 &#956;l (&#8722;0.4055 vs. 0.955, t = 11.783 <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.007) were able to reduce XDR <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">aureus</italic> growth. Similar significant reductions were confirmed for the P-PG 180 &#956;l at 24 h (&#8722;0.354 vs. 0.976, t = 1.2 <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;4</sup>).</p><p>For hemo-components such as PL, FG, and thrombin, comparison of the mean ODs recorded at 18 and 24 h for all groups of bacteria showed a non-significant increase, except for FG for resistant bacteria, for which there was a reduction, although not significant.</p><p>By the broth microdilution method, non-transfusional hemo-components with and without leukocytes showed similar bacterial properties toward all bacterial strains tested, although a greater but not significant reduction was observed for L-PG 180 &#956;l, at both 18 h (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.252) and 24 h (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.306) (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figures 5</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F5" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Mean OD<sub>540nm</sub> values of Gram-positive bacteria observed after 18 and 24 h of incubation in presence of different non-transfusional hemo-components. L-PPP, leukocyte platelet-poor plasma; P-PPP, pure platelet-poor plasma; L-PRP, leukocyte platelet-rich plasma; P-PRP, pure platelet-rich plasma; L-PRP + Ca, leukocyte platelet-rich plasma with calcium gluconate; P-PRP + Ca, pure platelet-rich plasma with calcium gluconate; L-PRP + T, leukocyte platelet-rich plasma with thrombin-rich solution; P-PRP + T, pure platelet-rich plasma with thrombin-rich solution; L-PG10, leukocyte platelet gel 10 &#956;l; P-PG10, pure platelet gel 10 &#956;l; L-PG20, leukocyte platelet gel 20 &#956;l; P-PG20, pure platelet gel 20 &#956;l; L-PG40, leukocyte platelet gel 40 &#956;l; P-PG40, pure platelet gel 40 &#956;l; L-PG180, leukocyte platelet gel 180 &#956;l; P-PG180, pure platelet gel 180 &#956;l.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-746809-g0005.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Mean OD<sub>540nm</sub> values of Gram-negative bacteria observed after 18 and 24 h of incubation in the presence of different non-transfusional hemo-components. L-PPP, leukocyte platelet-poor plasma; P-PPP, pure platelet-poor plasma; L-PRP, leukocyte platelet-rich plasma; P-PRP, pure platelet-rich plasma; L-PRP + Ca, leukocyte platelet-rich plasma with calcium gluconate; P-PRP + Ca, pure platelet-rich plasma with calcium gluconate; L-PRP + T, leukocyte platelet-rich plasma with thrombin-rich solution; P-PRP + T, pure platelet-rich plasma with thrombin-rich solution; L-PG10, leukocyte platelet gel 10 &#956;l; P-PG10, pure platelet gel 10 &#956;l; L-PG20, leukocyte platelet gel 20 &#956;l; P-PG20, pure platelet gel 20 &#956;l; L-PG40, leukocyte platelet gel 40 &#956;l; P-PG40, pure platelet gel 40 &#956;l; L-PG180, leukocyte platelet gel 180 &#956;l; P-PG180, pure platelet gel 180 &#956;l.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-746809-g0006.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F7" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Mean OD<sub>540nm</sub> values of leukocyte-rich formulations and leukocyte-poor formulations observed after 18 h of incubation in the presence of different non-transfusional hemo-components. PPP, platelet-poor plasma; PRP, platelet-rich plasma; PRP + Ca, platelet-rich plasma with calcium gluconate; PRP + T, platelet-rich plasma with thrombin-rich solution; PG10, platelet gel 10 &#956;l; PG20, platelet gel 20 &#956;l; PG40, platelet gel 40 &#956;l; PG180, platelet gel 180 &#956;l.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-746809-g0007.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F8" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Mean OD<sub>540nm</sub> values of leukocyte-rich formulations and leukocyte-poor formulations observed after 24 h of incubation in the presence of different non-transfusional hemo-components. PPP, platelet-poor plasma; PRP, platelet-rich plasma; PRP + Ca, platelet-rich plasma with calcium gluconate; PRP + T, platelet-rich plasma with thrombin-rich solution; PG10, platelet gel 10 &#956;l; PG20, platelet gel 20 &#956;l; PG40, platelet gel 40 &#956;l; PG180, platelet gel 180 &#956;l.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-746809-g0008.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion and Conclusions</title><p>Several studies have been conducted recently, mainly in human medicine, to demonstrate the antimicrobial effect of non-transfusional hemo-components for topical use.</p><p>Few studies have been performed <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> regarding the potential antimicrobial effect of animal hemo-components (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). One study showed antibacterial activity of thrombin-activated platelets in horses (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Platelet-rich plasma from rabbits had strong <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> antimicrobial properties against methicillin-susceptible and methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, Group A <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Moreover, Lopez evidenced a bacteriostatic effect of equine pure platelet-rich formulations (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). In addition, antibiofilm properties of equine platelet-rich plasma lysate were also highlighted (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>).</p><p>Some <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> experimental studies using animal models have also confirmed the potential antimicrobial effect of non-transfusional hemo-components (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>, <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>). Platelet-rich plasma showed antimicrobial properties in rabbit models of osteomyelitis (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>, <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>) and postoperative spinal implant-associated infections (<xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). Platelet-rich plasma improved healing of experimentally infected surgical wounds in rats (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>) and accelerated healing of canine skin wounds by exerting antibacterial activity, rapid reduction of inflammation, rapid re-epithelialization, and granulation tissue formation (<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>).</p><p>Based on this literature evidence on animals, this study assessed the antimicrobial activity of different hemo-components for non-transfusional use obtained from canine species against bacteria with different characteristics. To the authors' knowledge, this study represents the first steps conducted <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> to evaluate the potential inhibitory effect of canine non-transfusional hemo-components on bacteria collected from canine wounds and classified according to the sensitivity/resistance spectrum toward a known panel of human and veterinary antibiotics.</p><p>Although this study was performed on a pool of WB from a limited number of dogs, the results will potentially contribute to enrich the knowledge on this topic, in order to provide some answers to important questions recently posed by different schools of thought.</p><p>The action of the hemo-components has been evaluated against Gram-positive bacteria (<italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">aureus, S. cohnii</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">cohnii</italic>) and Gram-negative (<italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa, E. coli, K. pneumoniae</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">pneumoniae</italic>) isolated from biological samples of canine origin and previously classified as susceptible, resistant, or MDR to a panel of known antibiotics.</p><p>The potential antibacterial effect of the hemo-components has been evaluated by both agar gel diffusion (Kirby&#8211;Bauer), and broth inhibition using microtiter plates with spectrophotometer readings at a wavelength of 540 nm (OD<sub>540nm</sub>). PL, FG, and thrombin-rich solution were tested for the first time in veterinary medicine.</p><p>WB from dogs with degenerative joint disease who underwent intra-articular therapy with autologous PRP was used in this study; this choice was mainly determined by ethical reasons, but it also allowed us to be more adherent to daily clinical practice. To limit the impact of individual donor variations, as performed in other studies, a pool was created with WB collected from all dogs and all materials tested were obtained from the same pool of dogs (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>).</p><p>In this study, the cell counts contributed to define the quality of hemo-components preparation procedures, supporting the hypothesis of some authors who relate the platelet concentration to the clinical regenerative effect as it is positively correlated with the concentration of growth factors (<xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>). Conversely, an excessively high platelet concentration is considered counterproductive to the healing process, as it has the potential to inhibit the angiogenic process (<xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>). The platelet fold increase from WB and the platelet concentration obtained in the final product could be considered rough measures to define the quality of the production process and of the PRP for clinical use, respectively (<xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>).</p><p>Specifically, the platelet concentration in L-PRP was similar to what Mazzucco et al. considered a &#8220;reasonable compromise&#8221; for determining the quality of the PCs for regenerative medicine therapeutic purposes (<xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>, <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>).</p><p>Increases in platelet and leukocyte concentrations in PRP compared with baseline concentration in WB were similar to those obtained by Perego et al. (<xref rid="B79" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>).</p><p>Platelet and leukocyte contents in P-PRP were comparable to those in other studies (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>).</p><p>Platelet and leukocyte concentrations were much lower (45-fold and 140-fold, respectively) in L-PPP than the L-PRP formulation, similarly to Burnouf who obtained a 50-fold decrease in leukocytes and a 100-fold decrease in platelets (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>).</p><p>The potential antimicrobial role of leukocytes and platelets was evaluated by comparing the bacterial load (OD) inhibition values for PPP, PRP, PRP with calcium gluconate, PRP with thrombin, and PG in various amounts, in both leukocyte-rich formulations and leukocyte-poor (or pure) formulations. PPP, although rarely used in regenerative medicine for therapeutic purposes, has been tested to define the innate antimicrobial role of plasma or humoral immune response: the result of our study suggests that the antimicrobial bacteriostatic action, especially against Gram-negative bacteria, might be related to plasma components rather than the platelets. In this study, the presence of leukocytes has been shown not to be significant for the antimicrobial activity of hemo-components, although in the presence of leukocytes a reduction in growth was observed for a greater number of microorganisms than in the action of hemo-components without leukocytes. The effect of leukocytes in PCs is the focus of heated scientific debate. Many authors have suggested that the addition of white blood cells could enhance the antibacterial potential (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>). However, Anitua and collaborators have shown that the addition of leukocytes does not significantly improve the strong antibacterial properties. It is also possible that leukocytes could increase the inflammatory response at the site because they secrete metalloproteinases, pro-inflammatory proteases, and acid hydrolases (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Other authors agree that the presence of leukocytes does not increase the antibacterial effect of PCs (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>). In our study, the presence of leukocytes is confirmed to be non-significant for the antimicrobial activity of non-transfusional hemo-components.</p><p>By the Kirby&#8211;Bauer method, the antibacterial effect of platelet gel (PG), both with and without leukocytes, has been documented as early as 4 h for some bacteria, confirmed at 18 h, especially for slow-growing bacteria, and remained constant until 24 h. Results obtained by the agar gel diffusion method (Kirby&#8211;Bauer) were confirmed by broth inhibition using microtiter plates and reading by spectrophotometry. Both L-PG and P-PG showed a reduction in the bacterial load of Gram-negative bacteria, also PDR <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>.</p><p>Studies using the broth inhibition method did not agree with the observed results. Edelblute et al. showed no antibacterial activity of PG against <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, while significant bactericidal activity was observed against <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Acinetobacter baumannii</italic> (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Drago et al. showed a lack of action of P-PRP, against <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>; on the contrary, growth inhibition was recorded for Gram-positive and yeasts: <italic toggle="yes">E. faecalis, Candida albicans, Streptococcus agalactiae</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus oralis</italic> (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>).</p><p>Zones of inhibition were observed with L-PG, at the amount of 35 &#956;l in both MDR Gram-negative microorganisms (<italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">pneumoniae, P. aeruginosa</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>) and susceptible Gram-positive bacteria. In one study, 30 &#956;l of L-PG induced, after 3 h and up to 48 h, a significant growth inhibition effect for <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae, P. aeruginosa, E. coli</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>).</p><p>The results of our study are partly consistent with those described by Bielecki et al. who observed growth inhibition of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and methicillin-susceptible and methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> strains with L-PG 12 &#956;l. The measured inhibition zones were comparable to those of gentamicin and oxacillin, analog of methicillin (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). In contrast to our study, the same authors did not observe a reduction for <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p><p>As the amount of PG tested increased, the inhibitory effect on bacteria also increased, because of the observed reduction in bacterial load. L-PG 500 &#956;l decreased the growth of all microorganisms, except for methicillin-susceptible <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">aureus</italic> strain.</p><p>The potential antibacterial effect of leukocyte-poor or pure platelet gel (P-PG) was also tested in this study. At the amount of 35 &#956;l, P-PG already showed an area of growth inhibition exclusively for multiresistant <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">pneumoniae</italic>, whereas at the amount of 500 &#956;l P-PG showed growth inhibition for more types of bacteria: this effect was observed for all bacterial strains except MDR <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. conhii</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">cohnii</italic>.</p><p>Inhibitory action was also observed for formulations in the pre-activation phase (L-PRP, PRP-P), although not against Gram-positive bacteria.</p><p>In the inhibition zones, characterized by lower growth halos, a bacteriostatic action can be assumed, as for some antibiotic drugs.</p><p>A recent systematic review also observed a tendency of PCs to inhibit the growth of microorganisms during the first hours of incubation, whereas they did not seem to be able to completely break down the microbial load, indicating a bacteriostatic rather than a bactericidal activity (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>).</p><p>On this aspect, in the presence of thrombin-activated PRP, Wu et al. observed a reduction in the number of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli, P. aeruginosa</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> during the first 8 to 12 h, with the greatest reduction observed at 0 to 4 h. The number of bacteria increased again after the 4-h time point because the bacterial killing process was not complete; after this time point, bacterial growth exceeded the killing rate and growth continued until the stationary phase was reached at the 24-h time point (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>).</p><p>It is interesting to note that PL, FG, and thrombin had an inhibitory action only against Gram-negative bacteria. This finding could open up innovative therapeutic possibilities, potentially exploiting combined therapies in a clinical scenario with infections sustained by these types of bacteria, sometimes rather aggressive and difficult to treat. Specifically, thrombin at the amount of 8 &#956;l was able to create a visible zone of reduced growth for the two <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> strains (MDR and PDR). The only strain of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">aureus</italic> (susceptible to the panel of antibiotics) whose bacterial load was significantly decreased by FG was also moderately inhibited by PL and thrombin. Although studies on these hemo-components are very few in the literature, our findings are in contrast to Bielecki and collaborators who observed no inhibitory effect using 12 &#956;l of thrombin against <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus, E. coli, K. pneumoniae, P. aeruginosa</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">E. faecalis</italic> (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p><p>Other studies have shown that activation of platelets in PRP with thrombin leads to a significant increase in inhibitory activity on bacteria (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). In the same study, addition of thrombin to <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> was shown not to affect bacterial growth, and addition of thrombin to PPP did not increase the inhibitory effect (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>).</p><p>Although further studies will need to be done to clarify the mechanism of action, the thrombin-rich solution used in our study may have had antibacterial action by itself, because it is derived from autologous plasma, and it is not thrombin derived from complex chemical extraction.</p><p>Some studies have tested the potential link between the antibacterial effect and the platelet activation process with CaCl<sub>2</sub>, reaching discordant results (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). According to Burnouf et al., activation of coagulation to prepare PG may reduce antimicrobial activity by consuming complement or other inhibitors or by releasing components that support bacterial proliferation (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Contrariwise, Drago et al. observed that only activated materials were able to inhibit bacterial growth, suggesting that the activation of coagulation is a key step (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>).</p><p>The antibacterial action against Gram-negative bacteria, observed for L-PPP, P-PPP, L-PRP, and P-PRP and the same with the addition of calcium gluconate and thrombin, is consistent with that documented by Burnouf et al. Using PPP, PRP, and PL, these authors obtained inhibitory action against <italic toggle="yes">E. coli, P. aeruginosa</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic>, but not against Gram-positive microorganisms, except for <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). The zones of inhibition observed in our study showed a minimum area of 4 &#215; 4.5 mm in contrast to the zones of inhibition of 0.5, 0.5&#8211;1, and &gt;1 mm considered by Burnouf et al. (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Tohidnezhad et al. also observed antibacterial action of PRP with thrombin for <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa, Enterococcus faecalis, Bacillus megaterium</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Proteus mirabilis</italic> (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Li et al. found that PRP has strong antimicrobial properties <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> against bacteria such as methicillin-susceptible and methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, Group A <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>).</p><p>The bacteriostatic action of the PPP, with and without leukocytes, was shown only for Gram-negative bacteria (<italic toggle="yes">E. coli, P. aeruginosa</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> ssp. <italic toggle="yes">pneumoniae</italic>) belonging to the MDR and PDR groups. This finding suggests that the antimicrobial bacteriostatic action might be related to plasma components rather than platelets.</p><p>The mechanism of the antibacterial effect of PCs is not yet fully understood.</p><p>There are several studies suggesting that platelets play a very important role in the innate defense against the induction and progression of endovascular infections. This host defense capacity depends on the ability of platelets to release a group of antimicrobial peptides, known collectively as platelet protein microbicide, at the site of damage or endovascular infection. Indeed, platelets generate oxygen metabolites, including peroxide, hydrogen peroxide, and free radicals; are able to bind and aggregate microorganisms, improving the clearance of pathogens from the bloodstream; have chemotactic action on macrophages; participate in antibody-dependent cellular cytotoxicity functions against pathogens; and, finally, would release a series of potent antimicrobial peptides (<xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>, <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>).</p><p>In one study, PPP showed no impact on the growth parameters of any of the bacteria tested, whereas PRP showed an antibacterial effect with a strong correlation between platelet concentration and antibacterial activity (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Mariani et al., instead, showed that both PRP and PPP inhibited bacterial growth for up to 2 h of incubation, but the effect of P-PRP was significantly higher than that of PPP (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>).</p><p>One study proposed a possible molecular mechanism to explain the antimicrobial effect of PRP at least against <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> through the detection of an antimicrobial peptide in PRP, the human beta-defensin 2 (hBD-2) (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Another study showed that PCs induced a significant increase in hBD-2 expression in primary keratinocytes cell culture in a concentration- and time-dependent manner (<xref rid="B86" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>).</p><p>Several antibacterial peptides have also been identified in human platelets, including connective tissue-activating peptide 3 (CTAP-3), platelet factor 4 (PF-4), regulated upon activation&#8211;normal T-cell expressed and secreted protein (RANTES), thymosin &#946;-4 (T&#946;-4), platelet basic protein (PBP), fibrinopeptide A (FP-A), and fibrinopeptide B (FP-B) (<xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B89" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>).</p><p>Drago et al. also tested P-PPP against Gram-positive bacteria isolated from the oral cavity obtaining similar, although slightly lower, results to P-PRP, whereas platelets alone showed no antibacterial activity (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). The authors concluded that the antimicrobial activity of PCs against <italic toggle="yes">E. faecalis, S. agalactiae, S. oralis</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> is supported by a synergy of plasma components and platelet-derived factors (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>).</p><p>In our study, in relation to the different groups of microorganisms, significant reductions were observed only for Gram-negative MDR bacteria in the presence of PG 180 &#956;l, both with and without leukocytes. For P-PG 180 &#956;l, the inhibitory action was also documented for Gram-negative PDR bacteria.</p><p>The results of this study are certainly very encouraging and stimulate further studies to understand the mechanism of antibacterial effect. A greater knowledge of the mechanism of action could bring considerable advantages for potential practical applications, being able to better outline the indications, the limits, and the conditions of practical use, also for the antibacterial effect in addition to the consolidated regenerative effect of the non-transfusional hemo-components.</p><p>To justify the antibacterial effect of hemo-components, future research can be ideally oriented to the investigation of potential plasma factors, ideally starting from the peptides already identified for the human species but considering that there could be differences between the human and canine species, as evidenced by this study regarding the antibacterial effect.</p><p>Our study confirmed the hypothesized antibacterial properties of canine non-transfusional hemo-components. The bacteriostatic effect appeared to be higher against Gram-negative bacteria. The presence of neither leukocytes nor platelets seems to be essential for the antibacterial effect. Although the interaction of hemo-components with microbial pathogens needs further investigations because the exact mechanism responsible for the antibacterial activity is not yet fully known, non-transfusional hemo-components have been shown to represent a useful natural substance for infection control, especially at surgical sites in the immediate postoperative period. The emergence of multidrug-, extensively drug-, and pan drug-resistant bacteria poses a significant health and economic threat for animals and humans. Therefore, local application of non-transfusional hemo-components could support the action of molecules with antibiotic activity and represent a suitable alternative to control MDR pathogens.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s5"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be made available by the authors, without undue reservation.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by Animal Welfare Body of the University of Camerino. Written informed consent was obtained from the owners for the participation of their animals in this study.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>A-RA and AT contributed to the conception and design of the study. CI organized the database. ES and AT recruited the animals and prepared the hemo-components. A-RA, CI, AC, and ML performed the bacteriological evaluations. A-RA performed the statistical analysis. A-RA, CI, and AT wrote the first draft of the manuscript. AC, CR, GM, GR, LG, and VC wrote sections of the manuscript. All authors contributed to manuscript revision, read, and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="s8"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by a research grant from the University of Camerino, Italy (Fondo di Ateneo per la Ricerca 2014.2015).</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s9"><title>Publisher's Note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization (WHO)</collab></person-group>. <source>GLASS Whole-Genome Sequencing for Surveillance of Antimicrobial Resistance: Global Antimicrobial Resistance and Use Surveillance System (GLASS)</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name> (<year>2020</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/health-topics/antimicrobial-resistance" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/health-topics/antimicrobial-resistance</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cloeckaert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Duijkeren</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial Resistance in Animals and the Environment &#8211; ARAE 2015</article-title>. <source>Vet Microbiol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>194</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2016.09.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#246;rmeli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#246;rmeli</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ataoglu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#199;olak</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aslant&#252;rk</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ertem</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Multiple PRP injections are more effective than single injections and hyaluronic acid in knees with early osteoarthritis: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Knee Surg, Sport Traumatol Arthrosc.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>958</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00167-015-3705-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26233594</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samy</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of platelet rich plasma in management of fracture neck femur: new insights</article-title>. <source>Int Orthop.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>1019</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00264-015-2844-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26156712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martini</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Via</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fossati</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Randelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Randelli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cucchi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Single platelet-rich plasma injection for early stage of Osteoarthritis of the knee</article-title>. <source>Joints.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0037-1601405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29114622</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5672849</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alessio-Mazzola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Repetto</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trentini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Formica</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Felli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Autologous US-guided PRP injection versus us-guided focal extracorporeal shock wave therapy for chronic lateral epicondylitis: a minimum of 2-year follow-up retrospective comparative study</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Surg.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2309499017749986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29320964</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Intra-articular injections of platelet-rich plasma, hyaluronic acid or corticosteroids for knee osteoarthritis: a prospective randomized controlled study</article-title>. <source>Orthopade.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>239</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>47</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00132-018-03659-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30623236</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuksel</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aydin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Senturk</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turanli</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of effects of platelet-rich plasma on human facial skin</article-title>. <source>J Cosmet Laser Ther.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>206</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/14764172.2014.949274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25065381</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Picard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hersant</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bosc</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meningaud</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Should we use platelet-rich plasma as an adjunct therapy to treat &#8220;acute wounds,&#8221; &#8220;burns,&#8221; and &#8220;laser therapies&#8221;: a review and a proposal of a quality criteria checklist for further studies</article-title>. <source>Wound Repair Regen.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>163</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/wrr.12266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25683096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez-Zapata</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;-Carvajal</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sol&#224;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Exp&#243;sito</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bol&#237;bar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodr&#237;guez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Autologous platelet-rich plasma for treating chronic wounds</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>CD006899</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD006899.pub3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27223580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9308064</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moneib</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Youssef</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aly</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rizk</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelhakeem</surname><given-names>YI</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Autologous platelet-rich plasma versus conventional therapy for the treatment of chronic venous leg ulcers: a comparative study</article-title>. <source>J Cosmet Dermatol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>495</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>501</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jocd.12401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28834103</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burgos-Alonso</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lobato</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hern&#225;ndez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sebastian</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodr&#237;guez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>March</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Autologous platelet-rich plasma in the treatment of venous leg ulcers in primary care: a randomised controlled, pilot study</article-title>. <source>J Wound Care.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>S20</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12968/jowc.2018.27.Sup6.S20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29883294</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ronci</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferraro</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Missiroli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinopoli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Proposto</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Platelet-rich plasma as treatment for persistent ocular epithelial defects</article-title>. <source>Transfus Apher Sci.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>300</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.transci.2014.12.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25728718</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alio</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Arriba</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gisbert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelghany</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Treatment with platelet-rich plasma of surgically related dormant corneal ulcers</article-title>. <source>Eur J Ophthalmol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>515</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1120672117747042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29566537</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wr&#243;bel-Dudzi&#324;ska</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alio</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suchodo&#322;a-Ratajewicz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kosior-Jarecka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rymgay&#322;&#322;o-Jankowska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical efficacy of platelet-rich plasma in the treatment of neurotrophic corneal ulcer</article-title>. <source>J Ophthalmol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>2018</volume>:<fpage>3538764</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2018/3538764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30026985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6031214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabrizi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karagah</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahidi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zare</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Does platelet-rich plasma enhance healing in the idiopathic bone cavity? A single-blind randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>1175</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijom.2015.05.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26074365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Fabbro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bucchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lolato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Corbella</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Testori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taschieri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Healing of Postextraction Sockets Preserved With Autologous Platelet Concentrates. A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>75</volume>:<fpage>1601</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joms.2017.02.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28288724</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhujbal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kv</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parkar</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mb</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative evaluation of platelet rich plasma in socket healing and bone regeneration after surgical removal of impacted mandibular third molars</article-title>. <source>J Dent Res Dent Clin Dent Prospects.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>153</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15171/joddd.2018.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30443299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6231145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Fabbro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karanxha</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bucchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nadathur Doraiswamy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sankari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Autologous platelet concentrates for treating periodontal infrabony defects</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>CD011423</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD011423.pub2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30484284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6517213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saleem</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pisani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zahid</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Georgakopoulos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pustina-Krasniqi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xhajanka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Adjunctive platelet-rich plasma (PRP) in infrabony regenerative treatment: a systematic review and RCT's meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Stem Cells Int.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>2018</volume>:<fpage>9594235</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2018/9594235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29755531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5884028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fahie</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortolano</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guercio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Au</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>randomized controlled trial of the efficacy of autologous platelet therapy for the treatment of osteoarthritis in dogs</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>243</volume>:<fpage>1291</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/javma.243.9.1291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24134578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tambella</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Attili</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palumbo Piccionello</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vullo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Serri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Autologous platelet gel to treat chronic decubital ulcers: a randomized, blind controlled clinical trial in dogs</article-title>. <source>Vet Surg.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>726</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-950X.2014.12148.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24484268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iacopetti</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patruno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melotti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinello</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bedin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Badon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Autologous platelet-rich plasma enhances the healing of large cutaneous wounds in dogs</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>575449</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2020.575449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33195571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7649378</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perego</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spada</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baggiani</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martino</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Proverbio</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of a semi automated commercial closed system for autologous leukocyte- and platelet-rich plasma (l-prp) production in dogs: a preliminary study</article-title>. <source>Animals.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1342</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani10081342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32759643</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7459512</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perinelli</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonacucina</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pucciarelli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cespi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Serri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polzonetti</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rheological properties and growth factors content of Platelet-Rich plasma: relevance in veterinary biomedical treatments</article-title>. <source>Biomedicines.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>429</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biomedicines8100429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33081006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7603199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tambella</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartocetti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galosi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Catone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falcone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of autologous platelet-rich fibrin in post-extraction alveolar sockets: a randomized, controlled split-mouth trial in dogs with spontaneous periodontal disease</article-title>. <source>Animals.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1343</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani10081343</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32759693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7459700</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marx</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Platelet-rich plasma: evidence to support its use</article-title>. <source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>62</volume>:<fpage>489</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joms.2003.12.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15085519</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bielecki</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gazdzik</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arendt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szczepanski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kr&#243;l</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wielkoszynski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antibacterial effect of autologous platelet gel enriched with growth factors and other active substances: an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> study</article-title>. <source>J Bone Jt Surg - Ser B.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>417</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1302/0301-620X.89B3.18491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17356164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moojen</surname><given-names>DJF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Everts</surname><given-names>PAM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schure</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Overdevest</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Zundert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knape</surname><given-names>JTA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial activity of platelet-leukocyte gel against staphylococcus aureus</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Res.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>404</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jor.20519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17960651</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drago</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bortolin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vassena</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taschieri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Fabbro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial activity of pure platelet-rich plasma against microorganisms isolated from oral cavity</article-title>. <source>BMC Microbiol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2180-13-47</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23442413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3599521</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#243;pez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carmona</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giraldo</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#193;lvarez</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bacteriostatic effect of equine pure platelet-rich plasma and other blood products against methicillin-sensitive Staphylococcus aureus: an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> study</article-title>. <source>Vet Comp Orthop Traumatol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>372</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3415/VCOT-14-04-0054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25088784</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mariani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Filardo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Canella</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berlingeri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bielli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cattini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Platelet-rich plasma affects bacterial growth <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic></article-title>. <source>Cytotherapy.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1294</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>304</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcyt.2014.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25108654</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mariani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Canella</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berlingeri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bielli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cattini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Landini</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Leukocyte presence does not increase microbicidal activity of Platelet-rich Plasma <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> clinical microbiology and vaccines</article-title>. <source>BMC Microbiol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>149</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-015-0482-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26223356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4520275</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L-C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S-W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsou</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y-Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial activity of platelet-rich plasma and other plasma preparations against periodontal pathogens</article-title>. <source>J Periodontol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>310</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1902/jop.2014.140373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25345340</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Badade</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahale</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Panjwani</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaidya</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warang</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial effect of platelet-rich plasma and platelet-rich fibrin</article-title>. <source>Indian J Dent Res.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>300</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0970-9290.186231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27411660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aggour</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gamil</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial effects of platelet-rich plasma against selected oral and periodontal pathogens</article-title>. <source>Polish J Microbiol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>31</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5604/17331331.1235227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29359696</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karde</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sethi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahale</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khedkar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative evaluation of platelet count and antimicrobial efficacy of injectable platelet-rich fibrin with other platelet concentrates: an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> study</article-title>. <source>J Indian Soc Periodontol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>97</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jisp.jisp_201_17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29398852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5771122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maghsoudi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ranjbar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirjalili</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fasihi-Ramandi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Inhibitory activities of platelet-rich and platelet-poor plasma on the growth of pathogenic bacteria</article-title>. <source>Iran J Pathol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>87</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.30699/ijp.2017.23386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29760757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5938728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cie&#347;lik-Bielecka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bold</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zi&#243;&#322;kowski</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piercha&#322;a</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kr&#243;likowska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reichert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antibacterial activity of leukocyte- and platelet-rich plasma: an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> study</article-title>. <source>Biomed Res Int.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>2018</volume>:<fpage>9471723</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2018/9471723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30050949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6040244</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kour</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pudakalkatti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Das</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Padmanabhan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative evaluation of antimicrobial efficacy of platelet-rich plasma, platelet-rich fibrin, and injectable platelet-rich fibrin on the standard strains of Porphyromonas gingivalis and Aggregatibacter actinomycetemcomitans</article-title>. <source>Contemp Clin Dent.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>325</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ccd.ccd_367_18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30294166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6169270</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>&#199;etinkaya</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yenilmez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrone</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bekt&#246;re</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simsek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Platelet-rich plasma as an additional therapeutic option for infected wounds with multi-drug resistant bacteria: in vitro antibacterial activity study</article-title>. <source>Eur J Trauma Emerg Surg.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>555</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00068-018-0957-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29700554</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anitua</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Girbau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aguirre</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muruzabal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orive</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antibacterial effect of plasma rich in growth factors (PRGF&#174;- Endoret&#174;) against Staphylococcus aureus and Staphylococcus epidermidis strains</article-title>. <source>Clin Exp Dermatol.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>652</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2230.2011.04303.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22329713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>TAV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>TTP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luong</surname><given-names>NTM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial effect of platelet-rich plasma against porphyromonas gingivalis</article-title>. <source>Int J Dent.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>2019</volume>:<fpage>7329103</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2019/7329103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31214262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6535835</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tohidnezhad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Varoga</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wruck</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Podschun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sachweh</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bornemann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Platelets display potent antimicrobial activity and release human beta-defensin 2</article-title>. <source>Platelets.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>217</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/09537104.2011.610908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21913811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burnouf</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial activity of platelet (PLT)-poor plasma, PLT-rich plasma, PLT gel, and solvent/detergent-treated PLT lysate biomaterials against wound bacteria</article-title>. <source>Transfusion.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>138</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1537-2995.2012.03668.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22563709</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>R&#243;zalski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Micota</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadowska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paszkiewicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wieckowska-Szakiel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>R&#243;zalska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial/anti-biofilm activity of expired blood platelets and their released products</article-title>. <source>Postepy Hig Med Dosw.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>321</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5604/17322693.1046009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23619231</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial properties of single-donor-derived, platelet-leukocyte fibrin for fistula occlusion: an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> study</article-title>. <source>Platelets.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>632</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/09537104.2012.761685</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23402660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drago</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bortolin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vassena</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roman&#242;</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taschieri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Fabbro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Plasma components and platelet activation are essential for the antimicrobial properties of autologous platelet-rich plasma: an in vitro study</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e107813</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25232963</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4169456</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edelblute</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Donate</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hargrave</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heller</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Human platelet gel supernatant inactivates opportunistic wound pathogens on skin</article-title>. <source>Platelets.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/09537104.2013.863859</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24433255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Intravia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Durant</surname><given-names>TJS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>MBR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beitzel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> evaluation of the anti-bacterial effect of two preparations of platelet rich plasma compared with Cefazolin and whole blood</article-title>. <source>Muscles Ligaments Tendons J.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11138/mltj/2014.4.1.079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24932452</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4049655</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aktan</surname><given-names>&#205;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dunkel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Equine platelets inhibit E coli growth and can be activated by bacterial lipopolysaccharide and lipoteichoic acid although superoxide anion production does not occur and platelet activation is not associated with enhanced production by neutrophils</article-title>. <source>Vet Immunol Immunopathol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>152</volume>:<fpage>209</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetimm.2012.12.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23332730</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilbertie</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaer</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menegatti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashton Lavoie</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Platelet-rich plasma lysate displays antibiofilm properties and restores antimicrobial activity against synovial fluid biofilms in vitro</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Res.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>1365</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jor.24584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31922274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8018705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>PRP as a new approach to prevent infection: preparation and in vitro antimicrobial properties of PRP</article-title>. <source>J Vis Exp.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>e50351</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3791/50351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23609458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3653398</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Fabbro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bortolin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taschieri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ceci</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial properties of platelet-rich preparations. A systematic review of the current pre-clinical evidence</article-title>. <source>Platelets.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>276</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/09537104.2015.1116686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26763769</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D'asta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halstead</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zecchi Orlandini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moiemen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The contribution of leucocytes to the antimicrobial activity of platelet-rich plasma preparations: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Platelets</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09537104.2017.1317731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28681651</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Varshney</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial effects of various platelet rich concentrates-vibes from in-vitro studies-a systematic review</article-title>. <source>J Oral Biol Craniofacial Res.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>299</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>305</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jobcr.2019.06.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31316893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6611965</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cetinkaya</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#220;nl&#252;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrone</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karabulut</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The efficacy of platelet-rich plasma gel in MRSA-related surgical wound infection treatment: an experimental study in an animal model</article-title>. <source>Eur J Trauma Emerg Surg.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>859</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>67</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00068-017-0852-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28965136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Serraino</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dominijanni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiritano</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caroleo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Platelet-rich plasma inside the sternotomy wound reduces the incidence of sternal wound infections</article-title>. <source>Int Wound J.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>260</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/iwj.12087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23692143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7950781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamman</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stout</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Theologes</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sass</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Da Graca</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Filardo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Relation between topical application of platelet-rich plasma and vancomycin and severe deep sternal wound infections after a first median sternotomy</article-title>. <source>Am J Cardiol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>113</volume>:<fpage>1415</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjcard.2013.12.046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24576548</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Treatment of chronic femoral osteomyelitis with platelet-rich plasma (PRP): a case report</article-title>. <source>Transfus Apher Sci.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.transci.2008.01.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18343727</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ai</surname><given-names>ZS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The prophylactic effects of platelet-leucocyte gel in osteomyelitis: an experimental study in a rabbit model</article-title>. <source>J Bone Jt Surg - Ser B.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>304</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1302/0301-620X.92B2.22042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20130329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CQ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of leukocyte- and platelet-rich plasma gel (L-PRP gel) in treating osteomyelitis in a rabbit model</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Res.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>949</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jor.22299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23280538</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamza</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tidwell</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clovis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Unique antimicrobial effects of platelet-rich plasma and its efficacy as a prophylaxis to prevent implant-associated spinal infection</article-title>. <source>Adv Healthc Mater.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1277</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/adhm.201200465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23447088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3774283</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirzaei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daneshpajooh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farsinezhad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jafarian</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebadzadeh</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saberi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The therapeutic effect of intravesical instillation of platelet rich plasma on recurrent bacterial cystitis in women: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>Urol J.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>609</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.22037/uj.v0i0.5239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31535359</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sangiovanni</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiebzak</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prospective randomized evaluation of intraoperative application of autologous platelet-rich plasma on surgical site infection or delayed wound healing</article-title>. <source>Foot Ankle Int.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>470</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1071100715623994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26683126</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farghali</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>AbdElKader</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>AbuBakr</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aljuaydi</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khattab</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elhelw</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial action of autologous platelet-rich plasma on MRSA-infected skin wounds in dogs</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>12722</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-48657-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31481694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6722138</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tarantino</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gobbi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salom&#233;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Un nuovo semplice metodo per l'ottenimento della colla di fibrina autologa ad uso chirurgico</article-title>. <source>La Trasfus del sangue.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soffer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ouhayoun</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dosquet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meunier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anagnostou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of platelet lysates on select bone cell functions</article-title>. <source>Clin Oral Implants Res.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>581</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0501.2004.01063.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15355401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eberl</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Speth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hermann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hagleitner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deshmukh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Candida: Platelet interaction and platelet activity <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic></article-title>. <source>J Innate Immun.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000491030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30176656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6738150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Magiorakos</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carmeli</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falagas</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giske</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Multidrug-resistant, extensively drug-resistant and pandrug-resistant bacteria: An international expert proposal for interim standard definitions for acquired resistance</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Infect.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>268</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2011.03570.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21793988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI)</collab></person-group>. <source>Performance Standards for Antimicrobial Disk and Dilution Susceptibility Tests for Bacteria Isolated From Animals</source>. In: <edition>4th ed.</edition>, ed. CLSI supplement VET08. <publisher-loc>Wayne, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute</publisher-name> (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>The European Committee on Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing (EUCAST)</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Breakpoint tables for interpretation of MICs and zone diameters</article-title>. (<year>2018</year>) Version 8.1. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.eucast.org/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.eucast.org/</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leitner</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neum&#252;ller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kloimstein</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#246;cker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Platelet content and growth factor release in platelet-rich plasma: a comparison of four different systems</article-title>. <source>Vox Sang.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>91</volume>:<fpage>135</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1423-0410.2006.00815.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16907874</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rughetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caloprisco</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borean</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Necozione</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dell'Orso</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Platelet gel: assays of three growth factors</article-title>. <source>Blood Transfus.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>92</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>101</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCarrel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fortier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Temporal growth factor release from platelet-rich plasma, trehalose lyophilized platelets, and bone marrow aspirate and their effect on tendon and ligament gene expression</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Res.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1033</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jor.20853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19170097</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giusti</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rughetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Ascenzo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Millimaggi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pavan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dell'Orso L, Dolo V. Identification of an optimal concentration of platelet gel for promoting angiogenesis in human endothelial cells</article-title>. <source>Transfusion.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>771</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1537-2995.2008.02033.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19170984</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><label>77.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tambella</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Attili</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dupr&#233;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cantalamessa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuteri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Platelet-rich plasma to treat experimentally-induced skin wounds in animals: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>e0191093</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0191093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29324848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5764374</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><label>78.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazzucco</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balbo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guaschino</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>&#8220;Reasonable compromise&#8221; to define the quality standards of platelet concentrate for non-transfusion use (CPunT)</article-title>. <source>Transfus Apher Sci.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>207</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.transci.2012.06.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22795794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><label>79.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perego</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Proverbio</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baggiani</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nora Roggero</surname><given-names>BDGGSE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>In house double centrifugation method for preparation of homologous platelet-rich plasma (Prp) in dogs EC</article-title>. <source>Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>126</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><label>80.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bielecki</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dohan Ehrenfest</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>A Everts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiczkowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of leukocytes from L-PRP/L-PRF in wound healing and immune defense: new perspectives</article-title>. <source>Curr Pharm Biotechnol.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1153</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/138920112800624373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21740376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><label>81.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cie&#347;lik-Bielecka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reichert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skowro&#324;ski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kr&#243;likowska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bielecki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A new aspect of in vitro antimicrobial leukocyte- and platelet-rich plasma activity based on flow cytometry assessment</article-title>. <source>Platelets.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>728</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09537104.2018.1513472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30252585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><label>82.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Prysak</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zukofsky</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Everts</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Optimizing the safety of intradiscal platelet-rich plasma: an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> study with Cutibacterium acnes</article-title>. <source>Regen Med.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>955</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>67</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/rme-2019-0098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31587600</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><label>83.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giusti</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Francesco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D'Ascenzo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palumbo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rughetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dell'Orso</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Leukocyte depletion does not affect the in vitro healing ability of platelet rich plasma</article-title>. <source>Exp Ther Med.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>4029</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>38</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/etm.2018.5887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29556269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5844025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><label>84.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeaman</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of platelets in antimicrobial host defense</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis.</source> (<year>1997</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>951</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>68</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/516120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9402338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><label>85.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klinger</surname><given-names>MHF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jelkmann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Role of blood platelets in infection and inflammation</article-title>. <source>J Interf Cytokine Res.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>913</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/10799900260286623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12396713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><label>86.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lammel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rademacher</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gro&#223;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siggelkow</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lippross</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Platelet-released growth factors induce the antimicrobial peptide human beta-defensin-2 in primary keratinocytes</article-title>. <source>Exp Dermatol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>460</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/exd.12966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26843467</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><label>87.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeaman</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selsted</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial peptides from human platelets</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>6524</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.70.12.6524-6533.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12438321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC132966</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B88"><label>88.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mussano</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Genova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munaron</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrillo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erovigni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carossa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cytokine, chemokine, and growth factor profile of platelet-rich plasma</article-title>. <source>Platelets.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>467</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/09537104.2016.1143922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26950533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B89"><label>89.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuss</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Untrauer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Platelet-rich plasma for the treatment of tissue infection: Preparation and clinical evaluation</article-title>. <source>Tissue Eng - Part B Rev.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>225</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/ten.teb.2018.0309</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30712506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6589492</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>