<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8241929</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8241929.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8241929</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8241929</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34222403</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.680208</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Dietary Supplementation With Xylo-oligosaccharides Modifies the Intestinal Epithelial Morphology, Barrier Function and the Fecal Microbiota Composition and Activity in Weaned Piglets</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names initials="J">Jiayi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/599328/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="W">Wanghong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names initials="C">Cui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names initials="P">Peifeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blachier</surname><given-names initials="F">Francois</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiangfeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/638259/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Hunan Provincial Key Laboratory of Animal Nutritional Physiology and Metabolic Process, Chinese Academy of Sciences Key Laboratory of Agro-Ecological Processes in Subtropical Region, National Engineering Laboratory for Pollution Control and Waste Utilization in Livestock and Poultry Production, Institute of Subtropical Agriculture, Chinese Academy of Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Changsha</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Universit&#233; Paris-Saclay, AgroParisTech, INRAE, UMR PNCA</institution>, <addr-line>Paris</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Amlan Kumar Patra, West Bengal University of Animal and Fishery Sciences, India</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Yuheng Luo, Sichuan Agricultural University, China; Alessandra Pelagalli, University of Naples Federico II, Italy</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Xiangfeng Kong <email>nnkxf@isa.ac.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Animal Nutrition and Metabolism, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">374996</issue-id><elocation-id>680208</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>07</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-08-11 16:25:22.930"><day>11</day><month>08</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2021 Su, Zhang, Ma, Xie, Blachier and Kong.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Su, Zhang, Ma, Xie, Blachier and Kong</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-08-680208.pdf"/><abstract><p>The present study determined the effects of dietary xylo-oligosaccharides (XOS) supplementation on the morphology of jejunum and ileum epithelium, fecal microbiota composition, metabolic activity, and expression of genes related to colon barrier function. A total of 150 piglets were randomly assigned to one of five groups: a blank control group (receiving a basal diet), three XOS groups (receiving the basal diet supplemented with 100, 250, and 500 g/t XOS, respectively), as well as a positive control group, used as a matter of comparison, that received the basal diet supplemented with 0.04 kg/t virginiamycin, 0.2 kg/t colistin, and 3,000 mg/kg ZnO. The trial was carried out for 56 days. The results showed that the lowest dose tested (100 g/t XOS) increased (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) the ileal villus height, the relative amount of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> spp., and the concentration of acetic acid and short-chain fatty acid in feces when compared with the blank control group. In conclusion, dietary 100 g/t XOS supplementation modifies the intestinal ecosystem in weaned piglets in an apparently overall beneficial way.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>colon barrier function</kwd><kwd>intestine morphology</kwd><kwd>metabolites</kwd><kwd>microbiota</kwd><kwd>weaned piglets</kwd><kwd>xylo-oligosaccharides</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="7"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="52"/><page-count count="9"/><word-count count="6537"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Weaning is a critical stage for piglets that is associated with alterations in the morphology, architecture, and function of the gut, as well as changes in the enteric microbiota (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Weaned piglets consistently exhibit underdeveloped immune systems, digestive disorders, and post-weaning diarrhea (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), all of which decrease growth performance and cause economic loss for the swine industry (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Antibiotics and ZnO have long been incorporated into the diets of piglets to solve post-weaning problems (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), maybe by ameliorating the intestinal disorders that are concomitant with weaning. However, their continuous use and misuse have led to the emergence of drug resistance, the risk of residual antibiotics in animal products, and Zn-residues in the environment (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). In addition, the use of antibiotics in feed has been banned in China since 2020 to avoid development of antibiotic resistance among pathogenic microorganisms (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Moreover, the country has also limited the amount of zinc oxide in feed. These regulations promoted the exploration of natural plant bioactive compounds, probiotics, prebiotics, and other potential alternatives as feed additives to improve productivity, welfare, and health of livestock and poultry (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p><p>Natural plant bioactive compounds can improve barrier function and nutrient transport in the gastrointestinal and have antimicrobial, antioxidant, and various pharmacological effects (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). The consumption of probiotic bacteria contributes to intestinal function by maintaining paracellular permeability, enhancing the physical mucous layer, stimulating the immune system, and modulating resident microbiota composition and activity (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Prebiotics are compounds that, from an overall point of view, have the potential to influence positively some physiological functions, consequently, animal health, and well-being. Prebiotics may affect specifically and selectively the intestinal bacteria composition and/or metabolic activity (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Dietary modulation of the gut microflora by prebiotics is designed to improve health, and notably gut health, by stimulating numbers and/or activities of the so-called beneficial bacteria, such as the <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacilli</italic>. These beneficial bacteria may contribute to the increased resistance to pathogenic bacteria and the stimulation of the immune response (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>).</p><p>It is well-known that, for instance, &#946;-(2-1)-fructans, which include inulin and fructo-oligosaccharides (FOS), are considered as truly prebiotics, while xylo-oligosaccharides (XOS) are considered as candidate prebiotics (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). The XOS is a functional polymerized sugar made up of 2-8 xylose molecules bonded by &#946;-(<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) glycosidic bounds. In addition to xylose molecules, XOS is usually found in combination with other side groups such as &#945;-D-glucopyranosyl uronic acid or its 4-O-methyl derivative, acetyl groups, or arabinofuranosyl residues, resulting in branched XOS with diverse biological properties (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p><p>As pigs do not have endogenous enzymes in the small intestine to digest XOS, it is expected that unabsorbed XOS can reach the hindgut where they will be used for the growth of favorable bacteria and be fermented by the microbiota (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>) leading to the production of various metabolites. Some studies have shown that XOS preferentially stimulates the growth or activity of advantageous bacteria such as <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> and other lactic acid bacteria in the gastrointestinal tract (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Liu et al. (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) found that XOS supplementation may increase slightly ADFI, as well as the digestive enzyme trypsin and amylase activity, and fecal microbial shedding of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacilli</italic>, while decreasing fecal <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> counts. Chen et al. (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) have reported that dietary XOS supplementation enhanced the growth performance, improved intestinal morphology and modulated the relative abundance of specific bacteria by changing the overall microbial composition and bacterial metabolite production. The increased population of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> and decreased abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium_sensu_stricto_1, Escherichia_Shigella</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Terrisporobacter</italic> in piglets fed XOS 500 might be a contributor for improved growth characteristics (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p><p>Our previous study showed that XOS can significantly improve the growth of weaned pigs (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). The inclusion of XOS in weaned pigs' diets may enhance immune function and improve the growth of the intestinal mucosa layer and intestinal microbiota diversity (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). We hypothesized that dietary supplementation with XOS may exert beneficial effects on the jejunum and ileum morphology, fecal microbiota composition and bacterial metabolite concentrations, as well as expression of genes related to intestinal barrier function and cytokine production in colon of weaned piglets. Therefore, the aim of this study was to test this hypothesis and to determine what dose was most beneficial for the intestinal health of the weaned piglets.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Animals, Housing, and Treatment</title><p>A total of 150 Duroc &#215; Landrace &#215; Large White piglets weaned at 21-day-old with an average body weight of 7.02 &#177; 0.05 kg were used in this study. The piglets were randomly assigned to one of five groups with six replicates per group and five piglets per replicate. The five groups consisted of a blank control group (receiving a basal diet), three groups receiving the basal diet supplemented with 100, 250, or 500 g/t XOS group (XOS is mixed in the basal diet as one of feed additives), as well as a comparative group receiving a classical mixture of compounds (the basal diet supplemented with 0.04 kg/t virginiamycin, 0.2 kg/t colistin, and 3,000 mg/kg ZnO). The XOS were provided by Shandong Longlive Bio-technology Co. Ltd (Shandong, China), which contain xylobiose, xylotriose, and xylotetraose at &#8805;35%. The doses used for supplementation was according to the manufacturer's recommendations.</p><p>All pigs were housed in 2.0 m &#215; 2.5 m pens with hard plastic slatted flooring and had <italic toggle="yes">ad libitum</italic> access to drinking water and the experimental diets. Each pen was equipped with a stainless-steel feeder and a nipple drinker. The room temperature was maintained at 25&#8211;27&#176;C. The composition and nutrient levels of the basal diet are shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The trial lasted for 56 days.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Composition and nutrient levels of the basal diet (fed-basis).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Ingredients</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Stages of the trial</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7&#8211;28 days</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>29&#8211;40 days</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>41&#8211;56 days</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corn</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">695.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Extruded corn</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Broken rice</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat flour</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean meal (46% CP)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean meal (43% CP)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Puffed soybean</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fermented soybean meal</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean protein concentrate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fish meal</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasma</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low-protein whey powder</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Egg powder</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat bran</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean oil</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Citric acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Premix<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1000.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nutrient component<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DE (MJ/kg)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.81</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.59</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EE</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.71</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.47</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CF</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.76</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Met</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cys</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><label>a</label><p><italic toggle="yes">The premix provided the following per kg of the diet: VA 6 200 IU, VD3 700 IU, VE 88 IU, VK 4.4 mg, VB2 8.8 mg, Pantothenate 24.2 mg, nicotinic acid 33 mg, Chloride choline 330 mg, Cu 10 mg, Zn 100 mg, Fe 145 mg, Mn 40 mg, Se 0.1 mg, I 0.3 mg</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN2"><label>b</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Nutrient contents are calculated values. DE, digestible energy; CP, crude protein; EE, ether extract; CF, crude fiber; Lys, lysine; Met, methionine; Cys, cysteine</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Sample Collection and Preparation</title><p>At days 7, 21, and 56 of the trial, the feces were collected and stored at &#8722;20&#176;C for analysis of short-chain fatty acids (SCFA) and of the microbiota composition. At the end of the 56-day trial period and 12 h after the last feeding, a medium-sized piglet per replicate was sacrificed using general anesthesia with Zoletil (15 mg tiletamine/kg body weight, 15 mg zolazepam/kg body weight, intramuscular injection) (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). After intestine recovery, samples of the jejunum, ileal, and colonic samples (~2 cm) were collected after washing with cold physiological saline, the jejunum and ileum were immediately fixed in 10% neutral formalin solution until further morphological analysis, and colon samples were frozen in liquid nitrogen and then stored at &#8722;80&#176;C until gene expression analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>The Measurement of Jejunal and Ileal Morphology</title><p>Histological slides were prepared from 3 cross-sections (5 &#956;m thick) of each intestinal sample, which were processed in low-melt paraffin and stained with hematoxylin-eosin. Villus height (VH) and crypt depth (CD) were measured using the Olympus BX-51 microscope (Olympus, Center Valley, PA, USA), and VH:CD (V/C) ratio were calculated.</p></sec><sec><title>DNA Extraction and Fecal Microbiota Analysis</title><p>Total microbial DNA was extracted and purified using a QIAamp DNA Stool Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) and stored at &#8722;80&#176;C. The 16S rRNA gene sequences of <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes, Bifidobacterium</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> were cloned into the pMD19-T vector (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Gene sequences were amplified from fecal total DNA using the primers listed in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. A total of five clones with 16S rRNA gene sequences belonging to different taxa were used as templates to test primer specificity. Standard curves were constructed with DNA from representative species for a concentration range of 10<sup>2</sup>&#8211;10<sup>10</sup> DNA copies/mL using a Lightcycler 480II instrument (Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, CA, USA). The general microbial DNA extracted from feces and specific DNA from recombinant microbiota were quantified by RT-PCR. Reaction conditions were 2 min at 50&#176;C, an initial denaturation step at 95&#176;C for 5 min, and then 40 cycles of denaturation at 94&#176;C for 20 s, primer annealing at a species-specific temperature for 30 s, and primer extension at 60&#176;C for 1 min (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>16S rRNA gene-targeted group-specific primers used in this study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Items</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sequence (5<sup><bold>&#8242;</bold></sup>&#8211;3<sup><bold>&#8242;</bold></sup>)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Amplicon length (bp)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F:GGARCATGTGGTTTAATTCGATGAT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R:AGCTGACGACAACCATGCAG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> spp.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F:TCGCGTCYGGTGTGAAAG</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R:GGTGTTCTTCCCGATATCTACA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F:CATGCCGCGTGTATGAAGAA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R:CGGGTAACGTCAATGAGCAAA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F:AGCAGTAGGGAATCTTCCA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">345</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R:ATTCCACCGCTACACATG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R:ACGTCRTCCMCNCCTTCCTC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Analysis of the Fecal Concentrations of Metabolites</title><p>At time of euthanasia, the feces of each pigs were sampled, homogenized, and centrifuged at 1,000 &#215; g for 10 min (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). A mixture of supernatant fluid and 25% metaphosphoric acid solution (1:0.25 ml) was prepared for determining the SCFA by gas chromatography (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Analysis of mRNA Levels of Genes Related to Barrier Function in Colonic Tissues</title><p>The analysis of mRNA levels of genes related to barrier function in colonic tissues was conducted according to a previous study. Total RNA was isolated from colonic samples using the TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) and treated with DNAase. The RNA quality was checked by 1% agarose gel electrophoresis followed by staining with 10 &#956;g/mL ethidium bromide. The OD260:OD280 ratio of extracted RNA was between 1.8 and 2.0. Reverse transcription was performed using a Prime Script RT reagent Kit with gDNA eraser (Takara, Dalian, China). The mRNA levels of the selected genes in the colon tissues were determined by real-time quantitative (RT-qPCR) as described previously (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Selected genes were intestinal tight junction proteins, including <italic toggle="yes">occludin, Claudin 2</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Claudin 3</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">zonula occludens-1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">ZO-1</italic>); <italic toggle="yes">interleukin-10 (IL-10), IL-1</italic>&#946;, and <italic toggle="yes">IL-8</italic>. The primers used to amplify these genes are shown in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. The relative expression was reported as a ratio of the expression of the target genes to that of beta-actin (&#946;-actin), and data were expressed relative to those in the basal diet-treated piglets. The relative expression ratio (R) of mRNA was calculated as R = 2<sup>&#8722;&#916;<italic toggle="yes">&#916;Ct</italic></sup> &#215; (sample &#8722; control), where -&#916;&#916;Ct &#215; (sample &#8722; control) = (Ct<sub>target gene</sub> &#8722; Ct<sub>&#946;&#8722;<italic toggle="yes">actin</italic></sub>) &#215; sample &#8722; (Ct<sub>target gene</sub> &#8722; Ct<sub>&#946;&#8722;<italic toggle="yes">actin</italic></sub>) &#215; control. RT-qPCR was performed using a SYBR Green detection kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA), and conditions were as follows: 30 s denaturation at 94&#176;C, 30 s annealing at 60&#176;C, and 30 s extension at 72&#176;C for 40 cycles, followed by a melting curve program (60&#8211;99&#176;C with a heating rate of 0.1&#176;C/s and fluorescence measurement). A melting temperature (T<sub>m</sub>) peak at 85 &#177; 0.8&#176;C was used to determine the specificity of amplification. T<sub>m</sub> values are reported as the mean of three replicates.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Primers used for quantitative reverse transcription PCR.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Items</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Genbank accession number</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sequence (5<sup>&#8242;</sup>&#8211;3<sup>&#8242;</sup>)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Length (bp)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">&#946;-actin</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XM_003357928.1">XM_003357928.1</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F:GGACTTCGAGCAGGAGATGG<break/>R:GCACCGTGTTGGCGTAGAGG</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Occludin</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="NM_001163647.1">NM_001163647.1</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F:ATGCTTTCTCAGCCAGCGTA<break/>R:AAGGTTCCATAGCCTCGGTC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Claudin 2</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="NM_001161638">NM_001161638</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F:TGGTGGGTGGAGTCTTCTTC<break/>R: TTGGAGCGATTTCCTTGC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Claudin 3</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="NM_001160075">NM_001160075</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F:GATGCAGTGCAAAGTGTACGA<break/>R:GTCCTGCACGCAGTTGGT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ZO-1</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="XM_003353439.1">XM_003353439.1</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F:GAGGATGGTCACACCGTGGT<break/>R:GGAGGATGCTGTTGTCTCGG</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">169</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">IL-1&#946;</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="NM_214055.1">NM_214055.1</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F:AGTGGAGAAGCCGATGAAGA<break/>R:CATTGCACGTTTCAAGGATG</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">IL-8</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="NM_213867.1">NM_213867.1</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F:TAGGACCAGAGCCAGGAAGA<break/>R:AGCAGGAAAACTGCCAAGAA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">IL-10</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="NM_214041.1">NM_214041.1</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F:CTGCCTCCCACTTTCTCTTG<break/>R:TCAAAGGGGCTCCCTAGTTT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">&#946;, beta; IL, interleukin; ZO-1, zonula occludens-1</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Results were statistically analyzed using one-way ANOVA of SPSS 17.0 software (SPSS, Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). The pen was included as a random effect for data analysis. The data were presented as means, pooled SEM, and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values &lt; 0.05 were taken to indicate statistical significance.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>The Morphology of the Epithelium of Jejunum and Ileum</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, the CD and VH of jejunum in the 100 g/t XOS group increased (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in comparison to the positive control group. The V/C ratio of jejunum in the 500 g/t XOS group was higher (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) than the blank control group. The VH of ileum in the 100 g/t XOS group increased (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in comparison to the other four groups.</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Effects of dietary XOS supplementation on the morphology of jejunal and ileal epithelium in weaned piglets (n = 6; data are mean values in &#956;m).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Items</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Blank control group</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>XOS-supplemented groups (g/t)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Positive control group</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Pooled SEM</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P-</italic>value</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>100</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>250</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>500</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Jejunum</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Villus height</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">510.55<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">607.62<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">484.20<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">497.45<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">482.98<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crypt depth</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">324.42<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">377.73<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">297.89<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">277.68<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">297.08<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V:C ratio</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Ileum</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Villus height</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">418.70<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">492.4<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">389.53<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">428.41<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">401.92<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crypt depth</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219.66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">259.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222.78</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">242.92</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221.87</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">V:C ratio</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.92</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.84</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">Data in the same row with different superscripts differ significantly (P &lt; 0.05). V:C ratio, Villus height:Crypt depth ratio</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Composition of Fecal Microbiota in Piglets</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>, the relative abundances of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus, Bifidobacterium</italic> spp<italic toggle="yes">., Escherichia coli</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> in the feces did not change (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05) after XOS supplementation at day 7 of the trial. In the 250 and 500 g/t XOS groups and the positive control group, the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> was lower (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) than the blank control group at day 21 of the trial. At day 56 of the trial, the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> in the 100 g/t XOS group was higher (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) than the blank control group. In the 100, 250, and 500 g/t XOS groups, the relative abundances of <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> spp. was higher (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) than the blank control group. In the 100 g/t XOS group, the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic> was higher when compared to the positive control group.</p><table-wrap id="T5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Effects of dietary XOS supplementation on fecal microbiota abundance in weaned piglets (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6; lg copies/g).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Items</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Blank control group</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>XOS-supplemented groups (g/t)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Positive control group</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Pooled SEM</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P-</italic>value</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>100</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>250</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>500</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><bold>Day 7</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.82</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.89</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> spp.</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.44</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.68</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.58</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.84</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.35</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.71</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.79</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.68</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.69</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><bold>Day 21</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.90<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.33<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.94<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.57<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.50<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> spp.</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.78</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.84</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.91</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.54</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.84</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.80</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.55</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.54</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><bold>Day 56</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.36<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.84<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.47<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.43<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.57<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> spp.</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.20<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.15<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.13<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.14<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.94<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.61</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.49</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.58</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.90<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.10<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.85<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.98<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.66<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">Data in the same row with different superscripts differ significantly (P &lt; 0.05)</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Concentrations of Bacterial Metabolites in the Feces of Piglets</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="T6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>, at day 7 of the trial, the acetic acid concentration in 100, 250, and 500 g/t XOS groups and the positive control group were higher (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) than the blank control group. Dietary supplementation with 250 g/t XOS increased (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) the SCFA concentration compared with the blank control group. At day 21 of the trial, the concentration of isovaleric acid in the 100 g/t XOS group increased (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) compared with the other four groups. At day 56 of the trial, the concentration of acetic acid and SCFA in the 100 g/t XOS group was higher (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), as well as the butyric acid and SCFA in the 250 g/t XOS group, when compared with the two control groups.</p><table-wrap id="T6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Effects of dietary XOS supplementation on concentrations of short-chain fatty acids in colonic contents of weaned piglets (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6; data are mean value in mg/g).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Items</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Blank control group</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>XOS-supplemented groups (g/t)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Positive control group</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Pooled SEM</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P-</italic>value</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>100</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>250</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>500</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><bold>Day 7</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.85<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.65<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.96<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propionic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Butyric acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valeric acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isobutyric acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isovaleric acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short-chain fatty acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.74<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.87<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.72<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.55<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.39<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><bold>Day 21</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propionic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Butyric acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valeric acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isobutyric acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isovaleric acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short-chain fatty acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.74</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.69</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.97</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.58</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><bold>Day 56</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.94<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.82<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.66<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propionic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Butyric acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valeric acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isobutyric acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isovaleric acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short-chain fatty acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.37<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.66<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.97<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.28<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.59<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">Data in the same row with different superscripts differ significantly (P &lt; 0.05). Short-chain fatty acid, including acetic acid, ropionic acid, butyric acid, valeric acid, isobutyric acid, and isovaleric acid</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Expression of Genes Related to Intestinal Barrier Function and Cytokine in the Colon</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="T7" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>, dietary supplementation with 100 g/t XOS increased (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) the mRNA level of <italic toggle="yes">Claudin 2</italic> compared with the positive control group. Dietary supplementation with 250 g/t XOS increased (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) the mRNA level of <italic toggle="yes">ZO-1</italic> compared with the blank control group.</p><table-wrap id="T7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Effects of dietary XOS supplementation on colon mRNA levels related to epithelial cell barrier function and inflammation in weaned piglets (n = 6).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Items</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Blank control group</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>XOS-supplemented groups (g/t)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Positive control group</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Pooled SEM</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">P-</italic>value</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>100</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>250</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>500</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Occludin</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Claudin 2</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Claudin 3</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ZO-1</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">IL-1&#946;</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">IL-8</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">IL-10</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">Data in the same row with different superscripts differ significantly (P &lt; 0.05). IL, interleukin; ZO-1, zonula occludens-1; &#946;, beta</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Recently, the intestinal microbiota composition and related metabolic activities have emerged as important parameters affecting either positively or negatively &#8220;intestinal health&#8221; (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Components such as microbiota composition, diversity and bacterial metabolite concentrations can affect the epithelial integrity, barrier function, immunity, and enteroendocrine peptides secretion. It is known that the intestinal microbiota has genomic characteristics that allow it to use undigested or partially digested nutrients, notably proteins and undigested polysaccharides, present in feedstuff. In return, it benefits the host metabolism by providing energy through the production of metabolites that can be utilized and absorbed by colonic cells (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Conversely, some amino acid-derived bacterial metabolites have been shown to exert deleterious effects on colonic epithelial cells when present in excess (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). It has been demonstrated that regarding oligo-saccharides, numerous types of these compounds may represent a potential alternative to antibiotic treatment for contributing to the maintenance of microbial composition and/or metabolic activity with positive effect on gut health (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Indeed, David et al. (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>) reviewed the beneficial effects of different oligo-saccharides, including <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>-acetylglucosamine, oligo-fructose, lactulose, and various glycoproteins, as prebiotics to improve the gut health. Li et al. (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) found that XOS promotes the growth of <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> in the gut and increases the SCFA content in these intestinal microbes, these effects in turn being associated with an improvement of the intestinal barrier function (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). In the present study, three doses of XOS were used according to the manufacturer's recommendations.</p><p>Gut villus structure and barrier integrity play an important role in intestinal function, including nutrient digestibility, absorption, and protecting against pathogen infection (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). An increase of villus height suggests a larger surface area capable of greater absorption of available nutrients (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). The villus height/crypt height ratio is used as a criterion to estimate the nutrient final digestion step and absorption capacity of the small intestine (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Prebiotics were reported to improve growth <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> promoting nutrient absorption by improving intestinal structure (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). In this study, we found that dietary supplementation with 500 g/t XOS increased the villus height/crypt height ratio in jejunum. In addition, we found that dietary supplementation with 100 g/t XOS increased the villus height in ileum. This confirms the results obtained by Mourao et al. (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>) showing a positive relationship between dietary oligosaccharides supplementation and higher intestinal villi in piglets. Chen et al. found that villus height and villus height:crypt depth ratio of the ileum in the 500 g/t XOS treatment group was significantly increased compared to the CON group. De Maesschalck et al. (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) found that supplementation of 0.5% XOS to the broiler feed significantly improved the villus height of the ileum. These reports are all converging in showing that XOS can improve intestinal structure, in accordance with our finding, however with different doses used. Additional works are required in order to better clarify the relationship between dose and parameters related to intestinal functions.</p><p>Gut microbiota are the resident microorganisms in the digestive tracts of animals and humans, which affect nutrient digestion and the bioconversion of food compounds in the host organisms (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Oligosaccharides can be fermented in the large intestine by indigenous bacteria and are preferably used by probiotic bacteria (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Prebiotics are non-digestible feed ingredients that are believed to escape digestion in the upper gut and that may selectively stimulate the growth of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacilli</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> in colon, thereby possibly improving health (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). Our results indicated that 100 g/t XOS increased the growth of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bacteroidetes</italic>. What's more, 100, 250, and 500 g/t XOS increased the growth of <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> spp. at day 56 of the trial. It confirms that XOS can improve gut microbiota communities. Increased level of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> spp. has been proposed to reinforce the epithelial barrier function against common pathogens. The mechanisms are likely to include the excretion of organic acids (e.g., lactic acid and acetic acid), competition for nutrients with deleterious bacteria, competition at gut receptor sites, and immune-modulation and formation of specific antimicrobial agents (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Moreover, we found that the advantage of 100 g/t XOS in changing intestinal microecology was revealed by the analysis of the different kinetics time points, such analysis showing that the effects of XOS is a long-term process.</p><p>It is well-known that the SCFAs are main products of the microbial fermentation of complex carbohydrates (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). These SCFAs are the preferred energy source for the colonic epithelium and may stimulate colonocyte proliferation and influence various aspects of gut physiology. Most of functional oligosaccharides are not digested for lack of relevant enzymes, and reach the colon in their initial form, before being fermented by anaerobic bacteria (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Such metabolic process produces SCFAs. The amounts and types of SCFA produced depend on the type of non-digestible oligosaccharides as well as on the composition of the intestinal microbial flora (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). Our results showed that 100 g/t XOS increase the concentrations of acetic acid and SCFAs in the colon at day 56 of the trial. We have known that the production of SCFA results in decrease of pH in the colon, such a decrease inhibiting the growth of certain pathogenic bacterium while stimulating the growth of the beneficial bacteria (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). This also explains why the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> spp. increased at 56 days of the trial. The SCFAs have been noted to have immunomodulatory effects on colonic inflammation and suppress inflammatory cytokine secretion in cultured epithelial cells (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). Increased availability of butyric acid for the colonocyte may be associated with decreases of the inflammatory parameters (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). In the present study, 250 g/t XOS supplementation increased the concentration of butyric acid at day 56 of the trial, but did not regulate the mRNA levels of inflammatory cytokines (<italic toggle="yes">IL-1</italic>&#946;, <italic toggle="yes">IL-8</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">IL-10</italic>), which is not consistent with the findings presented above. The reason and significance needs further investigations.</p><p>The surface of the gut epithelium is protected by a layer of mucus, which is in constant contact with an abundant population of microbiota and their metabolites (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). One aspect of the intestinal barrier is related to an intact intestinal epithelium with functional junctional complex, consisting of tight junctions (TJ, including <italic toggle="yes">occludin, claudin</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">ZO-1</italic>), adherens junctions (AJs, including <italic toggle="yes">E-Cadherin</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">catenins</italic>), gap junctions, and desmosomes (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Such an intact epithelium is able to exclude the vast majority of the microbiota from access to the subepithelial cells in the lamina propria (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Our results indicated that the 250 g/t XOS up-regulated the mRNA level of <italic toggle="yes">ZO-1</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">ZO-1</italic> serves as a scaffold protein and anchors tight junction strand proteins (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). Yin et al. (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>) also have reported that dietary XOS markedly enhanced the mRNA level of <italic toggle="yes">ZO-1</italic> in the ileum. However, further work is needed to determine if such an increased expression of <italic toggle="yes">ZO-1</italic> is paralleled by a modification of the epithelial barrier function. Christensen et al. (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>) have reported that the relative abundances of beneficial microbiota have been found a highly association with gut barrier. But the data of our study did not prove such an association. Moreover, no differences in the mRNA levels of <italic toggle="yes">Occludin, Claudin 2</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Claudin 3</italic> were recorded when comparisons between XOS-supplemented groups and blank control group were done, thus indicating that the effect of XOS on <italic toggle="yes">ZO-1</italic> gene expression among other genes coding for tight junction protein appears rather specific. Additional studies are obviously required to define the complex relationships between the different parameters modified by dietary XOS supplementation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The lowest dose of xylo-oligosaccharides tested (100 g/t) increases the villus height in ileum, the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> spp. and the concentrations of acetic acid and short-chain fatty acid. Thus, 100 g/t xylo-oligosaccharides supplementation impacts the ileal morphology and colon ecosystem in weaned piglets. According to our findings, we recommend supplementation with 100 g/t xylo-oligosaccharides to feed in order to obtain the most presumed beneficial effects on the gut ecosystem.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The datasets presented in this study can be found in online repositories. The names of the repository/repositories and accession number(s) can be found at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by Animal Care and Use Committee of Institute of Subtropical Agriculture, Chinese Academy of Sciences.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>JS, WZ, CM, PX, and XK performed the experiments. JS, FB, and XK wrote the manuscript. JS and XK performed the statistical analysis. JS, WZ, and PX fed the animals. All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank staffs and postgraduate students of Hunan Provincial Engineering Research Center of Healthy Livestock for collecting samples and technicians from CAS Key Laboratory of Agro-ecological Processes in Subtropical Region for providing technical assistance.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> The present study was jointly supported by the National Key Research and Development Project (2018YFD0500404-4), National Natural Science Foundation of China (31772613), and Special Funds for Construction of Innovative Provinces in Hunan Province (2019RS3022).</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boudry</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peron</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le</surname><given-names>Huerou-Luron I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lalles</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seve</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Weaning induces both transient and long-lasting modifications of absorptive, secretory, and barrier properties of piglet intestine</article-title>. <source>J Nutr.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>134</volume>:<fpage>2256</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jn/134.9.2256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15333713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>GQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Differential expression of toll-like receptor 4 signaling pathway genes in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> F18-resistant and sensitive meishan piglets</article-title>. <source>Pol J Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>303</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/pjvs-2016-0037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27487503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amezcua</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friendship</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dewey</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gyles</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fairbrother</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Presentation of postweaning <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> diarrhea in southern ontario, prevalence of hemolytic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> serogroups involved, and their antimicrobial resistance patterns</article-title>. <source>Can J Vet Res.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>73</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>78</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11989737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC226986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antibiotic use in animal feed and its impact on human health</article-title>. <source>Nutr Res Rev.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>279</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>99</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/095442200108729106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19087443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monroe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial use and bacterial resistance</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Microbiol.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>496</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>501</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1369-5274(00)00129-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11050449</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kehrenberg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Use of antimicrobial agents in veterinary medicine and food animal production</article-title>. <source>Int J Antimicrob Agents.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>431</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0924-8579(01)00297-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11397611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Macleaya cordata extract, an antibiotic alternative, does not contribute to antibiotic resistance gene dissemination</article-title>. <source>J Hazard Mater</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>412</volume>:<fpage>125272</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jhazmat.2021.125272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33550129</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patra</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amasheh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aschenbach</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Modulation of gastrointestinal barrier and nutrient transport function in farm animals by natural plant bioactive compounds-a comprehensive review</article-title>. <source>Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>3237</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10408398.2018.1486284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29889546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boirivant</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strober</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The mechanism of action of probiotics</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Gastroenterol.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>679</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MOG.0b013e3282f0cffc</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17906447</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aachary</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prapulla</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Xylooligosaccharides (XOS) as an emergingprebiotic: microbial synthesis, utilization, structural characterization, bioactive properties, and applications</article-title>. <source>Compr Rev Food Sci Food Safety.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1541-4337.2010.00135.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Microbial-gut interactions in health and disease. Prebiotics</article-title>. <source>Best Pract Res Cl Ga.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>287</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>98</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpg.2003.10.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15123070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lecerf</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#233;peint</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clerc</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dugenet</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niamba</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rhazi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Xylo-oligosaccharide (XOS) in combination with inulin modulates both the intestinal environment and immune status in healthy subjects, while XOS alone only shows prebiotic properties</article-title>. <source>Brit J Nutr.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>108</volume>:<fpage>1847</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>58</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007114511007252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22264499</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freire</surname><given-names>JPB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esteves</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of xylo-oligosaccharides from corn cobs autohydrolysis on the intestinal microbiota of piglets after weaning</article-title>. <source>Livest Sci.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>108</volume>:<fpage>244</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.livsci.2007.01.053</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Summanen</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henning</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heiman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Xylooligosaccharide supplementation alters gut bacteria in both healthy and prediabetic adults: a pilot study</article-title>. <source>Front Physiol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>216</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2015.00216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26300782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4528259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Satyanarayana</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Xylooligosaccharides: an economical prebiotic from agroresidues and their health benefits</article-title>. <source>Indian J Exp Biol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>131</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25872243</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Production of xylooligosaccharide from wheat bran by microwave assisted enzymatic hydrolysis</article-title>. <source>Food Chem.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>138</volume>:<fpage>1531</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2012.09.124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23411277</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of probiotics and xylo-oligosaccharide supplementation on nutrient digestibility, intestinal health and noxious gas emission in weanling pigs</article-title>. <source>Asian-Australas J Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>1660</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5713/ajas.17.0908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29642680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6127592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Everaert</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of xylo-oligosaccharides on growth and gut microbiota as potential replacements for antibiotic in weaning piglets</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>641172</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.641172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33717037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7947891</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of xylo-oligosaccharide on growth performance, diarrhea rate and plasma biochemical parameters of weaned piglets</article-title>. <source>Chinese J Anim Nutr.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>2556</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3969/j.issn.1006-267x.2016.08.028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects and interaction of dietary electrolyte balance and citric acid on the intestinal function of weaned piglets</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jas/skaa106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32253427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7199884</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raveh-Sadka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Firek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Castelle</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Gut bacteria are rarely shared by co-hospitalized premature infants, regardless of necrotizing enterocolitis development</article-title>. <source>eLife.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e05477</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.05477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25735037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4384745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Decroos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eeckhaut</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Possemiers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verstraete</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Administration of equol-producing bacteria alters the equol production status in the simulator of the gastrointestinal microbial ecosystem (SHIME)</article-title>. <source>J Nutr.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>136</volume>:<fpage>946</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jn/136.4.946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16549455</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Soybean oligosaccharides alter colon short-chain fatty acid production and microbial population in vitro</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>90</volume>(<issue>Suppl. 4</issue>):<fpage>37</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/jas.50269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23365277</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>GQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blachier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary supplementation with soybean oligosaccharides increases short-chain fatty acids but decreases protein-derived catabolites in the intestinal luminal content of weaned Huanjiang mini-piglets</article-title>. <source>Nutr Res.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>780</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nutres.2014.08.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25236424</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization and regulation of the amino acid transporter SNAT2 in the small intestine of piglets</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e0128207</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0128207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26107628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4479573</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blachier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beaumont</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andriamihaja</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davila</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grauso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in the luminal environment of the colonic epithelial cells and physiopathological consequences</article-title>. <source>Am J Pathol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>187</volume>:<fpage>476</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>86</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajpath.2016.11.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28082121</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cani</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delzenne</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Gut microflora as a target for energy and metabolic homeostasis</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Clin Nutr Metab.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>729</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MCO.0b013e3282efdebb</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18089955</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piao</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of chito-oligosaccharide supplementation on the growth performance, nutrient digestibility, intestinal morphology, and fecal shedding of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> and Lactobacillus in weaning pigs</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>2609</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/jas.2007-0668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18502883</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>David</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Probiotics, prebiotics, and synbiotics: approaches for modulating the microbial ecology of the gut</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr.</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>1052S</fpage>&#8722;<lpage>7S</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ajcn/69.5.1052s</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10232648</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Summanen</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Komoriya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finegold</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> study of the prebiotic xylooligosaccharide (XOS) on the growth of <italic toggle="yes">Bifidobacterium</italic> spp and Lactobacillus spp</article-title>. <source>Int J Food Sci Nutr.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>919</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/09637486.2015.1064869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26171632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hydrogen peroxide-induced oxidative stress activates NF-kappa B and Nrf2/Keap1 signals and triggers autophagy in piglets</article-title>. <source>RSC Adv.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>15479</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>86</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C4RA13557A</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caspary</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Physiology and pathophysiology of intestinal absorption</article-title>. <source>Am J Clin Nutr.</source> (<year>1992</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>299S</fpage>&#8722;<lpage>308S</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ajcn/55.1.299s</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1728844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Montagne</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pluske</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hampson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A review of interactions between dietary fibre and the intestinal mucosa, and their consequences on digestive health in young non-ruminant animals</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>108</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>117</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0377-8401(03)00163-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The influences of soybean agglutinin and functional oligosaccharides on the intestinal tract of monogastric animals</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>554</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms19020554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29439523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5855776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mourao</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guedes</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saavedra</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of mannan oligosaccharides on the performance, intestinal morphology and cecal fermentation of fattening rabbits</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>126</volume>:<fpage>107</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2005.06.009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De</surname><given-names>Maesschalck C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eeckhaut</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maertens</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De</surname><given-names>Lange L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marchal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nezer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of xylo-oligosaccharides on broiler chicken performance and microbiota</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>81</volume>:<fpage>5880</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01616-15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26092452</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4551243</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Fermented green tea extract alleviates obesity and related complications and alters gut microbiota composition in diet-induced obese mice</article-title>. <source>J Med Food.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>549</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/jmf.2014.3265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25764354</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberfroid</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary modulation of the human colonic microbiota: introducing the concept of prebiotics</article-title>. <source>J Nutr.</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>75</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/NRR200479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7782892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Macfarlane</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Probiotics and prebiotics: can regulating the activities of intestinal bacteria benefit health?</article-title><source>Br Med J.</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>318</volume>:<fpage>999</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1003</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.318.7189.999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10195977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1115424</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fooks</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Probiotics as modulators of the gut flora</article-title>. <source>Br J Nutr.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>S39</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/BJN2002628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12215180</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laparra</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanz</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Interactions of gut microbiota with functional food components and nutraceuticals</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Res.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>219</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phrs.2009.11.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19914380</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crittenden</surname><given-names>RGA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Playne</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Production, properties and applications of food-grade oligosaccharides</article-title>. <source>Trends Food Sci Tech.</source> (<year>1996</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>353</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0924-2244(96)10038-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sako</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Recent progress on research and applications of non-digestible galacto-oligosaccharides</article-title>. <source>Int Dairy J.</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>0</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0958-6946(99)00046-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Defoirdt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Halet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sorgeloos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bossier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verstraete</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Short-chain fatty acids protect gnotobiotic artemia franciscana from pathogenic vibrio campbellii</article-title>. <source>Aquaculture.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>261</volume>:<fpage>804</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquaculture.2006.06.038</pub-id>17391334</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hojo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Inhibition of the cytotoxic effect of Clostridium difficile in vitro by Clostridium butyricum MIYAIRI 588 strain</article-title>. <source>J Med Microbiol.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>60</volume>:<fpage>1617</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.033423-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21700738</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Collierhyams</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The bacterial fermentation product butyrate influences epithelial signaling via reactive oxygen species-mediated changes in cullin-1 neddylation</article-title>. <source>J Immunol.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>182</volume>:<fpage>538</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.182.1.538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19109186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2872164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borthakur</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anbazhagan</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raheja</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dudeja</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The probiotic Lactobacillus plantarum counteracts TNF-{alpha}-induced downregulation of SMCT1 expression and function</article-title>. <source>AM J Physiol-Gastr L.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>299</volume>:<fpage>928</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpgi.00279.2010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20671196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2957335</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartsock</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Adherens and tight junctions: structure, function and connections to the actin cytoskeleton</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta Biomembr.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>1778</volume>:<fpage>660</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamem.2007.07.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17854762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2682436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ukena</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dringenberg</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Engelhardt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seidler</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Probiotic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> Nissle 1917 inhibits leaky gut by enhancing mucosal integrity</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>e1308</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0001308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18074031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2110898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buschmann</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romero-Calvo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sailer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of molecular remodeling in differential regulation of tight junction permeability</article-title>. <source>Semin Cell Dev Biol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>204</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.semcdb.2014.09.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25263012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4253049</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>FN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary xylo-oligosaccharide improves intestinal functions in weaned piglets</article-title>. <source>Food Funct.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>2701</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C8FO02485E</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31025998</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Licht</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bahl</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bifidogenic effect of whole-grain wheat during a 12-week energy-restricted dietary intervention in postmenopausal women</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Nutr.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>1316</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ejcn.2013.207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24149441</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><glossary><def-list><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term>AJ</term><def><p>adherens junctions</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IL</term><def><p>interleukin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RT-qPCR</term><def><p>real-time quantitative PCR</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SCFA</term><def><p>short-chain fatty acids</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TJ</term><def><p>tight junctions</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>XOS</term><def><p>xylo-oligosaccharides</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ZO</term><def><p>zonula occludens.</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></back></article></pmc-articleset>