<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Vet Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Vet Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2350</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jvms</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JVMS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Veterinary Medical Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0916-7250</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1347-7439</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8498835</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8498835.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8498835</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8498835</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34248083</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.21-0216</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">21-0216</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Internal Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Full Paper</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Dynamic computed tomography evaluation of the nasopharynx in normal Beagle dogs</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>NOH</surname><given-names initials="D">Daji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>CHOI</surname><given-names initials="S">Sooyoung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>CHOI</surname><given-names initials="H">Hojung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>LEE</surname><given-names initials="Y">Youngwon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>LEE</surname><given-names initials="K">Kija</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1)</label>College of Veterinary Medicine, Kyungpook National University, Daegu 41566, Korea</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2)</label>College of Veterinary Medicine, Kangwon National University, Chuncheon 24341, Korea</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3)</label>College of Veterinary Medicine, Chungnam National University, Daejeon 34134, Korea</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Correspondence to: Lee, K.: <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="leekj@knu.ac.kr">leekj@knu.ac.kr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>7</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>83</volume><issue>9</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">391530</issue-id><fpage>1356</fpage><lpage>1362</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>09</day><month>4</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>09</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2021-10-14 00:16:38.120"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2021</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169;2021 The Japanese Society of Veterinary Science</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License. (CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"> https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>)</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jvms-83-1356.pdf"/><abstract><p>Pharyngeal collapsibility has been used as diagnostic criteria in dogs, whereas the normal range and quantitative method have not been studied. Dynamic and static computed tomography (CT)
was performed in 23 normal Beagle dogs to quantify the nasopharyngeal collapsibility at different locations. Using dynamic CT, maximum and minimum nasopharyngeal cross-sectional areas (CSAs)
were measured at the level of the cranial end of the soft palate, pterygoid hamulus, foramen lacerum, bony labyrinth, and caudal end of the soft palate. The ratio of all maximum and minimum
CSA to nasopharyngeal CSA at the level of the caudal hard palate (rCSAmax and rCSAmin) and the nasopharyngeal collapsibility were calculated. The differences of rCSAmax, rCSAmin, and
nasopharyngeal collapsibility were analyzed at various locations. The nasopharyngeal collapsibility at the level of foramen lacerum, bony labyrinth, and caudal end of soft palate were higher
than the others. At the level of the caudal end of the soft palate, rCSAmin was lower than that of the foramen lacerum and bony labyrinth, whereas rCSAmax at foramen lacerum was higher than
that of the caudal end of the soft palate. These results indicated that the nasopharynx at the level of foramen lacerum and caudal end of the soft palate were considered notable locations
for evaluating collapsibility. Dynamic CT could show the nasopharyngeal dynamic profile and will be an adequate modality for evaluating nasopharynx. Our results will be helpful for further
comparative studies in dogs with and without nasopharyngeal collapse.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>collapsibility</kwd><kwd>dog</kwd><kwd>dynamic computed tomography</kwd><kwd>nasopharynx</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC-ND</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Maintenance of the upper airway patency depends on a balance between forces dilating or collapsing the airway. These forces are composed of tissue stresses that act as radials through the
airway and local airway pressure in the upper and thoracic airways [<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. During the respiratory cycle, local airway pressure changes, and affects the luminal
area of the upper airway and the pharyngeal walls [<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. When an
anatomic abnormality or pharyngeal dilator myopathy are present, the change of the luminal area in the upper airway is increased, causing a clinical pharyngeal collapse in humans [<xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. For dogs, this is still unclear due to lack of studies [<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. In small animal practice, pharyngeal collapse is anecdotally encountered on radiographs in both
non-brachycephalic and brachycephalic dogs with and without stertor. In previous studies, the pharyngeal collapse is defined as complete when the pharynx losses the total air column, or partial
air column when the luminal collapsibility is over the 50% in fluoroscopic study [<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. However, there have been
no studies focusing on a detailed quantification method for nasopharyngeal collapsibility and its normal range in dogs.</p><p>In veterinary medicine, computed tomography (CT) has been used in several studies of brachycephalic obstructive airway syndrome owing to its advantages in evaluating the entire upper
respiratory system in detail and allowing reconstruction of original data into multiplanar and 3-dimensional images [<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. However, these studies used static CT, which has limitations because it does not reflect the dynamics of changes in the upper airway. In
contrast, dynamic CT has the advantage of the feasibility of acquiring high-quality images that sufficiently delineate the upper airway contour and quantify the dynamic profile, as well as the
advantages of static CT [<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="r26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. However, there have been very few dynamic
CT studies of the upper airway in dogs [<xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>In humans, there are differences in pharyngeal collapsibility by location, according to the presence or severity of obstructive sleep apnea [<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. In dogs, a study in Pugs and French Bulldogs with obstructive airway syndrome showed that the smallest nasopharyngeal cross-sectional area (CSA) was
located at the level of the caudal end of the soft palate [<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. However, the previous study evaluated the nasopharyngeal CSA using conventional CT and not
by comparing the maximum and minimum cross-sectional area using dynamic CT. Thus far, there has been no study for nasopharyngeal collapsibility by location in dogs. Based on previous studies in
humans that showed pharyngeal collapsibility in normal subjects and its variation by location [<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], we hypothesized that normal dogs have nasopharyngeal CSA change according to their respiratory cycle, and the
degree of nasopharyngeal CSA change may differ depending on the location. Moreover, we hypothesized that nasopharyngeal collapsibility is correlated with adjacent structures, including soft
palate and epiglottis. The study aimed to analyze nasopharyngeal collapsibility at various locations and to analyze its correlation with adjacent structures using static and dynamic CT in normal
dogs. Consequently, our study aimed to determine the locations for evaluating nasopharyngeal collapsibility.</p><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s1"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec><title>Animals</title><p>A prospective and cross-sectional designed study was performed. Twenty-three male Beagle dogs were included in the study. The mean age was 5.0 years (1.8&#8211;5.5 years), and the mean body
weight was 10.3 kg (8.0&#8211;13.3 kg). All procedures were in accordance with Kyungpook National University Animal Care and Use Committee guidelines (No. KNU 2020-0033). All dogs had a physical
examination including cardiac and lung auscultation, and cervical tracheal manipulation to check the presence of coughing. Dogs with nasal discharge, sneezing, coughing, stertor, stridor,
and retching were not included in this study. Before the CT scan, thoracic radiographs, a complete blood count, and a biochemical serum profile were performed. Ventrodorsal and right lateral
thoracic radiographs were acquired in all dogs to identify the presence of lower airway collapse, cardiac disease, and pulmonary disease.</p></sec><sec><title>Experimental protocol</title><p>Based on previous research showing that endotracheal intubation could change airway pressure [<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], endotracheal intubation was not performed in this
study. For sedation, 0.02 mg/kg medetomidine (Domitor; Pfizer, New York, NY, USA) was injected intravenously. The dog was positioned in sternal recumbency on the CT table. The head was held
up using a sponge to maintain it in an extended neutral position with the hard palate parallel to the CT table. A self-manufactured bite block was placed between both canine teeth to
maintain mouth opening for better visualization of upper airway structure [<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. The tongue was pulled out between the bite blocks. The respiratory rate
was recorded after the respiratory rate fell to less than 20 breaths/min.</p><p>CT scans were performed using 32-Multislice CT (Alexion<sup>TM</sup>; Canon Medical System, Otawara, Japan). The examination range included the rhinarium to the third cervical vertebra to
evaluate the length and thickness of soft palate and to help choose the locations for dynamic CT. The CT scan parameters were as follows: 120 kV, 130 mA, 1.0 mm slice thickness, and 0.75 sec
rotation times. All transverse images perpendicular to the hard palate and reconstructed sagittal images were obtained.</p><p>Transverse images were reviewed focused on the nasopharynx, and the following locations for the subsequent dynamic CT scans were chosen: (1) at the caudal hard palate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig. 1B</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_001" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>The transverse CT images of the nasopharynx where dynamic CT scan was performed. Sagittal <bold>(A) </bold>and transverse nasopharyngeal images are shown in bone window setting
(window width, 2700 HU, window level, 350 HU) at the level of the caudal hard palate <bold>(B)</bold>, the cranial end of the soft palate <bold>(C)</bold>, defined as the point where
the torus palatinus discontinues, the pterygoid hamulus <bold>(D)</bold>, defined as the point where the pterygoid hamulus extends most ventral (white arrow), the foramen lacerum
<bold>(E)</bold>, defined as the point where the widest canal of foramen lacerum (black arrow) is shown, the bony labyrinth <bold>(F)</bold>, and the caudal end of the soft palate
<bold>(G)</bold> where the caudal aspect of the intact soft palate (asterisk) is shown.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jvms-83-1356-g001.jpg"/></fig>); (2) at the cranial end of the soft palate, defined as the point where the torus palatinus discontinues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig. 1C</xref>); (3) at the pterygoid
hamulus, defined as the point where the pterygoid hamulus extends to most ventral (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig. 1D</xref>); (4) at the foramen lacerum, defined as the point where
the widest canal of foramen lacerum is shown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig. 1E</xref>); (5) at the bony labyrinth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig. 1F</xref>); and (6) at
the caudal end of the soft palate, defined in front of the point where the soft palate diverges (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_001">Fig. 1G</xref>).</p><p>Dynamic CT scan was performed including at least two breathing cycles at 1-sec intervals. A field of view was used with the image being acquired in such a way as to place the nasopharynx in
the center for each location. The dynamic CT images were obtained at the cranial end of the soft palate, pterygoid hamulus, foramen lacerum, bony labyrinth, and caudal end of the soft
palate, respectively. After dynamic CT scan, 0.1 mg/kg atipamezole (Antisedan; Pfizer) was injected intramuscularly for sedation reversal and the condition was monitored until the dogs were
able to stand on their own.</p></sec><sec><title>CT data analysis</title><p>All CT imaging assessments and measurements were performed using a picture archiving and communication system (PACS) and its software (ZeTTA PACS Viewer; Taeyoung Soft, Seoul, Korea).</p><p>Using the mid-sagittal images of head and neck, the angle between hard palate and dorsal margin of the vertebral canal of axis was measured to verify the uniformity of CT scan positions.
Based on the method in a previous study [<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], soft palate length and thickness was measured at bone windows (window width, 2,700 HU; window level, 350
HU). The soft palate length was defined as the distance from the caudal margin of the hard palate to the tip of the soft palate. The soft palate thickness was defined as the thickest
distance between the dorsal and ventral margin of the soft palate perpendicular to the soft palate length. On the transverse images of the head, nasopharyngeal CSA was measured at the level
of the caudal hard palate. Regions of interest were drawn manually following the inner edge of the nasopharynx and were consequently calculated using the PACS software. In addition, the
location of the epiglottis, whether it was below or above the soft palate, was recorded.</p><p>Using the dynamic CT images of the nasopharynx, maximum and minimum nasopharyngeal CSA were measured at bone windows at five locations: cranial end of the soft palate, pterygoid hamulus,
foramen lacerum, bony labyrinth, and caudal end of the soft palate. For normalization, the ratio of all maximum and minimum CSAs at different locations to nasopharyngeal CSA at caudal hard
palate (rCSAmax and rCSAmin) was calculated. The nasopharyngeal collapsibility was calculated at five locations: cranial end of the soft palate, pterygoid hamulus, foramen lacerum, bony
labyrinth, and caudal end of the soft palate. Nasopharyngeal collapsibility was defined as the percentage of the difference between the maximum and minimum nasopharyngeal CSA, divided by the
maximum nasopharyngeal CSA.</p><p>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Collapsibility&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>%</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>maximum&#160;CSA</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#8722;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>minimum&#160;CSA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>maximum&#160;CSA</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>&#215;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All statistical analyses were performed using a commercial software program (SPSS 24.0; IBM SPSS statistics, Armonk, NY, USA). Shapiro&#8211;Wilk tests were used for the assessment of normality.
According to distribution, Pearson or Spearman&#8217;s correlation was used to evaluate the association of body weight with the dimensions of the soft palate and nasopharyngeal area variants,
including maximum and minimum nasopharyngeal CSAs, rCSAmax, rCSAmin, and nasopharyngeal collapsibility at the cranial end of the soft palate, pterygoid hamulus, foramen lacerum, bony
labyrinth, and caudal end of the soft palate. Moreover, the association between the dimensions of the soft palate and nasopharyngeal collapsibility was analyzed. Mann-Whitney
<italic toggle="yes">U</italic> tests were used to ascertain the difference of nasopharyngeal collapsibility according to the epiglottis location.</p><p>To identify the differences in the nasopharynx at different locations, repeated ANOVA tests followed by <italic toggle="yes">post hoc </italic>Bonferroni test were performed in rCSAmax, rCSAmin, and
nasopharyngeal collapsibility. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values less than 0.05 were considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s2"><title>RESULTS</title><p>The mean value &#177; standard deviation (SD) of the angle between hard palate and dorsal margin of the vertebral canal of axis was 172.9&#176; &#177; 4.5&#176; (range, 165.7&#176;&#8211;178.7&#176;). The mean values &#177; SD for
soft palate length and thickness were 64.51 &#177; 4.89 mm and 6.48 &#177; 1.14 mm, respectively. The mean values &#177; SD for the dimensions of the soft palate, maximum and minimum nasopharyngeal CSA,
rCSAmax, and rCSAmin are summarized in <xref rid="tbl_001" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref> and<xref rid="tbl_002" ref-type="table"> 2</xref><table-wrap id="tbl_001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><title>Dimensions of the soft palate and their correlation with body weight in Beagle dogs (n=23)</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean &#177; SD</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Correlation coefficient <break/>with body weight</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soft palate length (mm)</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.51 &#177; 4.89</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.060<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soft palate thickness (mm)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.48 &#177; 1.14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.574<sup>a, </sup>**</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>a, Pearson correlation coefficient; **, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="tbl_002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><title>Maximum and minimum nasopharyngeal cross-sectional areas and its normalization at different locations in Beagle dogs (n=23)</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">Location</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Nasopharyngeal CSA (mm<sup>2</sup>)<hr/></th><th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">rCSAmax</th><th rowspan="2" align="center" colspan="1">rCSAmin</th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CrSP</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 &#177; 0.15</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 &#177; 2.29</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 &#177; 0.10</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 &#177; 0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PH</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 &#177; 0.33</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12 &#177; 0.32</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 &#177; 0.32</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 &#177; 0.31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FL</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 &#177; 0.52</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 &#177; 0.50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 &#177; 0.55</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 &#177; 0.53</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BL</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 &#177; 0.45</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 &#177; 0.45</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 &#177; 0.50</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 &#177; 0.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CdSP</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 &#177; 0.44</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 &#177; 0.43</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 &#177; 0.49</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 &#177; 0.46</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The data presents the mean values &#177; standard deviation. CSA, cross-sectional area; rCSAmax, the ratio of maximum nasopharyngeal CSA to nasopharyngeal CSA at the level of the caudal hard
palate; rCSAmin, the ratio of minimum nasopharyngeal CSA to nasopharyngeal CSA at the level of the caudal hard palate; CrSP, cranial end of the soft palate; PH, pterygoid hamulus; FL,
foramen lacerum; BL, bony labyrinth; CdSP, caudal end of the soft palate.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>. The median values with an interquartile range of nasopharyngeal collapsibility are summarized in <xref rid="tbl_003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref><table-wrap id="tbl_003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><title>The nasopharyngeal collapsibility at each location and its correlation with body weight and dimension of the soft palate in Beagle dogs (n=23)</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Nasopharyngeal collapsibility (%)<hr/></th><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Correlation coefficient<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1st / 3rd quartile</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BW</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPL</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPT</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CrSP</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5 / 4.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.073</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.102</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.208</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PH</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0 / 7.1</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.366</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.347</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.427*</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FL</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3 / 12.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.112</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.172</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.325</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BL</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0 / 13.4</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.499*</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.162</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.393</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CdSP</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.6</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7 / 22.3</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.132</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8722;0.445*</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>BW, body weight; SPL, soft palate length; SPT, soft palate thickness; CrSP, cranial end of the soft palate; PH, pterygoid hamulus; FL, foramen lacerum; BL, bony labyrinth; CdSP, caudal
end of the soft palate; *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>.</p><p>There was significant positive correlation between soft palate thickness and body weight (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>=0.574, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.001, <xref rid="tbl_001" ref-type="table">Table
1</xref>). Among the nasopharyngeal area variants, collapsibility at the bony labyrinth showed a positive correlation with body weight (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>=0.499, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05,
<xref rid="tbl_003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><p>In the analysis of the correlation between the dimensions of the soft palate and nasopharyngeal collapsibility, collapsibility at the caudal end of the soft palate showed a negative
correlation with soft palate length (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>=&#8722;0.445, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05) and collapsibility at the pterygoid hamulus showed a positive correlation with soft palate thickness
(<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>=0.427, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p><p>The epiglottis was located below and above the soft palate in 13 and 10 dogs, respectively. In the analysis of differences in nasopharyngeal collapsibility according to epiglottis location,
collapsibility at the caudal end of the soft palate was significantly larger when the epiglottis was located under the soft palate (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>=0.026).</p><p>In the analysis of the differences of nasopharyngeal area variants according to locations in each dog, there were significant differences in rCSAmax, F (2.01, 44.29)=5.08,
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.05; rCSAmin, F (1.86, 41.01)=6.35, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01; and nasopharyngeal collapsibility, F (1.83, 40.17)=11.79, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>&lt;0.01. The results of
Bonferroni post hoc tests in nasopharyngeal area variants according to locations in each dog are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig_002">Fig. 2</xref><fig orientation="portrait" fig-type="figure" id="fig_002" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Comparison of the nasopharyngeal area variants at the level of the cranial end of the soft palate (CrSP), pterygoid hamulus (PH), foramen lacerum (FL), bony labyrinth (BL), and the
caudal end of the soft palate (CdSP) in Beagle dogs (n=23). All data is presented as the mean values with error bars (95% confidential intervals). The ratio of maximum cross-sectional
area (rCSAmax) is significantly higher at the PH than that of CrSP, and rCSAmax at the level of FL is significantly higher than that of CdSP <bold>(A)</bold>. rCSAmin at the level of PH
is significantly higher than that of CrSP. rCSAmin at the level of CdSP is significantly lower than that of PH, FL, and BL <bold>(B)</bold>. Nasopharyngeal collapsibility at CrSP and PH
levels are significantly lower than those of FL, BL, and CdSP levels <bold>(C)</bold>. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values less than 0.05 are presented as *.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jvms-83-1356-g002.jpg"/></fig>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s3"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>In this study, nasopharyngeal CSA change during the respiratory cycle was detected and there was remarkable nasopharyngeal collapsibility at the level of foramen lacerum, bony labyrinth, and
caudal part of the soft palate in normal Beagle dogs. These findings support the hypothesis that nasopharyngeal CSA change may exist even in normal dogs, and the degree of nasopharyngeal CSA
change may differ depending on the location. Moreover, nasopharyngeal collapsibility has relationships with dimension of the soft palate and with epiglottis location.</p><p>There are several diagnostic imaging modalities to evaluate the anatomic or dynamic changes of the upper airway in dogs especially in brachycephalic breeds including radiography, rhinoscopy,
fluoroscopy, static CT, and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) [<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Among these modalities, fluoroscopy has been used in dogs with obstructive airway syndrome because it has the feasibility of real-time assessment of the
dynamic profile of the upper airway and can be used without general anesthesia using an endotracheal tube [<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. However, this has its limitation in that only 2-dimensional evaluation is possible. In humans, dynamic CT and MRI are used for evaluating dynamic changing of the upper airway in
obstructive sleep apnea patients [<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Both modalities have the advantage of its feasibility of acquiring
high-quality images and quantifying the dynamic profile. Considering that dogs need anesthesia for CT or MRI scans, MRI has the disadvantage as the anesthetic time is longer than that of CT.
However, dynamic CT has several advantages including brief scan and anesthetic time and easy processing of imaging data for multiplanar reconstruction [<xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Therefore, dynamic CT was used in this study to evaluate dynamic profiles of the nasopharynx.</p><p>In this study, endotracheal intubation was not performed because it can induce artificial pressure given in the dogs [<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. During spontaneous
inspiration with intubation, the negative airway pressure is generated by respiratory musculature to overcome the resistance of the endotracheal tube, aggravating the nasopharyngeal collapse
in humans [<xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In brachycephalic dogs, changes of nasopharyngeal pressure may not appear because the endotracheal tube may act as a bypass, leading to
reduced air flow through the nasopharynx [<xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Therefore, the results of the present study aim to reflect the natural pressure gradient during
respiration, excluding artificial pressure factors. In addition, endotracheal intubation could affect the CSA of the caudal nasopharynx and soft palate length and it may preclude the
evaluation of changing of nasopharyngeal dynamics [<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. By not performing endotracheal intubation, this study
could measure the nasopharyngeal CSA and soft palate length reflecting the same conditions as in the nature state.</p><p>In this study, we measured the angle between the hard palate and the dorsal margin of the vertebral canal to quantify the degree of head flexion. In a previous study on horses, pharyngeal
diameter decreased with head flexion, which limited the airflow. This may result in turbulence followed by dynamic nasopharyngeal collapse [<xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Thus, the
dog was positioned in an extended neutral position, enabling the avoidance of artificial nasopharyngeal collapse. The angle measured between head and cervical vertebrae was used to normalize
the effect of head flexion in the nasopharyngeal area.</p><p>In humans, obstructive sleep apnea patients have a more collapsible velopharynx compared with normal subjects [<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, there has been no comparative
study for nasopharyngeal collapsibility according to specific location in dogs with and without upper airway obstruction. In this study, various locations were selected to evaluate
nasopharyngeal CSA and collapsibility at the level of the cranial end of the soft palate, pterygoid hamulus, foramen lacerum, bony labyrinth, and the caudal end of the soft palate. These
anatomical levels for nasopharyngeal evaluation were chosen based on previous studies on brachycephalic dogs, and on their easiness to find that could be used in landmarks on CT [<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].</p><p>The level of the caudal end of the soft palate and foramen lacerum were considered suitable locations for detecting nasopharyngeal CSA change. The nasopharynx at the level of the caudal end
of the soft palate showed lower rCSAmin and higher collapsibility. This result is consistent with a previous study that showed the smallest nasopharyngeal CSA at the level of the caudal end of
the soft palate in Pugs and French Bulldogs with obstructive airway syndrome [<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. These results may imply that the collapsibility at the caudal end of
the soft palate may be high, regardless of symptoms or breed differences. This suggests that other levels of the nasopharynx may be needed to avoid overlapping of collapsibility when comparing
dogs with and without obstructive airway syndrome. The nasopharynx at the foramen lacerum level was noteworthy as the rCSAmax and rCSAmin were higher than those of the caudal soft palate level
and showed higher collapsibility than those of the cranial end of the soft palate and pterygoid hamulus in normal dogs. This may indicate that the nasopharynx at the foramen lacerum level
could show differences in nasopharyngeal collapsibility with little overlap between normal dogs and dogs with clinical nasopharyngeal collapse. Further comparative studies of the nasopharynx
using dynamic CT are needed in dogs with and without nasopharyngeal collapse.</p><p>In this study, positive correlations were found for nasopharyngeal collapsibility at the level of the pterygoid hamulus with soft palate thickness and nasopharyngeal collapsibility at the
level of the bony labyrinth with body weight. These results are partially consistent with a previous study that revealed the soft palate thickness is the most relevant parameter in dogs with
severe brachycephalic obstructive airway syndrome, whereas soft palate length is not [<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In addition, weight gain can cause adipose tissue deposition
on the soft palate, and obesity is a possible risk factor for development of pharyngeal collapse [<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. These
previous studies and result of present study suggest that either thickening of the soft palate or weight gain, or both, could affect nasopharyngeal collapsibility even in normal
non-brachycephalic dogs.</p><p>In this study, dogs with the epiglottis located below the soft palate had higher nasopharyngeal collapsibility at the level of the caudal end of the soft palate. Epiglottis-overlying soft
palate may cause the narrowing of the caudal nasopharyngeal area, resulting in high negative pressure. Similar to this condition, dorsal displacement of the soft palate in equines obstructs
the normal airflow, resulting in more severe dynamic obstruction of the upper respiratory tract [<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Moreover, the epiglottis may block the upward
movement of the soft palate when it is located above the soft palate, causing lower nasopharyngeal collapsibility. In this condition, the inspiration-induced negative pressure causing
nasopharyngeal CSA change may be disturbed by the epiglottis blocking the upward movement of the soft palate. Anatomically, the natural location of the epiglottis at rest is dorsal to the soft
palate, allowing nasal breathing. However, when breathing through the mouth, the epiglottis moves downward in mesaticephalic dogs [<xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. When a dog with
respiratory distress presents open mouth breathing, nasopharyngeal collapsibility at the level of the caudal end of the soft palate may be higher in dogs with obstructive airway signs.</p><p>This study had some limitations. First, an anesthetic drug that may affect respiratory system was used because of the inevitable necessity of anesthesia for CT scans of dogs. However,
respiratory depression of medetomidine alone is lower than other sedatives, even at sublethal doses [<xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Moreover, medetomidine is safe and widely used
even in brachycephalic dogs with obstructive airway syndrome [<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Second, the dynamic CT scan was performed at fixed scan intervals, and CT images at
maximal inspiration and expiration may not have been obtained, which may be reflected in the calculated nasopharyngeal collapsibility. Third, Beagle dogs were used in this study and the result
may differ from brachycephalic dogs, which have different upper airway conformation [<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. However, considering that nasopharyngeal collapse was also
encountered in non-brachycephalic dog breeds [<xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], the method described in this study would be applicable to
non-brachycephalic dogs in small animal practice.</p><p>In conclusion, the findings from this study indicate that measurements of the nasopharyngeal collapsibility at the level of the caudal end of the soft palate and the foramen lacerum are
considered useful locations. Either thickening of the soft palate, weight gain, or epiglottis location could affect the nasopharyngeal collapsibility even in normal Beagle dogs. Dynamic CT
could show the dynamic profile of the airway and would be an adequate modality for evaluating the nasopharynx in dogs. Further dynamic CT study of the nasopharynx is needed to compare the
collapsibility in dogs with and without obstructive airway syndrome.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s4"><title>CONFLICT OF INTEREST</title><p>None of the authors have a financial or personal relationship with other people or organizations that could inappropriately influence or bias the content of the paper.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pdf_001" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Supplementary Materials</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jvms-83-1356-s001.pdf" mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" orientation="portrait" id="d31e736" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayappa</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year>. <article-title>The upper airway in sleep: physiology of the pharynx</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sleep Med. Rev.</italic></source><volume>7</volume>:
<fpage>9</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/smrv.2002.0238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12586528</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1972</year>. <article-title>Surgery of the canine pharynx and larynx</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J. Small Anim. Pract.</italic></source><volume>13</volume>:
<fpage>505</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>513</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1748-5827.1972.tb06879.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5079566</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Campana</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eckert</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malhotra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year>. <article-title>Pathophysiology &amp; genetics of obstructive sleep apnoea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Indian J. Med.
Res.</italic></source><volume>131</volume>: <fpage>176</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>187</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20308743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3858846</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Cehak</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rohn</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohnesorge</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year>. <article-title>Effect of head and neck position on pharyngeal diameter in horses</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet. Radiol.
Ultrasound</italic></source><volume>51</volume>: <fpage>491</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>497</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1740-8261.2010.01701.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20973380</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Chesen</surname><given-names>A. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitfield-Cargile</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year>. <article-title>Update on diseases and treatment of the pharynx</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet. Clin. North Am. Equine
Pract.</italic></source><volume>31</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cveq.2014.11.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25600454</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciscar</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;nez</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ram&#243;n</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lloret</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#237;nguez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armengot</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mar&#237;n</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basterra</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year>. <article-title>Magnetic resonance imaging of the pharynx in OSA patients and healthy subjects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur. Respir.
J.</italic></source><volume>17</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>86</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.01.17100790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11307760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Downing</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year>. <article-title>Anaesthesia of brachycephalic dogs</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J. Small Anim. Pract.</italic></source><volume>59</volume>:
<fpage>725</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>733</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jsap.12948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30374971</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiastro</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Habib</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>S. F.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1988</year>. <article-title>Pressure support compensation for inspiratory work due to endotracheal tubes and demand continuous positive airway pressure</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source><volume>93</volume>: <fpage>499</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>505</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.93.3.499</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3277803</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Fleck</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishman</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shott</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gutmark</surname><given-names>E. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McConnell</surname><given-names>K. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mylavarapu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Subramaniam</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szczesniak</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year>. <article-title>Dynamic volume computed tomography imaging of the upper airway in obstructive sleep apnea</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J. Clin. Sleep
Med.</italic></source><volume>13</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>196</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5664/jcsm.6444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27784422</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5263074</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Grand</surname><given-names>J. G. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bureau</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year>. <article-title>Structural characteristics of the soft palate and meatus nasopharyngeus in brachycephalic and non-brachycephalic dogs analysed by
CT</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J. Small Anim. Pract.</italic></source><volume>52</volume>: <fpage>232</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>239</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1748-5827.2011.01047.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21539567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Teshima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asano</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaya</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2020</year>. <article-title>Pharyngeal contraction secondary to its collapse in dogs with brachycephalic airway syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J. Vet. Med.
Sci.</italic></source><volume>82</volume>: <fpage>64</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>67</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.19-0515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31839650</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6983667</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Heidenreich</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gradner</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kneissl</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dupr&#233;</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year>. <article-title>Nasopharyngeal dimensions from computed tomography of Pugs and French bulldogs with brachycephalic airway syndrome</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Vet. Surg.</italic></source><volume>45</volume>: <fpage>83</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vsu.12418</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26731598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Huon</surname><given-names>L. K.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S. Y. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shih</surname><given-names>T. T. F.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P. C.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year>. <article-title>Dynamic upper airway collapse observed from sleep MRI: BMI-matched severe and mild OSA patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur. Arch.
Otorhinolaryngol.</italic></source><volume>273</volume>: <fpage>4021</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4026</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-016-4131-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27276991</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Isono</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Remmers</surname><given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sho</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishino</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year>. <article-title>Anatomy of pharynx in patients with obstructive sleep apnea and in normal subjects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Appl Physiol
(1985)</italic></source><volume>82</volume>: <fpage>1319</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1326</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jappl.1997.82.4.1319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9104871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2020</year>. <article-title>The impact of tongue dimension on air volume in brachycephalic dogs</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet.
Surg.</italic></source><volume>49</volume>: <fpage>512</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>520</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vsu.13302</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31361346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>An</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2019</year>. <article-title>Three-dimensional volumetric magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) analysis of the soft palate and nasopharynx in brachycephalic and
non-brachycephalic dog breeds</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J. Vet. Med. Sci.</italic></source><volume>81</volume>: <fpage>113</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>119</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.17-0711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30518706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6361641</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Laurenson</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zwingenberger</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cissell</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McPeters</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spriet</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year>. <article-title>Computed tomography of the pharynx in a closed vs. open mouth position</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet. Radiol.
Ultrasound</italic></source><volume>52</volume>: <fpage>357</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>361</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1740-8261.2011.01805.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21382119</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Troconis</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Genain</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalmar</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sargan</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ladlow</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year>. <article-title>Endotracheal tube placement during computed tomography of brachycephalic dogs alters upper airway dimensional measurements</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Vet. Radiol. Ultrasound</italic></source><volume>59</volume>: <fpage>289</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>304</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vru.12590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29336085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Malhotra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pillar</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fogel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beauregard</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year>. <article-title>Upper-airway collapsibility: measurements and sleep effects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Chest</italic></source><volume>120</volume>:
<fpage>156</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>161</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.120.1.156</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11451832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4372067</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Malhotra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fogel</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lazic</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pillar</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jakab</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kikinis</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year>. <article-title>Aging influences on pharyngeal anatomy and physiology: the predisposition to pharyngeal collapse</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am. J.
Med.</italic></source><volume>119</volume>: <fpage>72.e9</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>72.e14</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjmed.2005.01.077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16431197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2287192</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Noone</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year>. <article-title>Rhinoscopy, pharyngoscopy, and laryngoscopy</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Vet. Clin. North Am. Small Anim.
Pract.</italic></source><volume>31</volume>: <fpage>671</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>689</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0195-5616(01)50065-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11487950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Packer</surname><given-names>R. M. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hendricks</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tivers</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burn</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year>. <article-title>Impact of facial conformation on canine health: brachycephalic obstructive airway syndrome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS
One</italic></source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>e0137496</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0137496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26509577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4624979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year>. <article-title>The prevalence of dynamic pharyngeal collapse is high in brachycephalic dogs undergoing videofluoroscopy</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Vet. Radiol. Ultrasound</italic></source><volume>59</volume>: <fpage>529</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>534</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vru.12655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29931712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reetz</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year>. <article-title>Signalment, clinical presentation, concurrent diseases, and diagnostic findings in 28 dogs with dynamic pharyngeal collapse
(2008&#8211;2013)</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J. Vet. Intern. Med.</italic></source><volume>29</volume>: <fpage>815</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>821</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.12598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25903658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4895422</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarran</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Testault</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Segond</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Billet</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2018</year>. <article-title>Position of maximal nasopharyngeal maximal occlusion in relation to hamuli pterygoidei: use of hamuli pterygoidei as landmarks for
palatoplasty in brachycephalic airway obstruction syndrome surgical treatment</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J. Small Anim. Pract.</italic></source><volume>59</volume>:
<fpage>625</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>633</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30033632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.1111/jsap.12909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gefter</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pack</surname><given-names>A. I.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year>. <article-title>Dynamic imaging of the upper airway during respiration in normal subjects</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Appl. Physiol.
(1985)</italic></source><volume>74</volume>: <fpage>1504</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1514</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jappl.1993.74.4.1504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8514663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year>. <article-title>A review of the physiological effects of &#945;2-agonists related to the clinical use of medetomidine in small animal practice</article-title>.
<source><italic toggle="yes">Can. Vet. J.</italic></source><volume>44</volume>: <fpage>885</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>897</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14664351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC385445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group><name name-style="western"><surname>Yucel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Unlu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haktanir</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Acar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fidan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year>. <article-title>Evaluation of the upper airway cross-sectional area changes in different degrees of severity of obstructive sleep apnea syndrome:
cephalometric and dynamic CT study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">AJNR Am. J. Neuroradiol.</italic></source><volume>26</volume>: <fpage>2624</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2629</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16286412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7976204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>