<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8326516</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8326516.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8326516</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8326516</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34350223</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.644549</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Effect of 42-Day Exposure to a Low Deoxynivalenol Dose on the Immunohistochemical Expression of Intestinal ERs and the Activation of <italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">GSTP1</italic> Genes in the Large Intestine of Pre-pubertal Gilts</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaj&#281;cka</surname><given-names initials="M">Magdalena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>&#8224;</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/594760/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brzuzan</surname><given-names initials="P">Pawe&#322;</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn005"><sup>&#8224;</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1178582/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Otrocka-Domaga&#322;a</surname><given-names initials="I">Iwona</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn006"><sup>&#8224;</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/425043/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zielonka</surname><given-names initials="&#x141;">&#321;ukasz</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn003"><sup>&#8224;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lisieska-&#379;o&#322;nierczyk</surname><given-names initials="S">Sylwia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaj&#281;cki</surname><given-names initials="MT">Maciej T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn004"><sup>&#8224;</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1149000/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Veterinary Prevention and Feed Hygiene, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Warmia and Mazury in Olsztyn</institution>, <addr-line>Olsztyn</addr-line>, <country>Poland</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Environmental Biotechnology, Faculty of Environmental Sciences and Fisheries, University of Warmia and Mazury in Olsztyn</institution>, <addr-line>Olsztyn</addr-line>, <country>Poland</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Pathological Anatomy, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Warmia and Mazury in Olsztyn</institution>, <addr-line>Olsztyn</addr-line>, <country>Poland</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Independent Public Health Care Center of the Ministry of the Interior and Administration and the Warmia and Mazury Oncology Center in Olsztyn</institution>, <addr-line>Olsztyn</addr-line>, <country>Poland</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Arturo Anad&#243;n, Complutense University of Madrid, Spain</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Kehe Huang, Nanjing Agricultural University, China; Jean-Denis Troadec, Aix-Marseille Universit&#233;, France</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Magdalena Gaj&#281;cka <email>mgaja@uwm.edu.pl</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Veterinary Pharmacology and Toxicology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>&#8224;ORCID: Magdalena Gaj&#281;cka <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5507-5091">orcid.org/0000-0001-5507-5091</ext-link></p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn003"><p>&#321;ukasz Zielonka <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0983-5592">orcid.org/0000-0003-0983-5592</ext-link></p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn004"><p>Maciej T. Gaj&#281;cki <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7296-5344">orcid.org/0000-0001-7296-5344</ext-link></p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn005"><p>Pawe&#322; Brzuzan <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9701-5716">orcid.org/0000-0001-9701-5716</ext-link></p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn006"><p>Iwona Otrocka-Domaga&#322;a <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3271-0408">orcid.org/0000-0002-3271-0408</ext-link></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>7</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">374996</issue-id><elocation-id>644549</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>5</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>03</day><month>08</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-09 11:25:14.470"><day>09</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2021 Gaj&#281;cka, Brzuzan, Otrocka-Domaga&#322;a, Zielonka, Lisieska-&#379;o&#322;nierczyk and Gaj&#281;cki.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Gaj&#281;cka, Brzuzan, Otrocka-Domaga&#322;a, Zielonka, Lisieska-&#379;o&#322;nierczyk and Gaj&#281;cki</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-08-644549.pdf"/><abstract><p>Deoxynivalenol (DON) is a mycotoxin that contaminates various plant materials. Exposure to DON can disrupt hormonal homeostasis, decrease body weight gains and modulate the immune system in pigs. It can also cause diarrhea, vomiting, leukocytosis, hemorrhaging or even death. Prolonged exposure to low doses of DON can have serious health implications in mammals. This is the first <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> study to show that <italic toggle="yes">per os</italic> administration of low DON doses probably contributes to specific dysfunctions in steroidogenesis processes by inducing the immunohistochemical expression of estrogen receptors alpha (ER&#945;) in the entire gastrointestinal tract in strongly stained cells (3 points) and estrogen receptors beta (ER&#946;), but only in both investigated segments of the duodenum in pre-pubertal gilts. Therefore, the aim of this study was to determine whether a NOAEL dose of DON (12 &#956;g DON/kg BW) administered <italic toggle="yes">per os</italic> over a period of 42 days induces changes in the immunohistochemical expression of ER in different intestinal segments and the transcriptional activation of <italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">GSTP1</italic> genes in the large intestine of pre-pubertal gilts. This is the first report to demonstrate the expression of ER, in particular ER&#946;, with the associated consequences. The expression of ER was accompanied by considerable variations in the activation of <italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">GSTP1</italic> genes, but it supported the maintenance of a stable consensus between the degree of mycotoxin exposure and the detoxifying effect in pre-pubertal gilts.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>deoxynivalenol</kwd><kwd>intestines</kwd><kwd>ER&#945; and ER&#946; immunohistochemistry</kwd><kwd>colon</kwd><kwd>activation of <italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">GSTP1</italic> genes</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="9"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="56"/><page-count count="18"/><word-count count="9937"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Mycotoxins are substances that occur naturally in the environment (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). In addition to mycoestrogens such as zearalenone (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), selected trichothecenes, including DON and/or its metabolites (but <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>), can affect steroidogenesis (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) and changes in gene expression, which suggests that these compounds could disrupt hormonal homeostasis (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>).</p><p>Deoxynivalenol (DON), a polar organic compound produced mainly by <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium graminearum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium culmorum</italic> (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), is one of the most economically important mycotoxins in the world (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). The presence of a ketone group at position C8 is characteristic of B trichothecenes. Deoxynivalenol also contains an epoxide group which enables the mycotoxin to bind to a large number of eukaryotic ribosome subunits and disrupt the activity of peptide transferase, thus compromising the elongation or shortening of peptide chains (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Deoxynivalenol affects the cellular transport rate and enzyme metabolism in the cytoplasm (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), it leads to changes in affinity for active binding sites and disrupts protein synthesis (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>).</p><p>There is a general scarcity of <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and, in particular, <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> evidence that DON can directly trigger the overexpression of steroid hormone receptors or induce hormonal activity. However, DON affects steroidogenesis (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) and changes in gene expression (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), which suggests that it can potentially disrupt the functioning of the hormonal system. The available background knowledge indicates that estrogen receptors (ER) are essential for various physiological processes, including the regulation of the endocrine system, lipid profile, bone integrity, hemostasis and endothelial function. Estrogen receptors are inflammatory markers, and they promote the growth of various tissues, and contribute to pre-natal and post-natal development (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Estrogen receptors are divided into two subtypes, ER&#945; and ER&#946;, which have different identity (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>) and interact with different tissues. For example, ER&#945; is more prevalent in the gonads, mammary glands, kidneys and bronchi, and it stimulates proliferative processes in cells. In turn, ER&#946; is predominant in bones and pulmonary alveoli, and it delivers antiproliferative effects (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Unlike other steroid receptors, ERs bind to a wide range of exogeneous compounds, and are they are increasingly often classified as promiscuous receptors (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Ligand recognition and receptor-ligand binding are regarded as highly specific biological processes that activate the appropriate receptors and trigger specific responses to stimuli <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>. It is believed that protein-ligand recognition relies on a lock-and-key model and an improved induced-fit model. Estrogen receptors can bind to various ligands due to their unique ability to associate ligands and detect binding cavities. They appear to be an exception to the core concept of lock and key, and they do not discriminate between the bound ligands. It remains unknown whether the above mechanism also applies to non-steroid compounds. Estrogen receptors have evolved to play different tissue-dependent biological roles (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).</p><p>The fact that DON is not involved in phase I biotransformation reactions (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), and P450 isoenzymes, in particular CYP1A1, participate in the metabolism of many structurally different endogenous and exogenous compounds, especially the hydroxylation of estrogens (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), in distal segments of the intestines, had to be considered in the present research. Nandekar et al. (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) suggested that the <italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1</italic> gene in macroorganisms undergoes transcriptional activation under exposure to environmental contaminants (such as DON), in particular substrates of the CYP1A1 enzyme. Recent <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> studies have demonstrated that CYP1A1 can also act as a detoxifying enzyme (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p><p>Glutathione S-transferase (GST), also known as ligandin, is a phase II biotransformation enzyme and a biomarker of plant contamination (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) with undesirable substances such as mycotoxins (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Glutathione S-transferase isoenzymes are generally overexpressed under exposure to substances which modulate apoptotic processes and induce the expression of biologically active proteins, as well as during detoxification processes (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>).</p><p>The above problems were considered in the process of formulating the research objective. This study set out to determine whether DON can influence the expression of ER and genes encoding selected large intestine enzymes which participate in the detoxification of mycotoxins. A pioneering <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> study was conducted to verify the research hypothesis. The presented research is innovative because it aimed to determine whether the presence of a NOAEL dose of DON, which is not a contributing factor to clinical mycotoxicosis, can induce subclinical states such as steroidogenesis dysfunction or physiological detoxification. The aim of this study was to determine <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> whether a low dose of DON administered <italic toggle="yes">per os</italic> for 42 days can affect the immunohistochemical expression of ER in different intestinal segments on different dates of exposure or the expression of genes (<italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">GSTP1</italic>) encoding selected enzymes in the colon of pre-pubertal gilts.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Experimental Animals</title><p>The experiment, conducted at the Department of Veterinary Prevention and Feed Hygiene, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine (University of Warmia and Mazury in Olsztyn, Poland), involved 36 pre-pubertal gilts. The animals were clinically healthy, and had initial BW of 25 &#177; 2 kg. They were kept in group pens, with free access to water. The feed offered to gilts had been tested for the presence of the following mycotoxins: DON, ZEN and &#945;-ZEL. Mycotoxin concentrations were determined by separation techniques, using immunoaffinity columns (DON-Test<sup>TM</sup> DON Testing System, VICAM, Watertown, USA; Zearala-Test<sup>TM</sup> Zearalenone Testing System, G1012, VICAM, Watertown, USA) and HPLC (Hewlett Packard, type 1,050 and 1,100) (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) with fluorescence and/or UV detection [limit of detection: 1.0 ng/g for DON&#8211;(<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>); 3.0 ng/g for ZEN&#8211;(<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>)].</p></sec><sec><title>Experimental Design</title><p>The animals were divided into an exposed group (E = DON; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 18) and a control group (C, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 18) (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Group E gilts were administered DON <italic toggle="yes">per os</italic> at 12 &#956;g/kg BW &#8211; this value was consistent with the limits set by EFSA (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) and the NOAEL dose when the experiment was planned. Group C animals received a placebo. Deoxynivalenol was administered daily, before morning feeding, in gastro-soluble gel capsules, with feed as the carrier. The animals in group C received the same gel capsules, but without the mycotoxin.</p><p>The analyzed mycotoxin (DON) was biosynthesized, purified and standardized at the Department of Chemistry, Pozna&#324; University of Life Sciences (Poland). The experiment lasted for 42 days. The DON dose was adjusted to the BW of pre-pubertal gilts. In order to prevent uneven feed intake, DON was administered in capsules Deoxynivalenol samples were diluted in 500 &#956;L of 96% ethyl alcohol (SWW 2442-90, Polskie Odczynniki Chemiczne SA, Poland) to achieve the required dose (based on the BW of animals). Final solutions were stored for 12 h at room temperature to evaporate the solvent. During the adjustment period, the animals were weighed at 7-day intervals. Three gilts from the exposed and control groups (a total of six animals) were euthanized by intravenous administration of pentobarbital sodium (Fatro, Ozzano Emilia BO, Italy) and bleeding on experimental days 7 (week I), 14 (week II), 21 (week III), 28 (week IV), 35 (week V) and 42 (week VI). Immediately after cardiac arrest, sections of intestinal tissues were collected for analyses.</p></sec><sec><title>Reagents</title><sec><title>Deoxynivalenol</title><p>Deoxynivalenol was biosynthesized at the Department of Chemistry, Pozna&#324; University of Life Sciences (Poland), in accordance with a previously described procedure (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Chemicals and Apparatus</title><p>A chromatographic analysis of DON was conducted at the Department of Chemistry, Pozna&#324; University of Life Sciences (Poland), in accordance with a previously described procedure (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Immunohistochemistry</title><sec><title>Tissue Samples</title><p>Every week, post-mortem samples of porcine gastrointestinal tissues were rinsed with phosphate buffer. Cross-sectional tissue samples (measuring ~1 &#215; 1.5 cm, two samples from each examined tissue) were obtained from: the duodenum &#8211; the first part (duodenal cap) and the horizontal or third part; jejunum and ileum &#8211; middle parts; cecum &#8211; 1 cm from the ileocecal valve; and the colon &#8211; middle parts of the ascending colon and descending colon.</p></sec><sec><title>Location of ER&#945; and ER&#946;</title><p>The variability in ER expression was assessed in intestinal epithelial cells. Tissue specimens were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde solution and embedded in paraffin. The negative control sections were incubated with normal horse serum instead of the primary antibody and were processed together with the evaluated sections. The ovaries of multiparous pigs were used as a positive tissue control for the applied ER&#945; or ER&#946; antibodies. The analytical procedure has been described previously (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Optical Density (Scanning) of Stained Slides</title><p>The expression of ER&#945; and ER&#946; in the intestinal samples collected from gilts in both groups was analyzed in scanned slides (Pannoramic MIDI Scanner, 3DHISTECH, Budapest, Hungary) with the use of NuclearQuant software (3DHISTECH, Hungary) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The slides were converted into digital images, and nuclear immunoreactivity was evaluated. The nucleus detection profile was as follows: radius &#8211; 1.50-2.10 &#956;m, minimum nuclear area &#8211; 0.9 &#956;m, minimum circularity &#8211; 3, smoothness &#8211; 1. ER&#945; and ER&#946; expression was evaluated on a 4-point scale: negative = 0 (0 points), weak and homogeneous = + (1 point), mild or moderate and homogeneous = ++ (2 points), intense or strong and homogeneous = +++ (3 points). Staining intensity was evaluated on the following scale: from 0 &#8211; none of the below, + average intensity &lt;190 (CD BrownInt), ++ average intensity &lt;170 (CD BrownInt), +++ average intensity &lt;100 (CD BrownInt) (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). The results were presented in terms of the average percentage of cells expressing ER&#945; and ER&#946;. The presence of ER proteins was determined based on the value of P-ER which represents the average number of enterocytes showing nuclear expression of ER proteins in 10 fields of view for at least 1,000 cells. The analysis of optical density and the nuclear detection profile used was performed by the authors, and the results had been previously published in several papers (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Scanned slides of immunohistochemical expression of ER&#945; receptors in the descending colon in group C [<bold>(A)</bold> 0; <bold>(B)</bold> +; <bold>(C)</bold> ++; <bold>(D)</bold> +++] and group E [<bold>(E)</bold> 0; <bold>(F)</bold> +; <bold>(G)</bold> ++; <bold>(H)</bold> +++]. HE.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-644549-g0001.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Scanned slides of immunohistochemical expression of ER&#946; receptors in the descending colon in group C [<bold>(A)</bold> 0; <bold>(B)</bold> +; <bold>(C)</bold> ++; <bold>(D)</bold> +++] and group E [<bold>(E)</bold> 0; <bold>(F)</bold> +; <bold>(G)</bold> ++; <bold>(H)</bold> +++]. HE.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-644549-g0002.jpg"/></fig><p>The results of immunohistochemical examinations of the expression of ER&#945; and ER&#946; in the gastrointestinal tract of pre-pubertal gilts from both groups were analyzed statistically in two analytical approaches. In the first approach, the expression of both ER was analyzed statistically and compared between groups. In the second approach, the influence of sampling date (duration of exposure) on ER expression in each group and in a given intestinal segment was statistically analyzed. In both analytical approaches and in both groups, the effects of the 6-week exposure to DON on the expression of selected ER was evaluated in selected segments of the digestive tract on a 4-point scale (negative = 0 points; weak and homogeneous = 1 point; mild or moderate and homogeneous = 2 points; intense or strong and homogeneous = 3 points).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Expression of <italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">GSTP1</italic> Genes</title><sec><title>Collection and Storage of Samples for RNA Extraction</title><p>Segments of the ascending colon and descending colon were collected immediately after cardiac arrest. The specimens were stored in RNA<italic toggle="yes">later</italic> solution (Sigma-Aldrich; Germany), in accordance with the manufacturer's instructions. The samples were collected on the same days of slaughter.</p></sec><sec><title>Total RNA Extraction and cDNA Synthesis</title><p>The total RNA was extracted (~20 mg per sample tissue; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3 in each group), and purified using a Total RNA Mini Isolation Kit (A&amp;A Biotechnology; Poland). The final RNA concentration and purity was determined using a UV-Vis spectrophotometer (BioPhotometer, Eppendorf; Germany), obtaining A260/280 ratios between 1.70 and 1.86 in all the samples. Next, the samples were incubated with DNase I (Roche Diagnostics; Germany), and then used to synthesize cDNA using a RevertAid&#8482; First Strand cDNA synthesis kit (Fermentas; Lithuania). Briefly, the reaction contained 1 &#956;g of the DNAse-treated total RNA and 5 &#956;M of oligo(dT)<sub>18</sub> primer. After incubation at 65&#176;C for 5 min, the samples were chilled on ice, and the following reagents were added in: 4 &#956;L of 5&#215; Reaction Buffer, 20 U of RiboLock&#8482; RNAse Inhibitor, 1 mM of dNTP mix, and 200 U of RevertAid M-MuLV Reverse Transcriptase. The reaction was carried out at 42&#176;C for 60 min, followed by heat-inactivation at 70&#176;C for 5 min. Synthesized cDNA samples were stored at &#8722;80&#176;C until used.</p></sec><sec><title>qPCR</title><p>Real-Time PCR primers for target mRNAs were designed using the Primer-BLAST tool (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) based on the reference species (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The real-time PCR assay was carried out in the ABI 7500 Real-Time PCR system thermocycler (Applied Biosystems; USA) in singleplex mode. Each PCR reaction tube contained 10 &#956;L of the FastStart SYBR Green Master ROX mix (Roche Diagnostics), 0.25 (<italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1</italic>) or 0.5 (<italic toggle="yes">GSTP1</italic>) &#956;M of each primer (forward and reverse; <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), 1 &#956;L of previously synthesized cDNA as a template supplemented with PCR-grade H<sub>2</sub>O to a final volume of 20 &#956;L. Further details of the analytical procedure have been described elsewhere (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Real-time PCR primers used in this study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Primer</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Sequence (5&#8242; &#8594; 3&#8242;)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Final concentration (&#956;M)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Amplicon length (bp)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Reference</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cagagccgcagcagccaccttg</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_214412.1">NM_214412.1</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ggctcttgcccaaggtcagcac</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">GSTP1</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forward</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">acctgcttcggattcaccag</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="EW651453.2">EW651453.2</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ctccagccacaaagccctta</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>The activity of ER&#945; and ER&#946; in the digestive tract of gilts, and the expression of <italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">GSTP1</italic> genes in the ascending colon and the descending colon were presented as geometric mean values (&#177;) SD for each group, relative to control group from the beginning of the experiment (control 0d). The results were analyzed using Statistica software (StatSoft Inc., USA). Mean values in the control and exposed groups were compared by repeated measures one-way ANOVA based on the DON dose administered to pre-pubertal gilts. If differences were noted between groups, Tukey's <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> test was used to determine which pairs of group means were significantly different. In ANOVA, group samples are drawn from normally distributed populations characterized by the same variance. Since the above assumptions were not met in all cases, the equality of group means was tested using the Kruskal-Wallis test of ranks and the multiple comparisons test in ANOVA. Non-parametric tests were used to test for differences in samples.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>The experimental diets did not contain mycotoxins or their mycotoxin concentrations were below the sensitivity of the method (VBS, values below the sensitivity of the method). Clinical signs of DON mycotoxicosis were not observed during the experiment. The levels of modified or masked mycotoxins were not determined in the study. All laboratory and statistical analyses were carried out in 2013.</p><p>In the first analytical approach, the immunohistochemical expression of ER&#945; and ER&#946; in each segment of the porcine gastrointestinal tract (where the samples were collected) was compared in all (six) weeks of exposure, between the control group (C) and the experimental group (E). In this analytical approach, ER expression was presented graphically (refer to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 3</xref>&#8211;<bold>6</bold>). The results were not presented graphically for the segments of the intestinal tract where statistical differences were not found (refer to <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Figures 1&#8211;4</xref>).</p><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Immunohistochemical expression of ER&#945; (graded on a 4-point scale: negative = 0 points; weak and homogeneous = 1 point; mild or moderate and homogeneous = 2 points; intense or strong and homogeneous = 3 points) in different intestinal segments in selected weeks of exposure: <bold>(A)</bold> in week II; <bold>(B)</bold> in week III; <bold>(C)</bold> in week IV; <bold>(D)</bold> in week V. ER&#945; expression was presented as mean values (&#177;) and standard deviation (SD) for each sample. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#8804; 0.05 were compared with the control group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-644549-g0003.jpg"/></fig><p>In this analytical approach, no statistical differences in the immunohistochemical expression of ER&#945; not shown were observed in weeks I and VI (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Figures 1A,B</xref>). In week II (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>), statistical differences in the immunohistochemical expression of ER&#945; were noted in the duodenal cap and the jejunum, in week III (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>), differences were found in the third part of duodenum, in week IV (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3C</xref>), differences were noted in the ascending colon, and descending colon in week V (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3D</xref>), differences were observed in the ascending colon.</p><p>The levels of ER&#945; expression in different tissues and in different weeks of exposure were also presented graphically (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Immunohistochemical expression of ER&#945; in the control and exposed groups (graded on a 4-point scale: negative = 0 points; weak and homogeneous = 1 point; mild or moderate and homogeneous = 2 points; intense or strong and homogeneous = 3 points) in different intestinal segments and in selected weeks of exposure: <bold>(A)</bold> in group E; <bold>(B)</bold> average expression values from all weeks of exposure in both groups.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-644549-g0004.jpg"/></fig><p>The average percentage of cells expressing ER&#945; was similar in both groups. The highest average percentage of cells expressing ER&#945; was noted in unstained cells (0 points), in particular in group C, whereas the lowest average percentage of cells expressing ER&#945; was observed in the strongly stained cells (3 points) in group C. In group E, the average percentage of unstained cells (0 points) was lower, whereas the average percentage of stained cells (1&#8211;3 points) was generally higher. These results indicate that the average percentage of strongly stained cells (3 points) expressing ER&#945; increased steadily during exposure to DON.</p><p>In the same analytical approach (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>), differences in the immunohistochemical expression of ER&#946; were noted (at *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#8804; 0.05) in week II (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5A</xref>) in the duodenal cap, jejunum and the descending colon, and in the descending colon, and in week III (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5B</xref>), differences were found only in the descending colon. No significant differences in the immunohistochemical expression of ER&#946; were noted in weeks I, IV, V, or VI (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Figures 3A&#8211;D</xref>).</p><fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Immunohistochemical expression of ER&#946; (graded on a 4-point scale: negative = 0 points; weak and homogeneous = 1 point; mild or moderate and homogeneous = 2 points; intense or strong and homogeneous = 3 points) in different intestinal segments in selected weeks of exposure: <bold>(A)</bold> in week II; <bold>(B)</bold> in week III. ER&#946; expression was presented as mean values (&#177;) and standard deviation (SD) for each sample. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#8804; 0.05 were compared with the control group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-644549-g0005.jpg"/></fig><p>Similarly, the levels of ER&#946; expression were presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Figure 4</xref>. In general, no statistical differences in ER&#946; expression were found between the groups.</p><fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Immunohistochemical expression of ER&#946; in the control and exposed groups (graded on a 4-point scale: negative = 0 points; weak and homogeneous = 1 point; mild or moderate and homogeneous = 2 points; intense or strong and homogeneous = 3 points) in different intestinal segments and in selected weeks of exposure: <bold>(A)</bold> in group E; <bold>(B)</bold> average expression values from all weeks of exposure in both groups.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-644549-g0006.jpg"/></fig><p>The average percentage of cells expressing ER&#946; was similar in both groups. ER&#946; expression continued to increase in intensely stained cells (3 points) on successive days of exposure to DON in both groups. In group E, a considerable increase in ER&#946; expression was observed in the duodenal cap and the third part of the duodenum (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6B</xref>).</p><p>In the second analytical approach (evaluating the influence of exposure time on ER expression), ER expression was presented only graphically due to a large number of significant differences (refer to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figures 7</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>). The results were not presented graphically for the segments of the intestinal tract where significant differences were not found (refer to <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Figures 5, 6</xref>).</p><fig id="F7" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>The effect of DON on the immunohistochemical expression of ER&#945; (graded on a 4-point scale: negative = 0 points; weak and homogeneous = 1 point; mild or moderate and homogeneous = 2 points; intense or strong and homogeneous = 3 points) in the intestines of pre-pubertal gilts from <bold>group E: (A)</bold> in the duodenal cap in selected weeks of exposure; <bold>(B)</bold> in the third part of the duodenum in selected weeks of exposure; <bold>(C)</bold> in the jejunum in selected weeks of exposure; <bold>(D)</bold> in the ascending colon in selected weeks of exposure. ER&#945; expression is presented as mean values (&#177;) and standard deviation (SD) in selected samples. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#8804; 0.05 and **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#8804; 0.01 compared with the remaining groups.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-644549-g0007.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>The effect of DON on the immunohistochemical expression of ER&#946; (graded on a 4-point scale: negative = 0 points; weak and homogeneous = 1 point; mild or moderate and homogeneous = 2 points; intense or strong and homogeneous = 3 points) in the intestines of pre-pubertal gilts from <bold>group E: (A)</bold> in the duodenal cap in selected weeks of exposure; <bold>(B)</bold> in the ascending colon in selected weeks of exposure. ER&#946; expression is presented as mean values (&#177;) and standard deviation (SD) in selected samples. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#8804; 0.05 and **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#8804; 0.01 compared with the remaining groups.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-644549-g0008.jpg"/></fig><p>In this analytical approach, no significant differences in the immunohistochemical expression of ER&#945; were found in the descending colon in group C and in the cecum and the descending colon in group E.</p><p>An analysis of the results presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Figure 5</xref> indicates that the immunohistochemical expression of ER&#945; continued to decrease in unstained (negative and homogeneous, 0 points) cells and in weakly stained and homogeneous cells (1 point) on successive sampling dates and in successive intestinal segments. An increase in ER&#945; expression in intestinal cells [moderately (2 points) and strongly (3 points) stained cells] appears to be a normal process in pre-pubertal gilts.</p><p>In group E (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>), the percentage of unstained (negative and homogeneous, 0 points) cells also decreased, whereas the percentage of cells showing mild and homogeneous (2 points) and strong and homogeneous (3 points) expression of ER&#945; continued to increase. These findings indicate that feed contamination with low doses of DON increases the percentage of intestinal cells expressing ER&#945; (2 points and 3 points) in pre-pubertal gilts.</p><p>In this analytical approach, no significant differences in the immunohistochemical expression of ER&#946; were noted in the cecum and the ascending colon in group C, and in the duodenal cap, the third part of the duodenum, the cecum and the descending colon in group E.</p><p>It can be assumed that the observed ER&#946; expression levels in the intestinal cells of control group animals (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Figure 6</xref>) are normal (physiological) and typical of pre-pubertal gilts. In proximal intestinal segments, the percentage of unstained (negative and homogeneous, 0 points) cells expressing ER&#946; continued to decrease on successive days of exposure. In turn, the percentage of cells where ER&#946; expression was strong and homogeneous (3 points) increased during the experiment. These differences in ER&#946; expression levels disrupt the stability of endocrine processes.</p><p>Significant differences were noted only in the duodenum (in the proximal segment) and in the descending colon (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>). The presence of DON in feed increased the percentage of intestinal cells strongly expressing ER&#946; (3 points) from 45% in the duodenum on sampling date I to 79% in the jejunum on sampling date IV on average. More stable ER&#946; expression may have positive implications for endocrine processes in pre-pubertal gilts.</p><p>The ER expression index should be calculated for each receptor type to obtain prognostic information. The results can be used to determine the degree/direction of expression of both types of analyzed ER. The ER expression index (P-ER) was calculated in 576 samples. The mean values of P-ER reached 66 &#177; 10 for ER&#945; and 26 &#177; 11 for ER&#946; in group C, and 56 &#177; 9 for ER&#945; and 23 &#177; 7 for ER&#946; in group E. P-ER values were not normally distributed (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>ER expression at various absorption levels during the entire experiment in the analyzed segments of the gastrointestinal tract in pre-pubertal gilts.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Group</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Degree of ER expression</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Duodenal cap</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Third part of duodenum</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Jejunum</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cecum</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Ascending colon</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Descending colon</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><bold>ER</bold><italic toggle="yes"><bold>&#945;</bold></italic></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group E</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><bold>ER</bold><italic toggle="yes"><bold>&#946;</bold></italic></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Group E</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">The values of P-ERs were divided into four groups and presented for each group: very low (A), low (B), high (C) and very high (D)</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In group C, the average value of P-ER&#945; was determined at 66, reaching 62 and 73 in the lower and upper quartile, respectively. Based on the median, the upper and lower quartiles, the expression values were divided into four sub-groups: A &#8211; very low P-ER&#945; (P-ER&#945; &lt;62), B&#8211;low P-ER&#945; (62 &lt; P-ER&#945; &lt;66), C&#8211;high P-ER&#945; (66 &lt; P-ER&#945; &lt;73), and D &#8211; very high P-ER&#945; (P-ER&#945; &gt; 73) (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). In group C, very low (A), low (B), high (C) and very high (D) values of P-ER&#945; were noted in 7 (29%), 4 (17%), 7 (29%) and 6 (25%) cases, respectively. The statistical analysis, conducted for the mean, median, upper and lower quartile cut-off points, revealed no significant differences.</p><p>In group E, the average value of P-ER&#945; was determined at 56, reaching 52 and 61 in the lower and upper quartile, respectively. Based on the median, the upper and lower quartiles, the expression values were divided into four sub-groups: A &#8211; very low P-ER&#945; (P-ER&#945; &lt; 52), B&#8211;low P-ER&#945; (52 &#8804; P-ER&#945; &lt; 56), C&#8211;high P-ER&#945; (56 &lt; P-ER&#945; &lt; 61), and D &#8211; very high P-ER&#945; (P-ER&#945; &gt; 61) (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). In group E, very low (A), low (B), high (C) and very high (D) values of P-ER&#945; were noted in 8 (33%), 5 (21%), 5 (21%), and 6 (25%) cases, respectively. The statistical analysis, conducted for the mean, median, upper and lower quartile cut-off points, revealed no significant differences.</p><p>In group C, the average value of P-ER&#946; was determined at 26, reaching 22 and 33 in the lower and upper quartile, respectively. Based on the median, the upper and lower quartiles, the expression values were divided into four sub-groups: A &#8211; very low P-ER&#946; (P-ER&#946; &lt; 22), B&#8211;low P-ER&#946; (22 &lt; P-ER&#946; &lt; 26), C&#8211;high P-ER&#946; (26 &lt; P-ER&#946; &lt; 33), and D&#8211;very high P-ER&#946; (P-ER&#946; &gt; 33) (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). In group C, very low (A), low (B), high (C) and very high (D) values of P-ER&#946; were noted in 7 (29%), 5 (21%), 4 (17%) and 8 (33%) cases, respectively. The statistical analysis, conducted for the mean, median, upper and lower quartile cut-off points, revealed no significant differences.</p><p>In group E, the average value of P-ER&#946; was determined at 23, reaching 19 and 28 in the lower and upper quartile, respectively. Based on the median, the upper and lower quartiles, the expression values were divided into four sub-groups: A &#8211; very low P-ER&#946; (P-ER&#946; &lt; 19), B&#8211;low P-ER&#946; (19 &lt; P-ER&#946; &lt; 23), C&#8211;high P-ER&#946; (23 &lt; P-ER&#946; &lt; 28), and D &#8211; very high P-ER&#946; (P-ER&#946; &gt; 28) (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). In group E, very low (A), low (B), high (C) and very high (D) values of P- P-ER&#946; were noted in 7 (29%), 6 (25%), 5 (21%) and 6 (25%) cases, respectively. The statistical analysis, conducted for the mean, median, upper and lower quartile cut-off points, revealed no significant differences.</p><p>In group E, the expression of the <italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1</italic> gene in the ascending colon decreased in comparison with group C, which is related to inflammation (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), except in week VI when <italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1</italic> expression was significantly higher in group E. In week II, the observed difference was highly significant, and significant differences were found in weeks III, IV and V (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9A</xref>). In group E, a highly significant decrease in the expression of the <italic toggle="yes">GSTP1</italic> gene was observed in weeks I to IV, and a significant decrease was noted in weeks V and VI (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9B</xref>).</p><fig id="F9" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>The expression of selected enzymes in the colon in different weeks of exposure: <bold>(A)</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1 m</italic>RNA expression in the ascending colon; <bold>(B)</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">GSTP1 m</italic>RNA expression in the ascending colon; <bold>(C)</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1 m</italic>RNA expression in the descending colon; <bold>(D)</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">GSTP1 m</italic>RNA expression in the descending colon. The bars represent mean values (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3) of enzyme gene expression ratios (ER &#177; SE) relative to a control sample at the beginning of the experiment (ER = 1.00; dashed line). Symbols (*) indicate experimental (E) groups that showed significantly different <italic toggle="yes">m</italic>RNA levels compared to a respective control (C) group (*<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#8804; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#8804; 0.01).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-644549-g0009.jpg"/></fig><p>In the descending colon, the expression of the <italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1</italic> gene was significantly higher in group E in weeks I, IV and VI, and highly significantly higher in week V (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9C</xref>). Significant differences in the expression of the <italic toggle="yes">GSTP1</italic> gene (higher values in group C) were observed only in week II. In the remaining weeks of the study, the mean values of this parameter fluctuated in both groups, but no significant differences were found (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9D</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Estrogen Receptors</title><p>There is increasing evidence to suggest that mycotoxins and their metabolites [not only mycoestrogens&#8211;(<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>)] are directly involved in interactions that disrupt hormonal homeostasis [including steroid hormones, as demonstrated <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> by&#8211;(<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>)]. These interactions are also mediated by ER. One of the important questions that needs to be answered is whether DON, an undesirable substance of natural origin, poses potential health risks in humans (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) and animals (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p><sec><title>Optical Density</title><sec><title>First Analytical Approach</title><p>No differences in the expression of both ER were found in the first and last week of the experiment, which could have several explanations.</p><p>The results of this study (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 3</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>) can be divided into two parts, corresponding to the analyzed intestinal segments. Firstly, DON undergoes relatively rapid biotransformation (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) in the proximal intestinal segments (both segments of the duodenum and jejunum), regardless of the week of exposure, or a counter-response (no response) of the macroorganism to the presence of a small dose of an undesirable substance is observed (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). The absence of significant differences on the first sampling date could be attributed to a very low mycotoxin dose that is &#8220;ignored&#8221; by the body. This assumption is partially confirmed by other studies (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>), and it is consistent with the Tregs theory (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>) which postulates that the expression of Tregs cells is not induced when the number of infectious factors is very low. It is also possible that DON comes into short-lived contact with ER in enterocytes, or does not come into such contact at all, because the mycotoxin is too rapidly absorbed by the macroorganism. Similar conclusions were formulated in another study that investigated a different mycotoxin (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). The above could also be due to the fact that DON concentrations are initially low, and the process of tissue saturation with the mycotoxin begins only in the second week of exposure (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>).</p><p>Secondly, ER&#945; expression in the descending colon in group C reached nearly 100% in week I, and it was lowest (60%) in week IV when a negative value was noted (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>). In group E, ER&#945; expression was mostly intense or strong and homogeneous (3 points), ranging from 80% in weeks I and VI, through 60% in week IV to 42% in week V (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>). The above could result from a compensatory mechanism (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>), where the activity of low mycotoxin doses is suppressed and initial functions are restored despite ongoing exposure. According to an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> study conducted by Woelflingseder et al. (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>), the compensatory mechanism may interfere with the glutathione-depleting effect under prolonged exposure to DON, which can potentially reduce the cytotoxic effect. On the other hand, in the present study, <italic toggle="yes">GSTP1 m</italic>RNA expression in both segments of the colon (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9</xref>), in particular the ascending colon (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9B</xref>), decreased in group E. The above could decrease the proliferation of epithelial cells (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), which promotes apoptosis, leading to controlled proliferation (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>).</p><p>Therefore, the observed changes could be attributed to compensation as well as chemical stress resulting from exposure to DON (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Second Analytical Approach</title><p>This analytical approach confirms the observations made by Demaegdt et al. (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>) that DON is a partial agonist of ER&#945;. In this study, the immunohistochemical expression of ER&#945; was mild or moderate and homogeneous (2 points) and intense or strong and homogeneous (3 points). The differences in the percentage of ER&#945;-expressing cells were considerable (10% to 15% on average), but not statistically significant, and they were noted mainly in weeks III, IV and V (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>) in the duodenal cap, the third part of the duodenum, the jejunum and the ascending colon. These observations could be attributed to prolonged exposure to DON which disrupts physiological processes (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) and cell signaling and, consequently, leads to the inhibition of protein and nucleic acid synthesis, and disruption of steroidogenesis caused by cytochrome P450 (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Steroidogenesis processes occur in tissues where steroidogenic enzymes are expressed, including the gastrointestinal tract (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). The disrupting effects of DON are limited to local tissues (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), as confirmed by the decrease in <italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1 m</italic>RNA expression in the ascending colon (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9A</xref>), but not in the descending colon in group E.</p><p>In the second analytical approach, the immunohistochemical expression of ER&#946; in group C was mainly negative (0 points) and intense or strong and homogeneous (3 points) (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Figure 6</xref>). Negative expression was noted mainly in weeks II and I. Intense or strong and homogeneous expression (3 points) was observed mainly in weeks IV, V and VI in the duodenal cap, the third part of the duodenum, the jejunum and the descending colon. Considerable changes were noted in group E (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>): significant differences were found only in the duodenal cap and the ascending colon where ER&#946; expression was evaluated as intense or strong and homogeneous (3 points); a general decrease in expression processes was also noted in this group. In the highest percentage of ER&#946;-expressing cells, ER&#946; expression was also intense or strong and homogeneous (3 points) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8B</xref>). An analysis of the results noted on each sampling date revealed that DON was accumulated until week V, particularly in the ascending colon. This specific situation observed at the end of the experiment may be attributed to the transactivation of ER&#946; (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>), which could be due to intensified apoptosis (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>) and proliferation in intestinal tissues as a result of Ying/Yang interactions (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). These findings could also be explained by the absence of competition (absence of ER&#945;) in selected tissues [such as the colonic mucosa&#8211;(<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>)] whose functions are not affected by ER&#945;. The colon is one of the key organs targeted by DON, which is why the observations made in this region are most pronounced. These processes are accompanied by histological changes which have been described by Pinton and Oswald (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>) and Przybylska-Gornowicz et al. (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>), and which take place mainly in the mucosa. Non-genomic factors that modulate regulatory membrane proteins could also play a role (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>).</p><p>In the second analytical approach, enhanced expression of ER&#946; under exposure to a low DON dose was a biological effect that inhibited ER&#945;-related functions (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). A comparison of both analytical approaches with previous findings (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) indicates that the immunohistochemical expression of ER proceeds differently, which could be attributed to the fact that the cited study examined the effects of mixed mycotoxicosis (DON/ZEN). The exposure to both DON and ZEN increased ER&#945; expression in the jejunum and the ascending colon, but expression levels in these intestinal segments continued to decrease during exposure. The expression of ER&#223; decreased steadily during exposure, in particular in the cecum and the descending colon. The expression of ER&#223; continued to increase in the remaining intestinal segments. These observations suggest that during mixed (DON/ZEN) mycotoxicosis, ER&#223; plays a dominant role in the intestinal mucosa of pre-pubertal gilts. A comparison of previous findings (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) with the results of the present study indicates that at low concentration, DON acts as a partial agonist that only partially activates the receptors.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>ER Expression Index</title><p>The ER index was calculated by comparing P-ER&#945;/P-ER&#946; because both ER occur in various proportions. An increase in the ER index points to enhanced proliferative processes resulting from higher expression of ER&#945;. A decrease in the ER index suggests that steroidogenesis processes were inhibited and that ER&#946; expression was enhanced. The ER expression index (P-ER&#945;/P-ER&#946;) was calculated to determine whether DON is a potential disruptor of hormonal homeostasis at the level of nuclear receptor signaling or, in other words, whether DON can act as an exogenous ligand for both ER&#945; and ER&#946;. The values of the ER expression index were higher in group E between the cecum and the descending colon. However, the graphic presentation of ER expression (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4B</xref>) revealed that ER&#945; expression decreased whereas ER&#946; expression remained at a similar level in both groups (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6B</xref>). The slight differences between groups indicate that DON is a relatively weak agonist <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic>, but it is not a weak antagonist of ER as suggested by Demaegdt et al. (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). This minor difference in activity could lead to hormonal activation resulting from the fact that plant materials generally contain much higher levels of DON than other <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic> mycotoxins (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), which suggests that the bioavailability of DON increases during exposure (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>).</p><p>The fact that DON is capable of inducing the expression of ER&#946; at the same level as in group C (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6B</xref>) which is more abundant in intestinal walls (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>), indicates that this mycotoxin can participate in steroidogenesis (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>) and enhances antioxidant activity. The latter observation is justified by the fact that both ER mediate estrogen activity. An important question that should be answered is whether DON can be regarded as an antioxidant solely because it induces the expression of ER. At the same time, DON inhibits antioxidant enzymes, thus increasing the production of ROS (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>), and decreasing intracellular GSH levels (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). In the present study, <italic toggle="yes">GSTP1 m</italic>RNA expression decreased in the colon (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Figures 6B,D</xref>) (excluding in the descending colon in weeks III and IV&#8211;see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Figure 6D</xref>), the immunohistochemical expression of ER&#945; decreased and ER&#946; expression remained unchanged.</p><p>The maintenance of ER&#946; expression (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6B</xref>) and supression of ER&#945; (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4B</xref>) may lead to the stimulation of cell proliferation and promotion of apoptosis (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). The above suggests that the presence of DON in feed can offer protection against selected hormone-sensitive tumors and neoplastic changes in the large intestine in mammals.</p></sec></sec><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">m</italic>RNA Expression of Genes Encoding Selected Enzymes in the Colon</title><p>Unlike some other mycotoxins, DON is not biologically transformed into more toxic compounds and is not oxidized to less toxic compounds during phase I biotransformation (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Various DON inactivation mechanisms have been identified in phase II biotransformation. One of these mechanisms involves the induction of GST&#960; subfamilies, which suggests that DON can act as a substrate for GST during phase II biotransformation (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). A different hypothesis postulates that GST activity increases due to the oxidative stress induced by DON (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>).</p><p>The absence of definitive answers to the above questions was the key motivation for investigating the effect of DON on the activity of two enzymes, CYP1A1 and GSTP1, which play important roles in the biotransformation of <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic> mycotoxins.</p><sec><title>CYP1A1 Metabolic Enzyme</title><p>A review of the literature indicates that DON disrupts cell signaling in mammals (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>) and exerts multidirectional effects by distorting gastrointestinal homeostasis and steroidogenesis with the involvement of cytochrome P450 (CYP) (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Some of CYP enzymes, e.g., CYP1A1, are involved in the conversion of procarcinogens to carcinogens (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Transcriptional activation of the <italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1</italic> gene can take place under exposure to undesirable substances such as DON (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) or phytoestrogens (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Detoxifying effects can be achieved by suppressing the activity of the CYP1A1 enzyme (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). This type of activity was detected in the ascending colon on nearly all sampling dates (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9A</xref>), excluding week VI. The results noted on the last sampling date are difficult to interpret because expression levels were higher in group E. It has been hypothesized that CYP1A1 alleles may increase the risk of cancer because they encode enzymes with higher metabolic activity (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). However, it should be noted that the accumulation of DON in tissues (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) increased in successive weeks of exposure. The above suggests that biotransformation processes do not evolve continuously during exposure, and the carryover factor increased from 0.012&#8211;0.022 in weeks I to IV to 0.032&#8211;0.049 in the last week of the experiment. The above interpretation does not apply to the descending colon (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9C</xref>), where the carry-over of DON was detected only in week IV. These results can be extrapolated to suggest that the &#8220;transient dysbiosis&#8221; of the gut microbiota plays a key role in the biotransformation of DON, in particular in the large intestine of pre-pubertal gilts (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). However, further research is needed to validate this assumption in all mammals.</p><p>Considerable differences in <italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1 m</italic>RNA expression were found between the ascending colon and the descending colon, which complicates the interpretation of the results. The presence of DON in ingested feed inhibited gene expression in the ascending colon, which suggests that this mycotoxin can contribute to preventing steroid-dependent carcinogenesis. In the descending colon, DON increased gene expression, which, together with the presence of endogenous factors in the intestinal lumen, points to an increase in the enzyme's detoxifying activity.</p></sec><sec><title>GSTP1 Gene Encoding Phase II Metabolic Enzymes</title><p>In the current study, an attempt was also made to determine whether prolonged exposure to a low dose of DON modifies <italic toggle="yes">GSTP1 m</italic>RNA expression and the associated processes in pre-pubertal gilts. According to Woelflingseder et al. (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>), the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> modulatory effects of GSH on DON toxicity led to only a minor suppression of proliferative processes and cytotoxic effects. In the present study, <italic toggle="yes">GSTP1 m</italic>RNA expression decreased steadily in the ascending colon during the experiment (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9B</xref>). However, in the descending colon, <italic toggle="yes">GSTP1 m</italic>RNA expression was higher in group E in weeks III and IV (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9D</xref>). These observations could be attributed to: (i) balanced demand and supply (homeostasis) of <italic toggle="yes">GSTP1 m</italic>RNA which is required for the maintenance of cytoprotective and detoxifying functions during phase II biotransformation (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>); (ii) excessive saturation with intracellular GSH in the ascending colon and the descending colon in response to the overexpression of <italic toggle="yes">GSTP1 m</italic>RNA (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>); (iii) intensified transactivation of ER&#946; (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>); or (iv) intensified apoptosis (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>) and/or controlled proliferation in intestinal tissues (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). These observations are consistent with the results reported <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>).</p><p>The exposure to a low mycotoxin dose led to a controlled decrease in <italic toggle="yes">GSTP1 m</italic>RNA expression, and a consensus was maintained between intestinal cells, the degree of exposure to an undesirable substance and the detoxifying effect.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Summary</title><p>The aim of this study was to determine <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> the effect of DON, administered <italic toggle="yes">per os</italic> at 12 &#956;g/kg BW to pre-pubertal gilts for 42 days, on the immunohistochemical expression of intestinal ERs and the expression of genes encoding <italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1 m</italic>RNA and <italic toggle="yes">GSTP1 m</italic>RNA in the colon on different sampling dates. The research findings indicate that exposure to the analyzed DON dose led to (i) a decrease in ER&#945; expression by ~15% between the jejunum and the descending colon; (ii) an increase in ER&#946; expression in the duodenum, and the maintenance of its expression at the same level as in group C in the remaining intestinal segments; (iii) a significant decrease in <italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1 m</italic>RNA expression in the ascending colon, and a significant increase in its expression in the descending colon; and (iv) a decrease in <italic toggle="yes">GSTP1 m</italic>RNA expression in the colon on most sampling dates.</p><p>To the best of the authors' knowledge, the is the first study to indirectly demonstrate that the presence of the analyzed DON dose in feed (12 &#956;g DON/kg BW <italic toggle="yes">per os</italic> for a period 42 days) probably offers protection against uncontrolled proliferation in the large intestine of pre-pubertal gilts, and contributes to maintaining a stable consensus between the degree of exposure to DON and the detoxifying effect in mammals.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s5"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Material</xref>, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author/s.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>All procedures in this study were carried out in compliance with Polish legal regulations for the determination of the terms and methods for performing experiments on animals and with the European Community Directive for the ethical use of experimental animals. The protocol was approved by the Local Ethical Council in Olsztyn (opinion No. 88/N of 16 December, 2009).</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>MG, &#321;Z, and MTG designed the experiments. The data were analyzed and interpreted by MG, IO-D, PB, and SL-&#379;. The manuscript was drafted and critically read by MG, &#321;Z, and MTG. The manuscript was revised, read, and approved by all authors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> The study was supported by the Polish Ministry of Science and Higher Education as part of Project No. 12-0080-10/2010. The project was financially co-supported by the Minister of Science and Higher 613 Education under the program entitled Regional Initiative of Excellence for the years 2019-2022, 614 Project No. 010/RID/2018/19, amount of funding PLN 12,000,000.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s8"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2021.644549/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2021.644549/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Demaegdt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daminet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Evrard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scippo</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pussemier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Endocrine activity of mycotoxins and mycotoxin mixtures</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>107</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2016.07.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27481073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Urbanek</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Habrowska-G&#243;rczy&#324;ska</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kowalska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sta&#324;czyk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Domi&#324;ska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piastowska-Ciesielska</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Deoxynivalenol as potential modulator of human steroidogenesis</article-title>. <source>J Appl Toxicol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>695</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jat.3623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29611633</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rykaczewska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaj&#281;cka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Onyszek</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciepli&#324;ska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dabrowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lisieska-&#379;o&#322;nierczyk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Imbalance in the blood concentrations of selected steroids in prepubertal gilts depending on the time of exposure to low doses of zearalenone</article-title>. <source>Toxins.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>561</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins11100561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6832454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31557818</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zielonka</surname><given-names>&#321;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaj&#281;cka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lisieska-&#379;o&#322;nierczyk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dabrowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaj&#281;cki</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of different doses of zearalenone in feed on the bioavailability of zearalenone and alpha-zearalenol, and the concentrations of estradiol and testosterone in the peripheral blood of prepubertal gilts</article-title>. <source>Toxins.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>144</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins12030144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7150765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32111008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khoshal</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>PGP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neves</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schatzmayr</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Co-occurrence of DON and emerging mycotoxins in worldwide finished pig feed and their combined toxicity in intestinal cells</article-title>. <source>Toxins.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>727</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins11120727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31835876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6950336</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cimbalo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso-Garrido</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Font</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manyes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Toxicity of mycotoxins <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> on vertebrate organisms: a review</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>137</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2020.111161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32014537</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanyu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yokoi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mycotoxin deoxynivalenol has different impacts on intestinal barrier and stem cells by its route of exposure</article-title>. <source>Toxins.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>610</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins12100610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32987679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7598581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Deoxynivalenol induces inflammatory injury in IPEC-J2 cells via NF-_B signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>Toxins.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>733</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins11120733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6950076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31888297</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaj&#281;cka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dabrowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Otrocka-Domaga&#322;a</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brzuzan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rykaczewska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciepli&#324;ska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Correlation between the exposure of deoxynivalenol and zearalenone and the immunohistochemical expression of estrogen receptors in the intestinal epithelium and <italic toggle="yes">m</italic>RNA of selected colonic enzymes in prepubertal gilts</article-title>. <source>Toxicon.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>173</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxicon.2019.11.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31734251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Versatility or promiscuity: the estrogen receptors, control of ligand selectivity and an update on subtype selective ligands</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>8709</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph110908709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25162709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4198987</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bandolia</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A review on selective estrogen receptor modulators</article-title>. <source>Res Pharm Health Sci.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>179</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32463/rphs.2019.v05i03.03</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Discovery of estrogen receptor modulators: a review of virtual screening and SAR efforts</article-title>. <source>Expert Opin Drug Discov.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1517/17460440903490395</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22823969</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taheri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinger</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghafouri-Fard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Perspectives on the role of non-coding RNAs in the regulation of expression and function of the estrogen receptor</article-title>. <source>Cancers.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>2162</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cancers12082162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32759784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7465269</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Judson</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>EADB: an estrogenic activity database for assessing potential endocrine activity</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Sci.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>135</volume>:<fpage>277</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/toxsci/kft164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23897986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bayala</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zoure</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Joussineau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simpore</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lobaccaro</surname><given-names>J-MA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacological modulation of steroid activity in hormone-dependent breast and prostate cancers: effect of some plant extract derivatives</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>3690</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms21103690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32456259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7279356</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Payros</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alassane-Kpembi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pierron</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loiseau</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oswald</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Toxicology of deoxynivalenol and its acetylated and modified forms</article-title>. <source>Arch Toxicol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>2931</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>57</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00204-016-1826-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27663890</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Piotrowska-Kempisty</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klupczy&#324;ska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trzybulska</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kulcenty</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sulej-Suchomska</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuci&#324;ska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Role of CYP1A1 in the biological activity of methylated resveratrol analogue, 3,4,5,40-tetramethoxystilbene (DMU-212) in ovarian cancer A-2780 and non-cancerous HOSE cells</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Lett.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>267</volume>:<fpage>59</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxlet.2016.12.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28049037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nandekar</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khomane</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhary</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rathod</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borkar</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhandi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of leads for antiproliferative activity on MDA-MB-435 human breast cancer cells through pharmacophore and CYP1A1-mediated metabolism</article-title>. <source>Eur J Med Chem.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>115</volume>:<fpage>82</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejmech.2016.02.061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26994845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bocedi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noce</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marrone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noce</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cattani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gambardella</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Glutathione transferase p1-1 an enzyme useful in biomedicine and as biomarker in clinical practice and in environmental pollution</article-title>. <source>Nutrients.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1741</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu11081741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31357662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6723968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Basharat</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yasmin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Energy landscape of a GSTP1 polymorph linked with cytological function decay in response to chemical stressors</article-title>. <source>Gene.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>609</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2017.01.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28153749</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zwierzchowski</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaj&#281;cki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Obremski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zielonka</surname><given-names>&#321;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baranowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The occurrence of zearalenone and its derivatives in standard and therapeutic feeds for companion animals</article-title>. <source>Pol J Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>289</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15633789</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wa&#347;kiewicz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beszterda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kostecki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zielonka</surname><given-names>&#321;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goli&#324;ski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaj&#281;cki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Deoxynivalenol in the gastrointestinal tract of immature gilts under <italic toggle="yes">per os</italic> toxin application</article-title>. <source>Toxins.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>973</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>87</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins6030973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24603665</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3968371</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zielonka</surname><given-names>&#321;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wa&#347;kiewicz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beszterda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kostecki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dabrowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Obremski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Zearalenone in the intestinal tissues of immature gilts exposed <italic toggle="yes">per os</italic> to mycotoxins</article-title>. <source>Toxins.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>3210</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins7083210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26295259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4549746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heberer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lahrssen-Wiederholt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schafft</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pzyrembel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henning</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Zero tolerances in food and animal feed-Are there any scientific alternatives? A European point of view on an international controversy</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Lett.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>175</volume>:<fpage>118</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxlet.2007.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18024010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>The Commission of the European Communities</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Commission Recommendation (2006/576/EC, 2006) of 17 August 2006 on the presence of deoxynivalenol, zearale-none, ochratoxin A, T-2 and HT-2 and fumonisins in products intended for animal feeding</article-title>. <source>Off J Eur Union.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>L229</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://data.europa.eu/eli/reco/2006/576/oj">http://data.europa.eu/eli/reco/2006/576/oj</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kostecki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goli&#324;ski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Che&#322;kowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Biosynthesis, isolation, separation and purification of zearalenone, deoxynivalenol and 15-acetyldeoxynivalenol</article-title>. <source>Mycotoxin Res.</source> (<year>1991</year>) <volume>7A</volume>:<fpage>156</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF03192202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23605897</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kostecki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goli&#324;ski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Che&#322;kowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Biosynthesis, isolation, separation and purification of nivalenol, fusarenone-X and zearalenone</article-title>. <source>Mycotoxin Res.</source> (<year>1991</year>) <volume>7A</volume>:<fpage>160</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF03192203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23605898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaj&#281;cka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of low-dose experimental zearalenone intoxication on the immunoexpression of estrogen receptors in the ovaries of pre-pubertal bitches</article-title>. <source>Pol J Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>685</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2478/v10181-012-0106-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23390758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singhai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaiswal</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tayade</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>E-cadherin as a diagnostic biomarker in breast cancer</article-title>. <source>N Am J Med Sci.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>227</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4297/najms.2011.3227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22558599</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3337742</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coulouris</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaretskaya</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cutcutache</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rozen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Primer-BLAST: a tool to design target-specific primers for polymerase chain reaction</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>134</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-13-134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22708584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3412702</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Spachmo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arukwe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Endocrine and developmental effects in Atlantic salmon (<italic toggle="yes">Salmo salar</italic>) exposed to perfluorooctane sulfonic or perfluorooctane carboxylic acids</article-title>. <source>Aquat Toxicol.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>108</volume>:<fpage>112</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquatox.2011.07.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22265611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Renton</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cytochrome P450 regulation and drug biotransformation during inflammation and infection</article-title>. <source>Curr Drug Metab.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>235</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1389200043335559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15180493</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaj&#281;cka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zielonka</surname><given-names>&#321;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaj&#281;cki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Activity of zearalenone in the porcine intestinal tract</article-title>. <source>Molecules.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules22010018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28029134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6155780</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ares</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;nez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;nez-Larra&#241;aga</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Epigenetic upregulation of galanin-like peptide mediates deoxynivalenol induced-growth inhibition in pituitary cells</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Appl Pharm.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>403</volume>:<fpage>115166</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.taap.2020.115166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32738333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goyarts</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danicke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bioavailability of the fusarium toxin deoxynivalenol (DON) from naturally contaminated wheat for the pig</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Lett.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>171</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxlet.2005.10.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16326049</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pestka</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amuzie</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Tissue distribution and proinflammatory cytokine gene expression following acute oral exposure to deoxynivalenol: comparison of weanling and adult mice</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>2826</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2008.05.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18614267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2620205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hlavov&#225;</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#352;t&#283;p&#225;nov&#225;</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#352;t&#224;stn&#253;</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lev&#225;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hodkovicov&#225;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>V&#237;cenov&#225;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Minimal concentrations of deoxynivalenol reduce cytokine production in individual lymphocyte populations in pigs</article-title>. <source>Toxins.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>190</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins12030190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32197345</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7150743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva-Campa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mata-Haro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mateu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hern&#225;ndez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome virus induces CD4+CD8+CD25+Foxp3+ regulatory T cells (Tregs)</article-title>. <source>Virology.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>430</volume>:<fpage>73</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2012.04.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22609353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dabrowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Obremski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaj&#281;cka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaj&#281;cki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zielonka</surname><given-names>&#321;</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in the subpopulations of porcine peripheral blood lymphocytes induced by exposure to low doses of zearalenone (ZEN) and deoxynivalenol (DON)</article-title>. <source>Molecules.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>557</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules21050557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27128894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6272943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Piotrowska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sli&#380;ewska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#379;ielonka</surname><given-names>&#321;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zakowska</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaj&#281;cka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of experimental <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium mycotoxicosis</italic> on microbiota diversity in porcine ascending colon contents</article-title>. <source>Toxins.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>2064</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins6072064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25025709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4113742</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryden</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mycotoxin contamination of the feed supply chain: implications for animal productivity and feed security</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Tech.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>173</volume>:<fpage>134</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>58</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2011.12.014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Woelflingseder</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Favero</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bla&#381;evi&#263;</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heiss</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haider</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Warth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of glutathione modulation on the toxicity of the <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium mycotoxins</italic> deoxynivalenol (DON), NX-3 and butenolide in human liver cells</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Lett.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>299</volume>:<fpage>104</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.toxlet.2018.09.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30244016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsybulsky</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucioli</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laffitte</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Callu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyazhri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Toxicity of deoxynivalenol and its acetylated derivatives on the intestine: differential effects on morphology, barrier function, tight junction proteins, and mitogen-activated protein kinases</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Sci.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>130</volume>:<fpage>180</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/toxsci/kfs239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22859312</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Odermatt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Strajhar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Engeli</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Disruption of steroidogenesis: cell models for mechanistic investigations and as screening tools</article-title>. <source>J Steroid Biochem Mol Biol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>158</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsbmb.2016.01.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26807866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#252;</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jamaluddin</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ginsenoside Rb1 blocks ritonavir-Induced oxidative stress and eNOS downregulation through activation of estrogen receptor-beta and upregulation of SOD in human endothelial cells</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>294</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms20020294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30642080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6358897</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>DiLeo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niv</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>J&#506;</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Estrogen receptor beta as target for colorectal cancer prevention</article-title>. <source>Cancer Lett.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>372</volume>:<fpage>48</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.canlet.2015.12.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26708506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4744541</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Viggiani</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polimeno</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Leo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Phytestrogens: dietary intake, bioavailability, and protective mechanisms against colorectal neoproliferative lesions</article-title>. <source>Nutrients.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1709</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu11081709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31344966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6722977</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>J&#506;</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>DHEA &#8211; a precursor of ER&#223; ligands</article-title>. <source>J Steroid Biochem.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>145</volume>:<fpage>245</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsbmb.2014.08.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25125389</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinton</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oswald</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of deoxynivalenol and other type B trichothecenes on the intestine: a review</article-title>. <source>Toxins.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1615</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins6051615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24859243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4052256</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Przybylska-Gornowicz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewczuk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prusik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanuszewska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrusewicz-Kosi&#324;ska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaj&#281;cka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The effects of deoxynivalenol and zearalenone on the pig large intestine. A light and electron microscopic study</article-title>. <source>Toxins.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>148</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins10040148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5923314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29617295</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerre</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mycotoxin and gut microbiota interactions</article-title>. <source>Toxins.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>769</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins12120769</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7761905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33291716</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#243;pez-Calderero</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carnero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Astudillo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palacios</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Benavent</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prognostic relevance of estrogen receptor-&#945; ser167 phosphorylation in stage II-III colon cancer patients</article-title>. <source>Hum Pathol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>2437</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.humpath.2014.08.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25283475</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gouze</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laffitte</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rouimi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loiseau</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oswald</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galtier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of various doses of deoxynivalenol on liver xenobiotic metabolizing enzymes in mice</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>476</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>83</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2005.08.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16209902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freedland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cera</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fasullo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>CYP1A1 i462V polymorphism is associated with reduced genotoxicityin yeast despite positive association with increased cancer risk</article-title>. <source>Mut Res.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>815</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mrgentox.2017.02.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28283091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5393454</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Growth performance, serum biochemical profile, jejunal morphology, and the expression of nutrients transporter genes in deoxynivalenol (DON)- challenged growing pigs</article-title>. <source>BMC Vet Res.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>144</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12917-015-0449-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26138080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4490653</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Colon microbiome of pigs fed diet contaminated with commercial purified deoxynivalenol and zearalenone</article-title>. <source>Toxins.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>347</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins10090347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30158450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6162637</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><glossary><def-list><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term>BW</term><def><p>body weight</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>C</term><def><p>control group</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Cq</term><def><p>quantitative cycle</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic toggle="yes">CYP1A1</italic></term><def><p>cytochrome P450 1A1 gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>E</term><def><p>exposed group</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EDs</term><def><p>endocrine disruptors</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ERs</term><def><p>estrogen receptors</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ER&#945;</term><def><p>estrogen receptor alpha</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ER&#946;</term><def><p>estrogen receptor beta</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GSH</term><def><p>glutathione</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic toggle="yes">GSTP1</italic></term><def><p>glutathione S-transferase &#960; gene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NOAEL</term><def><p>no-observed-adverse-effect level</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>P-ER</term><def><p>ER expression index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Real-Time PCR</term><def><p>real-time polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SD</term><def><p>standard deviation.</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></back></article></pmc-articleset>