<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8377367</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8377367.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8377367</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8377367</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34422945</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.693506</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Efficacy of Tigecycline and Linezolid Against Pan-Drug-Resistant Bacteria Isolated From Companion Dogs in South Korea</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="DH">Dong-Hyun</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="JH">Jung-Hyun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1216202/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff><institution>Department of Veterinary Internal Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>College of Veterinary Medicine</addr-line>, <addr-line>Konkuk University</addr-line>, <addr-line>Seoul</addr-line>, <country>South Korea</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Marina Spinu, University of Agricultural Sciences and Veterinary Medicine of Cluj-Napoca, Romania</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Mahdi Askari Badouei, Ferdowsi University of Mashhad, Iran; Kumaragurubaran Karthik, Tamil Nadu Veterinary and Animal Sciences University, India</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Jung-Hyun Kim <email>junghyun@konkuk.ac.kr</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Veterinary Infectious Diseases, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>8</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">374996</issue-id><elocation-id>693506</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>4</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>7</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>21</day><month>08</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-09-19 16:25:17.893"><day>19</day><month>09</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2021 Kim and Kim.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kim and Kim</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-08-693506.pdf"/><abstract><p>The emergence of multidrug-resistant bacteria in companion animals is an increasing concern in view of the concept of One Health. The antimicrobials linezolid (LZD) and tigecycline (TGC) are effective against multidrug-resistant bacteria isolated from humans; however, thus far, no previous study has evaluated the efficacy of these drugs against bacteria isolated from companion animals. This study aimed to evaluate the efficacy of LZD and TGC against bacteria that were isolated from companion dogs and showed resistance to all classes of antimicrobial agents. Clinical samples <underline>(</underline>auditory channel, eye, skin, and urine) were collected from dogs that visited the Veterinary Medical Teaching Hospital of Konkuk University (Seoul, South Korea) from October 2017 to September 2020. In total, 392 bacterial isolates were obtained, of which 85 were resistant to all classes of antimicrobial agents tested and were, therefore, considered potentially pan-drug resistant (PDR). The susceptibility of isolates to LZD and TGC was determined by the disk diffusion method and interpreted using the Clinical Laboratory Standards Institute guidelines. In total, 95.6% (43/45) and 97.8% (44/45) of gram-positive isolates were susceptible to LZD and TGC, respectively, whereas 82.5% (33/40) of gram-negative isolates were sensitive to TGC. In conclusion, both agents showed favorable efficacy, with the susceptibility rates for all potential PDR bacteria, except <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas</italic> spp., ranging from 72.7 to 100%. Thus, these drugs may serve as excellent antimicrobial options for veterinary medicine in the future.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>linezolid</kwd><kwd>tigecycline</kwd><kwd>antimicrobial resistance</kwd><kwd>pan-drug-resistant</kwd><kwd>companion animals</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="4"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="44"/><page-count count="9"/><word-count count="5822"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The emergence of multidrug-resistant (MDR) bacteria, which are resistant to three or more categories of antimicrobials, in companion animals is highly concerning. Particularly, resistance to antimicrobials is growing among bacteria such as <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus, Staphylococcus pseudintermedius</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), which cause infections in dogs. The transmission of such bacteria can be either direct or indirect among dogs, owners, and veterinary staff. Indeed, practicing veterinarians are far more likely to experience nasal colonization with <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> than the general population (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Notably, under the One Health concept, companion animals have been documented to be reservoirs of some high-risk MDR clones of Enterobacteriaceae (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), which are likely to be acquired from their human owners. Overuse of antimicrobials in veterinary clinics may amplify antimicrobial resistance and result in a subsequent spread of resistant microorganisms to animal owners. Therefore, the appropriate use of antimicrobials to prevent pain, illness, or death should be adopted for infection management in animals to improve the public health of both humans and animals.</p><p>Previous studies that analyzed the temporal trends of antimicrobial resistance in small collections of bacterial isolates from infected companion animals have provided evidence for a significant increase in antimicrobial resistance, particularly to agents frequently used in clinical settings, such as cephalosporins, ampicillins, and quinolones (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p><p>Linezolid (LZD) is a member of the oxazolidinone class of synthetic antibacterial agents that inhibit bacterial protein synthesis through a unique mechanism. In contrast to other inhibitors of protein synthesis, oxazolidinones act early in translation by preventing the formation of a functional initiation complex (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Discovered in 1987 at E.I. DuPont de Nemours and Co., Inc., DuP-721 was the first well-characterized oxazolidinone (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>) that exhibited strong activity against MDR gram-positive pathogens (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). In fact, it is currently used for the treatment of clinical methicillin-susceptible and methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> infections and for managing infections caused by vancomycin-resistant enterococci (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) in humans.</p><p>Tigecycline (TGC) is a glycylcycline antibiotic that is effective against a variety of gram-positive and gram-negative bacteria (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). TGC is currently one of the most potent antimicrobial agents for treating infections caused by MDR bacteria in humans (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). This drug has demonstrated <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> activity against important resistant organisms, including methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, penicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic>, and vancomycin-resistant enterococcal species, in addition to extended-spectrum beta-lactamase-producing <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). A previous study has shown that more than 90% of Enterobacteriaceae isolates are susceptible to this drug (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p><p>Nevertheless, LZD and TGC have not been used as first- or second-line treatment options in companion animals owing to concerns that the overuse and abuse of antimicrobials in animals would limit treatment options for human bacterial infections, in view of the One Health concept. Moreover, no previous study has evaluated the efficacies of LZD and TGC against bacteria originating from companion animals.</p><p>The present study aimed to evaluate the efficacies of LZD and TGC against potential pan-drug-resistant (PDR) bacteria (i.e., resistant to all classes of antimicrobial agents) isolated from dogs. Antimicrobial stewardship and related policies are beyond the scope of the current work.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Sampling</title><p>A total of 359 clinical samples were collected from different lesions in dogs that visited the Veterinary Medical Teaching Hospital of Konkuk University (Seoul, South Korea) from October 2017 to September 2020. The samples were immediately placed into a transport medium (ESwab, Copan, Brescia, Italy). The sampling sites included the auditory channels, eyes/conjunctiva, gastrointestinal tract, skin/mucosa, blood, and urogenital tract (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Auditory channel, eye, and skin samples were routinely collected using sterile cotton swabs, and urine samples were collected by cystocentesis. In addition, we collected at least 2 g of feces, which were cubed to ~<inline-formula><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> inch on a single side using a fecal loop. Peripheral blood was collected by venipuncture of the jugular vein to identify systemic infections. Furthermore, cerebrospinal fluid was obtained at the junction between lumbar vertebrae 5 and 6 using a conventional lumbar tapping method, and samples from the peritoneal walls were collected with sterile cotton swabs. All samples were immediately transported to the NosVet Laboratory (Gyeonggi-do, South Korea) and analyzed within 3&#8211;4 h.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Distribution of sampling sites and isolates.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sites</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>No. of samples</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>No. of isolates</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urogenital tract</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Auditory channel</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin/mucosa</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eye/conjunctiva</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gastrointestinal tract</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tooth</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Joint effusion</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blood</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Respiratory tract</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other sites<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>*</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">359</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">392</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><label>*</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Other sites include cerebrospinal fluid, tissue of various types, synovial capsule, foreign body, mass, bone (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary File 1</xref>)</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The animal study and the protocol was reviewed and approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (KU20218). Written informed consent was obtained from the owners for the participation of their animals in this study.</p></sec><sec><title>Bacterial Isolates</title><p>In total, 392 isolates were obtained from the dogs by directly inoculating blood agar plates with the clinical samples using cotton swabs, followed by incubation of the agar plates at 37&#176;C for up to 24 h. Morphologically identical colonies were picked and sub-cultured onto blood agar plates, and species were identified using a matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization mass spectrometer (ASTA, Gyeonggi-do, South Korea). Bacterial stock solutions were stored at &#8722;20&#176;C.</p></sec><sec><title>Antibiotic Susceptibility Testing</title><p>Commercial antimicrobial disk diffusion tests were performed by NosVet, Inc., according to the Clinical Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI) guidelines (VET08). Susceptibility to 21 antibiotics from 10 classes, namely, amikacin (AK), amoxicillin/clavulanic acid (AMC), ampicillin (AMP), azithromycin (AZM), cefixime (CFM), cefotaxime (CTX), cefpodoxime (CPD), ceftazidime (CAZ), cephalexin (CL), cephazolin (KZ), ciprofloxacin (CIP), clindamycin (DA), doxycycline (DO), enrofloxacin (ENR), erythromycin (E), gentamicin (CN), lincomycin (MY), ofloxacin (OFX), spiramycin (SP), sulfamethoxazole/trimethoprim (SXT), and tetracycline (TE), was determined using a Vitek&#174; AST-P601 card (bioM&#233;rieux, Marcy l'&#201;toile, France).</p><p>Two additional antibiotics, namely, LZD and TGC (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA), which are not included in the CLSI VET08 guidelines, were tested against potential PDR strains. Susceptibility to LZD and TGC was determined by the disk diffusion method and interpreted based on the CLSI guidelines. The European Committee on Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing (EUCAST) guidelines were used when information was missing in the CLSI guidelines. Briefly, bacteria were inoculated from stock solutions onto Mueller&#8211;Hinton agar plates and incubated at 37&#176;C for 24 h. Colonies were suspended in normal saline, and the turbidity was adjusted to a 0.5 McFarland standard equivalent (~10<sup>8</sup> colony-forming units per milliliter). Sterile cotton swabs were dipped into inoculation broth and subsequently streaked over Mueller&#8211;Hinton agar plates. Antibiotic disks of 30 &#956;g of LZD and 15 &#956;g of TGC were then placed on these plates, followed by incubation of the plates at 37&#176;C for 24 h. Diameters of the inhibition zones were used to categorize bacteria as susceptible, intermediate resistant, and resistant according to the CLSI and EUCAST guidelines.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Descriptive statistics were used for the analyses of signalment, clinical data, and laboratory findings. All statistical analyses were performed using Microsoft Excel (Microsoft Corp., Redmond, WA, USA). An exact chi-square test was used to compare the efficacies of LZD, TGC, and the 21 other antibiotics against potential PDR bacteria from dogs. Differences with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values of &lt;0.05 were considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>Based on the antibiotic sensitivity evaluation conducted by NosVet, Inc., 211 bacterial isolates were classified as extensively drug resistant (XDR), as previously described (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Of these 211 isolates, 57 were resistant to eight classes and 69 were resistant to nine classes, while 85 were resistant to all ten classes of antimicrobial agents tested and were thus considered potential PDR bacteria (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> presents the taxonomic distribution of the 85 isolates.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Species distribution of potential pan-drug-resistant isolates tested in this study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Gram</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Species</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>No. of isolates</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Proteus mirabilis</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Citrobacter freundii</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter aerogenes</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter cloacae complex</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pasteurellaceae bacterium</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus pseudintermedius</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecium</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecalis</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus schleiferi</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Corynebacterium auriscanis</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Rothia nasimurium</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus canis</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr style="border-top: thin solid #000000;"><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec><title>Gram-Positive Isolates</title><p>According to the tests conducted by NosVet, Inc., 163 (65%) of 249 gram-positive strains showed sensitivity to AK, 131 (52.6%) were sensitive to AMC, 90 (36.1%) were sensitive to AMP, 110 (44.2%) were sensitive to AZM, 5 (2.0%) were sensitive to CFM, 89 (35.7%) were sensitive to CTX, 88 (35.3%) were sensitive to CPD, 11 (4.4%) were sensitive to CAZ, 97 (39.0%) were sensitive to CL, 114 (45.8%) were sensitive to KZ, 20 (8.0%) were sensitive to CIP, 93 (37.3%) were sensitive to DA, 124 (49.8%) were sensitive to DO, 133 (53.4%) were sensitive to ENR, 99 (39.8%) were sensitive to E, 88 (35.3%) were sensitive to CN, 8 (3.2%) were sensitive to MY, 125 (50.2%) were sensitive to OFX, 87 (34.9%) were sensitive to SP, 84 (33.7%) were sensitive to SXT, and 85 (34.1%) were sensitive to TE. Among these strains, 215 (86.3%) were MDR, 125 (50.2%) were XDR, and 45 (18.0%) were potential PDR bacteria (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary File 1</xref>).</p><p>Among the potential PDR gram-positive bacteria, 95.6% (43/45) and 97.8% (44/45) of isolates were susceptible to LZD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) and TGC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>), respectively. Superiority of LZD and TGC over the other antibiotics was statistically analyzed, and the result is presented in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Tables 3</xref>, <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">4</xref>. Overall, the potential PDR bacteria were significantly more susceptible to these two agents than to the other 21 agents (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The average diameter of the zone of inhibition for LZD was 31 mm, which fell within the susceptibility zone diameter of gram-positive bacteria for LZD. The average diameter of the zone of inhibition was 24.5 mm for TGC, which exceeded the zone of resistance size.</p><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Efficacy of linezolid compared to 21 antibiotics for potential pan-drug-resistant (PDR) bacteria from dogs. Circles indicate the susceptibility of gram-positive potential PDR isolates for each antibiotic. Squares indicate the average susceptibility of gram-positive potential PDR isolates.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-693506-g0001.jpg"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Efficacy of tigecycline compared to 21 antibiotics for potential pan-drug-resistant (PDR) bacteria from dogs. Circles indicate the susceptibility of potential PDR isolates for each antibiotic. Squares indicate the average susceptibility of potential PDR isolates.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-693506-g0002.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Superiority of linezolid efficacy over 21 different antibiotics to eradicate potential pan-drug-resistant bacteria from dogs.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Antibiotic</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Susceptible (%)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Linezolid <italic toggle="yes">P-value</italic></bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amikacin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.1%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amoxycillin/Clavulanic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ampicillin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Azithromycin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefixime</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefotaxime</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefpodoxime</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ceftazidime</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cephalexin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cephazolin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ciprofloxacin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clindamycin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Doxycycline</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.3%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enrofloxacin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Erythromycin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gentamicin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lincomycin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.2%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ofloxacin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spiramycin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sulfamethoxazole/Trimethoprim</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tetracycline</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linezolid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.7%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Superiority of tigecycline efficacy over 21 different antibiotics to eradicate potential pan-drug-resistant bacteria from dogs.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Antibiotic</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Susceptible (%)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Tigecycline <italic toggle="yes">P-value</italic></bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amikacin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.0%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amoxycillin/Clavulanic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ampicillin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Azithromycin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefixime</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefotaxime</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.1%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefpodoxime</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ceftazidime</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cephalexin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cephazolin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ciprofloxacin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clindamycin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Doxycycline</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.8%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enrofloxacin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Erythromycin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gentamicin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lincomycin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ofloxacin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spiramycin</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sulfamethoxazole/Trimethoprim</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tetracycline</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tigecycline</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.6%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus</italic> spp.</title><p>One hundred sixty <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus</italic> spp. isolates showed sensitivity to AK (93.7%), followed by AMC (53.1%) and DA (52.4%). Of these isolates, 30 (18.7%) were potential PDR strains, and all of them were susceptible to LZD and TGC, with an average diameter of the zone of inhibition of 31.7 mm.</p></sec><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> spp.</title><p>Forty-two <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> spp. isolates showed sensitivity to AMP (17.5%), followed by AMC (16.8%). Of these isolates, 11 (26.2%) were potential PDR strains. The sensitivity of potential PDR <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecium</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecalis</italic> isolates to LZD was 83.3% (5/6) and 80.0% (4/5), respectively, and the sensitivity to TGC was 83.3% (5/6) and 100% (5/5), respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Uncommonly Encountered Species</title><p>One <italic toggle="yes">Rothia nasimurium</italic>, one <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus canis</italic>, and two potential PDR <italic toggle="yes">Corynebacterium auriscanis</italic> isolates were susceptible to LZD and TGC.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Gram-Negative Isolates</title><p>According to the tests conducted by NosVet, Inc., 105 (73.4%) of the 143 gram-negative strains showed sensitivity to AK, 68 (47.6%) were sensitive to AMC, 33 (23.1%) were sensitive to AMP, 37 (25.9%) were sensitive to AZM, 56 (39.2%) were sensitive to CFM, 61 (42.7%) were sensitive to CTX, 59 (41.3%) were sensitive to CPD, 83 (58.0%) were sensitive to CAZ, 55 (38.5%) were sensitive to CL, 49 (34.3%) were sensitive to KZ, 17 (11.9%) showed sensitivity to CIP, 4 (2.8%) were sensitive to DA, 58 (40.6%) were sensitive to DO, 64 (44.8%) were sensitive to ENR, 11 (7.7%) were sensitive to E, 79 (55.2%) were sensitive to CN, 1 (0.7%) showed sensitivity to MY, 71 (49.7%) were sensitive to OFX, 1 (0.7%) showed sensitivity to SP, 53 (37.1%) were sensitive to SXT, and 50 (35.0%) were sensitive to TE. Among these strains, 130 (90.9%) were MDR, 87 (60.8%) were XDR, and 40 (27.9%) were potential PDR bacteria (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary File 1</xref>).</p><p>Of note, 82.5% (33/40) of the potential PDR gram-negative isolates were sensitive to TGC. The average inhibition zone diameter was 18.5 mm for positive isolates, which slightly exceeded the resistance cutoff. Among Enterobacteriaceae, 100% (12/12) of the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains and 72.7% (8/11) of the <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> strains, as well as single <italic toggle="yes">Citrobacter freundii, Enterobacter aerogenes</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter cloacae</italic> complex isolates, were susceptible to TGC. The overall sensitivity to TGC was 88.5% (23/26).</p><sec><title>Escherichia coli</title><p>Fifty-two <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolates showed sensitivities of 27.3% to AK and 21.0% to CN. Of these, 12 (23.0%) were potential PDR strains, as recommended by the CLSI VET08 guidelines. The average diameter of the zone of inhibition for TGC was 18.6 mm, which fell within the susceptibility zone (&#8805;18 mm).</p></sec><sec><title>Klebsiella pneumoniae</title><p>Nineteen isolates of <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> showed &lt;10% sensitivity to the 21 antibiotics, and 11 (57.8%) were potential PDR strains, which was very high compared to that in other species. Furthermore, <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> showed the highest resistance rate (27.3%; 3/11) to TGC among the bacteria tested in this study. The inhibition zone diameters of the resistant isolates were in the range of 13&#8211;17 mm, which was within the resistance zone (&#8805;18 mm).</p></sec><sec><title>Proteus mirabilis</title><p>Among the 31 <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> isolates, 10 were classified as potential PDR strains, and only one of these (10%; 1/10) was classified as being resistant to TGC.</p></sec><sec><title>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</title><p><italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> isolates were less sensitive to the 21 antibiotics tested than those of other species. Only three of the 13 isolates were classified as potential PDR strains, and all three isolates (100%) were resistant to TGC, with an inhibition zone diameter of 0 mm.</p></sec><sec><title>Uncommonly Encountered Species</title><p>One (100%) isolate of each of the following species was susceptible to TGC: <italic toggle="yes">C. freundii, E. aerogenes, E. cloacae</italic> complex, and an unclassified species of Pasteurellaceae.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>To the best of our knowledge, no studies reported the susceptibility of <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic>, isolated from animals, to LZD and TGC; however, some reports indicated that all human <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> isolates show susceptibility to these drugs (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), consistent with our isolates from dog samples.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">S. pseudintermedius</italic>, the most common opportunistic pathogen in dogs (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), exhibits resistance to commonly used antimicrobials (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). It is the most common pathogen causing recurrent skin infections in dogs because of allergies, endocrine diseases, or other immunocompromising factors including old age and cancer (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). The possibility of <italic toggle="yes">S. pseudintermedius</italic> transmission from animals to humans was evaluated in four clinical human cases, among which two dog owners and their dogs carried identical <italic toggle="yes">S. pseudintermedius</italic> strains (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Although some strains can acquire methicillin resistance and cause severe refractory infections, even potential PDR strains are susceptible to LZD and TGC.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">R. nasimurium</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. pseudintermedius</italic> can exhibit increased pathogenicity through synergistic effects (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>); if these bacteria are potential PDR, then the associated fatality rate can significantly increase.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">E. faecalis</italic> is the most frequently encountered enterococcal species in the anus and tonsils of dogs, followed by <italic toggle="yes">E. faecium</italic> (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). These two species are considered the third and fourth most prevalent nosocomial human pathogens worldwide, respectively (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), necessitating their control in both humans and animals. Although there is scarce evidence for susceptibility testing of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> spp. in animal samples, the sensitivity of <italic toggle="yes">E. faecalis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">E. faecium</italic> isolates from human samples to LZD was 94.3 and 93.5%, respectively (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). In another study, the sensitivity of <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> spp. isolates to TGC was 100% (201/201) (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), consistent with our results.</p><p>Oxazolidinones, including LZD, are excluded from gram-negative bacteria-related infection treatment because they enhance pump activity against LZD and expel the antibiotic from the cytoplasm, resulting in lower LZD accumulation levels in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli, C. freundii</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">E. aerogenes</italic> than in <italic toggle="yes">S. aureus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">E. faecium</italic> (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>).</p><p><italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> is frequently encountered and causes severe infections in both humans and dogs (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). The possible transmission of virulent and/or resistant <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains between animals and humans through numerous pathways is highly concerning (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> represents a main reservoir of resistance genes probably responsible for treatment failure in both human and veterinary medicine (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Indeed, an increasing number of resistance genes have been identified in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> during the past decades, mostly acquired through horizontal gene transfer (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). In the enterobacterial gene pool, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> acts as a donor and recipient of resistance genes from other bacteria (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Hence, the broad-spectrum resistance of this species is quite likely, considering that most recommended antimicrobials do not effectively inhibit its growth. Therefore, TGC may broaden antimicrobial treatment choices for refractory <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> infections.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> is an important nosocomial agent that spreads easily (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) and causes community-onset infections in companion animals and humans. It is the second most common Enterobacteriaceae species causing urinary tract infections in dogs; strains are frequently MDR, posing important therapeutic limitations (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). In previous studies, 84.6% (55/60) and 87.6% (340/388) of human <italic toggle="yes">K. pneumoniae</italic> isolates showed TGC susceptibility (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Our results showed a lower susceptibility TGC rate (73.7%), indicating the stronger resistance of isolates of animal origins to TGC. The resistance gene appears to have originated from the chromosome of a <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas</italic> species and may have been transferred to plasmids by adjacent site-specific integrases. Although the gene appears to be rare in human clinical isolates, the transferability of the gene cluster and its broad-spectrum substrate make further dissemination of this mobile TGC resistance determinant possible (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). The rapid development of TGC resistance necessitates further expansion of other treatment options.</p><p>Human <italic toggle="yes">Proteus</italic> spp. and <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> isolates exhibit strong resistance to TGC. Nevertheless, we evaluated their susceptibility to TGC because strains of the same species may have different antimicrobial susceptibility profiles depending on their host of origin (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> is the epitome of an opportunistic nosocomial pathogen in humans and animals (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>), causing urinary tract infections (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) and chronic otitis externa (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) in companion animals. Moreover, <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> has low susceptibility to TGC (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Moreover, a novel TGC resistance gene, <italic toggle="yes">tet</italic>, has recently been identified in <italic toggle="yes">Proteus</italic> species isolated from animals (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Fortunately, isolates from the current study, collected over 3 years, showed sensitivity to TGC, suggesting that TGC-resistant <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis</italic> has not yet been disseminated in Korea.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> is a clinically important opportunistic pathogen causing serious acute and chronic infections (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). It is ubiquitous in the environment and can persist in water and soil despite minimal nutrients, tolerating a broad spectrum of humidity and temperature conditions (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> is one of the pathogens that most frequently acquire or develop multidrug resistance (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). The exceptional array of intrinsic and acquired drug resistance mechanisms employed by <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> renders the antibiotic-based treatment of these infections difficult. One important resistance mechanism is mediated by the resistance&#8211;nodulation&#8211;cell division family of efflux pumps (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). In one study, all (15/15) human <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> isolates were resistant to TGC (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Similarly, our results showed that TGC is not suitable for treating <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic> infections.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">C. auriscanis</italic> was first discovered in a dog with ear infection (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>) and typically acts as an opportunist in mixed infections associated with bacterial otitis externa, which can be resolved by treating and controlling other causative agents, but it may have pathological significance when occurring alone (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">C. auriscanis</italic> is often resistant to beta-lactam antibiotics; therefore, other antimicrobials may be necessary if skin lesions are not resolved after antimicrobial therapy (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>).</p><p><italic toggle="yes">S. canis</italic> is considered part of the healthy microbiota of the skin and mucosa of dogs but may be responsible for opportunistic infections. In dogs, <italic toggle="yes">S. canis</italic> is isolated from skin infections, urogenital and respiratory tract infections, otitis externa, septicemia, necrotizing fasciitis, and streptococcal toxic shock syndrome (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Only one strain was tested in this study and found to be susceptible to LZD and TGC, indicating they are possible treatment options for <italic toggle="yes">S. canis</italic> infections.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">E. aerogenes</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">E. cloacae</italic> complexes are members of the intestinal microbiota and are commonly MDR. Fortunately, both isolates were susceptible to TGC in this study, indicating the potential application of TGC for treating urinary tract infections, accounting for 38% (8/21) of animal cases, and wound infections, accounting for 19% (4/21) (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">C. freundii</italic> is intrinsically resistant to AMP, AMP/sulbactam, and cephalosporins and causes sepsis in dogs (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). A single isolate of this species was tested in this study and was susceptible to TGC; therefore, this antibiotic may be considered for treating <italic toggle="yes">C. freundii</italic> infections.</p><p>This study has several limitations. First, for certain bacteria (e.g., <italic toggle="yes">C. auriscanis</italic>, Pasteurellaceae, <italic toggle="yes">P. mirabilis, P. aeruginosa</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">R. nasimurium</italic>), there are no susceptibility or resistance criteria. Second, many countries prohibit LZD and TGC use in animal settings to preserve treatment options for human infections. However, these agents may be employed in the future under well-organized antimicrobial stewardship frameworks and policies, and our results provide foundational knowledge for using LZD and TGC in veterinary medicine.</p><p>In conclusion, we evaluated the efficacies of TGC and LZD against potential PDR bacteria that are frequently isolated from companion dogs, and the results showed resistance of the organisms to all other antimicrobial classes recommended by the veterinary CLSI guidelines. Both agents showed favorable efficacy, with susceptibility rates of all potential PDR bacteria, except <italic toggle="yes">P. aeruginosa</italic>, ranging from 72.7 to 100%. Thus, TGC and LZD may serve as promising antimicrobial options for veterinary medicine in the future. For application in patients, <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> pharmacokinetic and pharmacological studies are needed. To avoid exacerbating bacterial antibiotic resistance, legal regulations for TGC and LZD are needed to prevent their misuse.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s5"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s9">Supplementary Material</xref>, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author/s.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (KU20218). Written informed consent was obtained from the owners for the participation of their animals in this study.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>D-HK and J-HK conceptualized and designed the study, analyzed the data, drafted and edited the manuscript, and approved the final submission. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s8"><title>Publisher's Note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work was supported by Korea Institute of Planning and Evaluation for Technology in Food, Agriculture and Forestry (IPET) through (Development of technology for immunomodulatory ability of useful exosomes derived from stem cells for companion animal) Project, funded by Ministry of Agriculture, Food and Rural Affairs (MAFRA)(321013-01).</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s9"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2021.693506/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2021.693506/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.XLSX" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_2.pdf" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Reservoirs of antimicrobial resistance in pet animals</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>S148</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/519254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17683019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fury</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giffard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maiwald</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Carriage of methicillin-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> by veterinarians in Australia</article-title>. <source>Aust Vet J.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>152</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1751-0813.2011.00710.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21495985</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turnidge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trott</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Carbapenemase-producing bacteria in companion animals: a public health concern on the horizon</article-title>. <source>J Antimicrob Chemother.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>1155</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkt518</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24398342</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Normand</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carmichael</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial-resistance trends in bacterial isolates from companion-animal community practice in the UK</article-title>. <source>Prev Vet Med.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>267</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>78</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0167-5877(00)00149-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10960713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shinabarger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanism of action of the oxazolidinone antibacterial agents</article-title>. <source>Expert Opin Investig Drugs.</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1195</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>202</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1517/13543784.8.8.1195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15992144</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Slatter</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bush</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiba</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daley-Yates</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feenstra</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pharmacokinetics, toxicokinetics, distribution, metabolism and excretion of linezolid in mouse, rat and dog</article-title>. <source>Xenobiotica.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>907</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00498250210158249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12419019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seixas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilela</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>First report of a linezolid-resistant MRSA (methicillin resistant <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic>) isolated from a dog with a severe bilateral otitis in Portugal</article-title>. <source>Rev Vet.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.30972/vet.2221826</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Usui</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsuyuki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shiraishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Tigecycline susceptibility of <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> complex and <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> isolates from companion animals: the prevalence of tigecycline-nonsusceptible <italic toggle="yes">K.pneumoniae</italic> complex, including internationally expanding human pathogenic lineages.</article-title><source>Microb Drug Resist.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>860</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/mdr.2017.0184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29232167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meagher</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Passarell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cirincione</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Wart</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liolios</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Babinchak</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Exposure&#8211;response analyses of tigecycline efficacy in patients with complicated skin and skin-structure infections</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>1939</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.01084-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17353238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1891381</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoban</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reinert</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchillon</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dowzicky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Global in vitro activity of tigecycline and comparator agents: Tigecycline evaluation and surveillance trial 2004&#8211;2013</article-title>. <source>Ann Clin Microbiol Antimicrob.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>27</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12941-015-0085-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25958201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4489028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Falagas</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karageorgopoulos</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pandrug resistance (PDR), extensive drug resistance (XDR), and multidrug resistance (MDR) among gram-negative bacilli: need for international harmonization in terminology</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>1121</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/528867</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18444833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ballow</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biedenbach</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Multi-laboratory assessment of the linezolid spectrum of activity using the Kirby-Bauer disk diffusion method: report of the Zyvox&#174; Antimicrobial Potency Study (ZAPS) in the United States</article-title>. <source>Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>59</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0732-8893(01)00235-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11448565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sorl&#243;zano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guti&#233;rrez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salmer&#243;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luna</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;nez-Checa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rom&#225;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Activity of tigecycline against clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and extended-spectrum &#946;-lactamase-producing <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> in Granada, Spain</article-title>. <source>Int J Antimicrob Agents.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>532</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2006.07.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17045785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bannoehr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guardabassi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus pseudintermedius</italic> in the dog: taxonomy, diagnostics, ecology, epidemiology and pathogenicity</article-title>. <source>Vet Dermatol.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>253</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage>.e51. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3164.2012.01046.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22515504</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pinchbeck</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kowalski</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajala-Schultz</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bannerman</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genotypic relatedness of staphylococcal strains isolated from pustules and carriage sites in dogs with superficial bacterial folliculitis</article-title>. <source>Am J Vet Res.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>1337</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/ajvr.67.8.1337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16881845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lozano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezusta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>P&#233;rez-Laguna</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zarazaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruiz-Ripa</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus pseudintermedius</italic> human infection cases in Spain: dog-to-human transmission</article-title>. <source>Vector Borne Zoonotic Dis.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>268</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/vbz.2016.2048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28075235</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bemis</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brahmbhatt</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kania</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Synergistic hemolysis between &#946;-lysin-producing <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus</italic> species and <italic toggle="yes">Rothia nasimurium</italic> in primary cultures of clinical specimens obtained from dogs</article-title>. <source>J Vet Diagn Invest.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>437</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1040638714532098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24760132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC)</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Annual epidemiological report on communicable diseases in Europe</article-title>. <source>Euro Surveill.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>20012</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2900/14803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22114980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#225;ndez Canigia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanata</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giovanakis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bantar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Multicenter study to assess the in vitro activity of tigecycline by disk diffusion test against clinical isolates from Argentina</article-title>. <source>Chemotherapy.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>20</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000167788</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18974645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trittler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohnert</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>K&#252;mmerer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pag&#232;s</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>WV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Intracellular accumulation of linezolid in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli, Citrobacter freundii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter aerogenes</italic>: role of enhanced efflux pump activity and inactivation</article-title>. <source>J Antimicrob Chemother.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>1261</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkl380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16971414</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaper</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nataro</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mobley</surname><given-names>HLT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15040260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaster</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuskowski</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of urovirulence traits in <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> by comparison of urinary and rectal <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> isolates from dogs with urinary tract infection</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>337</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.41.1.337-345.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12517870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC149618</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Piras</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soggiu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Greco</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martino</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Chierico</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Putignani</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanisms of antibiotic resistance to enrofloxacin in uropathogenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> in dog</article-title>. <source>J Proteomics.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>127</volume>:<fpage>365</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jprot.2015.05.040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26066767</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scaria</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Antibiotic-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> and sequence type 131 in fecal colonization in dogs in Taiwan</article-title>. <source>Microorganisms.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1439</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms8091439</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32962221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7565575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brisse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Passet</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular epidemiology of colonizing and infecting isolates of <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic></article-title>. <source>mSphere</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>e00261</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSphere.00261-16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27777984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5071533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aboim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gama</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pomba</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Increase in antimicrobial resistance and emergence of major international high-risk clonal lineages in dogs and cats with urinary tract infection: 16 year retrospective study</article-title>. <source>J Antimicrob Chemother.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>73</volume>:<fpage>377</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkx401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29136156</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5890753</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aboim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavaco-Silva</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trigueiro</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gama</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evidence of sharing of <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic> strains between healthy companion animals and cohabiting humans</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>e01537</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.01537-18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30944193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6535590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Samonis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maraki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karageorgopoulos</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vouloumanou</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falagas</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Synergy of fosfomycin with carbapenems, colistin, netilmicin, and tigecycline against multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae, Escherichia coli</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> clinical isolates</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>695</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>701</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10096-011-1360-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21805292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Emergence of a plasmid-encoded resistance-nodulation-division efflux pump conferring resistance to multiple drugs, including tigecycline, in <italic toggle="yes">Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic></article-title>. <source>mBio</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.02930-19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32127452</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7064769</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>European Food and Safety Authority (EFSA)</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Guidance on the assessment of bacterial susceptibility to antimicrobials of human and veterinary importance</article-title>. <source>EFSA J.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>2740</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2903/j.esfa.2012.2740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuwajima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phenotypic and molecular characterization of antimicrobial resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Proteus mirabilis</italic> isolates from dogs</article-title>. <source>J Med Microbiol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>1561</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.081539-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25187600</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bubenik</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosgood</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waldron</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Frequency of urinary tract infection in catheterized dogs and comparison of bacterial culture and susceptibility testing results for catheterized and noncatheterized dogs with urinary tract infections</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>231</volume>:<fpage>893</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/javma.231.6.893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17867973</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zamankhan Malayeri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jamshidi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zahraei Salehi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification and antimicrobial susceptibility patterns of bacteria causing otitis externa in dogs</article-title>. <source>Vet Res Commun.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>435</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11259-010-9417-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20526674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Visalli</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Projan</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>AcrAB multidrug efflux pump is associated with reduced levels of susceptibility to tigecycline (GAR-936) in <italic toggle="yes">Proteus mirabilis</italic></article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>. (<year>2003</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>665</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.47.2.665-669.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12543675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC151746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of the novel tigecycline resistance gene <italic toggle="yes">tet</italic>(x6) and its variants in <italic toggle="yes">Myroides, Acinetobacter</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Proteus</italic> of food animal origin</article-title>. <source>J Antimicrob Chemother.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>75</volume>:<fpage>1428</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkaa037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32068864</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>L&#243;pez-de-la-Cruz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>P&#233;rez-Aranda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alcudia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Begines</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caraballo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pajuelo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dynamics and numerical simulations to predict empirical antibiotic treatment of multi-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>Commun Nonlinear Sci Numer Simul.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>91</volume>:<fpage>105418</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cnsns.2020.105418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paz-Zarza</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mangwani-Mordani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#237;nez-Maldonado</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#193;lvarez-Hern&#225;ndez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solano-G&#225;lvez</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>V&#225;zquez-L&#243;pez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>: pathogenicity and antimicrobial resistance in urinary tract infection</article-title>. <source>Rev Chilena Infectol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>180</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4067/S0716-10182019000200180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31344154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Visalli</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Projan</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sum</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Efflux-mediated resistance to tigecycline (GAR-936) in <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> PAO1</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>972</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.47.3.972-978.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12604529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC149306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoyles</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Falsen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robson</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Phenotypic and phylogenetic characterization of a new <italic toggle="yes">Corynebacterium</italic> species from dogs: description of <italic toggle="yes">Corynebacterium auriscanis</italic> sp. nov</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol.</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>3443</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.37.11.3443-3447.1999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10523531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC85662</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henneveld</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosychuk</surname><given-names>RAW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olea-Popelka</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyatt</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zabel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Corynebacterium</italic> spp. in dogs and cats with otitis externa and/or media: a retrospective study</article-title>. <source>J Am Anim Hosp Assoc.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>320</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5326/JAAHA-MS-5791</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22843832</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boynosky</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stokking</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Retrospective evaluation of canine dermatitis secondary to <italic toggle="yes">Corynebacterium</italic> spp</article-title>. <source>J Am Anim Hosp Assoc.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>372</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5326/JAAHA-MS-6243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26535455</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weese</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Investigation of <italic toggle="yes">Enterobacter cloacae</italic> infections at a small animal veterinary teaching hospital</article-title>. <source>Vet Microbiol.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>130</volume>:<fpage>426</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2008.02.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18374521</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wanger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chavez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>RSP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Actor</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Microbiology and Molecular Diagnosis in Pathology: A Comprehensive Review for Board Preparation, Certification and Clinical Practice, Microbiology and Molecular Diagnosis in Pathology</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name> (<year>2017</year>). <volume>96</volume> p.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Galarneau</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fortin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lapointe</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Citrobacter freundii</italic> septicemia in two dogs</article-title>. <source>J Vet Diagn Invest.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/104063870301500316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12735357</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>