<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8964599</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8964599.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8964599</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8964599</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35372542</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.840724</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Comparison of the Evaluation of Combination of Ultrasonography of the Reproductive Tract With Hormone Administration on Dairy Cow Fertility</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="B">Bingke</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names initials="J">Jinbang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1393882/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yongjie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names initials="C">Chuxi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="H">Hanbing</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yonghong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yaping</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c002" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/314417/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names initials="P">Pengfei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/314338/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>College of Veterinary Medicine, Northwest A&amp;F University</institution>, <addr-line>Yangling</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Key Laboratory of Animal Biotechnology, Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs, Northwest A&amp;F University</institution>, <addr-line>Yangling</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Yangling Nongfu Agriculture and Animal Husbandry Technology Co., Ltd.</institution>, <addr-line>Yangling</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Animal Husbandry Industry Test and Demonstration Center of Shaanxi Province</institution>, <addr-line>Xianyang</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Kangfeng Jiang, Yunnan Agricultural University, China</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Christian Hanzen, University of Li&#232;ge, Belgium; Asghar Mogheiseh, Shiraz University, Iran</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Pengfei Lin <email>linpengfei@nwsuaf.edu.cn</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Yaping Jin <email>yapingjin@163.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Animal Reproduction - Theriogenology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn002"><p>&#8224;These authors have contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>3</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">400313</issue-id><elocation-id>840724</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>31</day><month>03</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2022-04-04 16:16:44.330"><day>04</day><month>04</month><year>2022</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2022 Wang, Xiao, Ma, Gao, Li, Jia, Jin and Lin.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wang, Xiao, Ma, Gao, Li, Jia, Jin and Lin</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-09-840724.pdf"/><abstract><p>Further optimization of reproduction management programs in dairy cows is a contemporary research topic. In this context, our study aimed to compare a hormone program, named &#8220;uterus-ovary monitoring and classified use of hormone program&#8221; (M+C), with the Pre-OvSynch program. The M+C was based on regular application of B-mode ultrasonography during a voluntary waiting period to monitor the uterus and ovaries, while using various treatments under different conditions. Results of the 30&#8211;33-day and 60-day pregnancy/artificial insemination after the first AI of M+C were significantly better than the Pre-OvSynch (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). The pregnancy rates within 180 days in milk after M+C was significantly higher than that after Pre-OvSynch (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). The total number of inseminations used for M+C was significantly lower than that for Pre-OvSynch (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01). The number of open days was fewer after M+C than after the Pre&#8211;OvSynch throughout the experimental period with highly significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01). In summary, the use of M+C enhances reproductive benefits and reduces the need for hormone drugs among cows.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>reproduction program</kwd><kwd>ultrasonography</kwd><kwd>endometritis</kwd><kwd>hormone</kwd><kwd>dairy cow</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="6"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="39"/><page-count count="7"/><word-count count="5418"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Fertility in dairy cows is a major factor affecting the stable growth of core cattle herds and a sustained increase in milk production. It also has direct effects on the economic benefits of dairy farms (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Improving cow fertility remains a highly researched issue worldwide as fertility is closely related to many factors, including nutrition (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), genetics (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), environment (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), disease (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), and stress (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>), as well as to the implementation and optimization of the relevant reproduction programs.</p><p>Since its development, the synchronization of ovulation (OvSynch) and timed artificial insemination (TAI) program (OvSynch+TAI) has significantly reduced the time of the waiting period and the workload of reproductive workers. The Pre-OvSynch, Double-OvSynch, and ReSynch programs (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>), all of which are based on the OvSynch program, have been optimized for large-scale batch production management. Nevertheless, some OvSynch+TAI programs have demonstrated practical problems such as long handling time and the number of handlings, usage of hormones, high drug costs, and lack of screening for uterine and ovarian subclinical diseases before beginning the OvSynch protocol.</p><p>Endometritis, mainly due to bacterial infection, and ovarian dysfunction, caused by endocrine disorders, is the main reason for low postpartum reproductive function and delayed recovery (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). These conditions severely affect the outcome of OvSynch+TAI and reduce reproductive capability. In addition to synchronization programs, hormone drugs can also be used to treat reproductive disorders (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>); for example, gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) is used to treat ovarian dysfunction caused by ovarian cysts and postpartum anestrus (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Moreover, prostaglandin F2&#945; (PGF2&#945;), which initiates luteolysis, can be used to treat corpus luteum cysts, and promotes tissue debris excretion and inflammatory secretion from the uterus, thus preventing and resolving endometritis (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Nevertheless, a recent meta-analysis on the effect of PGF2&#945; in cows undergoing endometritis treatment reported that PGF2&#945; cannot be recommended to treat cows to improve their reproductive performance (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p><p>Hormone drugs should be used with caution in clinical practice. The causes of reproductive disorders are complicated, and hormone treatment alone does not show optimal curative results. Moreover, the wide use of hormones also results in economic waste. Although the side effects of hormone drugs have long been taken seriously in clinical medicine (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), relevant research in cattle remains insufficient. In dairy farms, the use of routine monitoring and disease detection has been widely applied for effective disease detection and early intervention. Ultrasonography provides unique advantages for examining organ status. With further development, ultrasonography could be accurately and conveniently used to monitor the status of both the uterus (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) and the ovaries (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), making it a practical and effective method for diagnosing endometritis and ovarian diseases (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Thus, the development and promotion of ultrasonography for disease monitoring demonstrate high potential (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p><p>Therefore, in this study, in order to effectively diagnose and treat endometritis, reduce the use of hormones, improve the reaction of dairy cows to the OvSynch program before AI, and optimize reproductive efficiency comprehensively, we develop and evaluate a precise hormone program, named the &#8220;uterus-ovary monitoring and classified use of hormone program&#8221; (M+C), based on regular application of B-mode ultrasonography during a voluntary waiting period to monitor the uterus and ovaries.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Cows and Dairy Farm</title><p>This experiment was conducted at a commercial dairy farm in Northwest of China, from June to August 2020. At the time of the experiment, this farm had 3,826 Holstein cows, of which 1,708 were lactating; their average parity number was 2.65, and average annual milk yield was 9,134 kg. All cows were fed a TMR three times a day and managed using the herd management system &#8220;Aladdin&#8221; (Beijing HemuXingbang Network Technology Co., LTD., China). The hardware facilities, diet formulation, staff, and herd structure remained consistent during the experimental period. Within 60 days after delivery in this farm during the whole experiment period, incidence of lameness, ketosis, placental retention, metritis, and milk fever were 5.1, 12.3, 1.9, 2.4, and 4.2%, respectively. After calving, postpartum cows with different parity were randomly divided into two groups, M+C group and Pre-OvSynch group, respectively, and the voluntary waiting period was 60 days for both. Finally, the cows that received the complete M+C (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 262) or Pre-OvSynch (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 264) program were included in subsequent statistical analysis. All animal handling procedures were approved by the Committee for the Ethics on Animal Care and Experiments at Northwest A&amp;F University.</p></sec><sec><title>M+C and Pre-OvSynch Program</title><p>In the M+C program, each cow underwent three regular reproductive organ inspections using B-mode ultrasonography (British BCF, model Easi-scan3) by an experienced technician before artificial insemination (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). The three examinations were performed at 20&#8211;34, 34&#8211;48, and 48&#8211;62 days in milk (DIM). Subsequently, different treatment protocols were adopted for cows depending on the ovarian cycle phase as examined by B-mode ultrasonography. If there was a mature corpus luteum in the ovary, a OvSynch+TAI protocol was chosen; GnRH (100 &#956;g/stem; Ningbo Sansheng Pharmaceutical, China) was injected first (Day 0), followed by an injection of PGF2&#945; (25 mg/pc, Ningbo Sansheng Pharmaceutical, China) on Day 7, and another GnRH injection on Day 9. If there was a mature follicle in the ovary (follicular phase), a pre-injection of GnRH was given, followed after 7 days by a complete OvSynch+TAI protocol as above. The typical ultrasound imaging findings of the mature corpus luteum were given as uniform gray image of regular boundary with 2&#8211;3 cm long and 1.5&#8211;2.5 cm wide. Mature follicles range from 1.5 to 2.0 cm in diameter (long axis).</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Schematic diagram of the M+C program. Each cow underwent three regular reproductive organ inspections before insemination. The first inspection was performed at 20&#8211;34 days in milk (DIM). B-mode ultrasonography was used to examine the uterus and ovary transrectally and to take appropriate measurements under different conditions. After 14 and 28 days, the same examination and treatment were performed again. At 20&#8211;34, 34&#8211;48, and 48&#8211;62 DIM, the images for cow uterus size and abnormal fluid in uterus cavity were classified into four grades: normal and endometritis level I to III; Chinese medicine was used to treat cows with endometritis, and antibiotics were used to treat cows with endometritis level II or III. If a cow was diagnosed with endometritis during examination and treated, we waited 14 days until the next examination for diagnosis. In all cows with endometritis, TAI was performed only after endometritis was resolved. Then, if DIM was &gt;55 at this time, different treatment protocols were adopted for cows without abnormalities depending on their ovary phase. If the corpus luteum was mature with a still developing ovarian follicle in the cow ovary (i.e., the luteal phase), then we applied OvSynch+TAI; if the cow ovary had a mature ovarian follicle (i.e., the follicular phase), GnRH was used first, followed by OvSynch+TAI after 7 days.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-840724-g0001.jpg"/></fig><p>In the Pre-OvSynch program, no ultrasonography took place but cows were treated with 25 mg of PGF2&#945; at 14&#8211;21 DIM, followed by two 25-mg treatments of PGF2&#945; at 14-day intervals, followed after 11 days by a complete OvSynch+TAI protocol.</p><p>Cows were scheduled to receive TAI ~16 h after the last GnRH treatment of the M+C and Pre-OvSynch protocols. The artificial insemination personnel were randomly assigned to three artificial insemination technicians on the dairy farm. The first pregnancy diagnosis through B-mode ultrasonography was performed by experienced veterinarians 30&#8211;33 days after TAI to observe signs of pregnancy. The second pregnancy diagnosis was performed 60 days after TAI to determine pregnancy loss. Cows that were not pregnant repeatedly underwent ultrasonographic examination of the ovary in M+C (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>), or perform the OvSynch+TAI program in the Pre-OvSynch group.</p></sec><sec><title>B-Mode Ultrasonography for Diagnosis of Endometritis Followed by Classification and Treatment</title><p>In this study, uterus size and abnormal uterine fluids at 20&#8211;34, 34&#8211;48, and 48&#8211;62 DIM were examined using B-mode ultrasonography (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), and then classified into four grades based on endometritis occurrence and severity:</p><p>1. No endometritis (Normal, Grade 0): No abnormal findings were noted in the uterus (no fluid or echo-free); the cervical diameter was &lt;7.5 cm, and no abnormalities were noted on clinical examination.</p><p>2. Endometritis grade I: A small amount of abnormal fluid (discontinuous hyperechogenic, thin &lt;1 mm) was detected in the uterus.</p><p>3. Endometritis grade II: A considerable amount of abnormal fluid (continuous hyperechogenic, thin &#8805;1 mm) was detected in the uterus.</p><p>4. Endometritis grade III: A considerable amount of abnormal fluid was detected in the uterus, accompanied by purulent fluid accumulation with some fluctuation (large amount of storage material that looked like a snowstorm).</p><p>Clinical examination of the cow tail, perineum, and vulva for purulent secretion in the uterus was also performed. If uterine purulent secretion was detected, the cows were directly classified with endometritis grade III.</p><p>For cows with endometritis grade I, Gongyankang (commercial Chinese medicine pills, with active ingredients including <italic toggle="yes">Epimedium, Actinolite, Angelica sinensis, Cyperus rotundus, Leonurus japonicus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Sophora flavescens</italic>; 10 capsules/bottle; Jilida, Jilin, China) were administered by uterine infusion. Cows with endometritis grade II or III were given antibiotics (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) (10% oxytetracycline uterine injectant; Eastern Along Pharmaceutical Co., LTD; China). If cows were diagnosed with endometritis, they would receive a course of treatment, and then receive B-mode ultrasonography diagnose on the next examination (14 days later) to determine therapeutic effect. Endometritis was considered completely cured when B-mode ultrasonography and clinical examination were at normal grades. For all cows with endometritis, TAI was only performed when endometritis was cured. The number of cows diagnosed as returning to grade 0 before AI expressed as a percentage of the total number of cows diagnosed with endometritis.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>All data are presented as the means &#177; standard error of the mean (SEM) and analyzed using SPSS (version 24.0). Logistic regression was used to analyze the pregnancy rates at 30&#8211;33 and 60 days after the first AI. Survival analysis with right censoring was used to analyze pregnancy rates within 180 DIM. The chi-square test was used to analyze the incidence and rate of endometritis. One-way analysis of variance was used to analyze the number of frozen semen straws, the cost of drugs, hormones, and frozen semen. Differences were considered significant when <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Effects of M+C and Pre&#8211;OvSynch Program on P/AI After First AI of Post-partum Cows</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, no significant difference in parity was observed between the two programs (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05). The 30&#8211;33 and 60-day P/AI of M+C were significantly higher than those of Pre-OvSynch (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). In addition, the pregnancy loss was not significantly different between the two programs (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05). The above results indicated that M+C might significantly improve P/AI after the first AI of postpartum cows.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The parity, 30&#8211;33-day P/AI, 60-day P/AI after first AI, and pregnancy loss of postpartum cows treated with the M+C and Pre-OvSynch program.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Item (%, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>M+C</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Pre-OvSynch</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parity (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47 &#177; 1.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.49 &#177; 1.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.817</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30&#8211;33-day P/AI (%, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.3 (137/262)<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.7 (110/264)<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60-day P/AI (%, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.3 (124/262)<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.7 (97/264)<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pregnancy loss (%, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5 (13/137)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8 (13/110)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.594</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">The data of the M+C and Pre-OvSynch programs in the table include cows with and without endometritis. Different superscripts between columns indicate significant difference (p &lt; 0.05)</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Pregnancy Rates Within 180 DIM, Number of Frozen Semen, and Cow Open Days With M+C and Pre&#8211;OvSynch Program</title><p>The pregnancy rates within 180 DIM after M+C was significantly higher than that after the Pre&#8211;OvSynch program (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). The total number of frozen semen used for M+C was significantly lower than that of Pre&#8211;OvSynch (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Meanwhile, the number of open days was significantly lower in M+C than in Pre&#8211;OvSynch (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). These results suggest that the application of M+C could significantly reduce the number of frozen semen straws and the number of open days.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The pregnancy rates within 180 DIM, number of frozen semen, and cow open days of the M+C and Pre&#8211;OvSynch program.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Item</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>M+C</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Pre-OvSynch</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pregnancy rates within 180 DIM (%, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.4 (242/262)<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.4 (236/264)<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frozen semen straws (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.95 &#177; 1.25<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.32 &#177; 1.34<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Open days (days)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.89 &#177; 34.43<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.83 &#177; 37.89<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">The data of the M+C and Pre-OvSynch programs in the table include cows with and without endometritis. Different superscripts between columns indicate significant difference (p &lt; 0.05)</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Ultrasonography-Based Diagnosis of Endometritis and Ovaries in M+C Program</title><p>Ultrasonography for the diagnosis of endometritis in M+C was performed at 20&#8211;34, 34&#8211;48, and 48&#8211;62 days, respectively (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Approximately 15% of cows were diagnosed with endometritis of grade I at 20&#8211;34 days postpartum, whereas the diagnostic rates gradually declined at 34&#8211;48 (about 7%) and 48&#8211;62 days (about 3%), respectively. Meanwhile, the total diagnostic rates of endometritis in grades II and III at 20&#8211;34 days postpartum were 6.5% and 6.1%, respectively, and the diagnostic rates also gradually declined at 34&#8211;48 and 48&#8211;62 days.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Ultrasonography-based diagnosis of endometritis in the M+C program.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>DIM (d)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Grade 0 (%)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Grade I (%)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Grade II (%)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Grade III (%)</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#8211;34</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34&#8211;48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48&#8211;62</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>To evaluate the effect of treatment of cases with different grades of endometritis, the cure rate and 60-day P/AI after the first AI of cows were analyzed (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). As the endometritis grade increased, the cure rate and 60-day P/AI after the first AI decreased; the cure rate for endometritis grade I was significantly higher than that for endometritis grade III (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). However, no significant differences were detected in 60-day P/AI after the first AI among the three endometritis grades (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Cure rate and 60-day P/AI after the first AI of cow with endometritis in the M+C program.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Grade</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Number<xref rid="TN1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>1</sup></xref></bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Cure rate<xref rid="TN2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>2</sup></xref></bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>60-day P/AI</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (Normal)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.6%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.0%<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.8%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.6%<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.9%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.5%<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><label>1</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Number = The total number of cows with the first diagnosis at this grade on three inspection days</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN2"><label>2</label><p><italic toggle="yes">Cure rate = Number of cows diagnosed as normal before AI/Total number of cows diagnosed with endometritis. Different superscripts between columns indicate significant difference, p &lt; 0.05</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The percentages of corpus luteum and ovarian follicles in the ovary at the first implementation of the OvSynch program in M+C were 82.4 and 17.6%, respectively, with those of 60-day P/AI after the first AI being 44.9 and 58.7%, respectively (<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Ultrasonography-based diagnosis of ovaries at the first implementation of the OvSynch program and 60-day P/AI after the first AI in M+C program.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Ovarian cycle</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Number of cows</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Proportion</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>60-day P/AI</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corpus luteum</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.4%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.9%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ovarian follicle</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.7%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">The data of the M+C and Pre-OvSynch programs in the table include cows with and without endometritis</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Cost of Drugs, Hormone, and Frozen Semen in M+C vs. Pre&#8211;OvSynch in 180 Days</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="T6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>, in addition to the extra drug cost in M+C, the average cost of hormone and frozen semen was significantly lower in M+C than in Pre-OvSynch (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Cost of drugs, hormone, and frozen semen in M+C and Pre&#8211;OvSynch program during 180 DIM.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Item</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>M+C</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Pre-OvSynch</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cost of drugs (USD/CNY)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77 &#177; 2.19/12.13 &#177; 15.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 &#177; 0.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cost of hormone (USD/CNY)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.50 &#177; 6.75/85.73 &#177; 46.29<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.24 &#177; 7.06/173.14 &#177; 48.45<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cost of frozen semen (USD/CNY)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.95 &#177; 6.59/68.27 &#177; 45.18<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.00 &#177; 7.22/82.30 &#177; 49.55<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">Different superscripts between columns indicate significant difference, p &lt; 0.05</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Increased pregnancy rate, reduced number of frozen semen straws used, and shortened number of open days are ideal attributes for dairy farms. At the same time, reducing the workload of reproductive workers in farms is also essential. Accordingly, the development and application of OvSynch+TAI has achieved remarkable results (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Further optimization of synchronization programs has been a dynamic topic of research, mainly focusing on increasing hormonal management of reproduction (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>), evaluating pregnancy diagnosis time (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>), using novel drugs (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>), enhancing estrus and hormone monitoring (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>), and monitoring the ovary cycle (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). It is well-known that the OvSynch program provides the best results when it is started at day 5&#8211;9 of the estrous cycle, and the Pre-OvSynch program was developed for this purpose, but increasing hormone use. Nevertheless, increased hormone dosage and frequency may reduce personnel working enthusiasm and potentially lead to negative effects. For example, Pre-OvSynch may increase the proportion of male calves (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p><p>Funakura et al. (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>) reported that using a portable ultrasound device to objectively evaluate the presence or absence of a functional corpus luteum could achieve a higher pregnancy rate than the conventional AI method based on estrus detection after administration of PGF alone in beef herds. Silva et al. (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) also concluded that assessing the corpus luteum functionality of Holstein cows using ultrasound at the first GnRH injection of Pre-OvSynch protocol could resolve the anovular condition before TAI and thus improve reproductive performance. In addition, using the synchronization program based on functionality of the corpus luteum as determined by ultrasonography may be a viable alternative to OvSynch, with an additional benefit of having lower costs (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Similarly, in the current study, before performing the synchronization programs, we first examined the ovaries using B-mode ultrasonography. If a corpus luteum with a developing dominant follicle was noted on days 5&#8211;12 of the estrus cycle, the cow was considered to have high sensitivity to GnRH, and the OvSynch+TAI procedure was performed directly. If mature follicles were present, GnRH was used first to promote follicular expulsion and formation of a new corpus luteum, followed by the OvSynch program 7 days later to induce a new follicular cycle and ovulation. The results showed that compared with the Pre&#8211;OvSynch, M+C significantly increased the P/AI of cows, reduced the number of frozen semen straws required, shortened the number of open days, and reduced the usage of hormone drugs.</p><p>The incidence of endometritis, which affects the internal environment of the uterus and destroys normal ovary function, resulting in reduced postpartum fertility in cows, can reach up to 40% (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Endometritis can be divided into clinical and subclinical types, with the former demonstrating typical clinical signs (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), while the latter usually requires endometrial cytology, biopsy, and leukocyte esterase testing to confirm the diagnosis (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>), all of which are difficult to implement in dairy farms. Currently, endometritis is usually diagnosed after 21 DIM once in farms (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>); however, because ultrasonography inspection can be susceptible to the probe position and orientation and the uterine state of cows (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>), it cannot be effectively used for diagnosing subclinical cases where no secretions are observed in the uterus (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Hence, selecting multiple time points for checking can help improve sensitivity. PGF2&#945; and intrauterine infusion of antibiotics are commonly used for endometritis treatment, but their effectiveness remains controversial (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>); however, the use of some herbal extracts has been investigated in the treatment of endometritis because they have antibacterial and anti-inflammatory characteristics, cause less irritability, and do not require milk to be discarded (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Based on the above reasons, in the current study, the M+C program referred and optimized the diagnosis method of endometritis used by Lenz et al. (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) and Kasimanickam et al. (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). The results showed a high incidence of endometritis at all grades in this trial within 20&#8211;34 days postpartum, with an overall diagnostic rate of 26.3%. The cure rate for endometritis grade I was significantly higher than that for endometritis grade II and III, and may be due to <italic toggle="yes">L. japonicus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">S. flavescens</italic> as the main ingredients of Gongyankang have been reported to have a beneficial anti-inflammatory effect on endometritis (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). However, our outcome for endometritis II and III treatment is still not ideal, and follow-up studies focusing on improving the treatment of severe endometritis are warranted. The M+C exhibits two advantages: first, endometritis cases were detected in a timely and effective manner through three regular examinations of the uterus before insemination. The effect of the treatment could be assessed on the next examination day, ensuring that the internal environment of the uterus is improved as much as possible before ovulation synchronization is performed. Second, cows categorized as having either mild or severe endometritis could be treated more specifically using different drugs, thus avoiding large-scale, blind use of hormone drugs, reducing drug costs, and achieving satisfactory results.</p><p>The measurement of economic benefits is an important part of evaluating the effectiveness of any program. In the evaluation of the optimized OvSynch+TAI program, the measurement of economic benefits usually requires a large amount of data and mathematical modeling, and based on preliminary analyses, compared with the Pre&#8211;OvSynch, M+C could reduce the amount of hormone drugs and frozen semen used; however, the costs of treatment drugs and B-mode ultrasonography were increased. In the future, we aim to continually improve and promote M+C and collect data to completely evaluate the cost of the different echographic examinations and the required time to make such examinations.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The advantages of using M+C include effective endometritis detection, classification, and treatment and precise hormone administration according to the ovary cycle. These enhance reproductive benefits and reduce the need for hormone drugs in cows. Thus, M+C is convenient and feasible with value for promotion and application.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/supplementary material, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author/s.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by Committee for the Ethics on Animal Care and Experiments in Northwest A&amp;F University (Approval ID: 2011ZX08008-002). Written informed consent was obtained from the owners for the participation of their animals in this study.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>BW, YJin, and PL: conceptualization and resources. BW: methodology. JX and YM: software. CG, YJia, and HL: validation. JX: formal analysis. BW and JX: investigation. JX and PL: writing&#8212;original draft preparation. BW, JX, YM, CG, HL, YJia, YJin, and PL: writing&#8212;review and editing. YJin and PL: supervision. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="s9"><title>Funding</title><p>This research was funded by the Key Research and Development (R&amp;D) program in Ningxia Hui Autonomous Region (2021BBF02037; 2018BBF33001) and the Science and Technology Innovation Project of Shaanxi Province.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>BW was employed by Yangling Nongfu Agriculture and Animal Husbandry Technology Co., Ltd. The remaining authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s10"><title>Publisher's Note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rutten</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steeneveld</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Inchaisri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogeveen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An ex ante analysis on the use of activity meters for automated estrus detection: to invest or not to invest?</article-title><source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>6869</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>87</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2014-7948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25242421</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodney</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Celi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breinhild</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lean</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of nutrition on the fertility of lactating dairy cattle</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>5115</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2017-14064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29605330</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucy</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Symposium review: selection for fertility in the modern dairy cow-current status and future direction for genetic selection</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>3706</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2018-15544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30692008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stachowicz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genotype by environment interactions in fertility traits in New Zealand dairy cows</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>10991</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1003</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2017-14195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30243634</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaters</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rushton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dulu</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of foot-and-mouth disease on fertility performance in a large dairy herd in Kenya</article-title>. <source>Prev Vet Med.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>2018</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.prevetmed.2018.08.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30314791</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6193135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gernand</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Konig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kipp</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of on-farm measurements for heat stress indicators on dairy cow productivity, female fertility, and health</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>6660</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2018-16011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31128870</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyabinwa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kashongwe</surname><given-names>OB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirwa</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bebe</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of endometritis on reproductive performance of zero-grazed dairy cows on smallholder farms in Rwanda</article-title>. <source>Anim Reprod Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>2020</volume>:<fpage>106584</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anireprosci.2020.106584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32889409</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dahiya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Onteru</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Postpartum uterine infection &amp; ovarian dysfunction</article-title>. <source>Indian J Med Res.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>148</volume>:<fpage>S64</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijmr.IJMR_961_18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30964082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6469370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gundling</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feldmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoedemaker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. [Hormonal treatments for fertility disorders in cattle]. <source>Tierarztl Prax Ausg G Grosstiere Nutztiere.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>255</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0038-1623121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22911233</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sterry</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolb</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fricke</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Strategic treatment of anovular dairy cows with GNRH</article-title>. <source>Theriogenology.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>534</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2008.08.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18926565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A weekly postpartum pgf2alpha protocol enhances uterine health in dairy cows</article-title>. <source>Reprod Biol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>295</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.repbio.2016.10.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27839674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haimerl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heuwieser</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arlt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Short communication: meta-analysis on therapy of bovine endometritis with prostaglandin f2alpha-an update</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>10557</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2018-14933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30172399</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Darendeliler</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Growth and growth hormone: recent papers on efficacy and adverse effects of growth hormone and world health organization growth standards</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Endocrinol Metab.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/jpem-2017-0531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29329107</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rizzo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gazza</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silvestre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maresca</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sciorsci</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Scopolamine for uterine involution of dairy cows</article-title>. <source>Theriogenology.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>2018</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2018.08.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30227302</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanzen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pieterse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scenczi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drost</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Relative accuracy of the identification of ovarian structures in the cow by ultrasonography and palpation per rectum</article-title>. <source>Vet J.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/tvjl.1999.0398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10712804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meira</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henriques</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sa</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of ultrasonography and histopathology for the diagnosis of endometritis in holstein-friesian cows</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>6969</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2011-4950</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23063156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasimanickam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duffield</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gartley</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Endometrial cytology and ultrasonography for the detection of subclinical endometritis in postpartum dairy cows</article-title>. <source>Theriogenology.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>1&#8211;2</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2003.03.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15159097</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oultram</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Herd monitoring to optimise fertility in the dairy cow: making the most of herd records, metabolic profiling and ultrasonography (research into practice)</article-title>. <source>Animal.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>2014</volume>:<fpage>185</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>98</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1751731114000597</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24709163</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lenz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drillich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heuwieser</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. [Evaluation of the diagnosis of subclinical endometritis in dairy cattle using ultrasound]. <source>Berl Munch Tierarztl Wochenschr.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>5&#8211;6</volume>:<fpage>237</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17555046</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Omori</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Optimization of diagnostic methods and criteria of endometritis for various postpartum days to evaluate infertility in dairy cows</article-title>. <source>Theriogenology.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>2018</volume>:<fpage>225</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2018.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30055393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheldon</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noakes</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of three treatments for bovine endometritis</article-title>. <source>Vet Rec.</source> (<year>1998</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>575</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/vr.142.21.575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9634707</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pursley</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mee</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiltbank</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Synchronization of ovulation in dairy cows using pgf2alpha and GNRH</article-title>. <source>Theriogenology.</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>915</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0093-691X(95)00279-H</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16727787</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karakaya-Bilen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bisinotto</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gumen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of presynchronization with prostaglandin f2alpha before the 5-d timed AI protocol on ovarian responses and pregnancy in dairy heifers</article-title>. <source>Theriogenology.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>2019</volume>:<fpage>138</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2019.03.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31022603</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caixeta</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guard</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bicalho</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Reproductive performance of dairy cows resynchronized after pregnancy diagnosis at 31 (+/-3 days) after artificial insemination (AI) compared with resynchronization at 31 (+/-3 days) after AI with pregnancy diagnosis at 38 (+/-3 days) after AI</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>7630</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2013-6723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24094532</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4353590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Lima</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemes</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Binelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madureira</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of a puberty induction protocol based on injectable long acting progesterone on pregnancy success of beef heifers serviced by TAI</article-title>. <source>Theriogenology.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>154</volume>:<fpage>128</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2020.05.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32603989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madureira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Polsky</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burnett</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silper</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soriano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sica</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Intensity of estrus following an estradiol-progesterone-based ovulation synchronization protocol influences fertility outcomes</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>3598</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>608</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2018-15129</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30738666</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sauls-Hiesterman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Voelz</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A shortened resynchronization treatment for dairy cows after a non-pregnancy diagnosis</article-title>. <source>Theriogenology.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>2020</volume>:<fpage>105</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2019.09.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31536859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Youssefi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vojgani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gharagozlou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akbarinejad</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>More male calves born after presynch-ovsynch protocol with 24-hour timed AI in dairy cows</article-title>. <source>Theriogenology.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>890</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2013.01.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23394973</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Funakura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shiki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsubakishita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mido</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Katamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kitahara</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Validation of a novel timed artificial insemination protocol in beef cows with a functional corpus luteum detected by ultrasonography</article-title>. <source>J Reprod Dev.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>109</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1262/jrd.2017-135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29311520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5902898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sterry</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fricke</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Assessment of a practical method for identifying anovular dairy cows synchronized for first postpartum timed artificial insemination</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>3255</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2006-779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17582109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McArt</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caixeta</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Machado</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guard</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galvao</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sa</surname><given-names>FO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Ovsynch versus ultrasynch: reproductive efficacy of a dairy cattle synchronization protocol incorporating corpus luteum function</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>2525</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2009-2930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20494160</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheldon</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Molinari</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ormsby</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bromfield</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Preventing postpartum uterine disease in dairy cattle depends on avoiding, tolerating and resisting pathogenic bacteria</article-title>. <source>Theriogenology.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>150</volume>:<fpage>158</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2020.01.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31973964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7234917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>LeBlanc</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duffield</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keefe</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Defining and diagnosing postpartum clinical endometritis and its impact on reproductive performance in dairy cows</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>2223</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(02)74302-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12362455</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagener</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gabler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drillich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A review of the ongoing discussion about definition, diagnosis and pathomechanism of subclinical endometritis in dairy cows</article-title>. <source>Theriogenology.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2017.02.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28407857</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barlund</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carruthers</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Waldner</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A comparison of diagnostic techniques for postpartum endometritis in dairy cattle</article-title>. <source>Theriogenology.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>714</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.theriogenology.2007.12.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18242670</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasimanickam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cornwell</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nebel</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of presence of clinical and subclinical endometritis at the initiation of presynch-ovsynch program on the first service pregnancy in dairy cows</article-title>. <source>Anim Reprod Sci.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>3&#8211;4</volume>:<fpage>214</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anireprosci.2005.10.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16298090</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heuwieser</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tenhagen</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tischer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luhr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of three programmes for the treatment of endometritis on the reproductive performance of a dairy herd</article-title>. <source>Vet Rec.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>338</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/vr.146.12.338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10777040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Leonurine ameliorates the inflammatory responses in lipopolysaccharide-induced endometritis</article-title>. <source>Int Immunopharmacol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>156</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2018.06.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29879659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaukat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Matrine alleviates <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> lipoteichoic acid-induced endometritis via suppression of Tlr2-mediated Nf-kappab activation</article-title>. <source>Int Immunopharmacol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>2019</volume>:<fpage>201</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2019.02.033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30822611</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>