<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8884245</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8884245.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8884245</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8884245</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35237678</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.806253</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Chlorogenic Acid Attenuates Oxidative Stress-Induced Intestinal Mucosa Disruption in Weaned Pigs</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="J">Jiali</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names initials="D">Daiwen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1172789/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names initials="B">Bing</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuheng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/231904/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names initials="P">Ping</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiangbing</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/652797/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names initials="J">Jie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names initials="J">Junqiu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1393703/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhiqing</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names initials="H">Hui</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names initials="J">Jun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/649812/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Institute of Animal Nutrition, Sichuan Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Chengdu</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Key Laboratory of Animal Disease-Resistance Nutrition</institution>, <addr-line>Chengdu</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Shandong Provincial Key Laboratory of Animal Biotechnology and Disease Control and Prevention, Department of Animal Science and Veterinary Medicine, Shandong Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Tai'an</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Francesco Gai, Italian National Research Council, Italy</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Cesar Augusto Pospissil Garbossa, University of S&#227;o Paulo, Brazil; Shu-cheng Huang, Henan Agricultural University, China</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Jun He <email>hejun8067@163.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Animal Nutrition and Metabolism, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">400313</issue-id><elocation-id>806253</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>12</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>04</day><month>1</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>01</day><month>03</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2022-03-03 15:16:50.260"><day>03</day><month>03</month><year>2022</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2022 Chen, Chen, Yu, Luo, Zheng, Mao, Yu, Luo, Huang, Yan and He.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Chen, Chen, Yu, Luo, Zheng, Mao, Yu, Luo, Huang, Yan and He</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-09-806253.pdf"/><abstract><p>Chlorogenic acid (CGA) is a natural polyphenol that possesses potent antioxidant activity. However, little is known about its exact role in regulating the intestinal health under oxidative stress. This study was conducted to explore the effect of dietary CGA supplementation on intestinal barrier functions in weaned pigs upon oxidative stress. Twenty-four weaned pigs were allocated to three treatments and were given a basal diet (control) or basal diet containing CGA (1,000 mg/kg) for 21 days. Pigs were challenged by sterile saline (control) or diquat [10 mg/kg body weight (BW)] on the 15th day. Results showed that CGA attenuated the BW reduction, reduced the serum concentrations of diamine oxidase and D-lactate, and elevated serum antioxidant enzymes activities in diquat-challenged weaned pigs (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Moreover, diquat challenge decreased villus height and activities of sucrase and alkaline phosphatase in jejunum and ileum (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), but CGA elevated the villus height and enzyme activities in the intestinal mucosa (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). In addition, CGA not only decreased the expression levels of Bax, caspase-3, and caspase-9 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) but also elevated the expression levels of sodium glucose transport protein-1, glucose transporter-2, occludin, claudin-1, zonula occludens-1, and antioxidant genes such as nuclear factor erythroid-derived 2-related factor 2 and heme oxygenase-1 in intestinal mucosa of weaned pigs upon oxidative stress (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). These findings suggested that CGA can attenuate oxidative stress-induced growth retardation and intestinal mucosa disruption, which was linked to elevated antioxidative capacity and enhanced intestinal barrier integrity.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>antioxidant capacity</kwd><kwd>intestinal barrier function</kwd><kwd>natural polyphenolic</kwd><kwd>small intestine</kwd><kwd>swine</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="36"/><page-count count="11"/><word-count count="6472"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The intestinal mucosa plays as one of the key barriers in living organisms. It is mainly composed of intestinal epithelial cells and intercellular tight junctions of enterocytes, which not only plays a critical role in nutrient absorption but also constitutes the first line of defense against various pathogens and toxins in the intestinal lumen (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). However, a variety of stimuli such as malnutrition, bacterial infections, and stresses can impair the integrity of the intestinal epithelium. In particular, oxidative stress, as a result of reactive oxygen species (ROS) overexpression, is a common feature of many chronic and acute intestinal diseases (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). For instance, it can induce atrophy of the intestinal mucosa and lead to the reduction of intestinal digestion and absorption ability (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Moreover, oxidative stress-induced overproduction of ROS could also induce DNA damage and apoptosis of the intestinal epithelial cells, which increased intestinal permeability and facilitates translocation of luminal antigens into sub-epithelial tissues, leading to growth retardation and a series of intestinal and systemic diseases (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Therefore, the potential interventions to alleviate the intestinal oxidative stress have attracted considerable research interest worldwide.</p><p>A variety of polyphenols have previously been reported to have the potential to alleviate oxidative stress-induced diseases (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Chlorogenic acid (CGA), formed by esterification of caffeic acid and quinic acid, is one of the most abundant natural polyphenolic compounds presented in coffee, fruits, and vegetables (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Previous studies indicated that CGA has multiple benefits for mammalian animals, including antioxidant, anti-inflammatory, and antibacterial activities (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). CGA has been reported to alleviate intestinal ischaemia and reperfusion injury by improving the antioxidant activities and ameliorate endotoxin-induced intestinal injury in rats (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). These attributes should make it an attractive health product for various oxidative stress-induced injuries and diseases. In a previous study, CGA was found to improve growth performance and intestinal health through elevating the activities of antioxidant enzymes in weaned pigs (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). However, there is little information available in the scientific literature on the evaluation of the protective effect and potential mechanisms of CGA supplementation on oxidative stress-induced intestinal injury in weaned pigs.</p><p>In the present study, we explored the effects of dietary supplementation with CGA on growth performance, antioxidant capacity, and the structure and functions of intestinal mucosa in pigs' exposure to oxidative stress. The oxidative stress was induced by using diquat that was a classic agent for the construction of oxidative stress models (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). This study will assist in developing of CGA to attenuate various oxidative stress-induced injury or diseases.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Animals, Diet, and Experimental Design</title><p>Twenty-four weaned pigs (Duroc &#215; Landrace &#215; Yorkshire, 21 days of age), with an initial average body weight (BW) of 7.47 &#177; 0.50 kg, were randomly allotted to one of three treatments (eight replicates each treatment) in a completely randomized design for a 21-day study. The three experimental treatments were as follows: (1) non-challenged weaned pigs fed a basal diet [control (CON) group]; (2) diquat-challenged weaned pigs fed a basal diet (Diquat group); and (3) diquat-challenged weaned pigs fed a basal diet supplemented with CGA (1,000 mg/kg; DCGA group). The supplementary level of CGA to feed was based on our previous study (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). On the 15th day of the trial, pigs from the CON group were intraperitoneally injected with sterile saline. The other two groups were challenged by diquat (intraperitoneal injection, diquat dibromide monohydrate, PS365; Sigma Co.) at a dose of 10 mg/kg BW. The basal diet was formulated according to our previous study (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), and ingredient composition and nutrient level are presented in <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>. All weaned pigs were housed in individual metabolic cages (1.5 &#215; 0.7 &#215; 1.0 m) and had free access to fresh water and feed throughout the experiment. The room temperature was maintained at 25&#8211;28&#176;C, and relative humidity controlled at 55&#8211;65%. The feed intake per pig was recorded daily, and pigs were weighed on the mornings of days 14 and 21 of the experiment. The average daily weight gain (ADG), average daily feed intake (ADFI), and feed conversion (F/G) were calculated.</p></sec><sec><title>Sample Collection</title><p>At the end of the trial, blood samples were collected <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> jugular venipuncture from all weaned pigs after 12-h fasting. The serum samples were obtained by centrifugation at 3,000 &#215; g for 15 min at 4&#176;C and then stored at &#8722;20&#176;C for further analysis. Subsequently, pigs were euthanized with an intravenous injection of sodium pentobarbital (200 mg/kg BW), and the abdomen was immediately opened to collect the intestinal segments (duodenum, jejunum, and ileum) according to the method described by Zheng et al. (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). About 3-cm segments of the middle of duodenum, jejunum, and ileum were isolated, gently flushed with ice-cold phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), and then fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde solution for histological analyses. The mucosa samples were harvested by scraping the segment using a sterile glass slide, snap-frozen in liquid nitrogen, and then stored at &#8722;80&#176;C until further analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Determination of Serum Parameters</title><p>The superoxide dismutase (SOD), catalase (CAT), glutathione peroxidase (GSH-Px), total antioxidant capacity (T-AOC), malondialdehyde (MDA), diamine oxidase (DAO), and D-lactic acid were measured by using the assay kits (Nanjing Jiancheng Institute of Bioengineering, Jiangsu, China) according to the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec><title>Intestinal Morphology Analysis</title><p>After fixation with 4% paraformaldehyde solution, the intestinal morphology was estimated according to previous method (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Briefly, the duodenum, jejunum, and ileum segments were dehydrated in a graded ethanol series, embedded in paraffin, sliced into 5-&#956;m-thick cross-sections by using a microtome and stained with hematoxylin and eosin. A minimum of 10 well-orientated crypt-villus units from each intestinal segment were chosen and measured. Villus height and crypt depth were determined with image processing and analysis system (ImagePro Plus 6.0, Media Cybernetics, Inc., Rockville, MD, USA). The ratio of villus height to crypt depth (VCR) was calculated as the villus height divided by crypt depth.</p></sec><sec><title>Intestinal Mucosa Parameters</title><p>About 1 g of mucosa samples of each section were homogenized after dilution with ice-cold saline solution (1:9, w/v) and then centrifuged (2,500 &#215; g, 10 min, 4&#176;C) to collect the supernatant. The activities of lactase, sucrose, maltase, and alkaline phosphatase (AKP) in duodenal, jejunal, and ileal mucosa were measured by using the assay kits (Nanjing Jiancheng Institute of Bioengineering, Jiangsu, China) according to the manufacturer's instructions. The total protein content in the mucosa samples was determined using the Bradford brilliant blue method. All samples were measured in triplicate. Enzyme activities were presented as units (U) per milligram of protein.</p></sec><sec><title>RNA Isolation and qPCR</title><p>Total RNA of duodenum, jejunum, and ileum mucosa was isolated by using TRIzol Reagent (TaKaRa, Dalian, China). The RNA concentration and purity were assayed by spectrophotometer (Beckman Coulter, DU800) at 260 and 280 nm. For each sample, reverse transcription was performed using the PrimeScript RT reagent kit with gDNA Eraser (TaKaRa, Dalian, China) according to the manufacturer's instructions. All primers were synthesized commercially by Sangon Biotech Limited and were shown in <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S2</xref>. Quantitative real-time PCR was performed to analyze the expression levels of sodium glucose transport protein-1 (SGLT1), glucose transporter-2 (GLUT2), zonula occludens-1 (ZO-1), occludin, claudin-1, B-cell lymphoma-2&#8211;associated X protein (Bax), B-cell lymphoma-2 (Bcl-2), caspase-3, caspase-9, nuclear factor erythroid-derived 2-related factor 2 (Nrf2), Kelch-like epichlorohydrin&#8211;associated protein 1 (Keap1), and heme oxygenase-1 (HO-1) using SYBR&#174; Premix Ex TaqTM II (Tli RNaseH Plus) reagents (TakaRa, Dalian, China) and the QuanStudioTM 6 Flex Real-Time PCR detection system (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). Each reaction was performed in a 10-&#956;l reaction volume, which contained 5 &#956;l of SYBR Premix Ex TaqTM (2 &#215;), 1 &#956;l of each primer, 2 &#956;l of doubled-distilled water, and 1 &#956;l of cDNA template. The PCR cycling parameters were as follows: 95&#176;C for 30 s, 40 cycles of 95&#176;C for 10 s, 60&#176;C for 25 s, and 72&#176;C for 5 min. After amplification, melting curve analysis was performed after each real-time quantitative PCR assay to verify the specificity of the reactions. The glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) gene was used as the reference gene. The target gene mRNA expression level was calculated using the 2<sup>&#8722;&#916;&#916;Ct</sup> method (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Each sample was tested simultaneously in triplicate on the same PCR plate.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Individual pig was used as the experimental unit, and all data were analyzed by general liner mode (GLM) procedure of SAS 9.4 (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA) after being assessed for normal distribution using the Shapiro&#8211;Wilk's statistic (W &gt; 0.05). Statistical differences among groups were determined by Tukey's multiple-range test. Results were presented as means and SEMs. Differences were taken to indicate significance when <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Growth Performance</title><p>The growth performance was not significantly affected by CGA before diquat challenge (1&#8211;14 days) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). However, diquat challenge resulted in a 44.42% reduction of ADFI and a 86.18% decrease of ADG compared with the CON pigs (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). In contrast, dietary supplementation with CGA (1,000 mg/kg) suppressed the diquat-induced decreases in ADFI (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Besides, dietary CGA supplementation attenuated the decrease of ADG in pigs upon diquat challenge (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) although the ADG of pigs in DCGA group was still lower than that in the CON group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Effects of CGA on the growth performance in weaned pigs upon oxidative stress<sup>1</sup>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Items</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CON</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Diquat</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>DCGA</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SEM</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1&#8211;14 days</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADFI (g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">385.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">386.13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">398.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.67</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.964</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADG (g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261.61</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266.79</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">294.40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.99</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.547</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F/G</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.773</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>15&#8211;21 days</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADFI (g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">540.33<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300.27<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">428.19<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.86</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADG (g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">361.67<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.00<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">224.17<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.57</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F/G</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n/a</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes"><sup>1</sup>Results are presented as mean and SEM. Labeled means in a row without a common superscript letter differ, P &lt; 0.05. ADFI, average daily feed intake; ADG, average daily gain; F/G, feed efficiency (the ratio of ADFI and ADG); CON, piglets fed a basal diet; Diquat, piglets fed the basal diet and challenged by diquat; DCGA, piglets fed the basal diet containing CGA (1,000 mg/kg) and challenged by diquat</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Serum Parameters</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> and <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, diquat-challenged pigs showed a significant increase in serum levels of DAO, D-lactate, and MDA (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), while a significant decrease in serum activities of SOD and GSH-Px (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). However, dietary CGA supplementation attenuated the increase of DAO and D-lactate levels (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) and the decrease of GSH-Px and SOD activities (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the serum to levels observed in pigs of CON group. Meanwhile, CGA supplementation suppressed the diquat-induced increase of serum MDA concentration but still higher than that in the CON group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). There were no significant differences in the levels of CAT and T-AOC among the groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Effects of CGA on serum DAO <bold>(A)</bold> and D-Lactate <bold>(B)</bold> levels in piglets upon oxidative stress. DAO, diamine oxidase; CON, piglets fed a basal diet; Diquat, piglets fed the basal diet and challenged by diquat; DCGA, piglets fed the basal diet containing CGA (1,000 mg/kg) and challenged by diquat.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-806253-g0001.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effects of CGA on serum antioxidant parameters in weaned pigs upon oxidative stress<sup>1</sup>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Item</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CON</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Diquat</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>DCGA</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SEM</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOD (U/ml)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.84<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.31<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.80<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDA (nmol/ml)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.94<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.53<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GSH-Px (U/ml)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">411.04<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">272.05<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">387.88<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAT (U/ml)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.302</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-AOC (U/ml)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.812</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes"><sup>1</sup>Results are presented as mean and SEM. Labeled means in a row without a common superscript letter differ, P &lt; 0.05. GSH-Px, glutathione peroxidase; CAT, catalase; T-AOC, total antioxidant capacity; SOD, superoxide dismutase; MDA, malondialdehyde; CON, piglets fed a basal diet; Diquat, piglets fed the basal diet and challenged by diquat; DCGA, piglets fed the basal diet containing CGA (1,000 mg/kg) and challenged by diquat</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Intestinal Morphology</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>, compared with the CON group, diquat-challenged pigs showed a significant decrease in villus height and the VCR in jejunum and ileum (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), while a significant increase in crypt depth in jejunum (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Compared with pigs in the Diquat group, pigs in the DCGA group exhibited increased villus height and VCR in jejunum as well as villus height in ileum to the levels observed in pigs of the CON group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). However, the ileal VCR of pigs in DCGA group was still lower than that in the CON group.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Effects of CGA on intestinal morphology in the Duodenum <bold>(A)</bold>, Jejunum <bold>(B)</bold>, and Ileum <bold>(C)</bold> of piglets upon oxidative stress. CON, piglets fed a basal diet; diquat, piglets fed the basal diet and challenged by diquat; DCGA, piglets fed the basal diet containing CGA (1,000 mg/kg) and challenged by diquat.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-806253-g0002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Enzyme Activities and the mRNA Expression Levels of Digestion and Absorption-Related Genes</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, diquat challenge not only decreased the mucosal activities of disaccharidases such as the sucrase, lactase, and maltase in the duodenum and jejunum (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) but also decreased the mucosal activity of AKP in the jejunum and ileum (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). However, compared with pigs in the Diquat group, dietary CGA supplementation significantly increased the activities of sucrose, lactase, and maltase in duodenum; the activities of sucrase, maltase, and AKP in jejunum; and the activities of sucrase and AKP in ileum (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The lactase activity of duodenum and jejunum as well as the sucrase activity of ileum in pigs of DCGA group were still lower than those in the CON group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Meanwhile, lower mRNA expression levels of SGLT1 in duodenum as well as SGLT1 and GLUT2 in jejunum were observed in pigs of Diquat group (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). However, dietary CGA supplementation mitigated the negative effects of diquat (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Effects of CGA on intestinal enzyme activities in weaned pigs upon oxidative stress<sup>1</sup>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Item</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CON</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Diquat</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>DCGA</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SEM</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>
</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Duodenum</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sucrase (U/mg prot)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.37<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.63<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.71<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.83</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lactase (U/mg prot)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.01<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.80<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.09<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.93</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maltase (U/mg prot)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">259.11<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206.07<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">257.16<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AKP (U/mg prot)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.713</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Jejunum</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sucrase (U/mg prot)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185.81<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.88<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154.17<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.70</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lactase (U/mg prot)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.88<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.84<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.32<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.88</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maltase (U/mg prot)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265.75<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">193.79<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">267.38<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AKP (U/mg prot)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.08<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.60<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.84<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Ileum</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sucrase (U/mg prot)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121.87<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.14<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.29<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lactase (U/mg prot)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.92</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.86</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.584</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maltase (U/mg prot)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">236.62</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212.72</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">240.66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.63</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.468</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AKP (U/mg prot)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.81<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.21<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.74<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.67</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes"><sup>1</sup>Results are presented as mean and SEM. Labeled means in a row without a common superscript letter differ, P &lt; 0.05. AKP, alkaline phosphatase; CON, piglets fed a basal diet; Diquat, piglets fed the basal diet and challenged by diquat; DCGA, piglets fed the basal diet containing CGA (1,000 mg/kg) and challenged by diquat</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Effects of CGA on expression levels of intestinal digestion and absorption-related genes in the Duodenum <bold>(A)</bold>, Jejunum <bold>(B)</bold>, and Ileum <bold>(C)</bold>. SGLT1, sodium glucose transport protein-1; GLUT2, glucose transporter-2; CON, piglets fed a basal diet; Diquat, piglets fed the basal diet and challenged by diquat; DCGA, piglets fed the basal diet containing CGA (1,000 mg/kg) and challenged by diquat. <sup>a, b</sup> Bars with different letters between treatment groups indicate significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-806253-g0003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>mRNA Expression Levels of Intestinal Function and Barrier-Related Genes</title><p>As presented in <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>, diquat strongly increased the mRNA expression levels of Bax and Bax/Bcl2 in the duodenum and jejunum as well as the mRNA expression levels of caspase-3 and caspase-9 in the three intestinal sections. However, dietary CGA supplementation mitigated the negative effects of diquat (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), although the caspase-3 mRNA expression levels in duodenum and the caspase-9 mRNA expression levels in duodenum and jejunum were still higher than those in the group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). In addition, a significant decrease in mRNA expression levels of occludin in duodenum and jejunum, ZO-1 in jejunum and ileum, and claudin-1 in the three intestinal sections was observed under diquat stimulation (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>), which was strongly inhibited by CGA (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). However, the mRNA expression levels of claudin-1 in duodenum and jejunum of pigs in DCGA group were still higher than those in the CON group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Effects of CGA on expression levels of intestinal barrier-related genes in the Duodenum <bold>(A)</bold>, Jejunum <bold>(B)</bold>, and Ileum <bold>(C)</bold>. ZO-1, zonula occludens 1; CON, piglets fed a basal diet; Diquat, piglets fed the basal diet and challenged by diquat; DCGA, piglets fed the basal diet containing CGA (1,000 mg/kg) and challenged by diquat. <sup>a, b</sup> Bars with different letters between treatment groups indicate significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-806253-g0004.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Effects of CGA on expression levels of apoptosis-related genes in the Duodenum <bold>(A)</bold>, Jejunum <bold>(B)</bold>, and ileum <bold>(C)</bold>. Bcl2, B-cell lymphoma-2; Bax, B-cell lymphoma-2&#8211;associated X protein; CON, piglets fed a basal diet; Diquat, piglets fed the basal diet and challenged by diquat; DCGA, piglets fed the basal diet containing CGA (1,000 mg/kg) and challenged by diquat. <sup>a, b</sup> Bars with different letters between treatment groups indicate significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-806253-g0005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>mRNA Expression Levels of Critical Molecules in Antioxidant Signaling Pathway</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>, diquat challenge significantly decreased the expression levels of Nrf2 and HO-1 in duodenum and jejunum (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). However, dietary CGA supplementation significantly suppressed the diquat-induced decrease in the expression levels of Nrf2 and HO-1 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Moreover, duodenal HO-1 mRNA expression level of pigs was still lower in DCGA group than that in the CON group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><fig position="float" id="F6" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Effects of CGA on expression levels of intestinal antioxidant-related key genes in the Duodenum <bold>(A)</bold>, Jejunum <bold>(B)</bold>, and Ileum <bold>(C)</bold>. Nrf2, nuclear factor erythroid-derived 2-related factor 2; Keap1, Kelch-like epichlorohydrin&#8211;associated protein 1; HO-1, heme oxygenase-1; CON, piglets fed a basal diet; Diquat, piglets fed the basal diet and challenged by diquat; DCGA, piglets fed the basal diet containing CGA (1,000 mg/kg) and challenged by diquat. <sup>a, b</sup> Bars with different letters between treatment groups indicate significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-806253-g0006.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Oxidative stress is one of the critical factors leading to growth retardation and disruption of various tissues and organs in neonatal mammals (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Accumulating evidences showed that the intestine was more susceptible to oxidative stress than other tissues because of the frequent renewal of enterocytes and continuous exposure to various stimuli from the intestinal tract (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Oxidative stress could lead to overproduction of ROS, which would damage the integrity of intestinal barrier by disrupting the tight junction and triggering apoptosis of intestinal epithelium (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Previous research indicated that pigs subjected to oxidative stress usually showed negative growth performance (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Similarly, in the present study, intraperitoneal injection of diquat significantly decreased the ADFI and ADG in weaned pigs. However, dietary CGA supplementation improved the growth performance in the diquat-challenged weaned pigs, which is consistent with previous study (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), indicating that dietary CGA supplementation could alleviate the growth retardation of weaned pigs upon oxidative stress.</p><p>Diamine oxidase, an intracellular enzyme, is mainly synthesized and distributed in the intestinal epithelium (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Moreover, D-lactate is the special end product of bacteria in intestinal epithelia which exists mainly in cytoplasm. Once the integrity of intestinal barrier is destroyed, the levels of serum DAO and D-lactate will increase (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Therefore, the DAO activity and D-lactate level in serum are commonly adopted to monitor the injury degree of the intestinal barrier. In the present study, diquat-challenged pigs exhibited an increase in the serum levels of DAO and D-lactate, indicating that the intestinal barrier function was impaired and intestinal oxidative damage model was successfully constructed. Inversely, CGA significantly alleviated these adverse effects induced by diquat, which was in line with the previous results that dietary CGA supplementation effectively decreased the serum DAO activity in lipopolysaccharide (LPS)-challenged weaned rats (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>), demonstrating that dietary CGA supplementation helped to maintain the intestinal integrity of weaned pigs under oxidative stress.</p><p>Oxidative stress, a consequence of the imbalance of redox status, is closely related to animal health. GSH-Px and CAT are two critical antioxidant enzymes responsible for elimination of organic hydroperoxides and hydrogen peroxide (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), and MDA is widely considered to be an index used to monitor the degree of lipid peroxidation in mammals (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Therefore, their serum levels have been widely used as biomarkers for monitoring the antioxidant capacity of the body. Present study showed that supplementation of dietary CGA could attenuate the negative effects of diquat challenge on activities of GSH-Px and SOD in weaned pigs and suppress the diquat-induced increase in the MDA concentration in serum. Similarly, a previous study in rat showed that CGA supplementation had protective effect against methotrexate-induced liver oxidative injury through increasing glutathione (GSH) activity and decreasing MDA concentration (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). A recent study in porcine jejunum epithelial cell line (IPEC-J2) cells also demonstrated that CGA could attenuate diquat-induced intestinal oxidative injury, which was associated with elevated antioxidant capacity (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Therefore, CGA could maintain the antioxidant capacity of weaned pigs by improving the antioxidant enzymes activities. In addition, the antioxidant property of CGA may partly result from its special chemical structure. The CGA contains five hydroxyl groups, allowing itself to have the ability to scavenge the free radical (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p><p>Oxidative stress-induced overproduction of ROS was reported to cause intestinal morphological impairment (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). The integrity of intestinal villus-crypt morphological structure acts as the basis of nutrient digestion and absorption and is critical for maintaining the intestinal barrier function (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). The villus extends into the lumen to increase the surface area available for nutrition absorption, and the crypt is formed by the physically protected epithelial invagination that surrounds the villus base (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). In the current study, CGA administration significantly alleviated diquat-induced villus atrophy and crypt hyperplasia in jejunum of weaned pigs, suggesting that dietary CGA supplementation could improve the intestinal development of pigs upon oxidative stress possibly by the enhancing intestinal mucosal morphology integrity. Intestinal epithelium is the most important site for nutrient digestion and absorption, in which a variety of enzymes are expressed and secreted by the enterocytes (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Obviously, disruption of the intestinal epithelium will result in a decrease of the enzyme activities in the intestinal mucosa. Previous study has shown that diquat-induced oxidative stress could cause serious dysfunctions of nutrient digestion and absorption in weaned pigs (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Consistently, the results of the current study indicated that intraperitoneal injection of diquat significantly decreased the mucosal activities of disaccharidases (sucrase, lactase, and maltase) in the duodenum and jejunum and suppressed the activity of AKP in the jejunum and ileum of weaned pigs. However, CGA supplementation significantly alleviated the negative effects of diquat administration on intestinal mucosal enzyme activities, indicating the protective effects of CGA on digestion and absorption function of intestine in weaned pigs under oxidative stress. In addition, oxidative stress was also found to affect the expressions of nutrient transporters, leading to a decrease in nutrient absorption capacity (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Consistently, we further detected the mRNA expression of SGLT1 and GLUT2, which are critical glucose transporters located in the mucosa of the small intestine (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). The results showed that supplementation with CGA significantly suppressed the reduction of SGLT1 and GLUT2 expression levels induced by oxidative stress, indicating an increase energy supply for the growth of diquat-challenged weaned pigs. These results suggested that CGA supplementation was helpful in improving the intestinal digestion and absorption function of weaned pigs under oxidative stress, which may partly account for the promoting effect of CGA on growth performance as mentioned above (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>).</p><p>Previous study reported that intraperitoneal injection of diquat could lead to the imbalance of redox status and then destroy the intestinal barrier function by influencing the expression of key molecules (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Therefore, we further quantified the expression levels of critical genes related to the intestinal barrier functions. The intestinal barrier is mainly composed of the intercellular tight junction proteins, including transmembrane proteins (e.g., occludin and claudin families), intracellular linker proteins (ZOs), and many other regulatory proteins (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Thus, tight junction proteins are essential for the integrity of the intestinal barrier by regulating the paracellular permeability. As expected, the present study showed that diquat challenge decreased the expression levels of occludin and claudin-1 in the duodenum and jejunum, which was consistent with a previous study that the increased intestinal permeability of pigs was associated with downregulation of tight junction proteins upon oxidative stress (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Notably, CGA supplementation enhanced their expression levels in the intestinal mucosa. These results indicated that dietary CGA supplementation could alleviate oxidative stress-induced intestinal barrier dysfunction, which was associated with the improvement of intercellular junctions between epithelial cells. In addition, a previous study suggested that the oxidative stress-induced atrophy of intestinal villus and barrier dysfunction were partially associated with the apoptosis of intestinal epithelial cells (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). It is a well-known fact that the cell apoptosis is mainly regulated by multiple molecules, especially by the Bcl-2 and caspase family (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Oxidative stress was found to promote the expression of a series of apoptosis-related genes (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). In this study, diquat challenge significantly elevated the expression levels of the Bax, caspase-3, and caspase-9 in the duodenal and jejunal mucosa. Interestingly, CGA significantly decreased the Bax, caspase-3, and caspase-9 expression levels in small intestinal mucosa, which was probably due to the elevated antioxidant capacity of pigs in DCGA group. Therefore, these results suggested that CGA could improve the intestinal barrier integrity partly by maintaining the tight junction protein expression and suppressing the excessive apoptosis of intestinal epithelial cells in weaned pigs under oxidative stress.</p><p>The elevated antioxidative capacity was also supported by the expressions of several critical antioxidant genes. Nrf2, as a master regulator of the antioxidant response, has been implicated in regulating the expression levels of endogenous antioxidant enzymes that protect against oxidative stress (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). It has been reported that the activities of antioxidant enzymes could be enhanced by increasing the mRNA expression levels of Nrf2 (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Similarly, we found that CGA significantly elevated the expression levels of Nrf2 in the diquat-challenged weaned pigs in this study, which was in line with the increased activities of antioxidant enzymes mentioned above. A previous study in mice has suggested that polyphenols could further upregulate the expression of many antioxidative and cytoprotective genes by activating Nrf2 in the small intestine (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). HO-1 is one of the key antioxidant enzymes, which is located downstream of the Nrf2 and plays an important role in regulating the ROS levels of cells challenged by various stress (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). In this study, CGA supplementation significantly elevated the expression level of HO-1 in diquat-challenged pigs, which was in accord with the results of previous study (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>), further indicating that CGA supplementation could enhance the antioxidant capacity in oxidative stress-challenged weaned pigs.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, our results showed that oxidative stress not only decreased the growth performance but also induced disruption of the intestinal barrier in the weaned pigs. Dietary CGA supplementation could attenuate the oxidative stress-induced growth retardation and intestinal barrier disruption, which was associated with elevated antioxidant capacity and improved intestinal barrier integrity.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Material</xref>, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by the Animal Care and Use Committee of Sichuan Agricultural University (SICAU-2015-034).</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>JC and JH designed the experiment and wrote the manuscript. JC, DC, and BY performed the statistical analyses. YL, PZ, and XM carried out the animal experiment. JY and JL conducted the sample collection. ZH and HY carried out the sample analysis. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="s9"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31972599) and the Key Developmental Program of Sichuan Province (20ZDYF0003).</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s10"><title>Publisher's Note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors thank Huifen Wang and Quyuan Wang for their help during the animal trial and sample collections.</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s11"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2022.806253/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2022.806253/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Intestinal mucosal barrier function in health and disease</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Immunol.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>799</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>809</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri2653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19855405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Halpern</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Denning</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of intestinal epithelial barrier function in the development of NEC</article-title>. <source>Tissue Barriers.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e1000707</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21688370.2014.1000707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25927016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4389790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Development of an antioxidant system after early weaning in piglets</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>612</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/jas.2013-6986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24352957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schedl</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Proliferation rate and transit time of mucosal cells in small intestine of the diabetic rat</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology.</source> (<year>1977</year>) <volume>73</volume>:<fpage>1326</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0016-5085(19)31509-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">913975</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ames</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary carcinogens and anticarcinogens: oxygen radicals and degenerative diseases</article-title>. <source>Science.</source> (<year>1983</year>) <volume>221</volume>:<fpage>1256</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.6351251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6351251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blachier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tossou</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Oxidative stress and inflammation: what polyphenols can do for us?</article-title><source>Oxid Med Cell Longev.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>2016</volume>:<fpage>7432797</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2016/7432797</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27738491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5055983</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouayed</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rammal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dicko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Younos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soulimani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chlorogenic acid, a polyphenol from <italic toggle="yes">Prunus domestica</italic> (Mirabelle), with coupled anxiolytic and antioxidant effects</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Sci.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>262</volume>:<fpage>77</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jns.2007.06.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17698084</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Neuroprotective effects of chlorogenic acid against apoptosis of PC12 cells induced by methylmercury</article-title>. <source>Environ Toxicol Phar.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.etap.2007.12.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21783882</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rashid</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nafees</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Majed</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Protective effect of Chlorogenic acid against methotrexate induced oxidative stress, inflammation and apoptosis in rat liver: An experimental approach</article-title>. <source>Chem Biol Interact.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>272</volume>:<fpage>80</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cbi.2017.05.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28479099</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Itagaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurokawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogura</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>In vitro and in vivo antioxidant properties of chlorogenic acid and caffeic acid</article-title>. <source>Int J Pharmaceut.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>403</volume>:<fpage>136</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpharm.2010.09.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20933071</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Chlorogenic acid decreased intestinal permeability and ameliorated intestinal injury in rats via amelioration of mitochondrial respiratory chain dysfunction</article-title>. <source>Food Sci Biotechnol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>253</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10068-016-0037-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30263265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6049378</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary chlorogenic acid improves growth performance of weaned pigs through maintaining antioxidant capacity and intestinal digestion and absorption function</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>1108</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jas/skx078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29562339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6093540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Osburn</surname><given-names>WO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wakabayashi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nilles</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biswal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trush</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nrf2 regulates an adaptive response protecting against oxidative damage following diquat-mediated formation of superoxide anion</article-title>. <source>Arch Biochem Biophys.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>454</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.abb.2006.08.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16962985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1851923</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of dietary supplementation with glutamate and aspartate on diquat-induced oxidative stress in piglets</article-title>. <source>PLoS One.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e0122893</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0122893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25875335</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4398417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Arginine metabolism and its protective effects on intestinal health and functions in weaned piglets under oxidative stress induced by diquat</article-title>. <source>Brit J Nutr.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>117</volume>:<fpage>1495</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>502</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007114517001519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28701241</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Benzoic acid beneficially affects growth performance of weaned pigs which was associated with changes in gut bacterial populations, morphology indices and growth factor gene expression</article-title>. <source>J Anim Physiol An Nutr.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>101</volume>:<fpage>1137</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jpn.12627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27747941</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cottrell</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Furness</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wijesiriwardana</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Selenium and vitamin E together improve intestinal epithelial barrier function and alleviate oxidative stress in heat-stressed pigs</article-title>. <source>Exp Physiol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>101</volume>:<fpage>801</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/EP085746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27064134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Selenium-enriched yeast alleviates oxidative stress-induced intestinal mucosa disruption in weaned pigs</article-title>. <source>Oxid Med Cell Longev.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>2020</volume>:<fpage>5490743</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2020/5490743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32256952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7106930</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gessner</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fiesel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Most</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dinges</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ringseis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Supplementation of a grape seed and grape marc meal extract decreases activities of the oxidative stress-responsive transcription factors NF-&#954;B and Nrf2 in the duodenal mucosa of pigs</article-title>. <source>Acta Vet Scand.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1751-0147-55-18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23453040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3599961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Chlorogenic acid improves intestinal barrier functions by suppressing mucosa inflammation and improving antioxidant capacity in weaned pigs</article-title>. <source>J Nutr Biochem.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>84</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jnutbio.2018.06.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29986311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Chlorogenic acid decreases intestinal permeability and increases expression of intestinal tight junction proteins in weaned rats challenged with LPS</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e97815</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24887396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4041575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andreazza</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kauer-Sant'Anna</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kapczinski</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Oxidative stress markers in bipolar disorder: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disorders.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>111</volume>:<fpage>135</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2008.04.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18539338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wozniak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drewa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wozniak</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schachtschabel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Activity of antioxidant enzymes and concentration of lipid peroxidation products in selected tissues of mice of different ages, both healthy and melanoma-bearing</article-title>. <source>Z Gerontol Geriatr.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>184</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00391-004-0229-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15224238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chlorogenic acid attenuates oxidative stress-induced intestinal epithelium injury by co-regulating the PI3K/Akt and I&#954;B&#945;/NF-&#954;B signaling</article-title>. <source>Antioxidants.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1915</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antiox10121915</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34943017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8750628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pluske</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hampson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Factors influencing the structure and function of the small intestine in the weaned pig: a review</article-title>. <source>Livest Prod Sci.</source> (<year>1997</year>) <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>215</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0301-6226(97)00057-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Supplementation with exogenous catalase from penicillium notatum in the diet ameliorates lipopolysaccharide-induced intestinal oxidative damage through affecting intestinal antioxidant capacity and microbiota in weaned pigs</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Spectr.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e0065421</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/Spectrum.00654-21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34908474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8672903</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beumer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clevers</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cell fate specification and differentiation in the adult mammalian intestine</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>39</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41580-020-0278-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32958874</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of isoleucine on glucose uptake through the enhancement of muscular membrane concentrations of GLUT1 and GLUT4 and intestinal membrane concentrations of Na+/glucose co-transporter 1 (SGLT-1) and GLUT2</article-title>. <source>Brit J Nutr.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>116</volume>:<fpage>593</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>602</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007114516002439</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27464458</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Fish oil enhances intestinal barrier function and inhibits corticotropin-releasing hormone/corticotropin-releasing hormone receptor 1 signalling pathway in weaned pigs after lipopolysaccharide challenge</article-title>. <source>Brit J Nutr.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>115</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007114516001100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27080003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Diquat-induced oxidative stress increases intestinal permeability, impairs mitochondrial function, and triggers mitophagy in piglets</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>1795</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>805</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jas/sky104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29562342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6140957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duckworth</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miguel</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burkitt</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A mouse model of pathological small intestinal epithelial cell apoptosis and shedding induced by systemic administration of lipopolysaccharide</article-title>. <source>Dis Model Mech.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1388</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>99</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dmm.013284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24046352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3820262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Budihardjo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Slaughter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bid, a Bcl2 interacting protein, mediates cytochrome c release from mitochondria in response to activation of cell surface death receptors</article-title>. <source>Cell.</source> (<year>1998</year>) <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>481</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0092-8674(00)81589-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9727491</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Resveratrol attenuates inflammation and oxidative stress induced by myocardial ischemia-reperfusion injury: role of Nrf2/ARE pathway</article-title>. <source>Int J Clin Exp Med.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>10420</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26379832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4565215</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular basis of the Keap1-Nrf2 system</article-title>. <source>Free Radic Biol Med.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>100</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2015.06.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26117331</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scapagnini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sonya</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nader</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calogero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zella</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galvano</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Modulation of Nrf2/ARE pathway by food polyphenols: a nutritional neuroprotective strategy for cognitive and neurodegenerative disorders</article-title>. <source>Mol Neurobiol.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>192</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>201</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12035-011-8181-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21499987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5554938</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cytoprotective effect of chlorogenic acid against hydrogen peroxide-induced oxidative stress in MC3T3-E1 cells through PI3K/Akt-mediated Nrf2/HO-1 signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>Oncotarget.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>14680</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.14747</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28122344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5362435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>