<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8213023</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8213023.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8213023</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8213023</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34150899</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.684818</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Oral Delivery of <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> Expressing Chicken NK-2 Peptide Protects Against <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria acervulina</italic> Infection in Broiler Chickens</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wickramasuriya</surname><given-names initials="SS">Samiru S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/815911/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names initials="I">Inkyung</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/810984/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names initials="Y">Youngsub</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names initials="WH">Woo H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Przybyszewski</surname><given-names initials="C">Chris</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1307472/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gay</surname><given-names initials="CG">Cyril G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/804547/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Oosterwijk</surname><given-names initials="JG">Jolieke G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1279994/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names initials="HS">Hyun S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/475160/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Animal Bioscience and Biotechnology Laboratory, Agricultural Research Service, United States Department of Agriculture</institution>, <addr-line>Beltsville, MD</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>College of Veterinary Medicine, Institute of Animal Medicine, Gyeongsang National University</institution>, <addr-line>Jinju</addr-line>, <country>South Korea</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>US Biologic, Inc.</institution>, <addr-line>Memphis, TN</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>National Program Staff-Animal Health, Agricultural Research Service, United States Department of Agriculture</institution>, <addr-line>Beltsville, MD</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Rohana P. Dassanayake, National Animal Disease Center (USDA ARS), United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Ilias Giannenas, Aristotle University of Thessaloniki, Greece; Juan D. Latorre, University of Arkansas, United States; Guillermo Tellez, University of Arkansas, United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Hyun S. Lillehoj <email>hyun.lillehoj@usda.gov</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Veterinary Infectious Diseases, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>04</day><month>6</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">374996</issue-id><elocation-id>684818</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>3</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>05</day><month>5</month><year>2021</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>19</day><month>06</month><year>2021</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-04 17:25:14.210"><day>04</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2021 Wickramasuriya, Park, Lee, Kim, Przybyszewski, Gay, Oosterwijk and Lillehoj.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2021</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wickramasuriya, Park, Lee, Kim, Przybyszewski, Gay, Oosterwijk and Lillehoj</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-08-684818.pdf"/><abstract><p>Chicken NK-lysin peptide 2 (cNK-2) is a natural lytic peptide with direct cytotoxicity against many apicomplexan parasites including <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic>. Developing an effective oral delivery strategy to express cNK-2 in the intestine, where <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> parasites interact with the host's gut epithelial cells, may effectively reduce the fecundity of parasites and minimize intestinal damage. Furthermore, cNK-2 modulates gut immune responses to decrease local inflammation elicited by <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> infection in the intestine. Therefore, we developed a stable strain of <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>) that carries cNK-2 to the gut to determine its effectiveness in ameliorating the negative impacts of coccidiosis and to replace the use of antibiotics in controlling coccidiosis in commercial broiler chicken production. Chickens were randomly allocated into eight treatment groups: two control groups (NC: <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> infected non-<italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> control; CON: non-infected control); three <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>empty vector (EV) groups (EV6: 10<sup>6</sup> cfu/day/bird; EV8: 10<sup>8</sup> cfu/day/bird; EV10: 10<sup>10</sup> cfu/day/bird), and three <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 groups (NK6: 10<sup>6</sup> cfu/day/bird; NK8: 10<sup>8</sup> cfu/day/bird; NK10: 10<sup>10</sup> cfu/day/bird). All chickens, except those in the CON group, were challenged with 5,000 freshly sporulated <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> oocysts through oral gavage on day 15. Chickens were given an oral dose of <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> on days 14, 15, and 16. Body weight, weight gains, and fecal oocyst shedding were measured. To investigate the efficacy of oral <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-cNK-2 against coccidiosis, gene expression of gut health-related biomarkers was measured using RT-PCR. Markers included SOD1, CAT, and HMOX1 for oxidative stress in the spleen and intestinal mucosa, OCLN, ZO-1, and JAM2 for tight junction proteins, and MUC2 for mucin gene expression in the gut. The results showed that oral treatment of young chickens with <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 improved growth performance, enhanced gut integrity, and reduced fecal oocyst shedding. Altogether, these results confirm <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 treatment as a promising and effective alternative strategy to replace antibiotics against coccidiosis based on its ability to reduce parasite survival, to reduce coccidiosis-induced body weight loss, and to decrease gut damage based on the enhanced expression of proteins associated with gut integrity and intestinal health.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>NK-lysin</kwd><kwd>chicken</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic></kwd><kwd>coccidiosis</kwd><kwd>antimicrobial peptide</kwd><kwd>oxidative stress</kwd><kwd>growth performance</kwd><kwd>gut health</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="1"/><ref-count count="36"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="7166"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Coccidiosis is a major enteric disease of chickens that is caused by several distinct species of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> protozoan parasites infecting different areas of the gut. Coccidiosis primarily damages epithelial integrity in the intestine decreasing nutrient utilization and resulting in an annual loss of over $3.2 billion in the poultry industry globally (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). With the onset of coccidiosis, <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> elicits a local inflammatory response in the intestine, increasing gut permeability, and poor nutrient absorption that hinders optimal growth performance (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). A live attenuated coccidiosis vaccine is a cost-effective approach currently utilized to control coccidiosis in commercial poultry. However, the inability to induce consistent protection, evidence of residual virulence, increasing incidence of drug resistance in <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic>, and strict governmental regulation of in-feed medication in poultry production prompt the discovery of alternative strategies to control coccidiosis to support &#8220;no antibiotics ever&#8221; or &#8220;antibiotic-free&#8221; meat production for the poultry industry (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>).</p><p>Alternative strategies to antibiotics, including recombinant vaccines, hyperimmune IgY antibodies, probiotics, prebiotics, phytochemicals, and antimicrobial peptides (AMPs) have been shown to reduce the clinical symptoms of poultry diseases, to enhance host innate immunity, and growth performance at various levels of efficacy (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). These alternatives have also been shown to control coccidiosis in commercial poultry by maintaining gut health and enhancing immunity. Among these alternatives, AMPs are small peptides that may have direct cytotoxic effects against various pathogens, including parasites such as <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). The amphipathic structure of AMP molecules easily destroys a wide range of pathogens by interacting with negatively charged cationic residues (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p><p>NK-lysin is a cationic amphiphilic AMP originally identified in Natural killer (NK) cells of porcine intestinal tissue and later characterized in chicken (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). NK-lysin has a globular structure with 78 amino acid residues and is orthologous to human granulysin. NK-lysin, like other members of the saposin-like protein family, exhibits cytolytic activities against tumor cells and microbes (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). NK-lysin also mediates immune regulation at low doses, which may play a pivotal role in the induction of adaptive immunity and regulation of inflammatory response (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p><p>Chicken NK-lysin (cNK-2) is a natural lytic peptide that has been reported to have effective cytotoxicity against apicomplexan parasites such as <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> by disrupting the sporozoite membrane (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Chicken NK-2 derived from the cationic core region of the NK-lysin protein that is secreted from chicken cytotoxic lymphocytes during coccidiosis (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). The characterization and expression of cNK-2 have been previously studied and well-documented (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Additionally, cNK-2 has been shown to successfully destroy <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria spp</italic>. in both <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> studies (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>).</p><p>Even though the structure and function of cNK-2 have been studied extensively, a major gap remains the discovery of an effective oral delivery strategy to preserve the functional activity of cNK-2 in the chicken gut under commercial operations. Without an effective delivery system, AMPs may lose their activity with the presence of enzyme degradation in the gut (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). In a sustainable delivery system, AMPs not only promote host local immunity but also reduce parasite growth and promote a healthy gut microbial community. Moreover, an effective industry-friendly delivery strategy for antibiotic alternatives will reduce the cost of labor and increase the effectiveness of antibiotic-free animal production.</p><p>Gram-positive <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> is generally recognized as a highly resistant microbe to environmental stresses, stable, and safe environmental bacterium uniquely qualified for oral delivery of peptides (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> can transit through the digestive tract, and the self-assembly structure of <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus</italic> spores demonstrate its superior ability to work as a successful delivery vehicle (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). In previous studies, recombinant <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> spores with different protein expression levels were studied as a promising approach for sustainable delivery systems for mice, swine, and aquaculture (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p><p>To our knowledge, this is the first time <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> has been explored for cNK-2 peptide delivery to the gut in chickens as a prevention strategy against coccidiosis. Therefore, we developed a stable strain of probiotic <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> expressing cNK-2 to investigate its effectiveness as a carrier of cNK-2 to the gut and to explore its protective effect against coccidiosis challenge infection in commercial broiler chickens. In addition to evaluating the impact on growth and clinical signs caused by coccidiosis, we also evaluated gut integrity and immunity by looking at the presence of tight junction transcripts and antioxidative responses.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Recombinant <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> Construction</title><p>Recombinant <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> spores expressing empty vector (<italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-EV) or <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-cNK-2 were constructed and provided by US Biologic (Memphis, TN). The NK-lysin used for the expression in a bacterial vector was based on the chicken NK-lysin sequence (RRQRSICKQLLKKLRQQLSDALQNNDD) reported previously (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), which was then cloned into the pTTB2 expression vector (MoBiTec). Briefly, pTTB2-cNK was then expanded in BL21 competent <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (New England Biolabs, Inc., Ipswich, MA) and purified using the GeneJET Plasmid Miniprep Kit (Thermo Fischer Scientific, Madison, WI). Sequences were confirmed using Sanger sequencing and purified plasmids were religated using the Rapid DNA Ligation (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Madison, WI). Competent <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> cells (strain WB800N, MoBiTec) were transformed using 0.1 M EGTA and expanded on agar plates using 2% xylose as a selection agent. Single colonies were sequenced and expanded using 2xYT media (Difco, BD Diagnostic Systems, Sparks, MD).</p></sec><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> Killing Assays</title><p><italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-EV and <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-cNK-2 were grown in media and culture supernatants tested for anti-sporozoite activity using an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> assay as described (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Briefly, sporocysts from freshly sporulated <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> oocysts were harvested and purified using isopycnic centrifugation on a Percoll gradient followed by washing with ice-cold phosphate-buffered saline. Next, sporocysts were treated with excystation solution (0.25% trypsin, 0.014 M taurocholic acid) and incubated for 30 min at 41&#176;C to release sporozoites. Afterward, sporozoites were harvested by filtering the excystation solution and washed with Hank's balanced salt solution (HBSS; Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA). <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> sporozoites (1.0 &#215; 10<sup>7</sup>/mL) were mixed with the culture supernatant from <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-EV or <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-cNK-2 culture in a 1:1 ratio. Recombinant cNK-2 (Genscript, Piscataway, NJ) was used as control at a concentration of 100 &#956;g/mL. After 3 h incubation at 41&#176;C, the sporozoites were stained with fluorescence viability dye (AO/PI staining solution, Nexcelom Bioscience LLC, Lawrence, MA), and viable sporozoites were counted microscopically.</p></sec><sec><title>Chickens and Animal Care</title><p>Eighty one-day-old Ross broiler chicks (Ross 708) were obtained from a local hatchery (Longnecker Hatchery, Elizabethtown, PA) and housed in Petersime brooder units maintained in a temperature-controlled closed-house environment. Chickens were raised to 14 days of age with non-medicated commercial starter diets. After 14 days, chickens were moved to experimental grower cages and fed a non-medicated commercial grower diet until the end of the experimental period. <italic toggle="yes">Ad libitum</italic> feeds and fresh clean water were provided at all times.</p></sec><sec><title>Experimental Design</title><p>On day 14, body weights were recorded and chickens were randomly allocated to eight treatments (10 birds/two cages/treatment; each bird considered as a replicate), whilst ensuring similar body weight distributions among treatments and replicates. Experimental treatments included: non-infected control (CON), infected control without any <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> (NC), the infected treatment administered with <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>EV at three different dosages (10<sup>6</sup>, 10<sup>8</sup>, and 10<sup>10</sup> cfu/day/bird; EV6, EV8, and EV10, respectively), and the infected treatment with <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 at three different dosages (10<sup>6</sup>, 10<sup>8</sup>, and 10<sup>10</sup> cfu/day/bird; NK6, NK8, and NK10, respectively) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). On days 14, 15, and 16, groups receiving <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> were administered their dedicated dose (1 mL/bird) using oral gavage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). Groups receiving <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> challenge were challenged on day 15 with 5,000 freshly propagated <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> oocysts (ARS Beltsville strain #12) (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Treatment and <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> challenge infection.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Treatment</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Abbreviation</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Description</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic></bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>dosage</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-infected group</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CON</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infected group</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#8211;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-EV</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<sup>6</sup> cfu/mL</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(EV)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<sup>8</sup> cfu/mL</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EV10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<sup>10</sup> cfu/mL</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NK6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<sup>6</sup> cfu/mL</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NK8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(cNK-2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<sup>8</sup> cfu/mL</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NK10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<sup>10</sup> cfu/mL</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="F1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Schematic outline of the experimental design.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-684818-g0001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Body Weight and Sample Collection</title><p>Individual body weights were recorded for all chickens on day 14, 17, 21, 24, and 28. Pooled fecal samples were collected from each cage daily from day 21 (6 dpi) until day 24 (9 dpi). At the end of the experiment (28 days; 13 dpi), five birds from each treatment group were randomly selected for intestinal sample collection. Chickens were humanely sacrificed by cervical dislocation, and the spleen and the mucosa of mid-duodenum tissue were dissected and stored in RNAlater&#8482; (Invitrogen Corporation, Carlsbad, CA) at &#8722;20&#176;C.</p></sec><sec><title>Fecal Oocyst Assessment</title><p>The collected fecal samples were processed according to the method previously described (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Briefly, feces collected from individual cages were ground and homogenized with 3 L of water. Two subsamples from each cage were put into 50 mL tubes for oocyst counting. To count fecal oocysts, various dilutions were made initially to determine the optimum dilutions for enumeration of oocysts for each sample. Three different scientists independently counted oocysts microscopically using a McMaster counting chamber using a sodium chloride flotation method as described (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). The total number of oocysts shed per chicken was calculated using the following formula:</p><disp-formula id="E1"><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>Total&#160;oocysts/bird&#160;=&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>oocyst&#160;count&#160;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#215;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;dilution&#160;factor</mml:mtext></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#215;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#160;fecal&#160;sample&#160;volume/counting&#160;chamber&#160;volume</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mtext>&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;/&#160;number&#160;of&#160;birds&#160;per&#160;cage</mml:mtext><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula></sec><sec><title>RNA Extraction and qRT-PCR</title><p>Collected tissue samples were gently washed with ice-cold HBSS (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA) and homogenized using a handheld homogenizer (TissueRuptor; Qiagen, Hilden, Germany). Total RNA was extracted using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen) followed by DNase digestion as described (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Quantification and purity were assessed using a NanoDrop spectrophotometer (NanoDrop One; Thermo Scientific) at 260/280 nm. Synthesis of cDNA was performed using a QuantiTect&#174; Reverse Transcription Kit (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer's instructions. The gene expression levels of tight junction proteins such as junctional adhesion molecule 2 (JAM2), occluding (OCLN), and zonula occludens-1 (ZO1), mucin 2 (MUC2) expression in the duodenum samples, and antioxidant markers including superoxide dismutase 1 (SOD1), heme oxygenase 1 (HMOX1), and catalase (CAT), in both duodenum and spleen samples were investigated. All oligonucleotide primer sequences used in this experiment are shown in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The cDNA samples were diluted to 1:5 and 5-&#956;L aliquots were used for qRT-PCR amplification. The sample was analyzed using SYBR Green qPCR Master Mix (PowerTrack, Applied Biosystems, Vilnius, Lithuania) in triplicate using Applied Biosystems QuantStudio 3 Real-Time PCR Systems (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA). The following PCR conditions were followed: denaturation at 95&#176;C for 10 min followed by amplification at 60&#176;C for 1 min for 40 cycles. Glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) was used as the reference gene for gene expression. For relative quantification of the gene expression levels, the logarithmic-scaled threshold cycle (Ct) values were used in the 2<sup>&#8722;&#916;<italic toggle="yes">&#916;Ct</italic></sup> method before calculating the mean and standard error of the mean (SEM) for the references and individual targets.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Quantitative real-time PCR oligonucleotide primer sequences.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Target gene</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Primer sequence</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Accession No</bold>.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAPDH</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F 5&#8242;-GGTGGTGCTAAGCGTGTTAT-3&#8242;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="K01458">K01458</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R 5&#8242;-ACCTCTGTCATCTCTCCACA-3&#8242;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">JAM-2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: 5&#8242;-AGCCTCAAATGGGATTGGATT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM0,010,06257.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: 5&#8242;-CATCAACTTGCATTCGCTTCA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OCLN</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: 5&#8242;-GAGCCCAGACTACCAAAGCAA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM205,128.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: 5&#8242;-GCTTGATGTGGAAGAGCTTGTTG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZO-1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: 5&#8242;-CCGCAGTCGTTCACGATCT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XM01,527,8981.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: 5&#8242;-GGAGAATGTCTGGAATGGTCTGA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MUC-2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: 5&#8242;-GCCTGCCCAGGAAATCAAG</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM0,013,18434.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R: 5&#8242;-CGACAAGTTTGCTGGCACAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HMOX-1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F 5&#8242;-CTGGAGAAGGGTTGGCTTTCT-3&#8242;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM205344</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R 5&#8242;-GAAGCTCTGCCTTTGGCTGTA-3&#8242;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOD1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F 5&#8242;-ATTACCGGCTTGTCTGATGG-3&#8242;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM205064.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R 5&#8242;-CCTCCCTTTGCAGTCACATT-3&#8242;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F 5&#8242;-ACTGCAAGGCGAAAGTGTTT-3&#8242;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NM001031215.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R 5&#8242;-GGCTATGGATGAAGGATGGA-3&#8242;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">GAPDH, Glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase; JAM-2, Junctional Adhesion Molecule 2; OCLN, Occludin; ZO-1, Zonula occludens-1; MUC-2, Mucin 2; HMOX-1, heme oxygenase 1; SOD1, Superoxide Dismutase 1; CAT, Catalase; F, forward primer; R, reverse primer</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Data were analyzed using Mixed Model (PROC MIXED) in SAS (SAS Inc., Cary, NC). The individual chicken was considered the experimental unit for statistical analysis. The results are given as least-squares means and pooled SEM. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values &lt; 0.05 were considered to be significant. When the <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value between treatments was &lt;0.05, homogeneous subsets were evaluated by the PDIFF option in SAS. The dose-response of growth performances were determined using the Interactive Matrix Language (IML) procedure of SAS to generate coefficients for the evenly spaced orthogonal contrasts. These coefficients generated by the IML procedure were then used in the mixed procedure for contrasts.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> Assay for Sporozoite Viability</title><p>Sporozoites treated with cNK-2 (control) showed a significant decrease (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in sporozoites viability at the end of the 3 h incubation period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Culture supernatant from <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-cNK-2 also showed a similar (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05) sporozoites killing activity compared to control. However, sporozoites treated with the culture supernatant from <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-EV showed higher viability (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) compared to control and the group treated with <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-cNK-2 culture.</p><fig id="F2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> expressing empty vector (<italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-EV) or chicken NK2 (<italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-cNK-2) <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria acervulina</italic> sporozoites (1.0 &#215; 10<sup>7</sup>/mL) were incubated with culture supernatant from <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-EV or <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-cNK-2 for 3 h at 41&#176;C. Chicken NK-lysin (cNK-2) was used as control at a concentration of 100 &#956;g/mL. Sporozoites were stained with a fluorescence viability dye and viable sporozoites were counted microscopically. <sup>a, b</sup>Bars with no common letter differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-684818-g0002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Body Weight and Daily Gain</title><p>Body weights of all chickens did not significantly differ (day 14: <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05) between groups at the start of the trial (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). There were no significant changes (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05) between treatments at day 17 (2 dpi) regardless of <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> infection or the type and dose of <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> administration. Chickens infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> showed lower (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) body weight at day 21 (6 dpi) than the CON chickens. However, the body weights of chickens in the NK10 group were significantly higher (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) than those of NC chickens at day 24 (9 dpi). Chickens that received EV did not show (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05) any dose responses for body weight measurement throughout the study period. In contrast, chickens in the NK groups showed enhanced body weights in a dose-dependent manner (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) at day 21 and 24.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Body weights of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria acervulina</italic>-infected chickens following treatment with <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> expressing cNK-2.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes"><bold>P</bold></italic><bold>-value</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CON</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NC</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>EV6</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>EV8</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>EV10</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NK6</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NK8</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NK10</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SEM</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Treatment</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Linearity (dose response)</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>EV</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>NK</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="13" rowspan="1"><bold>Body weight, g</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;D 14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">397</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">394</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">398</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">399</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">390</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">393</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">392</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">391</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.661</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.998</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;D 17 (2 dpi)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">579</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">547</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">566</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">570</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">591</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">569</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">565</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">575</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.689</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.352</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.328</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;D 21 (6 dpi)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">854<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">751<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">753<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">750<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">749<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">742<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">760<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">791<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.934</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;D 24 (9 dpi)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,060<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">940<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">944<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">957<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">957<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">967<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">962<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,009<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.764</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;D 28 (13 dpi)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,384<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,251<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,256<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,263<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,258<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,257<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,269<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,301<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.079</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.996</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.154</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="13" rowspan="1"><bold>Average daily gain, g</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;D 14&#8211;17 (&#8722;1 to 2 dpi)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.986</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.814</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.786</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;D 17&#8211;21 (2&#8211;6 dpi)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.7<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.1<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.8<sup>cde</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.2<sup>cde</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.9<sup>e</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.2<sup>cde</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.9<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.0<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;D 21&#8211;24 (6&#8211;9 dpi)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.8<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.5<sup>d</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.9<sup>cd</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.9<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.0<sup>cd</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.1<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.1<sup>bcd</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.8<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.654</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;D 24&#8211;28 (9&#8211;13 dpi)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.104</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.136</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;D 17&#8211;24 (2&#8211;9 dpi)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.7<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.0<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.1<sup>cd</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.3<sup>cd</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.0<sup>d</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.0<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.8<sup>bcd</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.1<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.125</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#160;&#160;&#160;D 17&#8211;28 (2&#8211;13 dpi)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.9<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.1<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.1<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.3<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.8<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.1<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.0<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.107</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.121</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">D, day; dpi, days post-infection; SEM, standard error of the mean. All chickens except CON were infected by oral gavage at day 15 with 5,000 oocysts/chicken of E. acervulina. B. subtilis were administrated by oral gavage daily from d 14 to 16. EV, B. subtilis carrying empty vector; NK, Bacillus subtilis expressing cNK-2; NC, E. acervulina infected non-B. subtilis control; EV6, B. subtilis (empty vector) at 10<sup>6</sup> cfu/day; EV8, B. subtilis (empty vector) at 10<sup>8</sup> cfu/day; EV10, B. subtilis (empty vector) at 10<sup>6</sup> cfu/day; NK6, B. subtilis expressing cNK-2 at 10<sup>6</sup> cfu/day; NK8, B. subtilis expressing cNK-2 at 10<sup>8</sup> cfu/day; NK10, B. subtilis expressing cNK-2 at 10<sup>10</sup> cfu/day. <sup>a&#8722;e</sup>Means in the same row with different superscripts differ (p &lt; 0.05) and the difference was revaluated by PDIFF option in SAS when P-value between treatments was &lt;0.05</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Similar to the body weight data, no significant changes (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05) were seen in the average daily gain (ADG) of chickens among the different treatment groups up to day 17 (2 dpi) (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Thereafter, chickens infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> showed significantly lower (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) ADG than the CON group. However, chickens in the NK10 group showed significantly increased (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) ADG compared to that of the NC group from day 17 to 24 (2&#8211;9 dpi). After day 24, the NK10 group did not show any significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05) in ADG compared to the NC chickens regardless of NK treatment dose.</p></sec><sec><title>Fecal Oocyst Shedding</title><p>Chickens that were treated with an oral dose of <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 showed significantly reduced (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) fecal oocyst output between 6 and 9 dpi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). In particular, the NK10 group showed significantly decreased (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) oocyst shedding compared to the NC group.</p><fig id="F3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Fecal oocyst counts of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria acervulina</italic>-infected chickens fed daily oral treatment with <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis-</italic>cNK-2. All chickens except CON were infected by oral gavage at day 15 with 5,000 oocysts/chicken of <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> were administrated by oral gavage at days 14&#8211;16. EV, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-EV; NK, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2; NC, <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> infected non-<italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> control; EV6, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> (empty vector) at 10<sup>6</sup> cfu/day; EV8, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>EV at 10<sup>8</sup> cfu/day; EV10, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>EV at 10<sup>6</sup> cfu/day; NK6, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 at 10<sup>6</sup> cfu/day; NK8, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 at 10<sup>8</sup> cfu/day; NK10, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 at 10<sup>10</sup> cfu/day. <sup>a&#8722;<italic toggle="yes">c</italic></sup>Bars with no common letter differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Each bar represents the mean &#177; SEM (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 8). Fecal samples were collected from 6 to 9 dpi to calculate the oocyst shedding.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-684818-g0003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Gene Expression of TJ Proteins and Mucin</title><p>Gene expression profiles of tight junction proteins in the duodenal mucosa are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>. On 13 dpi, chickens in the NC group did not show any significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05) in the expression levels of OCLN, ZO-1, and JAM-2 compared to the CON group. However, chickens that were given <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 (NK6, NK8, and NK10) showed increased (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) OCLN gene expression compared to the NC chickens, regardless of doses of NK-lysin treatment. In comparison to <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 and <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>EV, no difference (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05) was observed in OCLN gene expression for each dose. Moreover, chickens in the NK8 and NK10 groups showed higher (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) expression of ZO-1 than chickens in the NC, EV8, and EV10 groups. Similarly, JAM-2 expression in the duodenum was higher (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the NK8 and NK10 treatment groups than in the EV8 and EV10 groups. Notably, MUC2 gene expression was lower (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in NC chickens than in CON chickens but increased in the EV6, EV10, and NK6 groups compared to NC chickens.</p><fig id="F4" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Tight junction gene expression in duodenal mucosa of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria acervulina</italic>-infected broiler chickens fed orally <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> expressing cNK-2 (13 dpi). All chickens except CON were infected by oral gavage at day 15 with 5,000 oocysts/chicken of <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> was administrated by oral gavage at days 14&#8211;16. EV, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> (empty vector), NK, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2; NC, <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> infected non-<italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> control; EV6, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>EV at 10<sup>6</sup> cfu/day; EV8, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>EV at 10<sup>8</sup> cfu/day; EV10, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>EV at 10<sup>10</sup> cfu/day; NK6, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 at 10<sup>6</sup> cfu/day; NK8, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 at 10<sup>8</sup> cfu/day; NK10, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 at 10<sup>10</sup>cfu/day. Transcript levels of <bold>(A)</bold> occludin (OCLN), <bold>(B)</bold> zonula occludens-1 (ZO1), <bold>(C)</bold> junctional adhesion molecule 2 (JAM2), and <bold>(D)</bold> Mucin-2 (MUC-2) in duodenal mucosa were measured by quantitative RT-PCR and genes expression were analyzed using the 2<sup>&#8722;&#916;<italic toggle="yes">&#916;Ct</italic></sup> method. <sup>a&#8722;<italic toggle="yes">d</italic></sup>Bars with no common letter differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Each bar represents the mean &#177; SEM (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-684818-g0004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Antioxidant Gene Expression in the Duodenal Mucosa</title><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref> shows the mucosal antioxidant gene expression profile in the duodenum. Chickens treated with <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 (NK6, NK8, and NK10) and infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> showed elevated (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) expression of HMOX1 in the duodenal mucosa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5C</xref>) compared to the chickens in the <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina-</italic>infected control (NC) group. There was no significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05) in the expression levels of the SOD1 and CAT genes in the duodenal mucosa at 13 dpi (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figures 5A,B</xref>).</p><fig id="F5" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Anti-oxidant gene expression in duodenal mucosa of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria acervulina</italic>-infected broiler chickens fed orally <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> expressing cNK-2 (13 dpi). All chickens except CON were infected by oral gavage at day 15 with 5,000 oocysts/chicken of <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> were administrated by oral gavage at days 14&#8211;16. EV, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>EV; NK, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2; NC, <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> infected non<italic toggle="yes">-B. subtilis</italic> control; EV6, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>EV at 10<sup>6</sup> cfu/day; EV8, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>EV at 10<sup>8</sup> cfu/day; EV10, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>EV at 10<sup>10</sup> cfu/day; NK6, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 at 10<sup>6</sup> cfu/day; NK8, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 at 10<sup>8</sup> cfu/day; NK10, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 at 10<sup>10</sup> cfu/day. Transcript levels of <bold>(A)</bold> superoxide dismutase 1 (SOD1), <bold>(B)</bold> catalase (CAT), <bold>(C)</bold> heme oxygenase (HMOX1) in duodenal mucosa were measured by quantitative RT-PCR and gene expression were analyzed using the 2<sup>&#8722;&#916;<italic toggle="yes">&#916;Ct</italic></sup> method. <sup>a&#8722;<italic toggle="yes">c</italic></sup>Bars with no common letter differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Each bar represents the mean &#177; SEM (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-684818-g0005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Antioxidant Gene Expression in Spleen</title><p>Gene expression profiles of antioxidant genes in the spleen are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>. The expression of CAT and HMOX1 was higher (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the CON group than in the NC and EV groups. Notably, chickens orally treated with higher doses of <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 (NK8 and NK10) showed similar (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05) levels of expression as those of the CON group.</p><fig id="F6" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Anti-oxidant gene expression in spleen of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria acervulina</italic>-infected broiler chickens fed orally <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> expressing cNK-2 (13 dpi). All chickens except CON were infected by oral gavage at day 15 with 5,000 oocysts/chicken of <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> were administrated by oral gavage at days 14&#8211;16. EV,v<italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>EV; NK, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2; NC, <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> infected non-<italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> control; EV6, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>EV at 10<sup>6</sup> cfu/day; EV8, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-EV at 10<sup>8</sup> cfu/day; EV10, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>EV at 10<sup>10</sup> cfu/day; NK6, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 at 10<sup>6</sup> cfu/day; NK8, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 at 10<sup>8</sup> cfu/day; NK10, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 at 10<sup>10</sup> cfu/day. Transcript levels of <bold>(A)</bold> superoxide dismutase 1 (SOD1), <bold>(B)</bold> catalase (CAT), <bold>(C)</bold> heme oxygenase (HMOX1) in the spleen were measured by quantitative RT-PCR and genes expression were analyzed using the 2<sup>&#8722;&#916;<italic toggle="yes">&#916;Ct</italic></sup> method. <sup>a&#8722;<italic toggle="yes">d</italic></sup>Bars with no common letter differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Each bar represents the mean &#177; SEM (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 5).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-08-684818-g0006.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Antibiotic alternatives including host defensin proteins such as NK-lysin are becoming important feed additives for the animal industry in the post-antibiotic era (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Antimicrobial peptides elicit first-line defense against pathogens in livestock animals and are recognized as a potential antibiotic alternative (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Among these peptides, the cNK-lysin peptide was reported to exert antibacterial activity by damaging bacterial cells (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Nevertheless, information concerning the efficient delivery systems to deliver these AMPs to the gut are scantly documented in poultry and livestock. Hence, the development of an effective oral delivery system that could deliver AMP across the gut lumen and stimulate immune responses is needed. To this end, this study was conducted to determine the effectiveness of stable <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> that carries cNK-2 peptide (<italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-cNK-2) as a carrier of NK-lysin peptide to the chicken gut and to investigate its effect against <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> infection in commercial broiler chickens. To the best of our knowledge, this study is the first to investigate and describe the potential effectiveness of oral delivery of stable <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> as a carrier for the cNK-2 peptide against coccidiosis infection in chickens.</p><p>Diversified approaches based on nanoparticles, natural polysaccharides, bacteria, and phages have been reported as promising delivery vehicles for AMPs (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Among these AMP delivery systems, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> has shown unique properties as an effective carrier for AMPs in previous studies with fish, mice, and swine (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Higher stability and extreme resistance to harsh environments, non-pathogenic nature, and ability to produce an industrial scale are the uniqueness of <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> as an attractive delivery system (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>).</p><p>To achieve our study objective, we followed the mode of action based on the NK-lysin peptide, which displays strong cytotoxicity against <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> as a consequence of altering the sporozoite outer membrane integrity and releasing intracellular contents (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Controlling <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> sporozoites invading gut epithelial cells will reduce gut damage and minimize production losses due to coccidiosis. Our <italic toggle="yes">in-vitro</italic> assay confirmed that the culture supernatant from <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-cNK-2 but not <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-EV contained anti-sporozoite activity against freshly prepared sporozoites.</p><p>In the present study, chickens in the <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic>-infected control treatment showed lower growth performance than their counterpart chickens in the uninfected control, as expected. Chickens infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> showed reduced growth performance because of the interruption of normal gut physiology and nutrition metabolism (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Rochell et al. (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>) and Kim et al. (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) also reported that <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> infection reduces growth performance in broiler chickens. Our results show that <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 treatment had a significant positive effect on the growth performance of coccidia-infected broiler chickens. Importantly, there was no growth improvement in chickens given an oral dose of <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>EV and infected with <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> confirming that cNK-2 delivered by <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> is responsible for reduced parasite fecundity and minimal growth depression in response to coccidia challenge in chickens. Consistent with our findings, Lee et al. (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>) reported improved body weight gain in <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic>-infected and cNK-2 peptide-treated broiler chickens. Findings from this study showing that the cNK-2 directly improved growth performance provides a strong indication that a stable <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> delivery system is a promising way to preserve cNK-2 functionality in the chicken gut. It was also noticeable that the effect of <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> infection on growth performance was more profound at the early stage of post-infection and was not significant in the later stages of the infection. These findings may be observed because the infection effect was reduced, and chickens began a recovery phase.</p><p>Enumeration of oocyst shedding in fecal samples is a commonly used measurement for understanding the severity of coccidiosis infections in broiler chickens. The reduction of oocysts is also used as a tool to determine the protective indices of different anti-parasite strategies against <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> invasion. In this study, <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina-</italic>infected chickens exhibited elevated fecal oocyst shedding, confirming the establishment of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> in the chicken gut. Chickens that were administered an oral dose of <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-EV showed numerically lower oocyst shedding than the infected control chickens, although no statistical significance was reached. Importantly, chickens that were given an oral dose of <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 showed a negative dose-dependent response to fecal oocyst shedding. Chickens given <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 at 10<sup>10</sup> cfu/day showed significantly lower oocyst shedding at 9 dpi than untreated infected control. This outcome supports the direct effect of cNK-2 activity against <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> which confirms our previous work (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). This indicates that the <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-cNK-2 at 10<sup>10</sup> cfu/day can be used as a remedial measure to control coccidiosis in the poultry industry. By preserving cNK-2 activity against <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> parasites in the chicken gut environment, <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> carriers are an effective and practical oral delivery vehicle for immunotherapeutic peptides such as AMP.</p><p>Tight junctions of gut epithelial cells work as a first-line defense system to protect animals from pathogen translocation by maintaining proper tight junction integrity (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Tight junctions are comprised of a multiprotein complex, such as OCLN, ZO-1, and JAM-2, at the apical end of epithelial cells that closely contact with the lumen (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Maintaining epithelial integrity by maintaining intestinal permeability enhances the gut health of chickens and nutrient absorption to improve growth performance (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Based on our current study, higher dosages of <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 increased tight junction gene expression in the duodenal mucosa compared to the infected control group. Recently, we showed that upregulation of these genes improved gut barrier function in the chicken intestine after <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> infection (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Moreover, elevated levels of ZO-1 and JAM-2 gene expression in chickens that were treated with higher dosages of <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 compared to control <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-EV demonstrated reduced damage by coccidiosis on gut barrier functions. Similar to tight junctions, the mucosal barrier defends against the invasion of bacteria, parasites, and other harmful species into the host (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Mucins are glycoproteins that form a mucus barrier over the epithelial cell surfaces of the intestine (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Among mucins, MUC-2 gene expression has been identified as a gut health marker in chicken and other poultry species, as it is the major mucin produced by goblet cells (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Our results indicate that <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina-</italic>infected chickens showed significantly decreased mucosal MUC-2 gene expression levels compared to the non-infected control. This result provides firm confirmation of mucus barrier failure in chickens challenged with coccidiosis. Chickens that were given an oral dose of <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 counteracted <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> infection-induced MUC-2 downregulation and increased its expression. This finding confirms previous studies showing increased MUC-2 gene expression in chickens fed <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> as a probiotic supplement (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>).</p><p>Previously, it was reported that coccidiosis triggers oxidative stress, thereby weakening intestinal barrier functions in chickens (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). For a robust understanding of gut health improvement with <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2, we also investigated mucosal oxidative stress markers. Higher production of reactive oxygen species (ROS) and reactive nitrogen species (RNS) cause imbalances between free radical production and endogenous antioxidant defense, creating oxidative stress in intestinal cells and leading to lipid peroxidation, DNA damage, and apoptosis (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Avoiding oxidative stress, free radical formation is prevented by the inactivation of precursors of free radicals or catalysts with the aid of enzymes, such as catalase, superoxide dismutase (SOD), and glutathione peroxidase (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). SOD enzymes catalyze the conversion of superoxide ions (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M2"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>O</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#8722;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>) to hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) and oxygen (O<sub>2</sub>) (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), whereas CAT enzymes catalyze the breakdown of hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) to H<sub>2</sub>O and O<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). HMOX1 is a rate-limiting enzyme responsible for heme-to-biliverdin catabolism (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). In this study, we did not observe any significant differences in SOD1 and CAT gene expression levels in the duodenal mucosa. However, significantly upregulated HMOX1 gene expression was observed in the duodenal mucosa from the <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic>-cNK-2-treated chickens compared to the untreated infected control. Compared to the mucosa, the spleen showed more pronounced antioxidant gene expression even though SOD1 expression remained unchanged. Both CAT and HMOX1 expression levels in the spleen were elevated with <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 treatments in this study. Although elevated expression levels of CAT and HMOX1 in the <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis-</italic>cNK-2 treated group was not significantly different from those in the infected control group, the results support the notion that cNK-2 reduced the oxidative stress induced by <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> infection.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>This study shows the effectiveness of a stable <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> carrying the cNK-2 as an oral delivery method for NK-lysin peptide to the <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic>-infected chicken gut, which resulted in improved growth performance via enhanced gut integrity and reduced oocyst shedding. These results also help to characterize the ability of cNK-2 to reduce oxidative stress induced by <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> infection in chickens. These findings indicate the need for future studies on the mechanisms of the <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> carrier system for successful AMP delivery and research on the NK-lysin approach as a strategy to reduce the coccidiosis-induced gut pathology in chickens. Further research characterizing the responses of higher doses of <italic toggle="yes">B. subtilis</italic> that carry cNK-2 together with different administration intervals and mode of delivery of <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus</italic> spores using different <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> challenges is warranted to develop effective commercializable strategies to replace antibiotics.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be made available by the authors, without undue reservation.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by Beltsville Agricultural Research Center Small Animal Care Committee (Animal Protocol No. 20-002).</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>HL, JO, IP, WK, and CG designed the research. IP, SW, WK, and YL conducted the research and analyzed data. JO produced and provided test materials for studies. SW, CG, and HL drafted the manuscript, and all authors reviewed and edited the manuscript to its final version. SW, IP, YL, WK, JO, CP, CG, and HL had responsibility for the content. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>JO and CP are employed by US Biologic, Inc. The remaining authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We appreciate the technical help of Drs. Alfredo Panebra, Hyoyun Nam, and Mingmin Lu.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> Funding was partly supported by ARS CRIS 8042-32000-107-00D, NIFA SBIR 2015-33610-23499, and NIFA SBIR 2016-33610-25686.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Parasiticidal activity of a novel synthetic peptide from the core &#945;-helical region of NK-lysin</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>197</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2013.04.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23664157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhari</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Involvement of T cell immunity in avian coccidiosis</article-title>. <source>Front. Immunol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>2732</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2019.02732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31824509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6886378</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria maxima</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic> infections on cecal microbial composition and the possible correlation with body weight gain in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Res Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>132</volume>:<fpage>142</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rvsc.2020.05.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32575030</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhari</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Beneficial effects of dietary supplementation of <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus</italic> strains on growth performance and gut health in chickens with mixed coccidiosis infection</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>277</volume>:<fpage>109009</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2019.109009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31862509</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehberger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The effects of dietary <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> supplementation, as an alternative to antibiotics, on growth performance, intestinal immunity, and epithelial barrier integrity in broiler chickens infected with <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria maxima</italic></article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>725</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2019.12.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32036975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7587808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Phytonutrients as non-nutritive feed additives to enhance growth and host immunity in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>496</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2527/jam2016-1035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gadde</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Alternatives to antibiotics for maximizing growth performance and feed efficiency in poultry: a review</article-title>. <source>Anim Health Res Rev.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>26</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1466252316000207</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28485263</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calsamiglia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Miyakawa</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cravens</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phytochemicals as antibiotic alternatives to promote growth and enhance host health</article-title>. <source>Vet Res.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13567-018-0562-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30060764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6066919</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Min</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of the immunomodulatory activity of the chicken NK-lysin-derived peptide cNK-2</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep45099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28332637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5362811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Siragusa</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bannerman</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial activity of chicken NK-lysin against <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria</italic> sporozoites</article-title>. <source>Avian Dis.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>302</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1637/8083-072307-ResNote.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18646461</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunne</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Agerberth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sillard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>NK-lysin, a novel effector peptide of cytotoxic T and NK cells. Structure and cDNA cloning of the porcine form, induction by interleukin 2, antibacterial and antitumour activity</article-title>. <source>EMBO J.</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1615</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/j.1460-2075.1995.tb07150.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7737114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC398254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Womack</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chicken NK-lysin is an alpha-helical cationic peptide that exerts its antibacterial activity through damage of bacterial cell membranes</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>93</volume>:<fpage>864</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.2013-03670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24706963</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalloul</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Min</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miska</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tuo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular cloning and characterization of chicken NK-lysin</article-title>. <source>Vet Immunol Immunopathol.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>110</volume>:<fpage>339</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>47</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetimm.2005.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16387367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Surface-displayed VP28 on <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> spores induce protection against white spot syndrome virus in crayfish by oral administration</article-title>. <source>J Appl Microbiol.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>111</volume>:<fpage>1327</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2011.05156.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21933311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Dossary</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Setlow</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Applications of <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> spores in biotechnology and advanced materials</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ. Microbiol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>86</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01096-20</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32631858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7440806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ricca</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baccigalupi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cangiano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Felice</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isticato</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mucosal vaccine delivery by non-recombinant spores of <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic></article-title>. <source>Microb Cell Fact.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12934-014-0115-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25112405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4249717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciabattini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parigi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isticato</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oggioni</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pozzi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Oral priming of mice by recombinant spores of <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic></article-title>. <source>Vaccine.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>4139</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2004.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15474704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khalique</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Surface display of antigen protein VP8<sup>*</sup> of porcine rotavirus on <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus Subtilis</italic> spores using CotB as a fusion partner</article-title>. <source>Molecules.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>3793</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules24203793</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31652492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6833084</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wickramasuriya</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmerman</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of dietary maltol on innate immunity, gut health, and growth performance of broiler chickens challenged with <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria maxima</italic></article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2021</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="doi" assigning-authority="pmc">10.3389/fvets.2021.667425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8173067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34095279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Panebra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Eimeria tenella</italic> elongation factor-1&#945; (EF-1&#945;) coadministered with chicken IL-7 (chIL-7) DNA vaccine emulsified in Montanide Gel 01 adjuvant enhanced the immune response to <italic toggle="yes">E. acervulina</italic> infection in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Avian Dis.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>342</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1637/11976-092418-Reg.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31251536</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gadde</surname><given-names>UD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Allium hookeri</italic> supplementation improves intestinal immune response against necrotic enteritis in young broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>97</volume>:<fpage>1899</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>908</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pey031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29538713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Immunity, immunomodulation, and antibiotic alternatives to maximize the genetic potential of poultry for growth and disease response</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>250</volume>:<fpage>41</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2018.09.016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chuanchuen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gay</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Alternatives to antibiotics: a symposium on the challenges and solutions for animal health and production</article-title>. <source>Antibiotics.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>471</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antibiotics10050471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33918995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8142984</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohtashamian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boddohi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nanostructured polysaccharide-based carriers for antimicrobial peptide delivery</article-title>. <source>J Pharm Investig.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>85</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40005-016-0289-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalloul</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of Pediococcus-based probiotic on coccidiosis in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ps/86.1.63</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17179417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rochell</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dilger</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria acervulina</italic> infection severity on growth performance, apparent ileal amino acid digestibility, and plasma concentrations of amino acids, carotenoids, and &#945;1-acid glycoprotein in broilers</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>95</volume>:<fpage>1573</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pew035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26933234</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bravo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Improved resistance to <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria acervulina</italic> infection in chickens due to dietary supplementation with garlic metabolites</article-title>. <source>Br J Nutr.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>109</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>88</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007114512000530</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22717023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Antimicrobial Activity of Chicken NK-2 Peptide Against Apicomplexan Protozoa</source>. United States patent US 8,691,943. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>US Department of Agriculture</publisher-name> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Macelline</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wickramasuriya</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Broilers fed a low protein diet supplemented with synthetic amino acids maintained growth performance and retained intestinal integrity while reducing nitrogen excretion when raised under poor sanitary conditions</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>949</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>58</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2019.10.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32036986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7587901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>AQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gay</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Bacillus</italic> spp. as direct-fed microbial antibiotic alternatives to enhance growth, immunity, and gut health in poultry</article-title>. <source>Avian Pathol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>339</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03079457.2018.1464117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29635926</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tellez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Escobar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of potential biomarkers for gut barrier failure in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>14</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2015.00014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26664943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4672187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of antibacterial peptide combinations on growth performance, intestinal health, and immune function of broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>6481</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2020.08.068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33248563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7810918</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aliakbarpour</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chamani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahimi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadeghi</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qujeq</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> and lactic acid bacteria probiotics influences intestinal mucin gene expression, histomorphology and growth performance in broilers</article-title>. <source>Asian Aust J Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1285</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5713/ajas.2012.12110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25049692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4092943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Oxidative stress in the poultry gut: potential challenges and interventions</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>60</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2019.00060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30886854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6409315</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Surai</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kochish</surname><given-names>II</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fisinin</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antioxidant defence systems and oxidative stress in poultry biology: an update</article-title>. <source>Antioxidants.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>235</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antiox8070235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31336672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6680731</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gadde</surname><given-names>UD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bravo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Growth-promoting and antioxidant effects of <italic toggle="yes">magnolia</italic> bark extract in chickens uninfected or co-infected with <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Eimeria maxima</italic> as an experimental model of necrotic enteritis</article-title>. <source>Curr Dev Nutr.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>nzy009</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cdn/nzy009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30019032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6041942</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>