<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="brief-report" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8960298</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC8960298.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">8960298</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">8960298</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35359668</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.760364</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Brief Research Report</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genome Wide Scan to Identify Potential Genomic Regions Associated With Milk Protein and Minerals in Vrindavani Cattle</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names initials="A">Akansha</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1126035/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names initials="A">Amit</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/597639/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gondro</surname><given-names initials="C">Cedric</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/497510/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names initials="AK">A. K.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1249013/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dutt</surname><given-names initials="T">Triveni</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names initials="BP">B. P.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1514015/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Animal Genetics Division, Indian Council of Agricultural Research-Indian Veterinary Research Institute</institution>, <addr-line>Bareilly</addr-line>, <country>India</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Animal Science, Michigan State University</institution>, <addr-line>East Lansing, MI</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Livestock Production and Management, Indian Council of Agricultural Research-Indian Veterinary Research Institute</institution>, <addr-line>Bareilly</addr-line>, <country>India</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Division of Animal Biotechnology, Indian Council of Agricultural Research-Indian Veterinary Research Institute</institution>, <addr-line>Bareilly</addr-line>, <country>India</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Sunday O. Peters, Berry College, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: George R. Wiggans, Council on Dairy Cattle Breeding, United States; Tara G. McDaneld, U.S. Meat Animal Research Center (USDA), United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Amit Kumar <email>vetamitchandan07@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Livestock Genomics, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>3</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">400313</issue-id><elocation-id>760364</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>8</month><year>2021</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>2</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>30</day><month>03</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-11 22:25:13.230"><day>11</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2022 Singh, Kumar, Gondro, Pandey, Dutt and Mishra.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Singh, Kumar, Gondro, Pandey, Dutt and Mishra</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-09-760364.pdf"/><abstract><p>In this study, genome-wide association study (GWAS) was conducted for identifying significantly associated genomic regions/SNPs with milk protein and minerals in the 96 taurine-indicine crossbred (<italic toggle="yes">Vrindavani</italic>) cows using 50K SNP Chip. After quality control, a total of 41,427 SNPs were retained and were further analyzed using a single-SNP additive linear model. Lactation stage, parity, test day milk yield and proportion of exotic inheritance were included as fixed effects in GWAS model. Across all traits, 13 genome-wide significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 1.20 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup>) and 49 suggestive significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 2.41 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup>) SNPs were identified which were located on 18 different autosomes. The strongest association for protein percentage, calcium (Ca), phosphorus (P), copper (Cu), zinc (Zn), and iron (Fe) were found on BTA 18, 7, 2, 3, 14, and 2, respectively. No significant SNP was detected for manganese (Mn). Several significant SNPs identified were within or close proximity to <italic toggle="yes">CDH13, BHLHE40, EDIL3, HAPLN1, INHBB, USP24, ZFAT</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">IKZF2</italic> gene, respectively. Enrichment analysis of the identified candidate genes elucidated biological processes, cellular components, and molecular functions involved in metal ion binding, ion transportation, transmembrane protein, and signaling pathways. This study provided a groundwork to characterize the molecular mechanism for the phenotypic variation in milk protein percentage and minerals in crossbred cattle. Further work is required on a larger sample size with fine mapping of identified QTL to validate potential candidate regions.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>crossbred cattle</kwd><kwd>genome-wide association studies</kwd><kwd>milk minerals</kwd><kwd>milk protein</kwd><kwd>Vrindavani</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="1"/><ref-count count="31"/><page-count count="8"/><word-count count="4630"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Milk and dairy products are considered a nutrient-rich diet, consisting of fat, protein, lactose along with several essential micronutrients including vitamins and minerals. Minerals representing a small fraction (~9 g/L) of bovine milk, are important for nutritional and technological properties of milk (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). The minerals in milk are present either as an inorganic ion (soluble phase) or form colloidal complexes with organic matter such as proteins, carbohydrates, and ligands including amino acids and citrates (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>).</p><p>Minerals play an important role in several physiological and biological activities. For instance, calcium, phosphorus, and magnesium are involved in the development of connective tissues such as bones, muscles, cartilages, and teeth in humans (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Calcium has been reported to play an important role in reducing cholesterol absorption, and in regulating blood pressure in humans (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). The zinc, manganese, iron, and copper are important components of several enzymes and play role in the immune system (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). These elements also serve as catalysts for many biochemical processes such as muscle contraction, nervous transmission, and nutrient absorption (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>).</p><p>The concentration of milk minerals influences the stabilization of casein micelle in milk. Calcium, phosphorus, and magnesium are an important components of casein micelle and positively regulates the coagulation properties of the milk (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). The milk minerals are complex traits, influenced by both genetic and non-genetic factors, including nutrition, lactation stage, parity, season, and breed (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Studies have shown that milk minerals have low to moderate heritability for Cu, Zn, Fe, and Mn (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>); and moderate to high heritability for Ca, P, and Zn (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). This provides the possibility to alter the concentration of bovine milk minerals through selective breeding.</p><p>The genome-wide association studies may improve our understanding of the genetic architecture and underlying molecular mechanism for variation in protein and minerals content in bovine milk. Studies have revealed about several potential candidate genes associated with milk protein percentage in different cattle breeds (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). However, for milk minerals only a limited number of genome-wide association studies has been reported (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Thus, the aim of this study was to identify genomic regions associated with milk protein percentage (%) and milk minerals including Ca, P, Cu, Zn, Fe, and Mn in Vrindavani cattle, a tropically adapted composite crossbred breed of dairy cattle of India.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Animals and Phenotypes</title><p>Morning milk samples (50 ml) were collected from 96 crossbred Vrindavani cattle of the ICAR-Indian Veterinary Research Institute, Bareilly. Vrindavani is a composite breed developed at Indian Veterinary Research Institute by crossing indicine (Hariana) with three taurine breeds (Holstein, Brown Swiss, and Jersey). Details of population structure and synthetic breed information of the Vrindavani population were described in a prior study by (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). The cows were kept in a loose housing system with free-stall dairy barn, fed <italic toggle="yes">ad libitum</italic> with mixed ration, and milked in a free-stall barn using automated milking systems. The cows were in milk (24-403 days) and from parity 1-8.</p><p>The protein percentage in milk was determined using a LactoScan milk analyzer (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). The milk minerals (Ca, P, Cu, Zn, Fe, and Mn) were estimated using Flame Atomic Absorption Spectrometer in technical triplicate samples. For the mineralization of milk samples, 5 ml of milk were dried in silica crucible using a hot-air oven. The dried samples were ashed using a muffle furnace. The ashed sample was mixed with 15 ml 1:1 diluted HCl and heated to dissolve the acid-soluble portion of total ash. The soluble portion was filtered and diluted to 100 ml using double distilled water. The digested samples were analyzed, using a flame atomic absorption spectrophotometer (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Genotyping and Quality Control</title><p>Blood samples were collected from individual cows, with the approval from the Institutional Animal Ethics Commit- tee (IAEC) on ICAR-Indian Veterinary Research Institute, Bareilly. Genomic DNA was isolated using Qiagen DNeasy Blood Mini Kit (Qiagen, Valencia, CA) according to the manufacturer's instructions. The quality and quantity of DNA were evaluated using NanoDrop spectrophotometer, agarose gel electrophoresis and Qubit fluorometer. The extracted genomic DNA were genotyped using Illumina BovineSNP50 Bead Chip platform (Illumina Inc., San Diego, CA) consisting of 53,218 SNPs across the genome. The quality control of the SNP genotypes was performed using PLINK v 1.9 (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). SNPs with call rate &lt;90%, minor allele frequency (MAF) &lt;0.05 and significantly deviating from the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium were excluded from the analysis. A total of 41,427 SNPs mapping autosomes were retained for further downstream analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analyses</title><p>Prior to GWAS, the admixture profile and the level of exotic inheritance of individual animal was estimated using ADMIXTRE V.13.0 (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) using a reference panel of purebred taurine (Holstein-Friesian, Brown Swiss, and Jersey) and indicine (Hariana) cattle downloaded from WIDDE (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://widde.toulouse.inra.fr/widde/widde/main.do?module=cattle" ext-link-type="uri">http://widde.toulouse.inra.fr/widde/widde/main.do?module=cattle</ext-link>) and KRISHI (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://krishi.icar.gov.in/jspui/handle/123456789/31167" ext-link-type="uri">https://krishi.icar.gov.in/jspui/handle/123456789/31167</ext-link>) web portals. The fixed effect of lactation stage, parity, test day milk yield, and the proportion of exotic inheritance (percentage of Holstein-Friesian, Jersey and Brown Swiss, estimated by admixture analysis) were tested with <italic toggle="yes">lm</italic> function in R. A single-SNP linear regression of phenotype on genotype was fitted for GWAS analysis using snpStats package in R following Gondro (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). The genotypes were tested for additive effect using model.</p><disp-formula id="E1"><mml:math id="M1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mtext class="textrm" mathvariant="normal">y</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext class="textrm" mathvariant="normal">X</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#946;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext class="textrm" mathvariant="normal">Z</mml:mtext><mml:mi>&#945;</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext class="textrm" mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mtext></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><p>Where <italic toggle="yes">y</italic> is the vector of phenotypic observations; <italic toggle="yes">X</italic> is an incidence matrix relating the phenotypes to the fixed effects including lactation stage, parity, test day milk yield, and the level of exotic inheritance computed by admixture analysis; &#946; is the vector of fixed effects; <italic toggle="yes">Z</italic> is incidence matrix of genotypes (0 for the first homozygote AA; 1 for the heterozygote AB or BA; 2 for the second homozygote BB) of the fitted SNP; &#945; is the vector of effects of the regression coefficient for SNPs, and <italic toggle="yes">e</italic> is the vector of residual effects with a normal distribution <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> ~ (0, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" overflow="scroll"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#963;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>), where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" overflow="scroll"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#963;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> is the residual variance.</p><p>The Bonferroni correction using 0.05/N, where &#8220;N&#8221; is the number of SNPs, was applied to the genome-wide significance threshold (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). The SNP effects were declared significant at a genome-wide level of <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 1.20 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup> (0.05/41,427). Since Bonferroni correction was stringent, a suggestive significance threshold of <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 2.41 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup> (1/41,427) was calculated (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Association between individual SNPs and each trait are shown in the Manhattan plot using R.</p><p>The Ensembl database UMDv3.1 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ensembl.org/Bos_taurus/Info/Annotation" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ensembl.org/Bos_taurus/Info/Annotation</ext-link>) was used to search for genes flanking a region of 500 kb from the genome-wide significant and suggestive SNPs using BEDtools (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Candidate genes close or containing significant SNPs were analyzed for functional enrichment using DAVID 6.8 (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). The significantly enriched pathways were identified based on enriched scores.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results and Discussion</title><p>The descriptive statistics for protein percentage and 6 individual minerals (Ca, P, Cu, Mn, Zn, and Fe) in the milk of Vrindavani cattle are presented in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. A total of 9 (2 genome-wide and 7 suggestive) significant SNPs for protein percentage; and 53 (11 genome-wide and 42 suggestive) significant SNPs for six different mineral traits were identified.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Descriptive statistics for protein percentage (%) and mineral (Ca, P, Cu, Mn, Zn, and Fe) in the Vrindavani milk.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Traits</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mean</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SD</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Min</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Max</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CV</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein percentage(%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.814</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.193</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.480</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.170</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.859</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca(mg/l)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,471</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">589</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">681</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,960</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.015</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P(mg/l)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,192</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">319</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">602</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,360</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.762</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zn(mg/l)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.694</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.526</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.130</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.773</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.310</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cu(mg/l)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.892</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.709</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.130</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.213</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.442</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe (mg/l)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.925</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.423</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.180</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.400</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.560</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mn(mg/l)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.794</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.350</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.180</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.930</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.121</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec><title>Protein Percentage</title><p>For protein percentage, two genome-wide significant SNPs (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 1.20 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup>) and 7 suggestive significant SNPs (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 2.41 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup>) were detected on BTA 3, BTA 6, BTA18, and BTA22 (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>; <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Of these, four significant SNPs found on BTA18 (7.63-99.15Mb) includes Beta-carotene oxygenase 1(<italic toggle="yes">BCO1</italic>), C-Maf inducing protein <italic toggle="yes">(CMIP</italic>), N-terminal EF-hand calcium binding protein 2 <italic toggle="yes">(NECAB2</italic>), Cadherin 13 (<italic toggle="yes">CDH13</italic>), oxidative stress induced growth inhibitor 1 (<italic toggle="yes">OSGIN1</italic>) and Solute carrier family 38 member 8 (<italic toggle="yes">SLC38A8</italic>) genes.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Manhattan plots for protein percentage in Vrindavani cattle milk. The red line represents genome-wide significant level (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 1.20 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup>), and the blue line represents suggestive significant level (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 2.41 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup>).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-760364-g0001.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Genome-wide and suggestive significant SNPs for protein percentage in Vrindavani milk.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SNP</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>BTA</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Position</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>P-value</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Nearest candidate gene</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-73708</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8037156</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.16 x 10<sup>&#8722;07</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BCO1, CMIP</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-85875</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9948949</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NECAB2, CDH13</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-39549</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9915057</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OSGIN1,<break/>SLC38A8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hapmap24079-BTA-136416</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21000933</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.25 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BHLHE40</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hapmap33287-BTC-032371</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33026144</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hapmap33121-BTC-033043</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33441527</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hapmap52589-rs29020496</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7630875</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CENPN, CMC2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-1337</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113666410</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USP 40, ATG16L1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTB-00158861</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113701688</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.28 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MROH2A, UGT1A1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Minerals</title><p>Among minerals, a total of 4, 17, 10, 7, and 15 significant SNPs were detected for Ca, P, Cu, Zn, and Fe, respectively. However, no significant SNP was detected for Mn (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2A-F</xref>; <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Manhattan plots for minerals in Vrindavani cattle milk. <bold>(A)</bold> Ca, <bold>(B)</bold> P, <bold>(C)</bold> Cu, <bold>(D)</bold> Zn, <bold>(E)</bold> Fe, <bold>(F)</bold> Mn. The red line represents genome-wide significant level (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 1.20 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup>), and the blue line represents suggestive significant level (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 2.41 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup>).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-760364-g0002.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Genome-wide and suggestive significant SNPs for minerals (Ca, P, Cu, Zn, Fe, and Mn) in Vrindavani milk.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Minerals</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SNP</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>BTA</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Position</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Nearest candidate gene</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTB-01363189</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86130978</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.20 x 10<sup>&#8722;08</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HAPLN1, VCAN</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTB-00005259</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86801082</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29 x 10<sup>&#8722;07</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EDIL3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTB-01259879</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89658972</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29 x 10<sup>&#8722;07</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RASA1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTB-00326076</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86044835</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.72 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XRCC4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hapmap45428-BTA-47987</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72214554</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.89 x 10<sup>&#8722;09</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">INHBB,CFAP221</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-85372</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72369610</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.47 x 10<sup>&#8722;08</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CFAP221</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hapmap39006-BTA-116188</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30481073</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SCN9A,SCN1A, SCN7A, TTC21B</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTB-01987495</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29215002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XIRP2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTB-01902301</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59461527</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.91 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HNMT</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UA-IFASA-4860</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20472340</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.17 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESRRG</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-20615</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5085168</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.67 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NAALAD2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-105277</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65530435</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.04 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NAT10</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-20993</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70957217</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.92 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EN1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-109852</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61611083</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CXCR4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-104967</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55642499</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CDH4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hapmap38699-BTA-81626</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55831708</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-58619</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71779928</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CFAP221</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-25171</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34486610</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARID3B</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hapmap60572-rs29010980</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78157760</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRB1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hapmap49377-BTA-91839</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21134492</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.28 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ESRRG</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-82451</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81016831</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.37 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CACNA1S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cu</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-1062</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92082212</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.68 x 10<sup>&#8722;07</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DHCR24, USP 24</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cu</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTB-01155381</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79282515</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">INSL5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cu</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTA-59703-no-rs</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22197501</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.73 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CACNG3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cu</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTB-00280101</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110508154</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.04 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CLNK</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cu</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTA-107777-no-rs</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73921609</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.19 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cu</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-100916</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105095758</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.61 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PPP2R2C</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cu</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTB-01951920</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21332376</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PPA2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cu</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-116643</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96258114</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.25 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLXNA4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cu</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hapmap32870-BTA-162083</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14189730</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SLC6A15</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cu</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-54036</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48734443</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.24 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALG14,ABCD3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zn</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-76248</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8879810</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50 x 10<sup>&#8722;07</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST3GAL1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zn</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hapmap31987-BTC-062044</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8425401</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.59 x 10<sup>&#8722;07</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZFAT</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zn</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UA-IFASA-7842</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9472109</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHF20L1,KCNQ3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zn</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-BAC-10375</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6616434</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.42 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zn</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hapmap26527-BTC-005059</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4176618</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.31 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGO2, DENND3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zn</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-92308</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67081069</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MANBAL</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zn</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-94105</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7691228</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FBXL2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-96204</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65600025</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.26 x 10<sup>&#8722;07</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NCKAP5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-32707</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67078207</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.59 x 10<sup>&#8722;07</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTA-11592-rs29017351</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69569936</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CFAP221</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-101411</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72163562</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">INHBB</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-22157</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71906695</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.42 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMEM177</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTB-01536946</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68429456</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.70 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DPP10</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-29914</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42706451</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.38 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DPY19L3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hapmap40319-BTA-19899</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102634206</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.86 x 10<sup>&#8722;06</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VWC2L</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-5074</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43588701</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RHPN2, FAAP24, LRP3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hapmap43494-BTA-122491</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94570405</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-60714</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102060979</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IKZF2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hapmap49519-BTA-19205</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68058489</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DPP10</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-113875</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3106988</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACTR1B, ZAP70</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ARS-BFGL-NGS-40198</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2617295</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">YTHDC2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fe</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hapmap57118-rs29009938</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39365195</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35 x 10<sup>&#8722;05</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EPB41L3</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>A total three genome-wide significant and 1 suggestive significant SNPs on BTA7 (86.04-89.65Mb) were found to be associated with Ca. The region contains several genes including Hyaluronan and proteoglycan link protein 1 (<italic toggle="yes">HAPLN1</italic>), Versican (<italic toggle="yes">VCAN</italic>), EGF like repeats, and discoidin domains 3 (<italic toggle="yes">EDIL3</italic>). A total of three genome-wide and 14 suggestive significant SNPs were found to be associated with P. The most significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 6.89 x 10<sup>&#8722;09</sup>) associated SNP (Hapmap45428-BTA-47987) was located 0.10 Mb downstream from Inhibin subunit beta B (<italic toggle="yes">INHBB</italic>) gene and 0.81 Mb downstream from Cilia and flagella associated protein 221 (<italic toggle="yes">CFAP221</italic>) gene on BTA2. Total 1 genome-wide and 9 suggestive significant SNPs were observed to be associated with Cu. The most significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 1.68 x 10<sup>&#8722;07</sup>) associated SNP (ARS-BFGL-NGS-1062) with Cu was identified at 0.63 Mb downstream from the 24-dehydrocholesterol reductase (<italic toggle="yes">DHCR 24</italic>) gene on BTA3. The SNP (BTA-59703-no-rs) significantly associated with Cu (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 4.73 x10<sup>&#8722;06</sup>) on BTA25 was located within Calcium voltage-gated channel auxiliary subunit gamma 3 (<italic toggle="yes">CACNG3</italic>) gene. A total of 2 genome-wide and 5 suggestive significant SNP were associated with Zn. Out of these 7 SNPs, 5 significant SNPs were located within 5.29 Mb (4.17-9.47 Mb) region of BTA14. The most significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 3.50 x 10<sup>&#8722;07</sup>) SNP (ARS-BFGL-NGS-76248) associated with Zn was located 0.09 Mb upstream from the ST3 beta-galactoside alpha-1 (<italic toggle="yes">ST3GAL1</italic>) gene. A total of 2 genome-wide and 15 suggestive significant SNPs were significantly associated with Fe. Total six significant SNPs were identified within 4.10 Mb region (65.60-72.17 Mb) on BTA2. The most significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 3.26 x 10<sup>&#8722;07</sup>) SNP (ARS- BFGL-NGS-96204) associated with Fe was located 0.45 Mb away from <italic toggle="yes">NCKAP5</italic> gene on BTA2. The most significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 1.02 x 10<sup>&#8722;04</sup>) associated SNP (Hapmap58269-rs29018185) with Mn was located on BTA 19, although it was below the cut-off threshold level of significance.</p><p>The functional enrichment of genes close to significant SNPs was involved in ion transport (GO:0005248), metal ion binding (GO:0005509), integral and transmembrane protein (GO:0086010), and signaling pathway (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>).</p><p>In the present study, several significant SNPs found to be associated with protein percentage and individual mineral concentration in the milk of Vrindavani cattle. To our knowledge, this is the first study to identify genomic regions associated with milk mineral content in composite Vrindavani cattle. Detection of several previously reported genes and genomic regions associated with different milk composition traits indicates their potential role in regulating the concentration of minerals and protein percentage in bovine milk.</p><p>For protein percentage, the significant 1.9 Mb region (8.03-9.94 Mb) on BTA 18 was partly overlapping with previously reported QTLs associated with milk coagulation (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). The milk coagulation is directly influenced by the casein composition, which indicates that this region may have the potential to influence the protein percentage in milk (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). This region includes the <italic toggle="yes">CDH 13</italic> (Cadherin-13) gene which is expressed in mammary tissues and associated with the protein content of the milk (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>).</p><p>On BTA2, 18 significant SNPs were identified for P and Fe content. Two significant SNPs associated with P and Fe were 0.10 and 0.35 Mb away from the inhibin subunit beta B (<italic toggle="yes">INHBB</italic>) gene on BTA2. In humans, <italic toggle="yes">INHBB</italic> gene plays a major role in regulating calcium and phosphorus during bone formation (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). More specifically, <italic toggle="yes">INHBB</italic> facilitates interaction with the beta glycan, which stimulates extracellular matrix mineralisation (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). The SNP associated with Fe is located 0.35 Mb downstream from the IKAROS family zinc finger 2 (<italic toggle="yes">IKZF2</italic>) is involved in metal ion binding (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) and host immune response (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p><p>On BTA3, three significant SNPs were associated with milk Cu content. Buitenhuis et al. (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>) identified several significant SNPs for Cu on BTA3 (91.0-91.3 Mb) in Danish Holstein milk. However, these SNPs do not overlap with the significant SNPs for Cu identified in our study. The most significant SNP associated with Cu is located 0.79 Mb upstream from the Ubiquitin Specific Peptidase 24 (<italic toggle="yes">USP24</italic>) gene. The <italic toggle="yes">USP24</italic> gene belongs to the cysteine proteases family and plays role in protein deubiquitination of the proteins which influences the stability of the casein micelle in the milk (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). However, the role of this gene in the regulation of milk Cu concentration is not known.</p><p>On BTA7, four significant SNPs associated with Ca, were located close to <italic toggle="yes">HAPLNI, VCAN</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">EDIL3</italic> genes. These genes are referred to as calcium-binding proteins (GO:0050850, positive regulation of calcium-mediated signaling) and are involved in tissue calcification and bone mineralization in vertebrates (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). In chickens, the EGF-like repeats and discoidin domains 3 (<italic toggle="yes">EDIL3</italic>) gene bind with the calcium ion to guide vesicular transportation of minerals during eggshell calcification (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Even though its role in milk calcium is not known, <italic toggle="yes">EDIL3</italic> could be considered as a candidate gene, which warrants fine mapping.</p><p>The SNP named Hapmap3 1987-BTC-062044 was significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 3.50 x 10<sup>&#8722;07</sup>) associated with Zn, is located at 0.12 Mb away from the Zinc finger and AT-hook domain containing (ZFAT) on BTA14, which is involved in the transcription of immune-related genes.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s4"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our study identified several candidate genes associated with milk protein percentage and milk minerals, that are involved in ion transport, signaling pathways <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> integral protein, transmembrane membranes, zinc-fingers, and metal ion binding. The strongest association for protein percentage was identified on BTA18. Among studied minerals, the strongest association for Ca, P, Cu, Zn, and Fe were found on BTA 7, 2, 3, 14, and 2, respectively. These roles of genes and genomic regions suggested that milk mineral concentration is probably regulated by transportation and homeostasis of ions. These identified variants are a step forward to characterize the molecular mechanism affecting milk minerals in Vrindavani cattle. However, additional validation of detected variants and their association with milk minerals is required on large sample size.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s5"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The datasets presented in this study can be found in online repositories. The names of the repository/repositories and accession number(s) can be found at: Figshare, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://figshare.com/articles/dataset/Genotypes/12808343/2" ext-link-type="uri">https://figshare.com/articles/dataset/Genotypes/12808343/2</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by Institute Animal Ethics Committee of Indian Veterinary Research Institute, Bareilly.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>AK conceived and designed the experiments. AS and AK performed the experiments, analyzed the data, and wrote the paper. CG, AP, and TD contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="s8"><title>Funding</title><p>This project work was supported by the CAAST-ACLH project of NAHEP. AS was recipient of fellowship from ICMR fellowship during her PhD programme.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s9"><title>Publisher's Note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s10"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2022.760364/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2022.760364/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_1.XLSX" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buitenhuis</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poulsen</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sehested</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Estimation of genetic parameters and detection of quantitative trait loci for minerals in Danish Holstein and Danish Jersey milk</article-title>. <source>BMC Genet</source>. (<year>2015</year>) 16: 1&#8211;8. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12863-015-0209-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25989905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4438472</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vegarud</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langsrud</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Svenning</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mineral-binding milk proteins and peptides; occurrence, biochemical and technological characteristics</article-title>. <source>British J Nutr</source>. (<year>2000</year>) <volume>84</volume>(<issue>S1</issue>):<fpage>91</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007114500002300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11242452</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boussaha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoz&#233;</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brochard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Sequence-based GWAS and post-GWAS analyses reveal a key role of SLC37A1, ANKH, and regulatory regions on bovine milk mineral content</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-87078-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33824377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8024349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cashman</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Milk minerals (including trace elements) and bone health</article-title>. <source>Int Dairy J</source>. (<year>2006</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1389</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>98</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.idairyj.2006.06.017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#243;rska-Warsewicz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rejman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laskowski</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Czeczotko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Milk and dairy products and their nutritional contribution to the average polish diet</article-title>. <source>Nutrients</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1771</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nu11081771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31374893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6723869</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diniz</surname><given-names>WJDS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tizioto</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cesar</surname><given-names>ASM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gromboni</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nogueira</surname><given-names>ARA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Iron content affects lipogenic gene expression in the muscle of Nelore beef cattle</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e0161160</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0161160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27532424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4988672</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toffanin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Marchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Villalobos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassandro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness of mid-infrared spectroscopy for prediction of the contents of calcium and phosphorus, and titratable acidity of milk and their relationship with milk quality and coagulation properties</article-title>. <source>Int Dairy J</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>68</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.idairyj.2014.10.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malacarne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franceschi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Formaggioni</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mariani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Summer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of micellar calcium and phosphorus on rennet coagulation properties of cows milk</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Res</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>81</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0022029913000630</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24345431</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manuelian</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Penasa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Visentin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zidi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cassandro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Marchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mineral composition of cow milk from multibreed herds</article-title>. <source>Anim Sci J.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>1622</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/asj.13095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30221430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaudhary</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jadhav</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naskar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Factors affecting milk minerals and constituents in indigenous vis-&#224;-vis crossbred cattle and buffaloes</article-title>. <source>Ind J Anim Sci</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genome-wide association study for milk protein composition traits in a Chinese Holstein population using a single-step approach</article-title>. <source>Front Genet</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>72</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fgene.2019.00072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30838020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6389681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van den Berg</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jenko</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pausch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boussaha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schrooten</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Meta-analysis for milk fat and protein percentage using imputed sequence variant genotypes in 94,321 cattle from eight cattle breeds</article-title>. <source>Genet Sel Evol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12711-020-00556-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32635893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7339598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehrotra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gondro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Silva Romero</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karthikeyan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Signatures of selection in composite vrindavani cattle of India</article-title>. <source>Front Genet</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>589496</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fgene.2020.589496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33391343</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7775581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trancoso</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roseiro</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trancoso</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Validation and quality assurance applied to goat milk chemical composition: minerals and trace elements measurements</article-title>. <source>Dairy Sci Technol</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>241</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/dst/2009013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Todd-Brown</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>PLINK: a tool set for whole-genome association and population-based linkage analyses</article-title>. <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>81</volume>:<fpage>559</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>75</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/519795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17701901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1950838</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Novembre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fast model-based estimation of ancestry in unrelated individuals</article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1655</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.094052.109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19648217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2752134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gondro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Genome wide association studies</article-title>. In: <source>Primer to Analysis of Genomic Data Using R</source>. <publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name> (<year>2015</year>). p. 73-103.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eskin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rapid and accurate multiple testing correction and power estimation for millions of correlated markers</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e1000456</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1000456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19381255</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2663787</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genome wide association study identifies 20 novel promising genes associated with milk fatty acid traits in Chinese Holstein</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e96186</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24858810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4032272</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quinlan</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>BEDTools: a flexible suite of utilities for comparing genomic features</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>841</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20110278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2832824</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lempicki</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bioinformatics enrichment tools: paths toward the comprehensive functional analysis of large gene lists</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkn923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19033363</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2615629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duchemin</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Glantz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Koning</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paulsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fikse</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of QTL on chromosome 18 associated with non-coagulating milk in Swedish Red cows</article-title>. <source>Front Genet</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fgene.2016.00057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27148354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4832587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frederiksen</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hammersh&#248;j</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Poulsen</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>S&#248;rensen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Composition and effect of blending of noncoagulating, poorly coagulating, and well-coagulating bovine milk from individual Danish Holstein cows</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>94</volume>:<fpage>4787</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>99</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2011-4343</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21943730</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glantz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gustavsson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertelsen</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>St&#229;lhammar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindmark-M&#229;nsson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paulsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Bovine chromosomal regions affecting rheological traits in acid-induced skim milk gels</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>1273</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2014-8137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25529417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farr</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roforth</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicks</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of age and estrogen on skeletal gene expression in humans as assessed by RNA sequencing</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e0138347</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26402159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4581624</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eijken</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Swagemakers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koedam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steenbergen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Derkx</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uitterlinden</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The activin A-follistatin system: Potent regulator of human extracellular matrix mineralization</article-title>. <source>FASEB J</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>2949</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1096/fj.07-8080com</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17449718</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cizkova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cizeron-Clairac</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vacher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Susini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrieu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lidereau</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Gene expression profiling reveals new aspects of PIK3CA mutation in ERalpha-positive breast cancer: major implication of the Wnt signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e15647</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0015647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21209903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3012715</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reverter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ballester</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alexandre</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#225;rmol-S&#225;nchez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalmau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quintanilla</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A gene co-association network regulating gut microbial communities in a Duroc pig population</article-title>. <source>Microbiome</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40168-020-00994-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33612109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7898758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wickramasinghe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rincon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Islas-Trejo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Medrano</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Transcriptional profiling of bovine milk using RNA sequencing</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-13-45</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22276848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3285075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kook</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The extracellular matrix protein Edil3 stimulates osteoblast differentiation through the integrin &#945;5&#946;1/ERK/Runx2 pathway</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e0188749</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0188749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29182679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5705136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gautron</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stapane</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Roy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nys</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez-Navarro</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hincke</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Avian eggshell biomineralization: an update on its structure, mineralogy and protein tool kit. BMC Mol</article-title>. <source>Cell Biol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12860-021-00350-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33579194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7881572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>