<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9893768</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC9893768.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">9893768</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">9893768</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36744221</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.1126460</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial: Helminth biodiversity</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sim&#245;es</surname><given-names initials="RDO">Raquel de Oliveira</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1052438/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robles</surname><given-names initials="MDR">Mar&#237;a del Rosario</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Departamento de Parasitologia Animal, Universidade Federal Rural Do Rio de Janeiro</institution>, <addr-line>Serop&#233;dica</addr-line>, <country>Brazil</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Centro Cient&#237;fico Tecnol&#243;gico La Plata (CONICET-UNLP), Facultad de Ciencias Naturales y Museo, Centro de Estudios Parasitol&#243;gicos y de Vectores</institution>, <addr-line>Buenos Aires</addr-line>, <country>Argentina</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited and reviewed by: Antoinette Marsh, The Ohio State University, United States</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Raquel de Oliveira Sim&#245;es &#9993; <email>raquel83vet@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Parasitology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">400313</issue-id><elocation-id>1126460</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>03</day><month>02</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-02-06 16:10:12.467"><day>06</day><month>02</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 Sim&#245;es and Robles.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sim&#245;es and Robles</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-09-1126460.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="commentary-article" xml:lang="en" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/26032/helminth-biodiversity"/><kwd-group><kwd>parasitology</kwd><kwd>taxonomy</kwd><kwd>ecology</kwd><kwd>phylogeny</kwd><kwd>biology</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="14"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="1661"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Biodiversity conservation has been a global concern, mainly due to the growing disturbance in the structure and function of ecosystems (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Consequently, this results in the loss of native diversity, including parasites from different vertebrate hosts (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). In view of this, the knowledge of helminth biodiversity is extremely important, since parasites can also bring relevant information about environmental stress, structure, and function in the food chain and biodiversity (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>).</p><p>The importance of recording biodiversity is compromised by the so-called taxonomy crisis. The purely taxonomic aims, which involve describing species, are conditioned by other aspects of interest, particularly economic-productive and/or sanitary-epidemiological. This situation is reflected in reduced inventories and concentrated representation of certain taxonomic groups. Other situations that are observed are the concentration of specialists in charismatic taxonomic groups, or in those that &#8220;inherit&#8221; from their trainers, leaving many groups unexplored. There are also the problems of generational replacement since there is little interest from the new generations of biologists in the discipline [e.g., (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>)].</p><p>In this context, within the framework of the parasitological discipline, the fact that parasitic organisms are a group that is not precisely characterized by concentrating efforts for their conservation is added to this crisis. In contrast, the parasites are usually approached with the objectives of partial eradication, in the case of those of medical-veterinary importance, while the rest, which is an integral part of the ecosystems, represent a very low portion of the goals of interest (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). In addition, it is even more worrying that the taxonomic aspects of different helminth groups are often underestimated and do not have a place in high-impact journals.</p><p>The aim of this Research Topic is to broaden and deepen the knowledge about helminths in wildlife or domestic hosts around the world focusing on the contribution to the taxonomic groups, ecology, phylogenetic, and biology. Thus, a multidisciplinary approach is given and can be used as a guide for scientific information. In this special collection, there are seven papers covering the following aspects.</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>(1) A new species of <italic toggle="yes">Pterygodermatites</italic> (Nematoda: Spirurida) is described as parasitizing the gastrointestinal tract of the didelphid marsupial <italic toggle="yes">Marmosa constantiae</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2022.955453" ext-link-type="uri">Andrade-Silva et al.</ext-link>). This marsupial was collected in the transitional phytogeography formed by ecotones from Cerrado/Amazon biomes in the north of the state of Mato Grosso, Brazil. These biomes are characterized by considerable biodiversity of mammals [(<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) and little known or characterized parasites in the <italic toggle="yes">M. constantiae</italic>].</p></list-item><list-item><p>(2) The use of integrative taxonomy is a useful tool for the diagnosis of species morphologically similar, mainly in the larval stage. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2022.909163" ext-link-type="uri">Santoro et al.</ext-link>, using scanning electron microscopy and molecular analysis, characterized the larvae of the cestode belonging to the family Gymnorhynchidae. These larvae infect the edible musculature of the Atlantic pomfret in the Mediterranean. The integrative taxonomy allowed for accurate discrimination between larvae of <italic toggle="yes">Molicola uncinatus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Gymnorhynchus gigas</italic> in co-infection.</p></list-item><list-item><p>(3) A review of cestodes that parasites Neotropical hystricomorphic rodent was done by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2022.885678" ext-link-type="uri">Jones</ext-link>. This update aimed to identify the cestodes found in the hunted rodent. Metacestodes of <italic toggle="yes">Echinococcus vogeli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Echinococcus oligarthrus</italic> were commonly found in the liver, muscle, and subcutaneous tissue of lappe (<italic toggle="yes">Cuniculus paca</italic>) and agouti (<italic toggle="yes">Dasyprocta leporine</italic>). In contrast, these cestode larvae were not recorded in the tissues of the capybara (<italic toggle="yes">Hydrochoerus hydrochaeris</italic>). This demonstrates the distinct feeding habits among capybara, agouti, and lappe and shows the importance of these animals as intermediate hosts of these zoonotic cestodes.</p></list-item><list-item><p>(4) Synanthropic rodents such as <italic toggle="yes">Mus musculus, Rattus rattus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Rattus norvegicus</italic> affect the ecology of the native communities (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>) as well as the epidemiology of some diseases, once infected with parasites (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Describing the pattern of gastrointestinal helminth infection from these rodents helps to understand the dispersion of helminths. In this work, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2022.929208" ext-link-type="uri">Grand&#243;n-Ojeda</ext-link> examined the helminths from the stomach and intestines of introduced rats in Chile and characterized the association between the abundance of parasites and biotic and abiotic factors.</p></list-item><list-item><p>(5) Many species of mollusks harbor nematodes of medically important and act as paratenic or intermediate hosts (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2022.1023426" ext-link-type="uri">Thiengo et al.</ext-link> evaluated and summarized the parasitological analyses done by their reference laboratory and reported the presence of nematodes with human and veterinary importance found in terrestrial snails in Brazil. This study is important to the knowledge of parasite transmission and the information produced can be used as a subsidy for control measures and parasite disease transmission, mainly where invasive mollusks are present.</p></list-item><list-item><p>(6) A case report of a female dog infected with aggressive <italic toggle="yes">Dirofilaria immitis</italic> infection is given (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2022.868115" ext-link-type="uri">Taweethavonsawat et al.</ext-link>). This article describes the clinical signs and procedure to remove the nematode from the heart and erratic places. The histopathology, molecular biology, and technique of necropsy were also reported in this case.</p></list-item><list-item><p>(7) The last article presented in this collection is a study that evaluated the usefulness of matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometry (MALDI-TOF MS) as an effective diagnostic tool for the specific identification of <italic toggle="yes">Trichuris</italic> (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2022.867919" ext-link-type="uri">Rivero et al.</ext-link>). The initial study confirmed the efficiency of MALDI-TOF MS as a fast and secure method for the correct identification of <italic toggle="yes">Trichuris</italic> species. Additionally, a MALDI-TOF MS profile of <italic toggle="yes">T. suis</italic> proteome was carried out to develop the first internal database of spectra for the diagnosis of trichuriasis and other <italic toggle="yes">Trichuris</italic> spp.</p></list-item></list><p>In summary, the studies and review above mentioned contribute to the knowledge of the taxonomy, biology, ecology, and diagnostic of helminth biodiversity around the world. These reports demonstrate the importance and necessity of studies in several aspects related to helminthology. After reading these articles, the reader will have an overview of helminth biodiversity and how much is not known and still needs to be done.</p><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>MR wrote the introduction and revised the text. RS wrote the central part with comments on the cited articles, conclusions, and references. Both authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s2"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hern&#225;ndez</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in the dynamics of functional groups in communities of dung beetles in Atlantic forest fragments adjacent to transgenic maize crops</article-title>. <source>Ecol Indic.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>216</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolind.2014.09.043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lafferty</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Biodiversity loss decreases parasite diversity: theory and patterns</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>367</volume>:<fpage>2814</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2012.0110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22966137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3427564</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poulin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Phylogeny, ecology and the richness of parasite communities in vertebrates</article-title>. <source>Ecol Monogr.</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>283</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>302</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2937061</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lafferty</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allesina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dobson</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Parasites in food webs: the ultimate missing links</article-title>. <source>Ecol Lett.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>533</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1461-0248.2008.01174.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18462196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2408649</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marcogliese</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Parasites: Small players with crucial roles in the ecological theater</article-title>. <source>Ecohealth.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10393-004-0028-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ho&#322;y&#324;ski</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Taxonomy crisis, biodiversity disaster&#8211;and sabotaging regulations</article-title>. <source>MunisEnt Zool.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayo</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Allkin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bake</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blagoderov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brake</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Alpha e-taxonomy: responses from the systematics community to the biodiversity crisis</article-title>. <source>Kew Bulletin</source>. (<year>2003</year>) <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12225-008-9014-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Poulin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Parasites and the neutral theory of biodiversity</article-title>. <source>Ecography.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>129</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0906-7590.2004.03695.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lacher</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alho</surname><given-names>CJR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Terrestrial small mammal richness and habitat associations in an Amazon Forest&#8211;Cerrado contact zone</article-title>. <source>Biotropica.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>171</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1744-7429.2001.tb00166.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A review of the evidence for potential impacts of black rats (Rattus rattus) on wildlife and humans in Australia</article-title>. <source>Wildlife Res.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>78</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>88</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/WR11086</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bordes</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H-W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Claude</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cosson</surname><given-names>J-F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Global parasite and <italic toggle="yes">Rattus</italic> rodent invasions: the consequences for rodent-borne diseases</article-title>. <source>Integr Zool.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>409</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1749-4877.12143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26037785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cowie</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Diverse of gastropod hosts of <italic toggle="yes">Angiostrongylus cantonensis</italic>, the rat lungworm, globally and with a focus on the Hawaiian Islands</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e94969</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0094969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24788772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4008484</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morassutti</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiengo</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sawanyawisuth</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graeff-Teixeira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Eosinophilic meningitis caused by <italic toggle="yes">Angiostrongylus cantonensis</italic>: an emergent disease in Brazil</article-title>. <source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>109</volume>:<fpage>399</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>407</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0074-0276140023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25075779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4155839</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oliveira</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>KL</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sim&#245;es</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Decanine</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>First report of <italic toggle="yes">Achatina fulica</italic> (Bowdich, 1822) naturally infected with nematodes from the families Angiostrongylidae and Rhabditidae in the city of Campo Grande, Mato Grosso do Sul, Brasil</article-title>. <source>J Neotrop Biol</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>83</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5216/rbn.v18i2.839</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>