<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9257223</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC9257223.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">9257223</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">9257223</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35812883</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.927185</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Prevalence and Molecular Characterization of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara cati</italic> Among Stray and Household Cats and Cat Owners in Tehran, Iran</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karimi</surname><given-names initials="P">Poorya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1784811/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shafaghi-Sisi</surname><given-names initials="S">Soheila</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meamar</surname><given-names initials="AR">Ahmad Reza</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1784169/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasiri</surname><given-names initials="G">Gelareh</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Razmjou</surname><given-names initials="E">Elham</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1677279/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Parasitology and Mycology, School of Medicine, Iran University of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Tehran</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Microbiology, School of Medicine, Shahid Beheshti University of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Tehran</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Vikrant Sudan, Guru Angad Dev Veterinary and Animal Sciences University, India</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Veeranoot Nissapatorn, Walailak University, Thailand; Amir Abdoli, Jahrom University of Medical Sciences, Iran; Jay Prakash Yadav, GADVASU, India</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Elham Razmjou <email>razmjou.e@iums.ac.ir</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Parasitology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">400313</issue-id><elocation-id>927185</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>5</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>07</day><month>07</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-14 14:25:20.380"><day>14</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2022 Karimi, Shafaghi-Sisi, Meamar, Nasiri and Razmjou.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Karimi, Shafaghi-Sisi, Meamar, Nasiri and Razmjou</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-09-927185.pdf"/><abstract><p><italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. are the most critical parasites common between humans and cats. The close association of cats with humans in urban areas persuaded us to investigate the prevalence of these parasites in stray and household cats and their possible role in the owners' infection. Herein, 132 and 33 fecal samples of stray and household cats, respectively, and 33 blood samples of their owners were collected in Tehran, Iran. The prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> was determined by targeting the <italic toggle="yes">B1</italic> gene in the feces of stray and household cats and the blood of cat owners. Furthermore, genotypes of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> were identified based on the multilocus genotyping of BTUB, GRA6, SAG3, and APICO loci. <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. were detected by targeting the second internal transcribed spacer (ITS-2) of the ribosomal DNA of these parasites in the cats' feces and the humans' blood. Also, <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> IgG was assessed in the human serum samples. The <italic toggle="yes">B1</italic> gene amplification showed that 15.2% of stray cats, 18.2% of household cats, and 51.5% of cat owners were infected with <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>. The multilocus sequence analysis revealed the predominance of genotype I of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> in stray cats and genotype II of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> in household cats and cat owners. The amplifying of ITS-2 revealed a high prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> infection (47.0%) in stray cats, whereas no infection was found in the feces of household cats or the serum of cat owners. Likewise, <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> IgG was not detected in the serum of humans. The lower prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> in stray/household cats than in the cat owners indicates the limited impact of close contact with infected cats in human toxoplasmosis. However, the high prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> infection in stray cats can cause contamination of the environment by excreting eggs that may lead to infecting humans through soil or water. Therefore, public health education in urban management planning is necessary for routine urban cat deworming programs and for training the healthcare workers to prevent, control, and treat these infections.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic></kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp.</kwd><kwd>zoonosis</kwd><kwd>human</kwd><kwd>cat</kwd><kwd>public health</kwd><kwd>Tehran</kwd><kwd>Iran</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="4"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="56"/><page-count count="13"/><word-count count="8679"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Cats (<italic toggle="yes">Felis catus</italic>) have lived in human societies for thousands of years, with a population of over 600 million worldwide. They are the most popular companion animal globally. Approximately 373 million cats were kept as pets in the world in 2018. (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/1044386/dog-and-cat-pet-population-worldwide/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.statista.com/statistics/1044386/dog-and-cat-pet-population-worldwide/</ext-link>). However, it is difficult to determine the number of cats that live freely in human societies (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Cats harbor some important zoonotic parasites that can affect public health. Toxoplasmosis and toxocariasis are the most important parasitic diseases common between humans and cats (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>).</p><p>Toxoplasmosis, caused by <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic>, is one of the most common protozoan parasitic infections in humans and animals. It is estimated that about two billion of the world's population are chronically infected with this obligate intracellular protozoan parasite (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Toxoplasmosis generally remains asymptomatic in people with effective immune responses. However, the acute disease may manifest symptoms such as fever, lymphocytosis, and lymphadenitis. The severe form of the disease rarely leads to encephalitis, pneumonia, muscle disorders, and death. Furthermore, early infection during pregnancy may cause abortion (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infections are acquired by consuming undercooked meat containing tissue cysts or contaminated food and water with oocysts defecated from cats that sporulate in the soil during 1&#8211;5 days (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>).</p><p>The oocysts of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma, Neospora</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Hammondia</italic> parasites are morphologically indistinguishable. Consequently, molecular methods apply to differentiate <italic toggle="yes">Hammondia</italic>-like organisms in the feline feces (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Molecular analysis has categorized <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> into three genotypes I, II, and III. Genotype II is the most prevalent genotype in humans (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), although animal toxoplasmosis is more closely related to genotypes II and III (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Whereas genotype I of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> is more implicated in acute and lethal infections in humans and animals (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p><p>Stray and household cats, as the definitive hosts of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> in urban communities, through a close relationship with humans, seem to be the leading cause of human infection by passing oocysts in feces (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Hence, information about the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> in stray and household cats and cat owners is necessary to identify the possible role of cats in infecting humans.</p><p>Toxocariasis, caused by zoonotic <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> species, is one of the most frequently reported parasitic zoonosis in humans worldwide (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Members of the <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> genus are among the most common helminths in canids and felids. They include essential human and animal health species, such as <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara cati, Toxocara canis</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Toxascaris leonina</italic>. Epidemiological studies indicate 1&#8211;100% of <italic toggle="yes">T. canis</italic> in dogs and 3.2&#8211;91% of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> in cats (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). The high amount of adult nematodes in the intestines of the definitive hosts leads to the contamination of playgrounds and urban areas that increases the risks of toxocariasis in humans, especially in children. Humans are infected by accidental ingestion of embryonic eggs or by ingesting undercooked meat containing encysted larvae (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Toxocariasis clinical manifestations are visceral larva migrans, ocular larva migrans, latent toxocariasis, and neurological toxocariasis (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). The close association of cats with humans in urban areas makes them an important source of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> infection. Therefore, knowing the exact number of infected cats is very effective for making the necessary decisions to prevent and control this disease. Limited studies on the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. in Iran (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) persuaded us to investigate the prevalence of these parasites in stray and household cats and their possible role in the owners' infection.</p><p>We applied the molecular analyses approach to fill the gap in our understanding of the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. in stray and household cats and determine the possible role of household cats in the infection of their owners. To reach these purposes, we determined the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. by molecular detection of the <italic toggle="yes">B1</italic> gene of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma</italic> and the ITS-2 region of the ribosomal DNA of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. in the feces of stray and household cats and the blood of cat owners in Tehran, Iran. In addition, genotypes of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> were determined to identify the possible role of cats in infecting humans based on the multilocus genotyping of BTUB, GRA6, SAG3, and APICO loci.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Study Areas</title><p>The study area was in Tehran (35.6892&#176; N, 51.3890&#176; E), the largest city and the capital of Iran (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). It covers an area of more than 730 km<sup>2</sup> and has a population of 8.694 million. The climate of Tehran is generally mild and pleasant in spring and autumn, hot and dry in summer, and cold and wet in winter. The average annual temperature in Tehran is 16.4&#176;C, and the mean annual rainfall is 220 mm.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The map of the study area. <bold>(A)</bold> Map of Iran. Tehran Province is indicated by green. <bold>(B)</bold> Map of Tehran Province. Tehran is highlighted in yellow. <bold>(C)</bold> Map of Tehran. The five study areas are indicated, and the percentage of the stray and household cat fecal samples and blood of cat owners collected from each region are shown.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-927185-g0001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Questionnaires</title><p>The cat questionnaire was designed to include information on cat demographic data (sex, age, breed, weight, and residence area). There was no history of anti-parasitic treatments in stray cats, although they confidently did not take these drugs at the sampling time. The questionnaire of household cat owners collected information on demographic data (gender, age, occupation, residence area, and education). The cat owners declared that their cats had received anthelmintic treatments six months before sampling. The questionnaires are available in the <xref rid="SM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Material</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Sample Collection</title><p>The stray cats injured in accidents or diseases have been transferred to veterinary clinics or pet hospitals in different parts of Tehran by animal-loving people or animal welfare associations. From 132 stray cats referred to these centers from different regions of Tehran's open public areas (north, south, east, west, and center), visibly-excreted fecal pellets were collected from October 2017 through March 2018. Thirty-three fecal samples were collected from household cats, and 33 blood samples were taken from their owners from January through September 2019. Six and seven milliliters of venous blood were collected in two tubes with and without EDTA to obtain the buffy coat and serum. Collected samples were transferred immediately to the research laboratory of the Department of Parasitology and Mycology, Iran University of Medical Sciences, for further analysis. Serum and buffy coats were stored at &#8722;80&#176;C until further investigation. The <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> IgG in serum samples was evaluated with an ELISA commercial kit (<italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> IgG ELISA kit; NovaTec Immunodiagnostic GmbH, Germany) following the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec><title>Fecal Samples Preparation</title><p>Fecal samples of stray and household cats (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 165) were submitted to the sucrose flotation procedure for concentrating cysts/oocysts of parasites (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Six to eight grams of each sample was dissolved into 50 mL PBS until a homogeneous suspension was prepared. Then, the suspension was passed through three layers of gauze to eliminate large particles. The fecal suspension was centrifuged at 800&#215;g for 5 min. For isolating cysts/oocysts, 50 mL PBS was added to the sediment. After complete mixing, 25 mL of suspension was layered gently over 20 mL of 1 M sucrose solution (specific gravity 1.13) in a 50 mL cleaned conical tube to form two completely distinct phases. The tubes were centrifuged at 800 &#215; g for 5 min at 4&#176;C. The interface and the upper layer of the sucrose were collected by a disposable pipette to a 15 mL clean conical tube. Then, the collected supernatant containing the purified cysts/oocysts of parasites was recentrifuged and washed three times with PBS to remove the residual sucrose. Finally, 100 mg of the sediment was re-suspended in 200 &#956;L 2% polyvinylpolypyrrolidone (PVPP) in PBS, mixed thoroughly, and after keeping at &#8722;20&#176;C for 24 h, stored at &#8722;80&#176;C until submitted to DNA extraction procedures.</p></sec><sec><title>DNA Extraction</title><p>The genomic DNA of parasites was extracted from fecal samples using the QIAamp DNA Mini Kit (QIAGEN Ltd., Hilden, Germany cat. no. 51306) and from serum or buffy coat using a QIAamp DNA Blood Minikit (QIAGEN Ltd., Hilden, Germany cat. no. 51104) according to the manufacturer's instructions. The isolated DNA was stored at &#8722;20&#176;C until used in PCR reactions.</p></sec><sec><title>PCR Amplification and Molecular Identification</title><p>Molecular identification of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> was performed by a PCR assay based on the 194-bp fragment amplification of the <italic toggle="yes">B1</italic> gene to screen the <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> DNA in the cat fecal samples and the buffy coat of blood samples of household cat owners. The <italic toggle="yes">B1</italic> gene of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> is a multi-copy sequence-specific and highly conserved gene in all <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> strains, making it highly useful in the molecular detection of the parasite (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). The PCR amplification was conducted by the primers designed by Schwab and McDevitt (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) and the PCR procedures introduced in our previous report (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). In addition, the multi-locus genotyping of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> in the <italic toggle="yes">B1</italic>-positive samples was performed based on the BTUB, GRA6, SAG3, and APICO genetic markers (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) by primers designated by Su et al. (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). The nested PCR was performed with Taq DNA Polymerase Master Mix (Amplicon III, Denmark, cat. no. 180301) in the conditions described by Arshadi et al. (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The genotype of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> was determined after sequencing the amplified fragment of each marker by internal amplification primers in both directions (Macrogen Inc., Seoul, South Korea).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Primer sequences and PCR conditions were used for the molecular identification and characterization of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii, Toxocara spp</italic>., and <italic toggle="yes">Toxascaris leonina</italic> in the present study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Target species</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Gene/ Marker</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Primer nucleotide Sequences (5&#8242;-3&#8242;)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Amplicon size (bp)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Ref</bold>.</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Cycling conditions</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Ref</bold>.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">B1</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: GGAACTGCATCCGTTCATGAG<break/> R: TCTTTAAAGCGTTCGTGGTC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">194</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 sec/95&#176;C, 50 sec/55&#176;C, 20 sec/72&#176;C, 40 cycles</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">APICO</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: TGGTTTTAACCCTAGATTGTGG<break/> R: AAACGGAATTAATGAGATTTGAA<break/> F: TGCAAATTCTTGAATTCTCAGTT<break/> R: GGGATTCGAACCCTTGATA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">639</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR 1: 30 sec/95&#176;C, 30 sec/50&#176;C, 30 sec/72&#176;C, 35 cycles PCR 2: 20 sec/95&#176;C, 15 sec/50&#176;C, 20 sec/72&#176;C, 40 cycles</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BTUB</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: TCCAAAATGAGAGAAATCGT<break/> R: AAATTGAAATGACGGAAGAA<break/> F: GAGGTCATCTCGGACGAACA<break/> R: TTGTAGGAACACCCGGACGC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">411</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR 1: 30 sec/95&#176;C, 30 sec/50&#176;C, 30 sec/72&#176;C, 35 cycles PCR 2: 20 sec/95&#176;C, 15 sec/48&#176;C, 20 sec/72&#176;C, 40 cycles</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GRA6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: ATTTGTGTTTCCGAGCAGGT<break/> R: GCACCTTCGCTTGTGGTT<break/> F: TTTCCGAGCAGGTGACCT<break/> R: TCGCCGAAGAGTTGACATAG</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">344</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR 1: 30 sec/95&#176;C, 30 sec/50&#176;C, 30 sec/72&#176;C, 35 cycles PCR 2: 20 sec/95&#176;C, 15 sec/50&#176;C, 20 sec/72&#176;C, 40 cycles</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SAG3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: CAACTCTCACCATTCCACCC<break/> R: GCGCGTTGTTAGACAAGACA<break/> F: TCTTGTCGGGTGTTCACTCA<break/> R: CACAAGGAGACCGAGAAGGA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCR 1: 30 sec/95&#176;C, 30 sec/50&#176;C, 30 sec/72&#176;C, 35 cycles PCR 2: 20 sec/95&#176;C, 15 sec/52&#176;C, 20 sec/72&#176;C, 40 cycles</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ITS-2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: GGAGAAGTAAGATCGTGGCACGCGT<break/> R: TTAGTTTCTTTTCCTCCGCT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">370</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 sec/94&#176;C, 30 sec/58&#176;C, 30 sec/72&#176;C, 35 cycles</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">T. canis</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ITS-2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: AGTATGATGGGCGCGCCAAT<break/> R: TTAGTTTCTTTTCCTCCGCT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">380</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 sec/94&#176;C, 30 sec/58&#176;C, 30 sec/72&#176;C, 35 cycles</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">T. leonina</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ITS-2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F: CGAACGCTCATATAACGGCATACTC<break/> R: TTAGTTTCTTTTCCTCCGCT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 sec/94&#176;C, 30 sec/58&#176;C, 30 sec/72&#176;C, 35 cycles</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Molecular identification of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. and <italic toggle="yes">T. leonina</italic> was performed by species identification PCR procedures to target unique regions of the second internal transcribed spacer (ITS-2) of the ribosomal DNA of <italic toggle="yes">T. canis, T. cati</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">T. leonina</italic>. The amplification of ITS-2 was performed according to the primers and PCR conditions specified by Jacobs et al. (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) in the cat fecal samples and the serum samples of household cat owners. The PCR product of 370 bp from <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic>, 380 bp from <italic toggle="yes">T. canis</italic>, and 300 bp from <italic toggle="yes">T. leonina</italic> were amplified by the Tcat1-NC2, Tcan1-NC2, and Tleo1-NC2 primer sets, respectively (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>PCR reactions were conducted on the samples using primer pairs and conditions listed in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, along with the genomic DNA of the related parasite as a positive control and sterile nuclease-free water as a negative control. The PCR products were analyzed by electrophoresis on 1.5% (w/v) agarose gel.</p></sec><sec><title>Sequencing and Phylogenetic Analyses</title><p>The PCR-positive amplification products were analyzed and excised from 1% (w/v) agarose gels after electrophoresis to purify using the MinElute gel extraction kit (QIAGEN Ltd., Hilden, Germany), directly sequenced in both directions using forward and reverse primers (Macrogen Inc., Seoul, South Korea). The obtained sequences were verified by the Chromas software (Technelysium Pty Ltd., Queensland, Australia). Then, each parasite sample's corresponding forward and reverse sequences were aligned and assembled using MEGA X software (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Finally, the final sequences were blasted (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov" ext-link-type="uri">http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link>) to identify the genotype of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>, confirm the PCR-positive samples of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic>, and compare the homology of the obtained sequences of each parasite isolate with the corresponding sequences earlier deposited in the GenBank database.</p><p>The obtained sequences were deposited in GenBank under accession numbers <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="LC700048-LC700062" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">LC700048&#8211;LC700062</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="LC700063-LC700066" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">LC700063&#8211;LC700066</ext-link>, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="LC700067-LC700080" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">LC700067&#8211;LC700080</ext-link>, and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="LC700081-LC700088" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">LC700081&#8211;LC700088</ext-link> for BTUB, GRA6, SAG3, and APICO loci of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>, respectively, and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide-range" xlink:href="LC700099:LC700103">LC700099&#8211;LC700103</ext-link> for the ITS-2 of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic>. The Phylogenetic trees were constructed by maximum likelihood (ML) algorithm with evolutionary distances calculated using the Kimura-2 parameter model and 1000 bootstrap values in the MEGA X software. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> represents a conceptual overview of sample analysis procedures.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Sample analysis procedures. Image created in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.Biorender.com" ext-link-type="uri">Biorender.com</ext-link>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-927185-g0002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analyses</title><p>The descriptive analysis evaluated the prevalence of parasites based on age, sex, breed, weight, and the urban region in cats and age, gender, occupation, residence area, and education in cat owners. Potential associations between qualitative variables were estimated by Chi-square tests with a 95% confidence interval (CIs) in SPSS 24.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA) to reveal statistically significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">P-</italic>value &lt;0.05).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Study Population</title><p>The demographic characteristics of 165 cats enrolled in the study, 132 strays and 33 household cats, were categorized into two age groups under or over 1 year old, three breeding groups of DSH (Domestic Short Hair), DLH (Domestic Long Hair), and the Persian cat, three weight groups of &lt;2 kg, between 2 and 4 kg and &gt;4 kg, and five geographic locations of north, center, south, west, and east of Tehran (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Thirty-three cat owners participated in the investigation, 57.6% men and 42.4% women. The mean age was 38.1 &#177; 2.15 (M &#177; SEM) years, ranging from 25 to 68 years. The demographic data of participants included in this study are shown in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Demographic characteristics of the stray and household cats and the prevalence (%) and the number positive (N) of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii and Toxocara cati</italic> in Tehran.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Factors</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="5" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>Stray cats</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>Household cats</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Samples</bold>
<break/>
<bold>% (N)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">
<bold>Toxoplasma gondii</bold>
</italic>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">
<bold>Toxocara cati</bold>
</italic>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Samples</bold>
<break/>
<bold>% (N)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">
<bold>Toxoplasma gondii</bold>
</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>% (N)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>% (N)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>% (N)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
<bold>Age</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;1 year</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.0% (62)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.8% (16)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0% (31)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.511</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2% (5)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0% (1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.909</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;1 year</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.0% (70)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.7% (4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.3% (31)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.8% (28)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9% (5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
<bold>Sex</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.5% (72)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7% (12)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.595</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.4% (37)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.265</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.5% (17)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.6% (3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.935</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.5% (60)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4% (8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.7% (25)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.5% (16)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.7% (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
<bold>Breed</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSH</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.7% (96)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.6% (14)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.761</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0% (48)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.275</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.3% (11)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.2% (3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.509</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DLH</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.8% (34)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.7% (6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.2% (14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1% (3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0% (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Persian</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5% (2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0% (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0% (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.6% (19)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8% (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
<bold>Weight</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;2 kg</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.0% (62)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.4% (12)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.447</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0% (31)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.123</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2% (6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.7% (1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.866</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#8211;4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.2% (53)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.3% (6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.8% (20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.6% (19)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1% (4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;4 kg</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.8% (17)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8% (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.7% (11)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2% (8)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.5% (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
<bold>Urban Region</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.8% (38)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8% (6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.761</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.4% (18)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.733</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.2% (7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.6% (2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.180</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Center</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.9% (25)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.0% (5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.0% (14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2% (8)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5% (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9% (17)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.8% (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.2% (7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0% (1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0% (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">West</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.5% (35)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1% (6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.6% (17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.4% (13)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7% (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">East</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.9% (17)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.9% (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3% (6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1% (4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.0% (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0% (132)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2% (20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.0% (62)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0% (33)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.2% (6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">DLH, Domestic long hair; DSH, Domestic short hair</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Demographic characteristics of the cat owners in Tehran and the prevalence (%) and the number positive (N) of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Factors</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Samples % (N)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">
<bold>Toxoplasma gondii</bold>
</italic>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>% (N)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Age</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#8211;29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3% (9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.3% (3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.047</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30&#8211;39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.3% (11)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.4% (4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40&#8211;49</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.2% (6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0% (6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&gt;50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.2% (7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.1% (4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Gender</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.6% (19)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.8% (7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.4% (14)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.4% (10)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Urban Region</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.2% (7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.1% (4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.792</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Center</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2% (8)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.5% (5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.0% (1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0% (0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">West</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.4% (13)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.1% (6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">East</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1% (4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0% (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Occupation</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-employment</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.3% (12)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0% (6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.521</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Employee</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.3% (12)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.7% (5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Housekeeper</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.2% (9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.7% (6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Education</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diploma</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.2% (9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.3% (3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.393</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Undergraduate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.4% (13)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.8% (7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postgraduate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.3% (11)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.6% (7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0% (33)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.5% (17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> Among Stray and Household Cats and Their Owners</title><p>Monitoring of the <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii B1</italic> gene showed that 15.2% (20/132; 95% CI 10.0&#8211;22.2) of stray cats, 18.2% (6/33; 95% CI 8.6&#8211;34.4) of household cats, and 51.5% (17/33; 95% CI 35.2&#8211;67.5) of cat owners were infected with <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>. There were no statistical differences between the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> in stray and household cats. However, the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> in cat owners was statistically higher than in both groups of cats. The prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection relative to demographic variables of stray cats, household cats, and cat owners are shown in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Tables 2</xref>, <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. There was no statistically significant relationship between sex, breed, weight, urban region, and infection with <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> in the stray and household cats. Moreover, statistical analysis found no association between urban region, occupation, and education of cat owners and <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection. However, age affected the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> in stray cats and cat owners. The highest prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection was detected in stray cats under 1 year old (25.8%; 95% CI 10.0&#8211;22.2; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.001) and cat owners aged 40&#8211;49 years (100.0%; 95% CI 61.0&#8211;100.0; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.047). Furthermore, the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> in the women cat owners 71.4% (10/14; 95% CI 45.4&#8211;88.3) was higher than in the men 36.9% (7/19; 95% CI 19.1&#8211;59.0) (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.049).</p><p>The species identification PCRs of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. and <italic toggle="yes">T. leonina</italic> revealed a high prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> infection (62/132; 47.0%; 95% CI 38.7&#8211;55.4) and no <italic toggle="yes">T. canis</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">T. leonina</italic> in stray cats. The ribosomal DNA of <italic toggle="yes">T. canis, T. cati</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">T. leonina</italic> was not detected in the feces of household cats or the serum of cat owners (0/33; 0.0%; 95% CI 0.0&#8211;10.4). In addition, the ELISA showed 33 sera samples of cat owners to be <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> IgG negative. Consequently, the <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> infections in stray cats were significantly higher than in household cats and cat owners. <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> infection relative to demographic variables of stray cats. There was no statistically significant relationship between any demographic variables and infection with <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> in the stray cats.</p><p>Overall, molecular examination showed at least one <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> infection occurred in 73 of 132 (55.3%; 95% CI: 47.7&#8211;63.6%) stray cats. In addition, coinfections with both parasites were observed in 9 of 132 stray cats (6.8%; 95% CI: 3.0&#8211;11.4%). However, coinfections did not ensue in household cats or their owners.</p></sec><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> Multilocus Genotyping of Isolates From Stray Cats, Household Cats, and Cat Owners</title><p>The multi-locus genotyping of 43 <italic toggle="yes">B1</italic> positive isolates of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> were performed based on the BTUB, GRA6, SAG3, and APICO genetic markers. The genotype of 26 (60.5%; 95% CI 45.6&#8211;73.6) <italic toggle="yes">B1</italic> positive isolates were determined with at least one locus, 12, 4, and 10, from stray cats, household cats, and cat owners, respectively. The BTUB, GRA6, SAG3, and APICO loci were amplified and successfully sequenced in 15 (34.9%), 4 (9.3%), 14 (32.6%), and 8 (18.6%) of the <italic toggle="yes">B1</italic> positive isolates, respectively (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The sequencing analysis of four markers showed 9 (34.6%) genotype I, 12 (46.2%) genotype II, and one (3.8%) genotype III (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Four (14.5%) isolates were inconsistently identified as the genotypes I or II with two markers (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>; <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Multi-locus genotyping of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> isolates from <italic toggle="yes">B1</italic> positive samples of stray cats (SC), household cats (C), and cat owners (H).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sample code</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="5" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>Genotype/genetic marker</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>BTUB</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>GRA6</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SAG3</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>APICO</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Final</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">III</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC48</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC54</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC77</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC80</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC102</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC109</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC112</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC117</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC121</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SC122</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I, II</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C15</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I, II</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C21</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C27</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C31</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I, II</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H11</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I, II</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H15</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H20</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H22</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">II</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">na, not successfully amplified</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The multiple alignments of BTUB gene sequences identified the 15 amplified isolates as genotype II from stray cats (three isolates), household cats (three isolates), and cat owners (nine isolates). In addition, sequencing analysis revealed 100% homology between 15 BTUB genotype II isolates and the reference sequence of <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AF249702">AF249702</ext-link> (BEVERLEY) and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AY143118">AY143118</ext-link> (B7) for genotype II (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). Only one isolate from the household cat (C15) and the corresponding owner (H15) were amplified and successfully sequenced at the BTUB locus. Phylogenetic analysis of the BTUB gene located all 15 BTUB amplified isolates in one cluster with genotype II sequence references (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AF249702">AF249702</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AY143118">AY143118</ext-link>), with a 98% bootstrap value (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>). Sequencing analysis revealed that four GRA6 amplified isolates belonged to genotype I (one cat owner isolate), II (one stray cat and one cat owner isolate), and III (one stray cat isolate). Moreover, the nucleotide sequence alignment and phylogenetic analysis of GRA6 isolates with the corresponding retrieved genotype I, II, and III sequences of GenBank showed 100% homology (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>), with 71% or 88% bootstrap value (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref>). Further sequence alignment and phylogenetic analysis of the SAG3 locus identified genotypes I (8 isolates), II (one isolate), and III (one isolate) in stray cats. In contrast, only genotype I was verified in household cats (two isolates) and cat owners (two isolates). <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C</xref> illustrates the identified isolates of the SAG3 locus classified in three clusters with sequence references representing genotypes I, II, and III with 89%, 99%, and 96% bootstrap support, respectively. The nucleotide sequence alignment revealed eight APICO amplified isolates belonged to genotype I (four stray cat isolates and one cat owner isolate), II (two stray cat isolates), and III (one stray cat isolate) with 100% homology with sequence references representing genotype I, II and III (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). The phylogenetic analysis of APICO isolates was clustered with the corresponding retrieved genotype I, II, and III sequences of GenBank with high bootstrap values (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3D</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Phylograms of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> genotypes were inferred based on the nucleotide sequences of the <bold>(A)</bold> BTUB, <bold>(B)</bold> GRA6, <bold>(C)</bold> SAG3, and <bold>(D)</bold> APICO. The evolutionary relationship of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> genotypes was constructed by the Maximum Likelihood method and Kimura 2-parameter model, based on the nucleotide sequences of <bold>(A)</bold> BTUB, <bold>(B)</bold> GRA6, <bold>(C)</bold> SAG3, and <bold>(D)</bold> APICO genetic markers of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> isolated from stray cats [SC], household cats [C], and cat owners [H] retrieved from this study (colored triangles) compared with reference sequences of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> genotype I, II, and III from GenBank. Bootstrap values obtained from 1,000 replicates are indicated on branches in percentage; only bootstrap values &gt;50% are displayed. Evolutionary analyses were conducted in MEGA X.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-927185-g0003.jpg"/></fig><p>The multilocus sequence analysis of 26 <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma</italic>-positive isolates revealed genotype I of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> was predominant in stray cats (7/12; 58.3%; 95% CI 32.0&#8211;80.7), although genotype II of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> was predominant in household cats (2/4; 50.0%; 95% CI 15.0&#8211;85.0) and cat owners (7/10; 70.0%; 95% CI 39.7&#8211;89.2). In addition to genotype I (58.3%), genotype II (3/12; 16.7%; 95% CI 4.7&#8211;44.8), genotype III (1/12; 8.3%; 95% CI 1.5&#8211;35.4), and the mix of genotypes I and II (1/12; 8.3%; 95% CI 1.5&#8211;35.4) were identified in stray cats. Genotype I (1/4; 25.0%; 95% CI 4.6&#8211;69.9) (1/10; 10.0%; 95% CI 1.8&#8211;40.4) and the mix of genotypes I and II (1/4; 25.0%; 95% CI 4.6&#8211;69.9) (2/10; 20.0%; 95% CI 5.7&#8211;51.0) showed less distribution in household cats and cat owners than genotype II (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>The Nucleotide Sequence Analysis of the ITS-2 Region Confirmed the Predominance of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> in Stray Cats</title><p>The species identification PCR procedures of the ITS-2 region of the ribosomal DNA of <italic toggle="yes">T. canis, T. cati</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">T. leonina</italic> showed 62 positive samples of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> in stray cats. Sequencing a 370-bp amplified fragment of four <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> PCR-positive samples confirmed the results. In addition, the nucleotide sequencing analysis of four <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> isolates revealed 100% homology with the corresponding fragment of the published ITS-2 sequences of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> retrieved from GenBank (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="MT341311" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">MT341311</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="KJ777157" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">KJ777157</ext-link>). Further phylogenetic analysis revealed four <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> isolates in one cluster with the published ITS-2 sequences of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> retrieved from GenBank, with a 94% bootstrap value (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Phylogram of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. and <italic toggle="yes">Toxascaris leonina</italic> was inferred based on the nucleotide sequences of the ITS-2 region of the ribosomal DNA. The evolutionary relationship of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. <italic toggle="yes">and T. leonina</italic> was constructed by the Maximum Likelihood method and Kimura 2-parameter model, based on the nucleotide sequences of the ITS-2 region of the ribosomal DNA of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara cati</italic> isolated from stray cats [SC] retrieved from this study (purple circles) compared with nucleotide sequences of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. and <italic toggle="yes">T. leonina</italic> from GenBank. Bootstrap values obtained from 1000 replicates are indicated on branches in percentage; only bootstrap values &gt;50% are displayed. Evolutionary analyses were conducted in MEGA X.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-927185-g0004.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Using the molecular analysis methods, we detected <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. infections in the feces of stray and household cats and the blood of cat owners by amplifying the <italic toggle="yes">B1</italic> gene of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> and the ITS-2 region of the ribosomal DNA of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. Furthermore, by employing the multilocus genotyping of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> based on BTUB, GRA6, SAG3, and APICO loci, we identified genotyping and genetic variability of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> isolated from cats and humans in Tehran, a metropolitan area in Iran. We found a higher prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> in cat owners than in cats, affected by the age and gender of humans and only the age of stray cats. Although we identified a high prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> infection in stray cats, we did not detect <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. or <italic toggle="yes">T. leonina</italic> in household cats or their owners. We also revealed the predominance of genotype I of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> in stray cats and genotype II of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> in household cats and cat owners.</p><p>Although infected cats usually shed the oocysts once in their lives and for a short time (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>), infected humans carry bradyzoites of parasite for long-lasting periods inside their cells, and latent infection may persist. These biological behaviors of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> can explain the higher prevalence of DNA parasites in the cat owner's buffy coat than in cats' feces. The reported prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> in cats in different parts of the world is variable according to the diagnostic methods used and the variety in geographic, environmental, and diet of studied cats. For example, the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> in stray cats in Tehran (15.2%), compared to other molecular studies in Iran, was higher than the previous prevalence reported in Mashhad (4.5%) (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) and Ahvaz (7.2%)(<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>), and lower than the prevalence (24.1%) reported in Shiraz (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Furthermore, compared to other molecular studies in the world, it is higher than the previous prevalence reported in South Korea (4.7% and 1.3%) (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>), the USA (2%) (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>), and Malaysia (13%)(<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>), and lower than the prevalence reported in South Korea (17.5% and 30.6%)(<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>) and Pakistan (34%)(<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). In addition, the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection in household cats in the current study (18.2%) was higher than the prevalence reported in Switzerland (0.58%) (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>), Poland (2.4%) (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>), Malaysia (4%) (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>), Thailand (4.7%) (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>) and Kenya (7.8%) (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>), and lower than reported from Italy (20.5%) (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study performed on the molecular prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection in cat owners worldwide. A systematic review and meta-analysis estimated that the seroprevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection in the general Iranian population was 39.3%, reported at 49% in Tehran (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>), which is very close to our results (51.5%). Our previous study (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) confirms that detecting DNA circulating in the blood is comparable to the seropositive results.</p><p>The investigation of possible factors associated with <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection showed it was more frequent in stray cats under 1 year old (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.001), similar to a study conducted in South Korea (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). However, Khodaverdi et al. (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) in Mashhad and Kwak et al. (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>) in South Korea had not observed any statistically significant relationship between the age of cats and the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection. Moreover, a significant difference between cat owners' age and the prevalence rate was observed, comparable to the highest incidence previously reported in the age group over 40 years (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>) and the correlation between increasing age and the prevalence of infection (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). It is assumed that through passing the years, exposure to microorganisms increases, whether through contaminated food and water, contact with infected cats, or other risk factors. The higher <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection in the women cat owners observed in our study was not confirmed by the earlier seroprevalence studies (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>).</p><p>Multi-locus genotyping of BTUB, GRA6, SAG3, and APICO loci of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma</italic>-positive isolates revealed genotype I in stray cats and genotype II in household cats and cats' owners were predominant. In addition, three genotypes of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> and the mix of genotypes I and II were typed in the stray cats of Tehran, which demonstrated more variables than previous studies. For example, genotype I (one case), III (32 cases), and the mix of I and III (two cases) in Ahvaz, southwest of Iran, by PCR-RFLP of SAG2 locus (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>), or genotype II in Mashhad (one case), northeastern Iran, by PCR-RFLP of SAG3 locus (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>), and in South Korea (two isolates) (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) by sequencing <italic toggle="yes">SAG5D</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">SAG5E</italic> genes were reported. Therefore, compared to our study, genotyping the limited number of samples or typing with just one locus in the mentioned reports is the foremost possible cause for not detecting all genotypes. Furthermore, as reported before, conflicting findings in multilocus typing could be seen regarding the small sample size (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>).</p><p>Despite the ubiquity of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infections, the presence of comprehensive multi-locus studies investigating the <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> genetic diversity in household cats and their cat owners are lacking. However, most studies in Iran have reported the <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> genotype of different hosts or soil isolates based on the analysis of one or two loci (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). In limited studies performed on household cats, in Switzerland, mixed infections with types I and II in the only positive sample, and in Germany, type II (83.8%) and type III (1.4%) have been reported in household cats (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). We characterized the simultaneous <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection in only a household cat (C15) and its owner (H15). The mix-infection of genotypes I and II in the cat and the genotype II in the cat owner was typed. Although we cannot definitively and accurately explain this finding, it is assumed that the cat was infected due to hunting or contact with contaminated soil through its roaming behavior, according to the declaration of the cat owner. Therefore, it is also possible that the cat and its owner were infected from two different sources.</p><p>The species identification PCRs of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. and <italic toggle="yes">T. leonina</italic> revealed a high prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> infection (62/132; 47.0%; 95% CI 38.7&#8211;55.4) and no <italic toggle="yes">T. canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">T. leonina</italic> in stray cats. The ribosomal DNA of <italic toggle="yes">T. canis, T. cati</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">T. leonina</italic> was not detected in the feces of household cats or the serum of cat owners. The high prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> infection (47.0%) was identified in stray cats by detecting the ribosomal DNA of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> in the feces. This finding increased the concern about the potential role of the cats as significant reservoirs for humans, especially children. Nevertheless, we did not find any cases of infection in the feces of household cats or the serum of cat owners. However, the reported prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> infection in cats has a variety of ranges depending on geographical regions and the detection methods. A relatively limited number of studies in different parts of Iran and the world have investigated the molecular prevalence of these nematodes in the feces of stray cats. The prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> in the current study was higher than in other studies performed on stray cats in the different cities of Iran (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>) and Malaysia (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). In this study, we performed PCR to detect the DNA of these nematodes in the serum of cat owners and the feces of household cats for the first time, which was confirmed by not detecting the <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> IgG in the sera of cat owners. However, the anti-<italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> antibodies were reported in the sera of residents of northeastern Iran (7.2%) (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>) and northern Iran (23.5%) (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). None of the household cats or their owners were positive, which could be due to the lack of risk factors such as younger age and living in rural areas (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>) or the result of attention to hygiene principles, routine anthelmintic therapy, and adequate veterinary care. Nevertheless, the high prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> infection in stray cats can cause contamination of the environment by excreting eggs that lead to infecting humans through soil or water. Therefore, the control and treatment of infection in cats are necessary to reduce the source of human disease and other paratenic hosts.</p><p>The main limitation of this study was collected samples from the sick or injured stray cats brought to veterinary centers and pet hospitals. Therefore, the results might not be a good representation of the entire stray cat population in the area, and this limitation should be considered in further studies. Another limitation was the relatively small sample size of household cats and their owners compared to the stray cats, which might be affected the prevalence and risk factors of infections. Nevertheless, finding many cat owners who didn't have other pets or had no close contact with other animals and were willing to cooperate in the study was difficult. Therefore, future studies with larger sample sizes are recommended to confirm the reported results in this study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The high prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. cati</italic> infection (47%) in stray cats leads to considering the role of cats in human toxocariasis. Whereas the low prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> in stray cats (15.2%) and household cats (18.2%) compared to their owners (51.5%) suggests a more subordinate role of direct contact with infected cats than consuming contaminated undercooked meat containing tissue cysts or contaminated food and water with sporulated oocysts in cases of human infections. The relatively high prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> infection in cats necessitates attention to routine urban cat deworming programs and public health education in urban management to generally promote physical and mental health in the community and specifically live happily and healthy coexistence with these urban animals.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The datasets presented in this study can be found in online repositories. The names of the repository/repositories and accession number(s) can be found in the article/<xref rid="s11" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Material</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The studies involving human participants and animal study were reviewed and approved by the Iranian Ministry of Health, Treatment, and Medical Education. The experimental protocols were reviewed by the Ethics Committee of Iran University of Medical Sciences (Approval No IR.IUMS.FMD.REC 1396.31834). The patients/participants provided their written informed consent to participate in this study.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>PK: conceptualization, methodology, validation, formal analysis, investigation, resources, data curation, and original draft writing. SS-S methodology, validation, formal analysis, investigation, resources, and data curation. ARM: validation, review, and editing of the final manuscript. GN: methodology and formal analysis. ER: conceptualization, methodology, validation, formal analysis, resources, data curation, original draft writing, review and editing of the final manuscript, visualization, supervision, project administration, and funding acquisition. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="s9"><title>Funding</title><p>The Iran University of Medical Sciences financially supported this study under grant number 96-03-30-31834 to ER.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s10"><title>Publisher's Note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors are grateful to the cat owners who donated their blood samples and their cat feces samples for this study. We want to thank the authorities, veterinarians, and staff of veterinary clinics and pet hospitals for their help providing samples. This work represents a part of the Ph.D. dissertation of PK.</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s11"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2022.927185/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2022.927185/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM2" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.PDF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Humane strategies for controlling feral cat populations</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>225</volume>:<fpage>1354</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/javma.2004.225.1354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15552308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kvac</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hofmannova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holubova</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horcickova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kicia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Stray cats are more frequently infected with zoonotic protists than pet cats</article-title>. <source>Folia Parasitol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>034</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14411/fp.2017.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29214976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goulart</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kupz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Dooren</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Control of human toxoplasmosis</article-title>. <source>Int J Parasitol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>121</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpara.2020.11.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33347832</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shwab</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Moving towards an integrated approach to molecular detection and identification of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic></article-title>. <source>Parasitology.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>137</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182009991065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19765337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blader</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C-T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gubbels</surname><given-names>M-J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Lytic cycle of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic>: 15 years later</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Microbiol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>463</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-micro-091014-104100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26332089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4659696</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pena</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gennari</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richtzenhain</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Differential diagnosis of oocysts of <italic toggle="yes">Hammondia</italic>-like organisms of dogs and cats by PCR-RFLP analysis of 70-kilodalton heat shock protein (HSP70) gene</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>103</volume>:<fpage>235</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-008-0957-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18398626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robert-Gangneux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dard&#233;</surname><given-names>M-L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiology of and diagnostic strategies for toxoplasmosis</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>264</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00026-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22491772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3346298</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maksimov</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hotop</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gro&#223;</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#228;ubener</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liesenfeld</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genotyping of samples from German patients with ocular, cerebral and systemic toxoplasmosis reveals a predominance of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> type II</article-title>. <source>Int J Med Microbiol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>304</volume>:<fpage>911</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijmm.2014.06.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25037927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sibley</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Toxoplasma gondii comprises three clonal lineages: Correlation of parasite genotype with human disease</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis.</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>172</volume>:<fpage>1561</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/infdis/172.6.1561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7594717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sibley</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ajioka</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic diversity of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> in animals and humans</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>364</volume>:<fpage>2749</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2009.0087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19687043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2865090</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubinsky-Elefant</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Human toxocariasis: diagnosis, worldwide seroprevalences and clinical expression of the systemic and ocular forms</article-title>. <source>Ann Trop Med Parasitol.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>104</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1179/136485910X12607012373957</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20149289</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hofmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>C-K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maizels</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Human toxocariasis</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>e14</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(17)30331-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28781085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikaeili</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirhendi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asgari</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kia</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> nematodes in stray cats from Shiraz, southern Iran: intensity of infection and molecular identification of the isolates</article-title>. <source>Iran J Parasitol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>593</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>600</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516741</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4266124</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozlati</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spotin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahbazi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahami-Oskouei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hazratian</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adibpor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic variability and discrimination of low doses of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. from public areas soil inferred by loop-mediated isothermal amplification assay as a field-friendly molecular tool</article-title>. <source>Vet world.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1471</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14202/vetworld.2016.1471-1477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28096624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5234066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valizadeh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biderouni</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahrokhi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghanimatdan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagahi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sequencing and phylogenetic analysis of mitochondrial <italic toggle="yes">cox1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">nad1</italic> genes in <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara canis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Toxascaris leonina</italic> isolates from Iran</article-title>. <source>Bulg J Vet Med.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>251</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15547/bjvm.2274</pub-id>24717402</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khademvatan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rahim</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tavalla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdizadeh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashemitabar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>PCR-based molecular characterization of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. using feces of stray cats: A study from Southwest Iran</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e65293</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0065293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23755213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3670902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coklin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parrington</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and molecular characterization of <italic toggle="yes">Giardia duodenalis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Cryptosporidium</italic> spp. in dairy cattle in Ontario, Canada</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>150</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>305</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2007.09.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17964724</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arshadi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akhlaghi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meamar</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alizadeh Ghavidel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasiri</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahami-Oskouei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Sero-molecular detection, multi-locus genotyping, and clinical manifestations of ocular toxoplasmosis in patients in northwest Iran</article-title>. <source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>113</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>202</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/trstmh/try137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30624725</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McDevitt</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Development of a PCR-enzyme immunoassay oligoprobe detection method for <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> oocysts, incorporating PCR controls</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>5819</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.69.10.5819-5825.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14532030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC201176</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grigg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ganatra</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boothroyd</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Margolis</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Unusual abundance of atypical strains associated with human ocular toxoplasmosis</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>184</volume>:<fpage>633</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/322800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11474426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gasser</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chilton</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>PCR-based methods for identification of potentially zoonotic ascaridoid parasites of the dog, fox and cat</article-title>. <source>Acta Trop.</source> (<year>1997</year>) <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>191</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>200</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0001-706X(97)00093-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9386794</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knyaz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MEGA</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis across Computing Platforms</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>1547</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msy096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29722887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5967553</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> infection in humans and animals in the United States</article-title>. <source>Int J Parasitol.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>1257</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>78</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpara.2008.03.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18508057</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elmore</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conrad</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindsay</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic>: epidemiology, feline clinical aspects, and prevention</article-title>. <source>Trends Parasitol.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>190</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pt.2010.01.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20202907</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khodaverdi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Razmi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and genotyping of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> in stray cats in Mashhad area, Iran</article-title>. <source>BMC Vet Res.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>463</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12917-019-2176-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31864371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6925478</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tavalla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asgarian</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kazemi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and genetic diversity of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> oocysts in cats of southwest of Iran</article-title>. <source>Infect Dis Health.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>203</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.idh.2017.08.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Asgari</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammadpour</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pirzad</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalantari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Motazedian</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naderi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular and serological detection of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> in stray cats in Shiraz, South-central, Iran</article-title>. <source>Iran J Parasitol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>430</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30483335</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6243156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> B1 gene detection in feces of stray cats around Seoul, Korea and genotype analysis of two laboratory-passaged isolates</article-title>. <source>Korean J Parasitol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>259</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3347/kjp.2015.53.3.259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26174818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4510672</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kwak</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>M-G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic analysis of zoonotic gastrointestinal protozoa and <italic toggle="yes">Microsporidia</italic> in shelter cats in South Korea</article-title>. <source>Pathogens.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>894</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/pathogens9110894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33121067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7693795</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lilly</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wortham</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>High prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> oocyst shedding in stray and pet cats (<italic toggle="yes">Felis catus</italic>) in Virginia, United States</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>266</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-6-266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24330950</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3849917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasiru Wana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohd Moklas</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zasmy Unyah</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alhassan Abdullahi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad Issa Alapid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular detection and genetic diversity of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> oocysts in cat faeces from Klang Valley, Malaysia, using B1 and REP genes in 2018</article-title>. <source>Pathogens.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>576</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/pathogens9070576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32708648</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7400314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>N-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chae</surname><given-names>H-S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>H-W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>W-J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> infection in feral cats in Seoul, Korea</article-title>. <source>J Parasitol.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>97</volume>:<fpage>153</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1645/GE-2455.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21348626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J-Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y-A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woo</surname><given-names>H-M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> infection in stray and household cats in regions of Seoul, Korea</article-title>. <source>Korean J Parasitol.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>267</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3347/kjp.2010.48.3.267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20877509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2945805</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Majid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haleem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akbar</surname><given-names>Nu</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zareen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taib</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Detection of toxoplasmosis in pets and stray cats through molecular and serological techniques in Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, Pakistan</article-title>. <source>BMC Vet Res.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>357</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12917-021-03064-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34798893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8603471</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Berger-Schoch</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schares</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#252;ller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gottstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and genotypes of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> in feline faeces (oocysts) and meat from sheep, cattle and pigs in Switzerland</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>177</volume>:<fpage>290</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2010.11.046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21183278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sroka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karamon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dutkiewicz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>W&#243;jcik Fatla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zajac</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cencek</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> infection in cats in southwestern Poland</article-title>. <source>Ann Agric Environ Med.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>576</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26444/aaem/94675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30260170</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chemoh</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sawangjaroen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nissapatorn</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sermwittayawong</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular investigation on the occurrence of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> oocysts in cat feces using TOX-element and ITS-1 region targets</article-title>. <source>Vet J.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>215</volume>:<fpage>118</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tvjl.2016.05.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27325616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyambura Njuguna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kagira</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muturi Karanja</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ngotho</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mutharia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wangari Maina</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> and other gastrointestinal parasites in domestic cats from households in Thika Region, Kenya</article-title>. <source>Biomed Res Int.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>2017</volume>:<fpage>7615810</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2017/7615810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28691033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5485282</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Veronesi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milardi</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diaferia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morganti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ranucci</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Detection of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> in faeces of privately owned cats using two PCR assays targeting the B1 gene and the 529-bp repetitive element</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>116</volume>:<fpage>1063</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-017-5388-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28127718</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daryani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarvi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aarabi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmadpour</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shokri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Seroprevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> in the Iranian general population: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Acta Trop.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>137</volume>:<fpage>185</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actatropica.2014.05.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24887263</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wyman</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedges-Muncy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Association between <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> seropositivity and memory function in nondemented older adults</article-title>. <source>Neurobiol Aging.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2017.01.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28235681</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5482532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ajzenberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yera</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marty</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paris</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalle</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Menotti</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genotype of 88 <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> isolates associated with toxoplasmosis in immunocompromised patients and correlation with clinical findings</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>199</volume>:<fpage>1155</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>67</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/597477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19265484</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdoli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arbabi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pirestani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mirzaghavami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghaffarifar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalimi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular assessment of <italic toggle="yes">Neospora caninum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> in hooded crows (<italic toggle="yes">Corvus cornix</italic>) in Tehran, Iran</article-title>. <source>Comp Immunol Microbiol Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cimid.2018.06.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30017081</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalir Ghaffari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalimi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular identification of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> in the native slaughtered cattle of Tehran Province, Iran</article-title>. <source>J Food Qual Hazards Control.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>153</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18502/jfqhc.6.4.1993</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tavalla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oormazdi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akhlaghi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shojaee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Razmjou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadighi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genotyping of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> isolates from soil samples in Tehran, Iran</article-title>. <source>Iran J Parasitol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>227</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23914235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3724147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zia-Ali</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fazaeli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khoramizadeh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ajzenberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dard&#233;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keshavarz-Valian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Isolation and molecular characterization of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> strains from different hosts in Iran</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>101</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-007-0461-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17333278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Armand</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solhjoo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kordshooli</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davami</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pourahmad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Orfaee</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> type I, predominant genotype isolated from sheep in South of Iran</article-title>. <source>Vet World.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>386</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14202/vetworld.2017.386-392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28507409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5422241</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arefkhah</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pourabbas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asgari</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moshfe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikaeili</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikbakht</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular genotyping and serological evaluation of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> in mothers and their spontaneous aborted fetuses in Southwest of Iran</article-title>. <source>Comp Immunol Microbiol Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>101342</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cimid.2019.101342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31437675</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharif</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amouei</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarvi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mizani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aarabi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>S-A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic diversity of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> isolates from ruminants: A systematic review</article-title>. <source>Int J Food Microbiol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>258</volume>:<fpage>38</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>49</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2017.07.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28756372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezanezhad</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Solhjoo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalantari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erfanian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic characterization of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> isolates from human spontaneous aborted fetuses in Jahrom, southern Iran</article-title>. <source>Microb Pathog.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>161</volume>:<fpage>105217</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2021.105217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34601055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pantchev</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vrhovec</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barutzki</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilking</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fr&#246;hlich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Atypical <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> genotypes identified in oocysts shed by cats in Germany</article-title>. <source>Int J Parasitol.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>285</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpara.2009.08.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19695254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Azimian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shokrani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fallahi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular evaluation of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> species in stray cats using loop-mediated isothermal amplification (LAMP) technique as a rapid, sensitive and simple screening assay</article-title>. <source>Vet Med Sci.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>647</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/vms3.431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33491880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8136963</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Torkan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghandehari-Alavijeh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khamesipour</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Survey of the prevalence of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara cati</italic> in stray cats in Isfahan city, Iran by PCR method</article-title>. <source>Trop biomed.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>550</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33592923</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ithoi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmud</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samsudin</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kek Heng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Detection of helminth eggs and identification of Hookworm species in stray cats, dogs and soil from Klang Valley, Malaysia</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e0142231</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0142231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26671680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4682862</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezaiemanesh</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Afzalaghaee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamidi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eshaghzadeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paydar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hejazi</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of toxocariasis and its related risk factors in humans, dogs and cats in northeastern Iran: a population-based study</article-title>. <source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>113</volume>:<fpage>399</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>409</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/trstmh/trz011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30892638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aghamolaie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seyyedtabaei</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Behniafar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foroutan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saber</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanifehpur</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Seroepidemiology, modifiable risk factors and clinical symptoms of <italic toggle="yes">Toxocara</italic> spp. infection in northern Iran</article-title>. <source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>113</volume>:<fpage>116</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/trstmh/try118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30407595</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><glossary><def-list><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term>APICO</term><def><p>apicoplast genetic marker</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BTUB</term><def><p>Beta-tubulin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DLH</term><def><p>Domestic long hair</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DSH</term><def><p>Domestic short hair</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GRA6</term><def><p>granule dense 6</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ITS-2</term><def><p>Internal transcribed spacer region 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MEGA</term><def><p>molecular evolutionary genetic analysis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Kimura</term><def><p>2-parameter</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ML</term><def><p>maximum likelihood</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NJ</term><def><p>neighbor-joining</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>nested PCR</term><def><p>nested polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PVPP</term><def><p>Polyvinylpolypyrrolidone</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SAG3</term><def><p>Surface antigen 3</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SNPs</term><def><p>single nucleotide polymorphisms.</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></back></article></pmc-articleset>