<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9662785</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC9662785.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">9662785</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">9662785</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36387405</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.1037492</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial: Soft ticks as parasites and vectors</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mans</surname><given-names initials="BJ">Ben J.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/170901/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Venzal</surname><given-names initials="JM">Jos&#233; M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/91530/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mu&#241;oz-Leal</surname><given-names initials="S">Sebasti&#225;n</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/865096/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Epidemiology, Parasites and Vectors, Agricultural Research Council</institution>, <addr-line>Pretoria</addr-line>, <country>South Africa</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Veterinary Tropical Diseases, University of Pretoria</institution>, <addr-line>Pretoria</addr-line>, <country>South Africa</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Life and Consumer Sciences, University of South Africa</institution>, <addr-line>Pretoria</addr-line>, <country>South Africa</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Centro Universitario Regional (CENUR) Litoral Norte, Universidad de la Rep&#250;blica</institution>, <addr-line>Salto</addr-line>, <country>Uruguay</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Department of Animal Science, University of Concepcion</institution>, <addr-line>Chill&#225;n</addr-line>, <country>Chile</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited and reviewed by: Josu&#233; Mart&#237;nez-de la Puente, University of Granada, Spain</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Ben J. Mans <email>MansB@arc.agric.za</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Parasitology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">400313</issue-id><elocation-id>1037492</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>9</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>9</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2023-05-21 01:25:20.263"><day>21</day><month>05</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2022 Mans, Venzal and Mu&#241;oz-Leal.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Mans, Venzal and Mu&#241;oz-Leal</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-09-1037492.pdf"/><related-article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" related-article-type="commentary-article" xml:lang="en" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/13300/soft-ticks-as-parasites-and-vectors"/><kwd-group><kwd>argasids</kwd><kwd>ecology</kwd><kwd>bloodmeal</kwd><kwd>salivary glands</kwd><kwd>distribution</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="1"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="1865"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Soft ticks are interesting ectoparasites due to their ecological habits and unique blood-feeding biology. The wide-ranging nature of research into these parasites is reflected in the diverse set of papers captured in this special issue. Fundamental questions are addressed in the 9 articles included in this Research Topic that focuses on ecology, tick-host interaction, host associations, geographic distribution, and microbial endosymbionts.</p><sec id="s1"><title>Geographic dispersal of soft ticks</title><p>Adult and nymphal soft ticks feed quickly and are therefore not extensively associated with their hosts. In addition, they are generally nest- or burrow-dwelling parasites. Therefore, how they disperse to new hosts and burrows is an interesting question to tackle. The study by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2020.570157" ext-link-type="uri">Rataud et al.</ext-link> investigated dispersal between yellow-legged gull (<italic toggle="yes">Larus michahellis</italic>) nests for the soft tick <italic toggle="yes">Ornithodoros maritimus</italic> (also known as <italic toggle="yes">Alectorobius maritimus</italic>) using a capture-mark-recapture strategy within a natural bird population during the breeding season. Overall dispersal rates were low, confirming the strong endophilic nature of this tick species. This contrasted with previous results on the random distribution of infectious organisms in this species that suggested extensive between-nest movement (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). The study considered the possibility that longer temporal scales of dispersal may be more relevant to argasid dispersal than short-term monitoring allows. The study certainly highlights great mysteries in soft tick biology that exist regarding geographic and temporal dispersal, and how life stage, seasonality, nest- or burrow-occupancy, and tick-feeding status may impact this.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Host identification through bloodmeal analysis</title><p>The ability of soft ticks to survive for extensive periods of time is linked with their slow metabolism and capability to store their bloodmeal for prolonged periods in an intact and undigested form. The fact that soft ticks can feed multiple times and that the previous bloodmeals survive feeding events in their guts offers the opportunity to utilize the bloodmeal to identify past hosts. This biological particularity would greatly expand the ability to associate soft ticks with their natural hosts, since the ticks are rarely collected on the host or dwell in burrows that harbor multiple vertebrate species, making host identification ambiguous. Two studies in this collection investigated various methods to detect hosts by bloodmeal analysis of the soft tick <italic toggle="yes">Ornithodoros (Pavlovskyella) turicata</italic>. On the one hand, the study by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2021.639400" ext-link-type="uri">Busselman et al.</ext-link> validated the use of PCR and Sanger sequencing in ticks artificially fed on chicken and pig blood and could detect host DNA up to 1,105 days after feeding. Based on these parameters, they screened 19 field-collected ticks from a cave in Austin, Texas, and showed evidence of the presence of raccoon, black vulture, Texas black rattlesnake, and human blood in bloodmeals. On the other hand, the study by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2021.620441" ext-link-type="uri">Kim et al.</ext-link> investigated species-specific qPCR analysis using ticks fed on various host species such as chicken, goat, and pig. According to their results, the specific origin of bloodmeals could be detected beyond 330 days post-feeding, through multiple molting events and multiple species in one bloodmeal. The authors also investigated the use of stable isotope analyses for the identification of bloodmeal origin in ticks, but their results suggest that this approach is less sensitive than qPCR. These studies highlighted the potential to use bloodmeal identification analyses as means to detect prior hosts and exploit the ability of soft ticks to retain intact host blood across molts and feeding events. While the strategies used, such as host-specific qPCR and direct Sanger sequencing may limit the ability to detect multiple hosts, future prospects such as cloning and sequencing of amplicons or implementing next-generation amplicon sequencing approaches will expand the opportunity to uncover the array of hosts parasitized by soft ticks in their natural habitats.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Domestic fowl as hosts of soft ticks</title><p>Most argasids parasitize wild animals and their impact on domestic animal or human health may be considered incidental, as found for the human that visited the cave frequented by <italic toggle="yes">O. (P.) turicata</italic> above (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2021.639400" ext-link-type="uri">Busselman et al.</ext-link>). However, when infestations of argasids are experienced in human homes or domestic animal dwellings, the impact can be quite severe, especially when infected with pathogenic agents. For instance, <italic toggle="yes">Argas persicus</italic> parasitize poultry and has a worldwide distribution with a preference for tropical regions, and is generally the expected tick species when poultry dwellings are investigated. In the current collection, two studies geographically distant from each other investigated the infestation of poultry by argasids. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2021.664731" ext-link-type="uri">Zahid et al.</ext-link> studied the infestation of domestic fowl in Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, Pakistan. From a large number of ticks collected from fowl dwellings (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7,219), the only tick found was <italic toggle="yes">A. persicus</italic>, as confirmed by morphological and molecular identification. The second study by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2021.704399" ext-link-type="uri">L&#243;pez et al.</ext-link> from the Caribbean region of Colombia surprisingly found the exclusive infestation of fowl dwellings by <italic toggle="yes">Ornithodoros puertoricensis</italic> (also known as <italic toggle="yes">Alectorobius puertoricensis</italic>) as confirmed by morphological and molecular identification. This was the first association of this tick species with domestic fowl. Both studies highlight the importance of confirming which tick species parasitize domestic fowl in a given region since this will also impact on risk assessment of zoonosis and the possibility that high infestations can spill over to nearby human dwellings.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Birds as hosts of soft ticks</title><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2021.637837" ext-link-type="uri">Palomar et al.</ext-link> collected soft ticks in wild birds from Spain. In this study, the authors were unable to identify the ticks to the species level using current available morphological keys. Species relationships were further investigated using mitochondrial 12S and 16S ribosomal RNA and cytochrome oxidase 1 genes. Phylogenetic analysis of the 16S rRNA indicated species identity with <italic toggle="yes">A. persicus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Argas reflexus</italic>, with at least two genotypes grouping with a clade formed by <italic toggle="yes">Argas japonicus, Argas lagenoplastis, Argas polonicus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Argas vulgaris</italic> and a genotype that grouped with <italic toggle="yes">Argas africolumbae</italic>. The study pointed out the important need for the development of accurate keys for the genus <italic toggle="yes">Argas</italic>, given that this genus comprises 44 species with many potential new <italic toggle="yes">Argas</italic> species, as found in the Palearctic region. The study also detected <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia, Coxiella, Francisella</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsiella</italic> species as well as a novel <italic toggle="yes">Babesia</italic> genotype, closely related to avian <italic toggle="yes">Babesia</italic> species. This highlights the potential role of <italic toggle="yes">Argas</italic> species in transmitting zoonotic bacterial and piroplasmid agents.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Bat-associated soft ticks</title><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2021.684737" ext-link-type="uri">S&#225;ndor et al.</ext-link> investigated the associations between soft ticks and hosts, using mammals as study models. Five main tick species were identified, namely, <italic toggle="yes">Carios vespertilionis, Chiropterargas boueti, Chiropterargas confusus, Reticulinasus salahi</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Secretargas transgariepinus</italic>. Except for <italic toggle="yes">C. vespertilionis</italic> which showed the widest distribution, the distribution maps for these ticks are data sparse and indicate a need for more studies on bats and their associated argasid species. The maps presented will serve as important reference points in this regard. Moreover, it is highlighted that most of these species would also parasitize humans and could be of zoonotic potential transmitting <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">Borrelia</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">Bartonella</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">Ehrlichia</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">Babesia</italic> spp., and several nairo- and flaviviruses. Though this hypothesis still needs investigation. Integration of host association data shows little evidence of host specificity. This study will definitely serve as an important resource for argasids associated with Palearctic bats.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Soft ticks in China</title><p>Another meta-analysis of argasid ticks in China synthesized current knowledge on the species and associated pathogens for this important but neglected region (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fvets.2022.865664" ext-link-type="uri">Chen et al.</ext-link>). Up to 15 argasid species were discussed including from the Argasinae: <italic toggle="yes">Argas assimilis, Argas beijingensis, Argas japonicus, A. persicus, Argas pusillus, A. reflexus, Argas robertsi, Argas sinensis, A. vulgaris, Ornithodoros lahorensis</italic> (also known as <italic toggle="yes">Alveonasus lahorensis</italic>); and from the Ornithodorinae: <italic toggle="yes">Argas vespertilionis</italic> (also known as <italic toggle="yes">Carios vespertilionis</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">Ornithodoros capensis</italic> (also known as <italic toggle="yes">Alectorobius capensis</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">Ornithodoros</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Ornithodoros</italic>) <italic toggle="yes">huajianensis, Ornithodoros</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Pavlovskyella</italic>) <italic toggle="yes">papillipes</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Ornithodoros</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Pavlovskyella</italic>) <italic toggle="yes">tartakovskyi</italic>. The study brings to light old Chinese papers (1930s to 1960s) on soft ticks and highlights that the diversity of argasid species in this region could be by far underestimated.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Salivary gland transcriptomes of soft ticks</title><p>Lastly, the study by <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fphys.2021.725635" ext-link-type="uri">Reck et al.</ext-link> described the salivary gland transcriptome of <italic toggle="yes">Ornithodoros</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Pavlovskyella</italic>) <italic toggle="yes">brasiliensis</italic> elucidated by next-generation sequencing. This study contributed a large number of genes from this species including secretory proteins and confirmed that these latter are highly abundant in argasid salivary glands. This gene catalog will be useful to identify toxins involved in toxicosis syndromes caused by this tick species in mammals.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s8"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This special issue highlighted the diversity of subject areas that can be illuminated by the study of argasid species and their biology. It also represents a summary of some areas of interest in contemporary argasid biology and promises that further study into these research lines will expand in the future.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Author contributions</title><p>BM: conceptualization and writing&#8212;original draft, and review and editing. JV and SM-L: writing&#8212;review and editing. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s10"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dupraz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toty</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Devillers</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanchon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elguero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vittecoq</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Population structure of the soft tick <italic toggle="yes">Ornithodoros maritimus</italic> and its associated infectious agents within a colony of its seabird host <italic toggle="yes">Larus michahellis</italic></article-title>. <source>Int J Parasitol Parasites Wildl</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>122</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijppaw.2017.05.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28620577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5460746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>