<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9510678</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC9510678.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">9510678</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">9510678</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36172608</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.957479</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Vaccination with recombinant <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> bradyzoite-formation deficient 1 (rTgBFD1) antigen provides partial protective immunity against chronic <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaowei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1658212/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhenke</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1982377/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wan</surname><given-names initials="G">Guangmin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names initials="T">Tong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="M">Meng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names initials="H">Hanqi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mei</surname><given-names initials="X">Xuefang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1510678/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhenchao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/555651/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiangrui</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/378830/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="S">Shuai</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c002" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/495391/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Xinxiang Key Laboratory of Pathogenic Biology, Department of Pathogenic Biology, School of Basic Medical Sciences, Xinxiang Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Xinxiang</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>MOE Joint International Research Laboratory of Animal Health and Food Safety, College of Veterinary Medicine, Nanjing Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Nanjing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Camila Koutsodontis Cerqueira C&#233;zar, S&#227;o Paulo State University, Brazil</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Ragab Makhlouf Mahmoud Fereig, South Valley University, Egypt; Khalid Hajissa, Omdurman Islamic University, South Sudan</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Xiangrui Li <email>lixiangrui@njau.edu.cn</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Shuai Wang <email>tongbaiws1003@163.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Parasitology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">400313</issue-id><elocation-id>957479</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>5</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>27</day><month>09</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2022-09-29 15:19:48.850"><day>29</day><month>09</month><year>2022</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2022 Tian, Yang, Wan, Xie, Wang, Sun, Mei, Zhang, Li and Wang.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Tian, Yang, Wan, Xie, Wang, Sun, Mei, Zhang, Li and Wang</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-09-957479.pdf"/><abstract><p>As an apicomplexan pathogen, <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> still remains a major threat to public health and requires special attention. In fact, positive attempts to identify more effective antigens to provide protection are important to control toxoplasmosis. Latest scientific advances in <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> study hint at the probability of the <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> bradyzoite-formation deficient 1 (TgBFD1) as an ideal vaccine candidate, since this molecule plays a critical role in regulating the chronic infection of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>. Thus, BALB/c mouse models of acute and chronic <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infections were used to evaluate the TgBFD1 protection efficacy in this study. Before conducting animal trials, antigen analysis of TgBFD1 was performed using DNAstar software and Western blots. The preliminary results suggested that TgBFD1 should be a potent immunogen. Then, this conclusion is confirmed by ELISA assays. After immunization with rTgBFD1, high levels of specific IgG, IgG1, IgG2a, and cytokines (Interferon &#947; and interleukin 10) were observed, indicating that TgBFD1 could induce strong protective antibody responses. While TgBFD1-specific IgG antibodies were measurable in vaccinated mice, no protection was observed in the acute <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection (RH strain) assay. However, a noticeable decrease in brain cysts counts of immunized mice compared with negative controls in the latent <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection (PRU strain) assay was observed. Taken together, these results indicated that rTgBFD1 had the remarkable ability to elicit both humoral and cellular immune responses and could provide partial protective immunity against chronic <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic></kwd><kwd>bradyzoite-formation deficient 1</kwd><kwd>recombinant antigen</kwd><kwd>protective immunity</kwd><kwd>BALB/c mice</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="33"/><page-count count="11"/><word-count count="5411"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>) is an opportunistic protozoon that is known to be responsible for approximately one-third of the global population infection (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). There is a risk of infantile encephalitis, miscarriage in pregnant women and livestock, and even death for immunocompromised individuals due to this disorder, which poses serious harm to the public and animal health (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Tachyzoites rapidly invade host-nucleated cells during the initial <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection. It is possible for tachyzoites to turn into bradyzoites for developing latent tissue cysts, which can lead to chronic infection in immunocompetent hosts (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>).</p><p>Until present, toxoplasmosis cannot be fully cured by currently available pharmacotherapy. Thus, immunoprophylaxis is the preferred method for controlling the disease (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). However, so far, no vaccine is available for preventing human toxoplasmosis. Over past decades, several vaccine forms, such as inactivated vaccines, live attenuated vaccines, DNA vaccines, and subunit vaccines, are considered to make safe and efficient vaccines suitable for humans (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). There is only one licensed vaccine against <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> at present: Toxovax (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). However, this vaccine cannot be applied for humans, because its format may revert to virulence. Therefore, discovering safe and effective antigens is urgent.</p><p>In recent years, multiple attempts have been made to identify the protective antigens from <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>. The antigens such as rhoptry proteins, dense granule proteins, and surface antigens expressed in tachyzoite and/or bradyzoite stages have exhibited the tremendous potential to be vaccine candidates (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), and of these, proteins expressed in the bradyzoite stage deserve more attention because bradyzoites have long-term latent infection ability. Studies demonstrated that bradyzoite-specific antigens BAG1 and MAG1 could induce early humoral and cell-mediated immune responses upon human infection (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Nevertheless, the research focused on the bradyzoite proteins was still limited.</p><p>A recent study suggested that bradyzoite-formation deficient 1 (TgBFD1) can be used as the candidate for the vaccine. Waldman et al. found TgBFD1 was a master regulator of chronic phase. <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> accumulates higher levels of TgBFD1 when faced with stress conditions, resulting in the conversion of the tachyzoite stage into bradyzoites. In addition, tachyzoites, which lack TgBFD1, could not transform into bradyzoites. Moreover, TgBFD1 played critical roles during cyst formation. TgBFD1-deficient strain can hardly generate tissue cysts in mice (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>).</p><p>Current studies suggest that TgBFD1 may serve as a potential vaccine candidate for the control of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>. The possible functions of TgBFD1 in the clearance of cysts provide reasons to expect its ability in providing immune protection against <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection. Taking into account that recombinant proteins for the production of vaccines are the appropriate method on a commercial basis (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), rTgBFD1 was performed for active immunizations. In this study, ISA 201 adjuvant (Seppic, France) is the appropriate choice considering the obvious advantages of its high safety profile, long-term protective immune response, and convenient-to-inject property (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Therefore, we aimed to determine the protective efficacy of TgBFD1 in BALB/c mouse models infected with <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>. Furthermore, active immunized mice assays suggested that TgBFD1 could provide partial protection against infection caused by <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> RH or PRU strains. In comparison, TgBFD1 protection efficacy for chronic infection performed better.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Mice and <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> strains</title><p>Female BALB/c mice (age 6 weeks) were bought from Charles River Animal Technology Company, Beijing, China and maintained under standard, pathogen-free conditions. Animal assays conducted in this study were reviewed and approved by the Ethics Committee of Xinxiang Medical University (No. XYLL-2021S016).</p><p><italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> strains (RH and PRU) were preserved in Xinxiang Key Laboratory of Pathogenic Biology, Department of Pathogenic Biology of Xinxiang Medical University in Henan, China. The tachyzoites of the <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> RH strain and the cysts of the <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> PRU strain were purified and collected as previously described (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Sequence analysis</title><p>According to the sequence analysis of the TgBFD1 open reading frame obtained from the ToxoDB database (Accession number: TGME49_200385-t26_1), the feature key domain of TgBFD1 (921&#8211;1023aa) predicted by uniport was chosen for subsequent assays. In addition, the DNASTAR software (Madison, WI, United States) was carried out to evaluate the possibility of TgBFD1 feature key domain as a candidate vaccine antigen in terms of the surface probability, the antigenic index, the hydrophilic plot, and the flexible region.</p></sec><sec><title>Recombinant TgBFD1 (rTgBFD1) antigen production</title><p>The sequence (921&#8211;1023aa) of TgBFD1 was successively cloned and inserted into a prokaryotic expression vector pET-30a. The technique of homologous recombination was performed for the construction of pET-30a-TgBFD1 using the ClonExpress II One Step Cloning Kit (Vazyme, Nanjing, China). Primer sequences were as follows: forward primer: taagaaggagatatacatatgATGTGGAGCGCTGAGGAGG (<italic toggle="yes">Nde</italic> I) and reverse primer: ctcgagtgcggccgcaagcttTCATAGGCGGGCATTGCTG (<italic toggle="yes">Hind</italic> III). rTgBFD1 was obtained by using <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> BL-21 (DE3) competent cells and purified by the His Bind<sup>&#174;</sup> Resin Chromatography kit (Merck, Darmstadt, Germany). The purified rTgBFD1 was monitored by reducing SDS-PAGE. The endotoxin was depleted by the Detoxi-Gel Affinity Pak Prepacked columns (Pierce, Rockford, USA) as noted previously (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), and the rTgBFD1 was confirmed to be endotoxin free using the Gel Clot Limulus Amebocyte Lysate Single Test kit (BIOENDO, Xiamen China). The concentration of rTgBFD1 was determined using a BCA Protein Assay Kit (Boster Biological Technology, Wuhan, China). At last, the purified and endotoxin-free rTgBFD1 was stocked at &#8722;70&#176;C for spare.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunogenicity analysis of rTgBFD1</title><p>This immunogenicity analysis referred to the previous study (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). The rTgBFD1 was separated by 12% SDS-PAGE gel and transferred to the nitrocellulose membranes (Millipore, Shanghai, China). The blots were blocked with 5% skim milk in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) with 0.5% Tween 20 (PBST) for 1 h at 37&#176;C and then incubated with the serum collected from normal or <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>-infected mice (1:100 dilution) for 1 h at 37&#176;C. After three washes, 5 min each using PBST buffer, the blots were incubated with goat anti-mouse IgG-HRP antibody (Sigma, Shanghai, China) (1:5000 dilution) for 1 h at 37&#176;C. After three washes, 5 min each using PBST buffer, the blots were finally visualized by the enhanced chemiluminescence kit (Vazyme, Nanjing, China).</p></sec><sec><title>Mice active immunization and infection assays</title><p>The 6-week-old BALB/c mice were randomly grouped (30 per group), and each mouse per group was immunized (three subcutaneous immunizations at 2-week intervals) with 20 &#956;g of rTgBFD1 in 50 &#956;l PBS emulsified with ISA 201 (volume 1:1), ISA 201 adjuvant (50 &#956;l ISA 201 + 50 &#956;l PBS), or PBS (100 &#956;l PBS) alone. The day of immunization was set as week 0. To detect antibody levels and cytokine contents, the serum of immunized mice was collected on weeks 0 and 6, respectively, and then stored at &#8722;20&#176;C for further use (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 10). For <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> challenge assays, ten mice from each group were infected by intraperitoneal vaccination with 1 &#215; 10<sup>2</sup> RH strain tachyzoites, and the remaining ten mice were infected <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> oral gavage with 10 PRU strain cysts at 2 weeks post the last inoculation. The day of parasite infection was considered day 0. The survival of mice challenged by tachyzoites of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> RH strain was recorded every 12 h until all mice had died. Mice infected by the <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> PRU cysts were observed daily for survival until 60 days after infection, and then, the cysts were removed from the brains for counting, which was conducted three times with a 10-&#956;l brain mixture. The brain mixture was obtained by grinding with 1 ml PBS. The calculation of the cysts number reduction ratio was indicated as follows: cysts number of PBS control mice&#8211;adjuvant vaccinated mice or PBS control mice &#215; 100%.</p></sec><sec><title>Determination of antibody response in sera by ELISA</title><p>Based on previous literature (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), rTgBFD1-specific antibody levels in immunized mice serum were determined using ELISA with rTgBFD1. First, 5 &#956;g/ml rTgBFD1 was used to cover the ELISA plates at 4&#176;C overnight for examining specific IgG, IgG1, and IgG2a. Approximately 5% skim milk in PBST was used to block for 1 h at 37&#176;C. After this operation, the ELISA plates were reacted with the primary antibody (immunized mice serum, 1:100 dilution) for 1 h at 37&#176;C and subsequently reacted with the secondary antibodies (anti-mice IgG-HRP, IgG1-HRP, or IgG2a-HRP, 1:8000 dilution) for 1 h at 37&#176;C. For specific IgG titers analysis, the primary antibody (immunized mice serum) was proceeded <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> serial dilution (1:10~1:10<sup>5</sup>). The ELISA plates washed with PBST were necessary after antibody incubations. Finally, after interaction with 3,3,5,5-tetramethylbenzidine, termination buffer 2 M H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> was supplied to stop this reaction. Optical density at 450 nm (OD450) was performed using a microplate reader (Thermo Fisher Scientific, MA, United States).</p></sec><sec><title>Cytokine detection</title><p>The mice sera obtained as described in the preceding paragraphs were used for the assessment of the cytokine content. In this assay, the commercial ELISA kits (Boster, Wuhan, China) were applied to quantitate cytokines interferon &#947; (IFN-&#947;), interleukin 4 (IL-4), interleukin 12p70 (IL-12p70), and interleukin 10 (IL-10) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Cytokine contents were figured out with the standard reference curve fitted by the mice recombinant IFN-&#947;, IL-12p70, IL-4, and IL-10 with a known quantity and their corresponding OD450. Four-parameter logistic regression equations were selected to fit these data. The units of four cytokine concentrations were picograms per milliliter (pg/ml).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data were statistically analyzed with the Graphpad Premier 8.0 software package (Graphpad Prism, CA, USA) in this study. Comparisons of the mean value (e.g., antibodies response, cytokines level) between all groups were conducted using one-way ANOVA. Survival analysis of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>-infected mice was carried out by the Kaplan&#8211;Meier method. Comparisons were deemed significant between groups if the <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value was less than 0.05. For all figures, the following notations were set to denote significance: <sup>*</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, <sup>***</sup><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, ns: non-significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Secondary structure predictions of TgBFD1</title><p>The epitope analysis is indicated in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, and the predicted region of TgBFD1 protein had predominant antigenic indices, which suggested that immunization with this antigen may provide a promising immune response.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Epitope analysis of TgBFD1. The linear-B cell epitopes of the TgBFD1 feature key domain were analyzed by DNAstar software, such as hydrophilicity plot, flexible regions, antigenic index, and surface probability.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-957479-g0001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Cloning, expression, and purification of TgBFD1</title><p>As seen in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>, a single band size amplified by PCR was consistent with the TgBFD1 gene using 1% agarose gel. Then, the target sequence was extracted, cloned into prokaryotic expression vector pET-30a, and DNA sequencing was performed. To yield pure rTgBFD1, BL21(DE3) strain was chosen to transform reconstructed pET-30a-TgBFD1 plasmid, and nickel columns were performed to purify the His fusion rTgBFD1 using affinity chromatography. The purified rTgBFD1 was confirmed by 12% SDS-PAGE gel, which presented a single band at a 12.7-kDa level stained with Coomassie blue (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Gene amplification, protein purification, and recognition of TgBFD1. <bold>(A)</bold> The amplification of TgBFD1 was determined by 1% agarose gel electrophoresis. <bold>(B)</bold> Purified rTgBFD1 was run in 12% SDS-PAGE gel and visualized using Coomassie blue G250. <bold>(C)</bold> Recognition of rTgBFD1 was performed using toxoplasmosis mice sera. M, protein molecular mass standards; Line 1, normal mice IgG served as control; Line 2, sera obtained at 6 weeks after infection from mice infected with the <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> PRU strain served as a primary antibody.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-957479-g0002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Immunogenicity of TgBFD1</title><p>The immunogenicity of TgBFD1 was evaluated to identify the vaccine viability of TgBFD1. As suggested in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C</xref>, a clear band around 12.7 kDa was typically detected in the positive control, whereas there was no band in the negative control using normal mice sera. The Western blot analysis of rTgBFD1 suggested that rTgBFD1 could be recognized by sera from <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>-infected mice.</p></sec><sec><title>rTgBFD1 immunization could elicit a strong humoral immunological response</title><p>For detection of specific antibody response, mice sera were collected after 6 weeks post-immunization and tested by ELISA against rTgBFD1 proteins. As illustrated in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>, mice that received rTgBFD1 inoculations reached anti-rTgBFD1 titers of 1:10<sup>4</sup>. In <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>, mice sera antibody levels did not differ significantly between all groups before vaccination (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05). After three immunizations, sera-specific IgG contents against rTgBFD1 appeared a significant increase (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, respectively) compared with PBS control and ISA 201 adjuvant group (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>). Similarly, the same considerable rise tendencies were observed both in the IgG1 and IgG2a levels after vaccinations (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, respectively), and IgG1 was the major subtype (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figures 4B,C</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Antibody titers of rTgBFD1 specific IgG antibodies detected by rTgBFD1-ELISA. Ten rTgBFD1 immunized mice sera were collected and used for rTgBFD1-ELISA while the normal mice sera served as the negative control. The dotted line represents the cutoff value at 0.64.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-957479-g0003.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Specific antibody responses analyses in mice inoculated with rTgBFD1. <bold>(A)</bold> Alterations in sera-specific IgG contents at 0 and 6 weeks after vaccination. <bold>(B)</bold> Alterations in sera-specific IgG1 contents at 0 and 6 weeks after vaccination. <bold>(C)</bold> Alterations in sera-specific IgG2a contents at 0 and 6 weeks after vaccination. Data were shown as mean &#177; SD from ten mice per group and analyzed by a one-way ANOVA. ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001 and ns (non-significant) compared with the PBS control and the ISA 201 adjuvant group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-957479-g0004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Cytokine response to rTgBFD1 vaccination</title><p>To determine cellular immune response induced by TgBFD1, serum cytokine levels (IL-12p70, IL-4, IFN-&#947;, and IL-10) were detected using ELISA. Serum samples were obtained before immunization (week 0) and at 6 weeks post-immunization with ISA 201-rTgBFD1. As observed in <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>, mice sera multiple cytokines levels did not differ significantly between all groups before vaccination (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05). Approximately 6 weeks after immunization, there were no statistical differences in IL-12p70 and IL-4 contents among the groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05, respectively) (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figures 5A,B</xref>). By contrast, IFN-&#947; and IL-10 levels in ISA 201-rTgBFD1 immunized mice sera were notably higher than that in control groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001, respectively) (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figures 5C,D</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F5" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Multiple cytokines IL-12p70 <bold>(A)</bold>, IL-4 <bold>(B)</bold>, IFN-&#947; <bold>(C)</bold>, IL-10 <bold>(D)</bold> concentrations of rTgBFD1 vaccinated mice at 0- and 6-weeks post-immunization. Data were shown as mean &#177; SEM from ten mice per group and analyzed by a one-way ANOVA. *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001 and ns compared with the PBS control and the ISA 201 adjuvant group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-957479-g0005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Immunization with rTgBFD1 was effective against <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection</title><p>Intraperitoneal infection of 10<sup>2</sup> tachyzoites of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> RH strain led to all the mice's death around 7 days post infection (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6A</xref>). By contrast, mice survival time did not present a significant difference between PBS control and ISA 201 adjuvant groups (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05). However, in ISA 201-rTgBFD1 immunized group, mice survival time was monitored slightly longer than the PBS control group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><fig position="float" id="F6" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Mice survival time analyses and brain cyst number statistics. <bold>(A)</bold> Mice survival time analyses in <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> RH strain infection assay. Data were analyzed by the Kaplan&#8211;Meier method. <bold>(B)</bold> Mice survival times analyses in the <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> PRU strain infection assay. The survival of PRU strain-infected mice was observed for a 60-day period. Data were analyzed by the Kaplan&#8211;Meier method. *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs. PBS control group. <bold>(C)</bold> Brain cyst number statistics of mice challenged with the <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> PRU strain. Data were presented as mean &#177; SEM and analyzed by a one-way ANOVA. *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 vs. PBS control group.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-957479-g0006.jpg"/></fig><p>As indicated in the <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6B</xref>, all mice from the ISA 201-rTgBFD1 immunized group infected oral gavage with 10 cysts of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> PRU strain survived over 2 months of observation. However, there were one mouse in the ISA 201 adjuvant group and two mice in PBS control group died in this assay. In particular, of primary concern was the brain cyst burdens, which decreased markedly in ISA 201-rTgBFD1 immunized mice brains compared with the PBS control group (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6C</xref>), with a rate of 36.4% (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The number of PRU cysts in rTgBFD1 pre-immunized mice brain.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Groups</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Cysts number in brain (mean &#177;SEM)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Cysts reduction rate (%)</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sPBS control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 &#177; 7<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISA 201 control</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 &#177; 11.1<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.09</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ISA 201-rTgBFD1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 &#177; 8.6<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Same letters in same column represent non-significant difference, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05. Different letters in same column represent significant difference, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Focusing on the current and potential harms posed by <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>, toxoplasmosis vaccine development for humans is required. Immunization with a live attenuated vaccine might lead to more excellent immunogenicity. However, as compared to this approach, recombinant subunit vaccines had exceptional safety and were rare to suffer any side effects since they were composed of high purity antigens. Thus, the identification of specific target proteins was the most essential factor for such a platform to work efficiently (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). In this study, the antigen TgBFD1 exhibited promising immunogenicity in the BALB/c mouse models. However, the immunization strategy entailing the use of adjuvant ISA 201 to improve the protective efficacy of rTgBFD1 was not satisfactory and improved adjuvant selection, or a more available antigen delivery system should be considered. Besides, according to the assessment of TgBFD1 vaccine efficacy, ISA 201-rTgBFD1 emulsion performed better in chronic toxoplasmosis infection than that in mice acute infection. This observation deserves more attention, so we believed that TgBFD1 still existed theoretical possibility to be a vaccine candidate.</p><p>The highly antigenic proteins are presumed as the most appropriate vaccine candidates (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). In the present study, we found that TgBFD1 has an important advantage owing to its immunogenicity, which is indicated by the epitope analysis. Further investigations also provided compelling evidence about the immunogenicity of rTgBFD1. In terms of Western blot and ELISA assays, TgBFD1 immunization not only elicited a strong rTgBFD1-specific humoral immune response but also could be identified by <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infected mice sera. Therefore, it is amply documented that TgBFD1 (921-1023aa) selected in this study was immunogenic.</p><p>As is known, <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> is an intracellular parasitic protozoan, Th1 immune response induced by the vaccine is advantageous for the host (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). The analysis of specific immune responses generated by rTgBFD1 suggested that ISA 201-rTgBFD1 can elicit both cell and humoral immunity with a mixed Th1/Th2 cells response. The elevated specific IgG, IgG1, and IgG2a contents indicated that rTgBFD1 triggered an IgG1-dominant immune response (Th2), which might lead to a very limited contribution to the survival of immunized mice challenged with <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>. Besides, we also attempted to elucidate the immunologic mechanisms from the changes in cytokine contents perspective. As the Th1-type cytokines, IL-12 and IFN-&#947; have significant roles in preventing <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). As seen in published studies, IFN-&#947; could induce immunity against toxoplasmosis by effectively facilitating CD8<sup>+</sup> T cell maturation to exert its cytotoxic functions (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Meanwhile, IL-12 was able to serve a synergistic effect during the infection stage. The concentration of cytokine IL-12 did not have elevation trend, but as expected, IFN-&#947; contents exhibited a clear ascending trend compared with controls, which might help to prevent <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection and to promote cysts clearance from mice brains. As a key immunoregulator, cytokine IL-10 could inhibit Th1 cell activities to maintain a balanced immune response (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) and played significant roles in controlling inflammatory responses throughout the <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> acute infection period (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Thus, as observed in IL-10 levels, an upward trend was presented at 6 weeks post-immunization compared with controls. It is well known that IL-4 as a Th2 cytokine would normally exhibit the antagonistic function of IFN-&#947; (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). The detection results of IL-4 concentrations appeared insignificant changes in the present study.</p><p>For the reasons of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> virulence and infection route, two strains (<italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> RH and PRU) were selected for our research. To date, a complete protection against the <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> RH strain, which displayed a highly virulent in mice strains, is not available. After rTgBFD1 vaccination, limited protection mediated by the recombinant proteins was observed in the acute assay. Although the rTgBFD1 inoculations prolonged the survival time of mice from the point of view of statistical analysis, there was an extra average of 0.5 days more than the mice survival time in the PBS control group. However, this does not mean that the rTgBFD1 vaccine has no value. Noteworthy is that the method of intraperitoneally infecting <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> tachyzoites in mice commonly performed in experimental studies was due to its facile operation. However, this manner was not a natural route. Therefore, oral inoculation with <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> cysts by mimicking a natural infecting manner was warranted (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). In the chronic assay, the <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> PRU cyst number investigated in mice immunized with rTgBFD1 suggested a significant degradation of cyst load, which might be realized by the specific antibodies and multiple cytokines induced by the vaccination of rTgBFD1. From the outcome of the animal assays, the rTgBFD1 vaccine had a better performance in the <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> PRU cyst infection stage. Furthermore, it is critical to recognize that only RH and PRU strains were verified in the current study, that different virulence of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> strains should be taken into account, and whether rTgBFD1 could generate efficient protection against <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> required more investigations.</p><p>As we all know, the primary purpose of active vaccination is to develop protective immune responses against <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection. Given that the vaccines based on a single recombinant protein do not provide satisfactory protection after infection with <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic>, multiple-immunogen combination vaccine should be considered when optimizing future vaccine regimens. In addition, some other factors may influence the effectivity of inoculation procedures (e.g., mice gender, breeds, age, vaccination plans, <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> strains as well as sources of <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> cysts, etc.) (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Moreover, in view that the vaccination will induce remarkably complex immune responses in mice, we still lacked a systemically summary and comprehensive evaluation of the immune response produced by rTgBFD1 under several parameters in mice experiments. Hence, the optimization of vaccination programs and more comprehensive immune response detections generated by rTgBFD1 should be taken into consideration in further research. Only then can the satisfying vaccine candidate be attained.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>On the whole, this study suggests that TgBFD1 is a good immunogen. Subcutaneous boosting with rTgBFD1 emulsified with ISA 201 adjuvant not only contributes to a strong humoral and cellular immune response but also has better protective efficacy for the hosts against chronic <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infection. However, in spite of some desirable properties indicating that rTgBFD1 can be studied as a vaccine candidate from <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> infected mouse models, further integrated investigations are still required to enhance the immune protective effects of TgBFD1.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be made available by the authors, without undue reservation.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by the Ethics Committee of Xinxiang Medical University (Approval number XYLL-2021S016).</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Conception or design of this study: XL, SW, and XT. Direction and supervision: XM, ZZ, and XL. Data analysis and drafting of this article: XT and ZY. Material acquisition: XT, GW, TX, HS, and MW. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="s9"><title>Funding</title><p>The current work received support from the Science and Technology Planning Project of Henan Province (Nos. 212102310749 and 222102310557), the Key Scientific Research Projects of Colleges and Universities in Henan Province (22A310004), the Doctoral Scientific Research Activation Foundation of Xinxiang Medical University (No. XYBSKYZZ202139), and the Scientific Research Cultivation Project of School of Basic Medical Sciences in Xinxiang Medical University (Nos. JCYXYKY202115 and JCYXYKY202103).</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s10"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madireddy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivas Chacon</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mangat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Toxoplasmosis</article-title>. 2021 Sep 28. In: <italic toggle="yes">StatPearls</italic>. Treasure Island, FL: StatPearls Publishing. (<year>2021</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33085433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almeria</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Foodborne transmission of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> infection in the last decade. An overview</article-title>. <source>Res Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>135</volume>:<fpage>371</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rvsc.2020.10.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33148402</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vado-Sol&#237;s</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su&#225;rez-Sol&#237;s</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jim&#233;nez-Delgadillo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zavala-Vel&#225;zquez</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Segura-Correa</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> presence in women with spontaneous abortion in Yucatan, Mexico</article-title>. <source>J Parasitol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>383</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1645/GE-3189.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22924922</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubey</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> abortion storm in sheep on a Texas farm and isolation of mouse virulent atypical genotype <italic toggle="yes">T. gondii</italic> from an aborted lamb from a chronically infected ewe</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2012.09.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23099088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vittecoq</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elguero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lafferty</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roche</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brodeur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gauthier-Clerc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Brain cancer mortality rates increase with <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> seroprevalence in France</article-title>. <source>Infect Genet Evol.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>496</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2012.01.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22285308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeffers</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tampaki</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A latent ability to persist: differentiation in <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic></article-title>. <article-title>Cell Mol Life Sci</article-title>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>75</volume>:<fpage>2355</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-018-2808-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5988958</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29602951</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Antczak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dzitko</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#322;ugo&#324;ska</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Human toxoplasmosis-searching for novel chemotherapeutics</article-title>. <source>Biomed Pharmacother.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>82</volume>:<fpage>677</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopha.2016.05.041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27470411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>NZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Recent advances in developing vaccines against <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic>: an update</article-title>. <source>Expert Rev Vaccines.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1609</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1586/14760584.2015.1098539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26467840</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foroutan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghaffarifar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharifi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalimi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jorjani</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rhoptry antigens as <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> vaccine target</article-title>. <source>Clin Exp Vaccine Res.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>26</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7774/cevr.2019.8.1.4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30775347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6369123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foroutan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zaki</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghaffarifar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Recent progress in microneme-based vaccines development against <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic></article-title>. <source>Clin Exp Vaccine Res</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>103</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7774/cevr.2018.7.2.93</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30112348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6082678</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fereig</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nishikawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Towards a preventive strategy for toxoplasmosis: current trends, challenges, and future perspectives for vaccine development</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>1404</volume>:<fpage>153</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4939-3389-1_10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27076296</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Buxton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Innes</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A commercial vaccine for ovine toxoplasmosis</article-title>. <source>Parasitology.</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>110</volume>:<fpage>S11</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S003118200000144X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7784124</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Advances in <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> vaccines: Current strategies and challenges for vaccine development</article-title>. <source>Vaccines (Basel).</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>413</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vaccines9050413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33919060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8143161</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezaei</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarvi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharif</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hejazi</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pagheh</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aghayan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A systematic review of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> antigens to find the best vaccine candidates for immunization</article-title>. <source>Microb Pathog.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>126</volume>:<fpage>172</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2018.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30399440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Cristina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Del Porto</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buffolano</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beghetto</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spadoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guglietta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> bradyzoite antigens BAG1 and MAG1 induce early humoral and cell-mediated immune responses upon human infection</article-title>. <source>Microbes Infect.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>164</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micinf.2003.11.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14998514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Waldman</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wadsworth MH</surname><given-names>2nd</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saeij</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shalek</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lourido</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of a master regulator of differentiation in <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma</italic></article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>180</volume>:<fpage>359</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>372.e16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2019.12.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31955846</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6978799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hiszczy&#324;ska-Sawicka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gatkowska</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grzybowski</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#322;ugo&#324;ska</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Veterinary vaccines against toxoplasmosis</article-title>. <source>Parasitology.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>141</volume>:<fpage>1365</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>78</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182014000481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24805159</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouguyon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goncalves</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shevtsov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maisonnasse</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Remyga</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goryushev</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>new adjuvant combined with inactivated influenza enhances specific CD8 T cell response in mice and decreases symptoms in swine upon challenge</article-title>. <source>Viral Immunol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>524</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/vim.2014.0149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26447972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Immune protection of rhoptry protein 21 (ROP21) of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> as a DNA vaccine against toxoplasmosis</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>909</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.00909</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29867820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5951983</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ehsan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The N- and C-terminal carbohydrate recognition domains of <italic toggle="yes">Haemonchus contortus</italic> galectin bind to distinct receptors of goat PBMC and contribute differently to its immunomodulatory functions in host-parasite interactions</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>409</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-017-2353-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28870237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5584048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> Tyrosine Hydroxylase (TH) activity and molecular immunoprotection against toxoplasmosis</article-title>. <source>Vaccines</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>158</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vaccines8020158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32244791</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7349186</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>DNA vaccination with a gene encoding <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> Deoxyribose Phosphate Aldolase (TgDPA) induces partial protective immunity against lethal challenge in mice</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>431</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-7-431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25201636</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4164750</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vartak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sucheck</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Recent advances in subunit vaccine carriers</article-title>. <source>Vaccines.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vaccines4020012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27104575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4931629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Recent advances in vaccine technologies</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin North Am Small Anim Pract.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>231</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cvsm.2017.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29217317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7132473</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanova</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mundhenke</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gigley</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The IL-12- and IL-23-dependent NK cell response is essential for protective immunity against secondary <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>203</volume>:<fpage>2944</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>58</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1801525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31604804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6864276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carruthers</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> infection on the brain</article-title>. <source>Schizophr Bull.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>745</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/schbul/sbm008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17322557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2526127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sturge</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yarovinsky</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Complex immune cell interplay in the gamma interferon response during <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>82</volume>:<fpage>3090</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.01722-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24866795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4136216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Couper</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blount</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>IL-10: the master regulator of immunity to infection</article-title>. <source>J Immunol.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>180</volume>:<fpage>5771</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.180.9.5771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18424693</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gazzinelli</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wysocka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hieny</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scharton-Kersten</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheever</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>K&#252;hn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>In the absence of endogenous IL-10, mice acutely infected with <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic> succumb to a lethal immune response dependent on CD4+ T cells and accompanied by overproduction of IL-12, IFN-gamma and TNF-alpha</article-title>. <source>J Immunol.</source> (<year>1996</year>) <volume>157</volume>:<fpage>798</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>805</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8752931</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wille-Reece</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dzierszinski</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A critical role for IL-10 in limiting inflammation during toxoplasmic encephalitis</article-title>. <source>J Neuroimmunol.</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>165</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jneuroim.2005.04.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16005735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The immune potential and immunopathology of cytokine-producing B cell subsets: a comprehensive review</article-title>. <source>J Autoimmun.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaut.2014.04.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24794622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hiramoto</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galisteo</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>do Nascimento</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Andrade</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>200 Gy sterilised Toxoplasma gondii tachyzoites maintain metabolic functions and mammalian cell invasion, eliciting cellular immunity and cytokine response similar to natural infection in mice</article-title>. <source>Vaccine.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>2072</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0264-410X(02)00054-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11972976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jongert</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gargano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>F&#246;rster-Waldl</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Vaccines against <italic toggle="yes">Toxoplasma gondii</italic>: challenges and opportunities</article-title>. <source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>105</volume>:<fpage>252</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0074-02762009000200019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19430651</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>