<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9878700</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC9878700.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">9878700</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">9878700</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36713856</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.1077555</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract on serum biochemical parameters, humoral immune response, and intestinal health in young pigeons</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaoshan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1979435/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zheng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/778245/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="X">Xing</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names initials="S">Shaohua</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names initials="D">Dongmei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yuxin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c002" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/832955/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Pigeon Breeding Laboratory, Institute of Animal Husbandry and Veterinary Medicine, Beijing Academy of Agriculture and Forestry Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>College of Life Science and Food Engineering, Hebei University of Engineering</institution>, <addr-line>Handan</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Balamuralikrishnan Balasubramanian, Sejong University, South Korea</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Adham Al-Sagheer, Zagazig University, Egypt; Ali Daneshmand, University of New England, Australia; Utthapon Issara, Rajamangala University of Technology Thanyaburi, Thailand; Hyeun Bum Kim, Dankook University, South Korea</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Dongmei Lin &#9993; <email>314725254@qq.com</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Yuxin Shao &#9993; <email>syu123@sina.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Animal Nutrition and Metabolism, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn002"><p>&#8224;These authors have contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">400313</issue-id><elocation-id>1077555</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>27</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-10-29 15:25:17.840"><day>29</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 Sun, Wang, Li, Du, Lin and Shao.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sun, Wang, Li, Du, Lin and Shao</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-09-1077555.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>It is of great importance to find antibiotic alternatives that can improve poultry performance and enhance immunity. Plant-derived extracts and their concentrates are natural bioactive compounds that are widely and effectively applied as the antibiotic alternatives in animal industries. This study was conducted to investigate the effects of <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract (YSE) on growth performance, serum biochemical parameters, immune function, intestinal morphology, and microbiota diversity of young pigeons.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>A total of 120 healthy White King pigeons (28 days old) with similar weight were randomly assigned to 4 treatments with six replicate cages. Each of the pigeons from 4 treatments was orally administrated with 0 (control), 5, 10, and 15 mg YSE per day, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The results showed that orally supplemental YSE had no significant effects (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05) on the growth performance and immune organ index of pigeons. The serum total protein and IgM contents in the 10 mg YSE group were significantly higher (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) than those in the control group. Supplemental 10 and 15 mg YSE significantly lowered the level of serum total cholesterol (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) and increased (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) the villi height in the jejunum compared with the control group. Supplemental 5 and 10 mg YSE significantly decreased (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) the level of serum alanine aminotransferase and the crypt depth in the ileum compared with the control group. The beta diversity showed a distinct difference in the ileum microbial composition between the control and the 10 mg YES group. YSE supplementation enriched the bacterial genera <italic toggle="yes">Sulfurospirillum, Solobacterium, Desulfovibrio, Desulfobulbus, Lactococcus, Parabacteroides, Acidaminococcus, Acetobacter</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus</italic>. Additionally, <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> genus showed a significantly negative correlation with serum alanine aminotransferase (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic> = &#8722;0.618, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.043). <italic toggle="yes">Actinomyces</italic> genus showed a significantly negative correlation with cholesterol (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic> = &#8722;0.633, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.036). <italic toggle="yes">Turicibacter</italic> genus showed a significantly positive correlation with villi height in the jejunum (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic> = 0.751, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.008).</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>In conclusion, orally supplemental YSE could improve serum biochemistry, immunoglobulin contents, and intestinal morphology by regulating the composition of microbial community in the ileum of young pigeons.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract</kwd><kwd>young pigeons</kwd><kwd>serum indexes</kwd><kwd>immune function</kwd><kwd>intestinal flora</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The present study was supported by the Pigeon Breeding Laboratory, Institute of Animal Husbandry and Veterinary Medicine, Beijing Academy of Agriculture and Forestry Sciences.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="6"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="55"/><page-count count="14"/><word-count count="8038"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Currently, domestic pigeons (<italic toggle="yes">Columba livia</italic>) are raised as a sort of commercial meat-type poultry in China (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), with a yearly production of around 680 million squabs, accounting for 80% of worldwide production (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). However, pigeons are the reservoirs of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Trichomonas gallinae</italic>, and young pigeons during 1&#8211;3 months old are very susceptible to infection because of the weaning stress (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Although antibiotics have played a critical role in preventing pathogen infection and promoting animal production, the food and drug security organizations have called for restricting the use of antibiotics and chemotherapies in poultry, livestock, and aquaculture because of their adverse consequence on the development of antimicrobial resistance, and thereby posing a potential threat to human health (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Thus, it is urgent to find antibiotic alternatives to improve growth performance, enhance immunity, and reduce stress of young pigeons (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Plant-derived extracts and their concentrates are natural bioactive compounds that are widely and effectively applied as the antibiotic alternatives in animal industries (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Our team previously conducted an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> study on the functions of eleven plant extracts, and finally found that <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract (YSE) can effectively inhibit the number of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli, Salmonella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Trichomonas</italic>, and promote the growth of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic>. Hence, we decided to further explore the potential role of YSE in young pigeons.</p><p>As a medicinal plant extract, YSE has been widely used as a natural additive in food industries. It has numerous health benefits, including hypocholesterolemic, hypoglycemic, anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, anticancer, and immunostimulatory properties (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Besides, YSE application in aquatic animals could effectively improve feed utilization, growth rate, and immune responses (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). And, it has also been demonstrated that in the livestock and poultry industries, YSE plays a significant role in promoting growth and production performance and reducing ammonia emission (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). It was reported that dietary supplemental YSE could improve intestinal barrier function and reduce nitrogen emission in sow and weaned piglets (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Furthermore, <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> administration increased the digestion of essential minerals, improved intestinal health and reduced the growth of pathogenic bacteria in broilers (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). However, whether supplemental YSE has benefits on young pigeons' intestinal health and immune system function has not been examined. We hypothesized that adding an appropriate level of YSE could improve the intestinal health and immune function of young pigeons. The current study's objective was to assess the effects of supplemental YSE on growth performance, serum biochemical indices, immune system function, and intestinal health, which could provide a theoretical basis for determining the appropriate requirment of YSE for young pigeons.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Animals and treatment procedure</title><p>The study was carried out in accordance with the guidelines set by the Animal Care and Use Committee (permit number: SYXK-2017-0005) of the Institute of Animal Husbandry and Veterinary Medicine, Beijing Academy of Agriculture and Forestry Sciences (IAHVM-BAAFS), Beijing, China. The protocols were approved by the Animal Care and Use Committee of IAHVM-BAAFS.</p></sec><sec><title>Birds, diets, and experimental design</title><p>A total number of 120, 28-day-old healthy White King pigeons with similar weight and size were randomly divided into four treatments, each consisting of six replicate cages (five birds per cage). The four groups were the control group, 5 mg YSE addition group (YSE5), 10 mg YSE addition group (YSE10), and 15 mg YSE addition group (YSE15). The pigeons were fed a mixed grain diet, and the compound feed was composed of maize, pea, soybean meal, wheat, and sorghum. The feed, sand, and water were available <italic toggle="yes">ad libitum</italic>. The ingredients and nutrient levels are shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Birds were raised in a room under a 16 h light and 8 h darkness cycle, and the temperature was kept at 22 &#177; 6&#176;C during the entire experimental period. After acclimatization for 1 week, the control group was orally administrated with 1mL/bird/day 0.9% NaCl solution, and the other groups were orally administrated with 1mL/bird/day YSE solution. All the birds were gavaged by a pipette with sterilized tips at 10 am once a day after feeding 3h throughout the entire experiment. The YSE was dissolved in 0.9% NaCl solution with the final concentration of 5, 10, and 15 mg/mL. We selected the tested levels of YSE according to the published studies about the roles of YSE in quails and hens (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Based on their dietary YSE levels (50, 100, and 150 mg/kg) and daily feed intakes (0.09 kg/d for hens), the levels of YSE (5, 10, and 15 mg/d per pigeon) were used in this study. The experiment lasted 14 days.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Ingredient compositions and nutrient levels of basal diets for young pigeons (on as-fed basis)<xref rid="TN1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919497; color:#ffffff;"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Ingredients</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Content %</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Nutrient composition<xref rid="TN3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maize</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.60</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolizable energy (Kcal/kg)<xref rid="TN3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,796</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.30</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crude protein<xref rid="TN4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sorghum</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.80</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcium<xref rid="TN4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pea</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.80</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phosphorus<xref rid="TN4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>d</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5%</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean meal</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean oil</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CaHPO<sub>4</sub>&#183;2H<sub>2</sub>O</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limestone</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NaCl</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DL-Methionine</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vitamin and mineral premix<xref rid="TN2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><label>a</label><p>The diet was composed of 70% whole-grain (maize, pea, wheat, and sorghum) and 30% pellet feed, and the pellet feed was composed of crushed maize, soybean meal, soybean oil, CaHPO<sub>4</sub>&#183;2H<sub>2</sub>O, limestone, NaCl, DL-Methionine and vitamin and mineral premix.</p></fn><fn id="TN2"><label>b</label><p>Supplied per kilogram of diet:vitamin A 4000 IU, vitamin D3 1725 IU, vitamin E 20 U, vitamin K3 1.0 mg, vitamin B1 2.5 mg, vitamin B2 8 mg, vitamin B6 2.5 mg, vitamin B12 0.015 mg, Pantothenic acid 7.5 mg, Niacin 15 mg, Folic acid 0.55 mg, Biotin 0.12 mg, Choline 200 mg, Zn (ZnSO<sub>4</sub>.7H<sub>2</sub>O) 50 mg, Cu (CuSO4.5H<sub>2</sub>O) 8 mg, Mn (MnSO<sub>4</sub>.H<sub>2</sub>O) 55 mg, Fe (FeSO<sub>4</sub>&#8226;7H<sub>2</sub>O) 40 mg, I (KI) 0.35 mg, Se (Na<sub>3</sub>SeO<sub>3</sub>) 0.15 mg.</p></fn><fn id="TN3"><label>c</label><p>Calculated values.</p></fn><fn id="TN4"><label>d</label><p>Analyzed values and each value based on triplicate determinations.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>YSE product and the main ingredients</title><p>The YSE (20.0% purity) was purchased from a commercial supplier (Xi'an Ruidi Biotechnology Co., Ltd., Xi'an, China). It is in the form of brown yellow powder with good water solubility. The main ingredients of YSE include the total flavonoids, phenols, polysaccharides, and saponins, and they were determined by the biochemicals kits (Norminkoda Biotechnology Co., Ltd. Wuhan, China). The contents of total flavonoids, phenols, polysaccharides, and saponins were 8.02 &#177; 0.058, 8.22 &#177; 0.240, 566.5 &#177; 7.071, 27.3 &#177; 0.853 mg/g, respectively based on triplicate assays.</p></sec><sec><title>Growth performance</title><p>Before weighing, the pigeons fasted for 12 h. Feed intake was recorded weekly. Pigeons, feed, and sand were weighed at 8 am on the first and last days of the experiment. Initial body weight (IBW), final body weight (FBW), average daily gain (ADG), average daily feed intake (ADFI), and the ratio of feed:gain (F/G) were measured and calculated at the end of the experiment.</p></sec><sec><title>Sample collection</title><p>On the 14th day of the experiment, six pigeons from each treatment (one bird from each replicate) were randomly selected. And, 7 mL of blood was collected aseptically from the wing portal vein and centrifuged at 3,000 &#215; g for 10 min at 4&#176;C, and the serum was obtained and stored at &#8722;20&#176;C for analysis of serum biochemical indexes. After collecting the blood, pigeons were killed by jugular exsanguination. The immune organs including the spleen, bursa, and thymus were collected and weighed after stripping fat, and the immune organ index was expressed as the organ weight relative to the living body weight (g/kg). Next, ~2-cm long segments of duodenum (the midpoint), jejunum (preceding the Meckel's diverticulum) and ileum (preceding the ileocecal junction) were separated and washed in PBS, fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde solution and kept at 4&#176;C for histological morphology analysis. The ileal contents were collected aseptically and stored at &#8722;80&#176;C for DNA extraction.</p></sec><sec><title>Serum biochemical parameters and immunoglobulins contents</title><p>The levels of total superoxide dismutase (T-SOD), total antioxidant capacity (T-AOC), alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), total triglyceride (TG), total cholesterol (T-CHO), albumin (ALB) and total protein (TP) in serum were determined by the commercial testing kits (Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute, Nanjing, China). Serum immunoglobulins concentrations, including immunoglobulin A (IgA), immunoglobulin G (IgG), and immunoglobulin M (IgM) were determined by ELISA tests (Bird IgA/IgG/IgM ELISA Quantitation kits, Shanghai Enzyme-linked Biotechnology Co., Ltd. Shanghai, China) following the manufacturer's protocol.</p></sec><sec><title>Intestinal histomorphology</title><p>Paraformaldehyde-fixed intestinal tissues were embedded in paraffin. Serial slices (5 &#956;m) were prepared using haematoxylin and eosin staining and observed for histomorphology under an Olympus optical microscope using ProgRes CapturePro software, version 2.7 (Jenoptik, Germany). The villus height (VH) and crypt depth (CD) were measured from 10 randomly selected villi and associated crypts with one section per bird at 40 &#215; magnification. The ratio of VH:CD was then calculated from the above measurements by dividing the villus height by the crypt depth.</p></sec><sec><title>DNA extraction and PCR amplification</title><p>The ileal contents were collected in sterilized plastic tubes and then immediately stored in liquid nitrogen to investigate the intestinal microflora. Total bacterial DNA was extracted from the collected digest samples using an E.Z.N.A. Stool DNA Kit (Omega Bio-Tek, Norcross, GA, USA) according to the manufacturer's protocol. The final DNA concentration and purity were determined by a NanoDrop 2000 UV&#8211;Vis spectrophotometer (Thermo Scientific, Wilmington, USA), and DNA quality was checked by 1% agarose gel electrophoresis. The V3-V4 hypervariable regions of the bacterial 16S rRNA gene were amplified with primers 338F (5&#8242;-ACTCCTACGGGAGGCAGCAG-3&#8242;) and 806R (5&#8242;-GGACTACHVGGGTWTCTAAT-3&#8242;) (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) using a thermocycler PCR system (GeneAmp 9700, ABI, Vernon, CA, USA). The PCR reactions were conducted with a high-fidelity polymerase using the following program: 3 min of denaturation at 95&#176;C, 27 cycles of 30 s at 95&#176;C, 30 s for annealing at 55&#176;C, and 45 s for elongation at 72&#176;C, and a final extension at 72&#176;C for 10 min. PCR reactions were performed in triplicate according to previous studies (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). The PCR products were visualized in a 2% agarose gel, and then purified using an AxyPrep DNA Gel Extraction Kit (Axygen Biosciences, Union City, CA, USA), and quantified using QuantiFluor-<sup>TM</sup>ST (Promega, USA) according to the manufacturer's protocol (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Illumina MiSeq sequencing of 16S rRNA gene</title><p>Purified amplicons were pooled in equimolar amounts and paired-end sequenced (2 &#215; 300) on an Illumina MiSeq platform (Illumina, San Diego, USA) according to the standard protocols (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) by Majorbio Bio-Pharm Technology Co., Ltd. (Shanghai, China). The raw reads were deposited into the NCBI Sequence Read Archive (SRA) database (accession number: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="PRJNA81814" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">PRJNA81814</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec><title>Processing of sequencing data</title><p>Raw fastq files were quality filtered by Trimmomatic software and merged by FLASH software (version 1.2, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://ccb.jhu.edu/sofware/FLASH/index.shtml" ext-link-type="uri">https://ccb.jhu.edu/sofware/FLASH/index.shtml</ext-link>) (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Operational taxonomic units (OTUs) were clustered with a 97% similarity cutoff using UPARSE (version 7.1, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.drive5.com/uparse/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.drive5.com/uparse/</ext-link>) analysis (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). The taxonomy of each 16S rRNA gene sequence was analyzed by the Ribosomal Database Project Classifier algorithm (version 11.1) against the Silva (SSU128) 16S rRNA database using a confidence threshold of 70% (The result of species annotation has the highest reliability using 70% confidence threshold) (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>All data were analyzed using SPSS statistical software (version 20.0) and presented as means &#177; standard error. Differences were evaluated by one-way ANOVA, and comparisons between multiple groups were analyzed by <italic toggle="yes">post-hoc</italic> Duncan's multiple range test. Polynomial orthogonal contrasts were used to determine the linear and quadratic responses of dependent variables to YSE levels. The <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 were considered to be significant, and 0.05 &#8804; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.10 was defined as a tendency.</p><p>The beta diversity was analyzed by principal coordinate analysis diagram (PCoA) and hierarchical clustering by unweighted pair group method with arithmetic average (UPGMA). Kruskal-Wallis tests with Wilcoxon test were used to visualize the highly significant abundant taxa at phylum and genus levels among the groups.</p><p>Linear discriminant analysis for effect size (LEfSe) identifies features that are statistically different among biological classes (Kruskal-Wallis sum-rank test, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). It then performs additional tests to assess whether these differences are consistent with respect to expected biological behavior (Wilcoxon ran-sum test, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Lastly, the effect relevance is estimated by the linear discriminant analysis (LDA) effect size. Pearson correlation coefficients between the top 20 abundant bacterial genera and serum biochemical indexes or intestinal morphology were displayed on the heat map.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Growth performance</title><p>The data of growth performance were shown in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Supplementation of different levels of YSE had no significant effects (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05) on IBW, FBW, ADG, ADFI and F/G of the young pigeons.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The effect of supplemental different levels of YSE on the growth performance of young pigeons<xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919497; color:#ffffff;"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Items</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Control</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>YSE5</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>YSE10</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>YSE15</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Linear</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Quadratic</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IBW(g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">433.7 &#177; 10.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">437.0 &#177; 3.61</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">436.9 &#177; 7.84</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">436.4 &#177; 5.46</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.998</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.974</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.843</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FBW(g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">463.8 &#177; 35.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">461.4 &#177; 8.80</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">463.5 &#177; 22.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">469.5 &#177; 25.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.950</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.680</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.682</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADG(g/d)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15 &#177; 2.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.74 &#177; 0.80</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90 &#177; 1.58</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.36 &#177; 1.64</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.920</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.797</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.527</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADFI(g/d)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.6 &#177; 6.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.4 &#177; 4.36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.4 &#177; 7.39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.6 &#177; 4.44</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.730</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.415</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.473</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F/G</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.55 &#177; 6.68</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.17 &#177; 14.75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.75 &#177; 11.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.29 &#177; 17.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.554</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.682</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.265</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN5"><label>a</label><p>n = 6 replicates (5 young pigeons per replicate) per treatment.</p></fn><p>Control, 0.9% NaCl solution; YSE5, 5 mg/mL YSE; YSE10, 10 mg/mL YSE; YSE15, 15 mg/mL YSE.</p><p>IBW, initial body weight; FBW, final body weight; ADG, average daily gain; ADFI, average daily feed intake; F/G, feed/ gain ratio.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Immune organ index</title><p>The immune organ indexes, including spleen, bursa, and thymus indexes were shown in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. No significant differences were observed in spleen and thymus indexes among the four groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Effects of supplemental different levels of YSE on immune organ index of young pigeons (g/kg)<xref rid="TN6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919497; color:#ffffff;"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Items</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Control</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>YSE5</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>YSE10</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>YSE15</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Linear</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Quadratic</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thymus index</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00 &#177; 1.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80 &#177; 0.78</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.90 &#177; 0.75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 &#177; 0.91</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.343</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.150</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.469</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bursa of Fabricius index</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80 &#177; 0.39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70 &#177; 0.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 &#177; 0.37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40 &#177; 0.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.090</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.280</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.431</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spleen index</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 &#177; 0.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 &#177; 0.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40 &#177; 0.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 &#177; 0.71</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.910</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.644</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.855</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN6"><label>a</label><p>n = 6 replicates (5 young pigeons per replicate) per treatment.</p></fn><p>Control, 0.9% NaCl solution; YSE5, 5 mg/mL YSE; YSE10, 10 mg/mL YSE; YSE15, 15 mg/mL YSE.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Serum biochemical parameters and immunoglobulin contents</title><p>The comparison of serum biochemical parameters was shown in <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. The content of TP increased linearly and quadratically with the increase of YSE supplementation (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), and pigeons gavaged with 10 mg YSE had a higher level of TP than the the control pigeons (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The level of T-CHO decreased significantly linearly with the increase of YSE addition (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), and pigeons gavaged with 5 and 10 mg YSE had lower levels of T-CHO than the control pigeons (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The level of ALT decreased quadratically with the increase of YSE supplementation (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), and compared with the control group, orally supplemental 10 and 15 mg YSE significantly decreased the levels of ALT (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). There was no significant difference in the activities of T-SOD, T-AOC, ALB, TG, and AST among the four groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Effects of supplemental different levels of YSE on serum biochemical parameters of young pigeons<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919497; color:#ffffff;"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Items</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Control</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>YSE5</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>YSE10</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>YSE15</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Linear</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Quadratic</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TP (mg/mL)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.28 &#177; 3.11<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.78 &#177; 3.08<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.31 &#177; 4.75<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.48 &#177; 4.97<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALB (g/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.0 &#177; 2.73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.22 &#177; 1.93</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.81 &#177; 1.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.52 &#177; 2.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.169</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.144</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.195</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63 &#177; 0.49</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.34 &#177; 1.57</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29 &#177; 0.49</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10 &#177; 0.59</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.758</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.307</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.899</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-CHO (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.79 &#177; 0.31<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.69 &#177; 0.65<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05 &#177; 0.35<sup>d</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.20 &#177; 0.34<sup>cd</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.496</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-AOC (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 &#177; 0.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 &#177; 0.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 &#177; 0.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97 &#177; 0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.792</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.686</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.446</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-SOD (U/mL)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.5 &#177; 1.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5 &#177; 1.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.2 &#177; 0.86</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.9 &#177; 1.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.374</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.472</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.158</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT (U/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.0 &#177; 16.7<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.4 &#177; 6.25<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.24 &#177; 6.67<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.4 &#177; 9.28<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.205</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST (U/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.4 &#177; 12.3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.2 &#177; 7.40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.9 &#177; 16.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.4 &#177; 15.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.176</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.747</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN7"><label>a</label><p>n = 6 replicates (5 young pigeons per replicate) per treatment.</p></fn><p><sup>b&#8722;d</sup>Within a row with no common superscripts differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><p>Control, 0.9% NaCl solution; YSE5, 5 mg/mL YSE; YSE10, 10 mg/mL YSE; YSE15, 15 mg/mL YSE.</p><p>TP, total protein; ALB, albumin; TG, total triglyceride; T-CHO, total cholesterol; ALT, alanine transaminase; AST, aspartate transaminase; T-AOC, total antioxidant capacity; T-SOD, total superoxide dismutase; ALT, alanine aminotransferase; AST, aspartate aminotransferase.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>A comparison of serum IgA, IgG, and IgM activity was shown in <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>. The content of IgM increased significantly linearly with the increase of YSE supplementation (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), and pigeons gavaged with 10 mg YSE had a higher serum IgM content than the the control pigeons (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). There was no significant difference in the serum IgG and IgA contents among the four groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Effects of supplemental different levels of YSE on serum immunoglobulins of young pigeons<xref rid="TN8" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919497; color:#ffffff;"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Items</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Control</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>YSE5</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>YSE10</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>YSE15</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Linear</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Quadratic</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgA (&#956;g/mL)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.6 &#177; 17.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.3 &#177; 16.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.9 &#177; 12.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.6 &#177; 17.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.532</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.246</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.658</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgG (&#956;g/mL)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">312.0 &#177; 54.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">281.3 &#177; 50.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">272.2 &#177; 72.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">297.4 &#177; 62.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.683</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.637</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.272</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgM (&#956;g/mL)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110.7 &#177; 11.7<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106.3 &#177; 16.1<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141.5 &#177; 7.1<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120.4 &#177; 22.8<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.224</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN8"><label>a</label><p>n = 6 replicates (5 young pigeons per replicate) per treatment.</p></fn><p><sup>b, c</sup>Within a row with no common superscripts differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><p>Control, 0.9% NaCl solution; YSE5, 5 mg/mL YSE; YSE10, 10 mg/mL YSE; YSE15, 15 mg/mL YSE.</p><p>IgA, immunoglobulin A; IgG, immunoglobulin G; IgM, immunoglobulin M.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Histomorphological parameters in the small intestine</title><p>The duodenum, jejunum, and ileum morphology, including VH, CD, and VH/CD were shown in <xref rid="T6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>. In the duodenum, no significant differences were observed in the VH, CD, and VH/CD among groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05). The VH in the jejunum increased linearly with the increase of YSE supplementation (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), and compared with the control group, orally supplemental 10 and 15 mg YSE increased significantly the VH (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). There were no significant differences in the CD and VH/CD among groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05). In the ileum, the CD decreased quadratically the increase of YSE supplementation (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), and pigeons gavaged with 5 mg and 10 mg YSE had lower CD than the the control pigeons (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). No significant differences were observed between the VH and VH/CD among the four groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Effect of supplemental different levels of YSE on the histomorphological parameters in the small intestine of young pigeons<xref rid="TN9" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919497; color:#ffffff;"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Items</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Control</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>YSE5</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>YSE10</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>YSE15</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic> value</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Linear</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Quadratic</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duodenum</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VH (&#956;m)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">542.5 &#177; 45.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">535.6 &#177; 47.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">605.9 &#177; 42.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">572.5 &#177; 56.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.233</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.132</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.590</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD (&#956;m)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.3 &#177; 9.84</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.5 &#177; 13.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.0 &#177; 4.38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.6 &#177; 4.70</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.692</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.627</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.942</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VH/CD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3 &#177; 2.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.1 &#177; 2.44</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3 &#177; 2.34</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.93 &#177; 0.89</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.987</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.826</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.939</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jejunum</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VH (&#956;m)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">344.0 &#177; 41.2<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">409.4 &#177; 41.9<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">432.8 &#177; 61.0<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">461.2 &#177; 56.3<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.424</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD (&#956;m)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.1 &#177; 4.58</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.0 &#177; 10.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.5 &#177; 7.82</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.8 &#177; 5.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.411</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.116</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.594</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VH/CD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.65 &#177; 1.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.92 &#177; 1.93</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.15 &#177; 2.39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.74 &#177; 2.18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.597</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.451</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.653</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ileum</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VH (&#956;m)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">168.9 &#177; 40.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.8 &#177; 22.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130.3 &#177; 53.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154.5 &#177; 20.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.350</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.520</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.099</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CD (&#956;m)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.7 &#177; 3.98<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.6 &#177; 9.93<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2 &#177; 4.80<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.4 &#177; 1.90<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.249</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VH/CD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.21 &#177; 1.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.22 &#177; 0.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.79 &#177; 0.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.97 &#177; 0.54</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.207</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.916</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN9"><label>a</label><p>n = 6 replicates (5 young pigeons per replicate) per treatment.</p></fn><p><sup>b, c</sup>Within a row with no common superscripts differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><p>Control, 0.9% NaCl solution; YSE5, 5 mg/mL YSE; YSE10, 10 mg/mL YSE; YSE15, 15 mg/mL YSE; VH, villus height; CD, crypt depth; VH/CD, the ratio of villus height to crypt depth.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Intestinal microflora</title><p>According to the results of different levels of YSE on serum biochemical and intestinal morphology-related indicators, pigeons gavaged with 10 mg YSE had significantly higher levels of TP and IgM than other three groups. And, pigeons gavaged with 10 and 15 mg YSE had a lower level of T-CHO and a higher VH in jejunum than the control group. Besides, pigeons gavaged with 5 and 10 mg YSE had lower levels of ALT and CD in ileum than the control group. Thus, based on the beneficial effects of YSE on the serum biochemical parameters, immunoglobulin contents, and intestinal morphology, the level of 10 mg YSE was chosen for further experiment. In addition, the ileum is the longest segment among the three small intestinal segments in young pigeons, so the contents of the ileum were chosen to analyze the microbial diversity and composition.</p></sec><sec><title>Histogram analysis-phylum and genus level</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>, Firmicutes, Proteobacteria, and Actinobacteria were the main phyla in the ileum, and they accounted for 98.02% in the control group and 98.47% in the YSE10 group. At the phylum level, the analysis results showed that orally supplemental YSE increased the relative abundances of Patescibacteria and Desulfobacterota in the ileum of young pigeons (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The composition of microbiota and the comparison of differences at the level of phylum in the ileum of young pigeons. <bold>(A)</bold> Percent of community abundance. <bold>(B)</bold> Wilcoxon rank-sum test bar plot. The relative abundances of phylum in all samples' sequence &lt;0.01 are classified as &#8220;others&#8221;. Control, 0.9% NaCl solution; YSE10, 10 mg/mL YSE.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1077555-g0001.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The composition of microbiota and the comparison of differences at the level of genus in the ileum of young pigeons. <bold>(A)</bold> Percent of community abundance. <bold>(B)</bold> Wilcoxon rank-sum test bar plot. The relative abundances of genus in all samples' sequence &lt;0.01 are classified as &#8220;others&#8221;. Control, 0.9% NaCl solution; YSE10, 10 mg/mL YSE.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1077555-g0002.jpg"/></fig><p>As shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, the dominant genera of the ileum were <italic toggle="yes">Entrococcus, Leucobacter</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">unclassified_f_ _Microbacteriaceae</italic>. At the genus level, the analysis results showed that compared with the control group, the relative abundances of <italic toggle="yes">norank_f__norank_o__Saccharimonadales, Clostridium_sensu_stricto_1, unclassified_f__Butyricicoccaceae, Arcobacter, Desulfovibrio, Acetobacter, unclassified_f_ _Rhodocyclaceae, unclassified_f__Carnobacteriaceae, Solibacillus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Lactococcus</italic> were increased in YSE10 group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Alpha diversity of microbial community</title><p>The abundance-based coverage estimator (ACE) index, Chao index, Shannon index, and Simpson index were selected to analyze alpha diversity within a community (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). There were no significant differences observed among the groups in the ACE index, Chao index, Shannon index, and Simpson index (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05).</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Alpha diversity of two groups. <bold>(A)</bold> Ace index; <bold>(B)</bold> Chao index; <bold>(C)</bold> Simpson index; <bold>(D)</bold> Shannan index. Control, 0.9% NaCl solution; YSE10, 10 mg/mL YSE.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1077555-g0003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Beta diversity of microbial community</title><p>Principal co-ordinates analysis (PCoA) was used to analyze the effects of YSE on the beta diversity of the microbial community based on the unweighted UniFrac metric, which was calculated based on the genus and relative abundance of the samples (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). The result displayed that a significant difference was observed in the diversity of the microbial communities between the control and the YSE10 group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.033).</p><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Principal component analysis of operational taxonomic units. PC1, principal coordinate (1) PC2, principal coordinate; (2) Control, 0.9% NaCl solution; YSE10, 10 mg/mL YSE.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1077555-g0004.jpg"/></fig><p>We used the LDA to determine the taxa that most likely explain the differences between the YSE10 and control samples (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>). Significant differences in microbiota were found when the LEfSe algorithm was used on genus-level OTU tables to determine taxa that characterize each biological class. The result confirmed the bacterial genera <italic toggle="yes">Sulfurospirillum, Solobacterium, Desulfovibrio, Desulfobulbus, Lactococcus, Parabacteroides, Acidaminococcus, Acetobacter</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Streptococcus</italic> were significantly enriched in the YSE10 group compared with those in the control.</p><fig position="float" id="F5" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>LDA Effect Size (LEfSe) algorithm was used on genus-level OTU tables to determine taxa that best characterize each biological class. Control, 0.9% NaCl solution; YSE10, 10 mg/mL YSE. LDA, linear discriminant analysis.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1077555-g0005.jpg"/></fig><p>A heatmap was used to assess the correlations among the bacterial genera, and serum biochemical parameters, immunoglobulin, and intestinal morphological structure by color shades (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>). The correlation heatmap showed that <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> had a significantly negative correlation with ALT (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic> = &#8722;0.618, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.043), but <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> had a significantly positive correlation with ALT (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic> = 0.682, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.021). A significantly negative correlation was observed between <italic toggle="yes">Actinomyces</italic> and cholesterol (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic> = &#8722;0.633, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.036), and a significantly positive correlation was observed between <italic toggle="yes">Turicibacter</italic> and the VH in jejunum (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic> = 0.751, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.008).</p><fig position="float" id="F6" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>A heatmap showing correlations among the bacterial genera, serum biochemical indexes, and intestinal morphology. <italic toggle="yes">X</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Y</italic> axes are environmental factors and genera, respectively. Red indicates a positive correlation; blue indicates a negative correlation. <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05 is marked with &#8220;*&#8221;, and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001 is marked with &#8220;**&#8221;. ALT, alanine aminotransferase; T-CHO, total cholesterol; IgM, immunoglobulin M; TP, total protein.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1077555-g0006.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Different from other poultry, pigeons are fed crop milk and soaked grains by parents in a mouth-to-mouth manner for nearly 28 days after hatching (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Thereafter, they gradually learn to feed independently, and some pigeons with good performance were reserved as the breeding pigeons. However, the changes of feeding patterns and the separation from breeding parents could bring a &#8220;weaning&#8221; stress for the 28-day-old young pigeons. And at this time, young pigeons are vulnerable to pathogenic microorganisms such as <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Trichomonas</italic>, leading to a high mortality (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Therefore, the young pigeons at 28 days reserved for breeding were focused on in the current study, so as to improve the health condition of young pigeons from the foundation. Previous studies demonstrated that dietary YSE supplementation improved the growth performance of broiler chickens during 1&#8211;42 days (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Unfortunately, the growth performance of young pigeons after adding YSE did not improve significantly in present study, and similar results had been reported in laying quails and hens (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). The body weight of pigeons changed very little after 28 days, implying that the 28-day-old pigeons have reached the mature body weight (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Perhaps YSE might be more effective in growth performance of the fast-growing broilers or squabs, not in the young pigeons. Besides, it may be caused by low levels of saponins (2.7%) and phenolic compounds (0.8%) in our YSE that could not improve digestion, absorption, and utilization of nutrients in the digestive tract (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>).</p><p>In addition, the thymus, bursa of Fabricius and spleen are important immune organs of birds, and the development of immune organs has an important impact on the immune function of the body (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). However, in our study, YSE did not result in any discernable effects on the weight of these organs. It is possible that the experiment duration (14 days) is too short to assess the effects of YSE on immune organs. In addition to immune organs, immune molecules also play important roles in regulating immune reactions among the immune system (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Serum IgG, IgM, and IgA contents are essential immune molecules to measure the functional status of the humoral immune system (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). In our study, the serum IgM level in the YSE10 group was significantly higher than in the control group. Dietary supplemental YSE significantly increased the IgG level observed in laying hens and broilers (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). These results indicated that YSE seems to be more advantageous in production of immunoglobulin. The main task of immunoglobulin in the immune system is to neutralize microorganisms and toxins <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> the nonspecific defense system of body. The steroidal saponin is one of the main chemical constituents of <italic toggle="yes">Y. schidigera</italic> extract, which is most studied and has been shown to be capable of enhancing the natural immune response by stimulating the secretion of cytokines and triggering antibody production and humoral and cellular immune responses (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Most notably, whether the high level of polysaccharides in our YSE could have functions in regulating immunity needs further demonstration. At present, there are few published studies on the role of polysaccharides from YSE. Therefore, the actual mechanisms involved in the protective effects of YSE remain undefined.</p><p>Many serum biochemical indicators can reflect the changes in nutrient metabolism and organ functions of animals (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). Serum glucose, TG and TP contents commonly reflect sugar, fat and protein metabolism in animals (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). In this study, orally supplemental 10 mg YSE increased the serum TP contents, indicating the optimum level of YSE may raise the utilization of TP and effectively inhibit the catabolism of reserve TP in young pigeons. The transaminases of ALT and AST are broadly present in mitochondria and have become the primary screening tool for detecting liver injury (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). The serum ALT level in the YSE10 group was significantly lower than that in the control group. The low level of liver enzymes may be attributable to the repair of hepatic injury in birds administered with the lemongrass essential oil (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Lemongrass has a cytoprotective effect because of its phenolic components, and fortunately, YSE is also rich in phenolic components (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). We inferred that YSE may have a positive effect on improving liver function. Further investigations are expected to confirm the speculation. The concentration of serum T-CHO was used to evaluate the serum lipid level, which could reflect the health status of the body. Saponins can combine with cholesterol to form water-insoluble complexes, accelerating the conversion rate of cholesterol in the liver to bile acid, and the content of cholesterol in the serum was reduced (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). Previous studies showed that dietary supplemental YSE decreased the serum T-CHO concentration in laying hens and quails (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). In this study, orally supplemental 10 and 15 mg YSE decreased serum T-CHO concentration in young pigeons, which is consistent with previous studies. In addition, it was reported that dietary supplemental YSE could increase the villus height and the villus height/crypt depth ratio of the intestine in broiler chickens (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). Our current study showed that orally supplemental YSE increased the villus height in the jejunum, and reduced the crypt depth in the ileum. It is concluded that YSE may promote intestinal development and enhance the integrity of the intestinal epithelium of young pigeons.</p><p>Gut microflora has important effects on the regulation of nutrient utilization, growth performance, energy homeostasis, and immune function by cooperating with the development of the gut system of the host (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). It was reported that <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> could reduce the diarrhea rate by the modification of the intestinal microbiota in weaned piglets (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). In this study, we found that oral supplementation of YSE enriched the abundance of Patescibacteria and Desulfobacterota phyla. In addition, the genera <italic toggle="yes">Sulfurospirillum, Solobacterium, Desulfovibrio, Desulfobulbus, Lactococcus, Parabacteroides, Acidaminococcus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Acetobacter</italic> were markedly increased in the YSE group. <italic toggle="yes">Desulfococcus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Desulfovibrio</italic> are the main components of sulfate-reducing bacteria (SRB), and <italic toggle="yes">Desulfovibrio</italic> may possess a variety of enzymes acting together to resist oxidative stress (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Meantime, the correlation results showed that <italic toggle="yes">Actinomyces</italic> was negatively correlated with cholesterol, and serum cholesterol in the YSE group decreased. The enzyme obtained from the mycelium of <italic toggle="yes">Actinomyces</italic> lavendula can effectively decrease cholesterol content (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). These results indicated that the YSE may reduce serum cholesterol levels by regulating the abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Actinomyces</italic> genus in the ileum. <italic toggle="yes">Actinobacteria</italic> can produce a wide range of secondary metabolites with structural diversity and are also the source of two-thirds of natural antibiotics and a series of anti-cancer, anti-worm, antifungal and immunosuppressive drugs (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Moreover, various studies investigated that the <italic toggle="yes">Desulfobacterota</italic> that has been found in the environment, but the proportion in intestinal microorganisms is relatively small and its function is seldom reported (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). In our study, <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus</italic> was negatively correlated with ALT. Dietary supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecium R1</italic> significantly reduced the activity of AST in the blood, so as to attenuate liver injury in LPS-challenged piglets (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). Therefore, our study indicated that the YSE supplementation has important influences on the intestinal microbial composition, and the serum biochemical parameters may alter as the changes in microbial communities.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In conclusion, orally supplemental 10 mg YSE could enhance the humoral immune function <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> increasing IgM content, regulate the serum biochemical indexes by decreasing the contents of alanine aminotransferase and total cholesterol, and improve intestinal health by promoting intestinal morphology and altering the beta diversity and composition of ileal microbiota. Therefore, YSE can be developed as a feed additive to boost the immunity and intestinal healthy of young pigeons.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The datasets presented in this study can be found in online repositories. The names of the repository/repositories and accession number(s) can be found in the article/supplementary material.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="s7"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by Animal Care and Use Committee (Permit number: SYXK-2017-0005) of the Institute of Animal Husbandry and Veterinary Medicine, Beijing Academy of Agriculture and Forestry Sciences (IAHVM-BAAFS), Beijing, China; Animal Care and Use Committee of IAHVM-BAAFS.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s8"><title>Author contributions</title><p>XS drafted the manuscript and conducted the experiment. XL and SD assisted the experiment. ZW and DL conceived the idea. YS modified the manuscript. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s10"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>QQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>XT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">in ovo</italic> injection of L-histidine on hatch performance and post-hatch development in domestic pigeons (<italic toggle="yes">Columba livia</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>3194</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>203</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pez046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30753623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>NX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>CQ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of dietary supplementation with dl-methionine and dl-methionyl-dl-methionine in breeding pigeons on the carcass characteristics, meat quality and antioxidant activity of squabs</article-title>. <source>Antioxidants (Basel).</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>435</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antiox8100435</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31581451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6826467</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Changes in the diversity and composition of gut microbiota in pigeon squabs infected with <italic toggle="yes">Trichomonas gallinae Sci Rep</italic></article-title>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>19978</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-76821-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33203893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7673032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Protective effects of Zinc on <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> invasion, intestinal morphology and immune response of young pigeons infected with <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> enterica serovar <italic toggle="yes">Typhimurium</italic></article-title>. <source>Biol Trace Elem Res</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>200</volume>:<fpage>4817</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12011-021-03057-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35028867</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Deep</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amber</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eid</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alrashood</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sakr</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The influence of dietary chicken egg lysozyme on the growth performance, blood health, and resistance against <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> in the growing rabbits' cecum</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>579576</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2020.579576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33195588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7593809</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Deep</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amber</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elgendy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawood</surname><given-names>MAO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elwakeel</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paray</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Oxidative stress, hemato-immunological, and intestinal morphometry changes induced by ochratoxin A in APRI rabbits and the protective role of probiotics</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>35439</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>48</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-09837-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32594444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saleh</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paray</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawood</surname><given-names>MAO</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Olive cake meal and bacillus licheniformis impacted the growth performance, muscle fatty acid content, and health status of broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Animals (Basel).</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>695</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani10040695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32316269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7222747</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dawood</surname><given-names>MAO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koshio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esteban</surname><given-names>M&#193;</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Beneficial roles of feed additives as immunostimulants in aquaculture: A review</article-title>. <source>Rev Aquac.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>950</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/raq.12209</pub-id>36100067</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Makkar</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bioactivity of phytochemicals in some lesser-known plants and their effects and potential applications in livestock and aquaculture production systems</article-title>. <source>Animal.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1371</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1751731107000298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22444893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lillehoj</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Calsamiglia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Miyakawa</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cravens</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Phytochemicals as antibiotic alternatives to promote growth and enhance host health</article-title>. <source>Vet Res.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>49</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13567-018-0562-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30060764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6066919</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alagawany</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd El-Hack</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Kholy</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Productive performance, egg quality, blood constituents, immune functions, and antioxidant parameters in laying hens fed diets with different levels of <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>6774</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-015-5919-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26662788</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elbialy</surname><given-names>ZI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salah</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elsheshtawy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rizk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abualreesh</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdel-Daim</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Exploring the multimodal role of Yucca schidigera extract in protection against chronic ammonia exposure targeting: growth, metabolic, stress and inflammatory responses in <italic toggle="yes">Nile tilapia</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Oreochromis niloticus</italic> L)</article-title>. <source>Animals (Basel)</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>2072</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani11072072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34359200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8300167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>F&#246;lde&#353;iov&#225;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bal&#225;&#381;i</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chrastinov&#225;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pivko</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kotwica</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrath</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> can promote rabbit growth, fecundity, affect the release of hormones <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>, induce pathological changes in liver, and reduce ovarian resistance to benzene</article-title>. <source>Anim Reprod Sci.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>183</volume>:<fpage>66</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anireprosci.2017.06.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28623008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saeed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arain</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naveed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alagawany</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd El-Hack</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhutto</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> can mitigate ammonia emissions from manure and promote poultry health and production</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollut Res Int.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>35027</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-018-3546-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30368697</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wolin</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of monensin and lasalocid-sodium on the growth of methanogenic and rumen saccharolytic bacteria</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol.</source> (<year>1979</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>72</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aem.38.1.72-77.1979</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16345418</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC243437</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2021</year>). <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract decreases nitrogen emission via improving nutrient utilisation and gut barrier function in weaned piglets</article-title>. <source>J Anim Physiol Anim Nutr (Berl).</source><volume>106</volume>:<fpage>1036</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jpn.13647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34668247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebru</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erdem</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Afsinya</surname><given-names>NU</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Torlak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> spraying in different litter materials on some litter traits and breast burn of broilers at the fifth week of production</article-title>. <source>Kafkas Univ Vet Fak Derg</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>749</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>753</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patra</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stiverson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of quillaja and yucca saponins on communities and select populations of rumen bacteria and archaea, and fermentation in vitro</article-title>. <source>J Appl Microbiol.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>113</volume>:<fpage>1329</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.2012.05440.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22925153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Camerlink</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract on growth performance and antioxidative function of small intestine in broilers</article-title>. <source>J Anim Physiol Anim Nutr (Berl).</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>103</volume>:<fpage>738</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jpn.13067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30702164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erdogan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Erdogan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of different dietary levels of <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> powder on the performance, blood parameters and egg yolk cholesterol of laying quails</article-title>. <source>J Vet Med A Physiol Pathol Clin Med.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>14</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1439-0442.2003.00487.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12650503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>CHY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An insight into intestinal mucosal microbiota disruption after stroke</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>568</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-18904-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29330443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5766598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dynamic alterations in yak rumen bacteria community and metabolome characteristics in response to feed type</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1116</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.01116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31191470</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6538947</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Spatial heterogeneity and co-occurrence of mucosal and luminal microbiome across swine intestinal tract</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>48</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.00048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29472900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5810300</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caporaso</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lauber</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berg-Lyons</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huntley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fierer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Ultra-high-throughput microbial community analysis on the Illumina HiSeq and MiSeq platforms</article-title>. <source>ISME J.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1621</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ismej.2012.8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22402401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3400413</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>UPARSE: highly accurate OTU sequences from microbial amplicon reads</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>996</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23955772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quast</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pruesse</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerken</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schweer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yarza</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peplies</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gl&#246;ckner</surname><given-names>FO</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The SILVA ribosomal RNA gene database project: improved data processing and web-based tools</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>D590</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gks1219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23193283</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3531112</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sales</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Janssens</surname><given-names>GPJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nutrition of the domestic pigeon (<italic toggle="yes">Columba livia domestica</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Worlds Poult Sci J.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>221</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/WPS20030014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12967260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>NX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>CQ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Leucine promotes the growth of squabs by increasing crop milk protein synthesis through the TOR signaling pathway in the domestic pigeon (<italic toggle="yes">Columba livia</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>5514</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pez296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31172174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaczorek-&#321;ukowska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sowi&#324;ska</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franaszek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dziewulska</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma&#322;aczewska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stenzel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Can domestic pigeon be a potential carrier of zoonotic <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic>?</article-title><source>Transbound Emerg Dis.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>2321</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tbed.13891</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33091215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8359358</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alfaro</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>AVF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maiorka</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Use of <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract in broiler diets and its effects on performance results obtained with different coccidiosis control methods</article-title>. <source>J Appl Poult Res.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>248</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>54</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/japr/16.2.248</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sahoo</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sethi</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract as feed additive on performance of broiler chicks in winter season</article-title>. <source>Vet World.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>556</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14202/vetworld.2015.556-560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27047134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4774811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chepete</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mendes LB Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ammonia emission and performance of laying hens as affected by different dosages of <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> in the diet</article-title>. <source>J Appl Poultry Res.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>522</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/japr.2011-00420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>CQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>MX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Growth curves and age-related changes in carcass characteristics, organs, serum parameters, and intestinal transporter gene expression in domestic pigeon (<italic toggle="yes">Columba livia</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>95</volume>:<fpage>867</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>77</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pev443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26787925</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of zinc-methionine on growth performance, intestinal flora and immune function in pigeon squabs</article-title>. <source>Br Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>403</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00071668.2014.919375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24784175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Work</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The immune system game</article-title>. <source>Am Biol Teach.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>382</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1525/abt.2015.77.5.11</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carsetti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosado</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wardmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Peripheral development of B cells in mouse and man</article-title>. <source>Immunol Rev</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>197</volume>:<fpage>179</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0105-2896.2004.0109.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14962195</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayoub</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sadek</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alagawany</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd El-Hack</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Othman S</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of liquid yucca supplementation on nitrogen excretion, intestinal bacteria, biochemical and performance parameters in broilers</article-title>. <source>Animals (Basel).</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1097</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani9121097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31818028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6940917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#252;m&#252;&#351;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imik</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effect of <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> powder added to lamb feed on fattening performance, some blood parameters, the immune system, and the antioxidative metabolism of the hepatic tissue</article-title>. <source>Turk J Vet Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>263</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3906/vet-1504-92</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nutrient digestibility, blood profiles and fecal microbiota are influenced by chitooligosaccharide supplementation of growing pigs</article-title>. <source>Livest Sci.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>125</volume>:<fpage>298</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>303</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.livsci.2009.05.011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghasemi</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of supplementary betaine on growth performance, blood biochemical profile, and immune response in heat-stressed broilers fed different dietary protein levels</article-title>. <source>J Appl Poult Res.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>301</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.japr.2019.11.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of dietary ramie level on growth performance, serum biochemical indices, and meat quality of Boer goats</article-title>. <source>Trop Anim Health Prod.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>1935</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11250-019-01891-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31134555</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alagawany</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Saadony</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Elnesr</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farahat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Attia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madkour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Use of lemongrass essential oil as a feed additive in quail's nutrition: its effect on growth, carcass, blood biochemistry, antioxidant and immunological indices, digestive enzymes and intestinal microbiota</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>101172</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2021.101172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33951594</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8111249</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Piacente</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montoro</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oleszek</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pizza</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> bark: phenolic constituents and antioxidant activity</article-title>. <source>J Nat Prod.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>882</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/np030369c</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15165156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bidinotto</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salvadori</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barbisan</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Protective effects of lemongrass (Cymbopogon citratus STAPF) essential oil on DNA damage and carcinogenesis in female Balb/C mice</article-title>. <source>J Appl Toxicol.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>536</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jat.1593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21089157</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sidhu</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oakenfull</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A mechanism for the hypocholesterolaemic activity of saponins</article-title>. <source>Br J Nutr.</source> (<year>1986</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>643</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/BJN19860070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3676181</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of caprylic acid and <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract on production performance, egg quality, blood characteristics, and excreta microflora in laying hens</article-title>. <source>Br Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>711</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00071668.2011.635638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22221237</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bafundo</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#228;nner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duerr</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The combination of quillaja and yucca saponins in broilers: effects on performance, nutrient digestibility and ileal morphometrics</article-title>. <source>Br Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>62</volume>:<fpage>589</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00071668.2021.1891523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33595409</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>B&#228;ckhed</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hooper</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The gut microbiota as an environmental factor that regulates fat storage</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>101</volume>:<fpage>15718</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0407076101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15505215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC524219</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isikhuemhen</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Performance assessment of broiler chickens given mushroom extract alone or in combination with probiotics</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>1856</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ps/86.9.1856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17704371</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ziema Bumbie</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of dietary <italic toggle="yes">Yucca schidigera</italic> extract and oral candida utilis on growth performance and intestinal health of weaned piglets</article-title>. <source>Front Nutr</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>685540</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnut.2021.685540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34124128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8187599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fournier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dermoun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Oxygen defense in sulfate-reducing bacteria</article-title>. <source>J Biotechnol.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>126</volume>:<fpage>87</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>100</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2006.03.041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16713001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Imshenetskii</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikitin</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nazarova</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shirshova</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muntian</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Decomposition of human blood cholesterol by the enzyme from <italic toggle="yes">Actinomyces</italic> lavendulae</article-title>. <source>Prikl Biokhim Mikrobiol.</source> (<year>1979</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>715</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">514995</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Demain</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Microbial drug discovery: 80 years of progress</article-title>. <source>J Antibiot (Tokyo).</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>62</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ja.2008.16</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19132062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7094699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biggerstaff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eichhorn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ewing</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shahan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soriano</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genomic characterization of three novel <italic toggle="yes">Desulfobacterota</italic> classes expand the metabolic and phylogenetic diversity of the phylum</article-title>. <source>Environ Microbiol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>4326</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1462-2920.15614</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34056821</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary supplementation with <italic toggle="yes">Enterococcus faecium R1</italic> attenuates intestinal and liver injury in piglets challenged by lipopolysaccharide</article-title>. <source>Animals (Basel).</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1424</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani11051424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34065711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8156331</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>