<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9263622</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC9263622.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">9263622</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">9263622</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35812860</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.852251</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effects of Galactomannan Oligosaccharides on Growth Performance, Mycotoxin Detoxification, Serum Biochemistry, and Hematology of Goats Fed Mycotoxins-Contaminated Diets</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yicheng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1461336/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names initials="A">Ao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names initials="X">Xiaokang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1786387/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ran</surname><given-names initials="T">Tao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1634522/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="G">Guijie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names initials="C">Chuanshe</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c002" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1572793/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhiliang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/384657/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>CAS Key Laboratory for Agro-Ecological Processes in Subtropical Region, National Engineering Laboratory for Pollution Control and Waste Utilization in Livestock and Poultry Production, Hunan Provincial Key Laboratory of Animal Nutrition Physiology and Metabolic Process, Institute of Subtropical Agriculture, Chinese Academy of Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Changsha</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>University of Chinese Academy of Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>College of Animal Science and Technology, Hunan Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Changsha</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>College of Pastoral Science and Technology, University of Lanzhou</institution>, <addr-line>Lanzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>School of Agriculture, Ningxia University</institution>, <addr-line>Yinchuan</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><sup>6</sup><institution>Hunan Co-innovation Center of Animal Production Safety, CICAPS</institution>, <addr-line>Changsha</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Elsa Lamy, University of &#201;vora, Portugal</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Yangchun Cao, Northwest A&amp;F University, China; Mohamed E. Abd El-Hack, Zagazig University, Egypt</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Tao Ran <email>rant@lzu.edu.cn</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Chuanshe Zhou <email>zcs@isa.ac.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Animal Nutrition and Metabolism, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn002"><p>&#8224;These authors have contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>6</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">400313</issue-id><elocation-id>852251</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>09</day><month>07</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2022-07-11 16:17:44.487"><day>11</day><month>07</month><year>2022</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2022 Wu, Ren, Lv, Ran, Zhang, Zhou and Tan.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wu, Ren, Lv, Ran, Zhang, Zhou and Tan</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-09-852251.pdf"/><abstract><p>This study was conducted to investigate the protective effects of mycotoxin adsorbent galactomannan oligosaccharides (GMOS) on growth performance, fermentation parameters, mycotoxins residues, serum biochemistry and oxidative stress parameters of the goats. The <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> test indicated that 0.05% GMOS outperformed yeast cell wall (YCW) and montmorillonite (MMT) in aflatoxins absorption. Then 20 3-month-old <italic toggle="yes">Xiangdong</italic> black goats (15.0 &#177; 1.9 kg) were randomly divided into two dietary treatments for the animal test. The control group (CON group) was fed a multi-mycotoxins contaminated diet, whereas the experimental group (GMOS group) received multi-mycotoxins contaminated diet plus 0.05% GMOS. The trail lasted for 60 days, with 12 days of adaptation period and 48 days of formal experiment period. There were no treatment effects (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.10) on growth performance, serum antioxidant capacity and activities of serum aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT), and alkaline phosphatase (ALP). The concentrations of zearalenone in the rumen were lower (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the GMOS group. GMOS significantly reduced (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) propionate concentration in the cecum, resulting in a rise (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01) in acetate/propionate ratio in GMOS as compared to CON. Goats of GMOS exhibited considerably greater (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) levels of creatine kinase but lower (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.02) levels of creatinine than CON. Compared with CON, GMOS supplementation significantly increased (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) platelet count (PLT), platelet volume distribution width (PDW), and platelet hematocrit (PCT), while decreased (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) albumin content (ALB). The 0.05% GMOS protected goats in ruminal fermentation parameters, mycotoxins residues and serum biochemistry. Moreover, GMOS had no adverse effect on goat health. To our knowledge, this is the first report of GMOS in small ruminants. These findings suggested the feasibility of dietary GMOS as a health-maintaining addictive in goat diets.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>galactomannan oligosaccharides</kwd><kwd>mycotoxins</kwd><kwd>biochemical parameters</kwd><kwd>goat</kwd><kwd>detoxification</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="6"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="45"/><page-count count="9"/><word-count count="6356"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The prevalence of mycotoxins in feed is one of the major factors affecting feed quality, particularly in the humid and rainy areas of southern China (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Mycotoxins can affect animal health, with poultry being the most sensitive, followed by pigs and ruminants (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Toxins such as aflatoxins B1 (AFB1), ochratoxin A (OTA), zearalenone (ZEN) and deoxynivalenol (DON) have been detected throughout the food chain, contaminating animal products (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Therefore, mycotoxins of feed origin are regarded as a significant threat to human and animal health worldwide. Bentonite, Zeolite and activated charcoal are widely used for mycotoxin elimination to reduce their impact (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). However, they bind to minerals and vitamins in the diet (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). As a result, researchers have concentrated their efforts on developing effective methods for removing mycotoxins from the diets without substantial nutrient loss.</p><p>Functional oligosaccharides are widely used as feed additives due to their green and non-toxic qualities (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Both galactomannan oligosaccharides (GMOS) and mannan oligosaccharides (MOS) are functional oligosaccharides (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>) and the use of GMOS and MOS as feed additives have been approved in China (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Previous report has shown that MOS can dramatically promote the proliferation of beneficial bacteria in the gastrointestinal tract (GIT), thereby enhancing animal immune function, and regulating animal growth and metabolism (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). For ruminants, MOS maintained the overall health and performance of crossbred calves (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) and dairy calves (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). In addition, the capacity of MOS to adsorb mycotoxins such as ZEN and OTA had been well established using static <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> models (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p><p>Due to the special GIT structure of ruminants, it is commonly considered that rumen microbes could degrade oligosaccharides and weaken their activity (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). However, based on the positive effects of MOS on growth performance in sheep and MOS is an effective organic adsorbent to bind various mycotoxins while posing no toxicity to essential dietary components (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). We hypothesized that adding GMOS to goat diets would be beneficial to the adsorption of mycotoxins in the GIT, hence alleviating the deleterious impact of mycotoxins on animal health. To our knowledge, this is the first report of GMOS on the efficiency of toxin decontamination in small ruminants.</p><p>Therefore, the current study sought to evaluate the effects of GMOS supplementation in mycotoxin-contaminated diets on the growth and health of goats and establish a theoretical basis for the use of GMOS as a mycotoxin adsorbent in goat feeds.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>The present study included an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> mycotoxin adsorption experiment and a goat feeding trial. The <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> experiment was carried out at the Institute of Subtropical Agriculture, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Changsha, China in May 2019; while the animal study was conducted at the <italic toggle="yes">Xiangdong</italic> Black Goat Reproduction Center, Liuyang, Hunan province, China from 29 April 2019 to 27 June 2019.</p><sec><title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> Toxins Adsorption Test</title><p>The adsorbents used in the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> adsorption test included GMOS, yeast cell wall (YCW) and montmorillonite (MMT). The GMOS was kindly provided by Jiangsu Kangwei Biologic Co., Ltd. (Jiangsu, China); yeast cell wall (YCW) and montmorillonite (MMT), provided by Xuzhou Saifu Biological Co., Ltd. (Xuzhou, China), were used as controls to determine the toxin adsorption efficiencies of GMOS. All other reagents were of analytical grade or higher and purchased from Jiangsu Kangwei Biologic Co., Ltd. (Jiangsu, China). Feed materials were stored at 37&#176;C and 15% humidity for a week to let them mildew (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>). Feed samples were collected, dried, pooled, and ground through a 1 mm screen for AFB1 extraction. Five grams of feed powder was weighed into a 50 mL conical tube (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, USA) that contained 20 mL of a mixture of methanol: water (1:1 v/v). The mixture was vigorously mixed on a multitube vortexer for 10 min, followed by centrifugation at 4,000 rpm for 5 min. The supernatants were collected and filtered through 0.45 &#956;m filters (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, USA), used as testing samples. Adsorbent solutions of different concentrations (0.00, 0.01, 0.02, 0.03, 0.04, 0.05, 0.06, 0.07, 0.08, and 0.09%) were prepared by diluting GMOS with ultra-pure water. The <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> adsorption experiment was then performed as described by Saleemi et al. (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Then the concentration of GMOS with the best toxin adsorption efficiency was selected for further comparision with conventional adsorbents such as YCW (0.05%), MMT (0.05%) following the methods described by Marroquin et al. (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). The concentrations of AFB1 extracted from feed samples treated with or without adsorbents were measured using an enzyme-linked immunosorbent assays (ELISA) kit (Neogen Co., Shanghai, China) according to the description of Aazami et al. (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Animal Management and Dietary Treatments</title><p>Twenty <italic toggle="yes">Xiangdong</italic> goats (3-month-old, 15.0 &#177; 0.1 kg) were randomly divided into two feeding treatments. The control group (CON) was fed a naturally contaminated diet, while the GMOS group (GMOS) was fed the control diet supplemented with 0.05% GMOS, which was added to the naturally contaminated diet in the mixer as the last step in mixing. The ingredients and nutrient compositions, and the initial mycotoxin concentrations of the basal experimental diets are illustrated in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Ingredients and nutrient compositions of the experimental diet (DM basis).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Ingredients</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Contents (%)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Nutritional level</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Contents (%)</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corn stalk</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.00</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ME (MJ/kg)<sup>1</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.52</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corn</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.44</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CP (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.69</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean meal</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EE (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.06</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soy protein concentrate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.45</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NDF (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fat powder</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.09</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADF (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Salt</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RDP (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.91</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Premix<sup>2</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RUP (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.78</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcium carbonate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcium (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcium hydrogen phosphate</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phosphorus (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic toggle="yes">ME, metabolic energy; CP, crude protein; EE, ether extract; NDF, neutral detergent fiber; ADF, acid detergent fiber; RDP, rumen digested protein; RUP, rumen undigested protein.</italic>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes"><sup>1</sup>ME was calculated according to Zhang (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>).</italic>
</p><p><italic toggle="yes"><sup>2</sup>Premix composition (Premix/kg): provided per kilogram of diet: vitamin A, 419,491.5254 IU/kg; vitamin E, 12,711.86441 IU/kg; Ferric, 1.5 g/kg; Copper, 0.5 g/kg; Cobalt, 0.0055 g/kg; Iodine, 0.0075 g/kg.; Manganese, 3 g/kg; Zinc, 2.5 g/kg; Selenium, 0.0025 g/kg</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The animal study lasted 60 days, with 12 days of pre-feeding and 48 days of formal experiment. All goats were housed individually in stainless steel metabolic cages (150 &#215; 60 &#215; 80 cm) with plastic slatted floors. Goats were individually fed a naturally contaminated diet twice daily (08:00 and 18:00) with the same amount of diet. All goats had free access to clean water. During the feeding trial, body weight was recorded weekly before morning feeding. Feed offered and refusals for each goat were recorded daily throughout the experiment period to calculate the dry matter intake (DMI), average daily gain (ADG), and feed to gain ratio (F/G).</p></sec><sec><title>Sample Collection and Handling</title><p>Refusals and experimental diets were sampled for chemical analysis. Feed samples were oven-dried at 65&#176;C for 72 h, ground to pass through a 1-mm sieve and sealed in bags before chemical analysis. Blood samples were obtained by jugular venipuncture before morning feeding on the 27<sup>th</sup> and 28<sup>th</sup> of the formal experimental period. A pair of 5 ml blood samples were collected into test tubes (Guangzhou Improve Medical, China), among which one contained EDTA for the routine hematological parameters and the other tube contained no anticoagulants for the serum biochemical analysis. After 30 min still standing, samples were centrifuged at 3,500 rpm for 15 min, 1 ml plasma was taken for antioxidant capacity and biochemical parameters analysis. At the end of the experiment, all goats were fasted for 24 h and water was withheld for 12 h. The animals were weighed, electrically stunned, and exsanguinated under commercial procedures. One hundred milliliter rumen content and 20 g cecum content were extracted upon euthanasia with an alcohol-cleaned spatula and stored at &#8722;80&#176;C. Cecal digesta was diluted with deionized water. After vortexing, ~10 ml rumen content and cecum content were centrifuged at 10,000 rpm for 15 min at 4&#176;C, 1 ml supernatant was transferred into tubes containing 0.1 ml of 25% (w/v) metaphosphoric acid, and then frozen at &#8722;20&#176;C for subsequent determination of volatile fatty acids (VFAs) and ammonia nitrogen (NH<sub>3</sub>-N) concentration. Frozen feed materials, ruminal and cecal content samples were thawed, dried, pooled, and ground through a 1 mm screen for AFB1, ZEN and DON extraction.</p></sec><sec><title>Samples Analyses</title><p>Feed samples and feces were used for nutrient composition analysis. The dry matter (DM) (method 934.01), ash (method 927.02), ether extract (EE, method 920.39), crude protein (CP, method 976.06), calcium (Ca, method 978.02), total phosphorus (TP, method 946.06) were determined according to AOAC (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Neutral detergent fiber (NDF) and acid detergent fiber (ADF) contents were determined using a Fibretherm Fiber Analyzer with F57 filter bags (ANKOM A200, ANKOM Technology Corp., Fairport, NY, USA) according to Van Soest et al. (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Rumen degradable protein (RDP), rumen undegradable protein (RUP) were calculated according to the description of Kekana et al. (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). The AFB1, ZEN and DON residues in the ruminal and cecal contents of the two treatments and the basal diet were carried out according to the description of Guo et al. (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>).</p><p>Volatile fatty acids and NH<sub>3</sub>-N concentrations were measured according to Chen et al. (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Hematological examination of blood samples was performed following the standard method reported by Bafti and Mozaffari (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>) using a CELL-DYN 3700 analyzer. Routine hematological parameters include white blood cell (WBC), mononuclear cells (MON), eosinophil granulocyte counts (EOS), basophil granulocyte counts (BAS), neutrophils (NEU), lymphocyte (LYM), red blood cell counts (RBC), platelet count (PLT), platelet volume distribution width (PDW), and platelet hematocrit (PCT) were tested. The detection of serum antioxidant capacity, including total antioxidant capacity (T-AOC), superoxide dismutase (SOD) and malondialdehyde (MDA) levels were performed using commercial kits according to the manufacturer's protocols (Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute, Nanjing, China). Serum activities of alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alkaline phosphatase (ALP) and creatine kinase (CK) and concentrations of albumin (ALB), blood urea nitrogen (BUN) and creatinine (CREA) were determined using an automatic biochemistry analyzer (Sekisui Medical Co. Ltd., Tokyo, Japan) using commercially available kits (Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute, Nanjing, China).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>All data were processed preliminarily by Excel. Then the data of the growth performance, toxins concentration, fermentation parameters, serum biochemistry, and hematology indexes of the two groups were analyzed using the Shapiro&#8211;Wilk test for normal distribution and followed by student <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>-test to compare means using SPSS 19.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, USA) (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Statistical significance was defined as <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05, and tendencies at 0.05 &#8804; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.10.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Ability of GMOS to Adsorb Mycotoxins <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic></title><p>The results of GMOS on adsorbing aflatoxins in a naturally contaminated diet are presented in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. The added level of 0.05% GMOS showed the lowest AFB1 concentration (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>), suggesting the best efficacy in adsorbing AFB1. Furthermore, the concentration of AFB1 in 0.05% GMOS treat was significantly lower (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) than 0.05% YCW and 0.05% MMT treats (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref>), indicating that 0.05% GMOS outperformed traditional adsorbents like YCW and MMT in absorption of aflatoxins.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The ability of GMOS to adsorb mycotoxins (Aflatoxins B1, AFB1), which were measured <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> using ELISA. <bold>(A)</bold> Effects of different addition levels of GMOS (0.00, 0.01, 0.02, 0.03, 0.04, 0.05, 0.06, 0.07, 0.08, and 0.09%) on AFB1 concentration. <bold>(B)</bold> Effects of 0.05% GMOS, 0.05% Yeast cell wall (YCM), 0.05% Montesserstone (MMT) on AFB1 concentration. <sup>a, b</sup> Mean values within a row with different superscript letters were significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-852251-g0001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Dry Matter Intake, Average Daily Gain, and Feed to Gain Ratio</title><p>The DMI, ADG and F/G of goats from GMOS treatment were numerically more remarkable than that of CON goats in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>; however, not reach statistically significant differences (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.10).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effects of dietary supplementation of GMOS on growth performance in goats.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Parameter</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>Treatments</bold>
<sup>
<bold>1</bold>
</sup>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SEM</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-Value</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CON</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>GMOS</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial BW (kg)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.91</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Final BW (kg)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DMI (g/d)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">332.52</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">347.45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADG (g/d)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.57</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.62</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F/G</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic toggle="yes">BW, body weight; DMI, dry matter intake; ADG, average daily gain; F/G, feed to gain ratio; SEM, standard error of the mean.</italic>
</p><p><italic toggle="yes"><sup>1</sup>CON, control diet, without additive; GMOS, control diet + 0.05% GMOS</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Mycotoxins Concentration in the Gastrointestinal Tracts</title><p>The concentrations of mycotoxins including AFB1 and DON did not differ between CON and GMOS treatments either in ruminal or cecal digesta; whereas, the concentration of ZEN in rumen was significantly lower (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01) in GMOS treatment than that in CON (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Notably, the concentration of ZEN in cecal digesta was greater than that in ruminal digesta.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Effects of dietary supplementation of GMOS on concentrations of toxins in the gastrointestinal digesta in goats.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Gastrointestinal</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Parameters</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>Treatments</bold>
<sup>
<bold>1</bold>
</sup>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SEM</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-Value</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CON</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>GMOS</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rumen</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFB1 (&#956;g/kg)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZEN (&#956;g/kg)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.08<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.40<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DON (mg/kg)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cecum</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFB1 (&#956;g/kg)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.82</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZEN (&#956;g/kg)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104.13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.78</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DON (mg/kg)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic toggle="yes"><sup>a, b</sup>Mean values within a row with different superscript letters were significantly different (P &lt; 0.05).</italic>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">AFB1, aflatoxins B1; ZEN, zearalenone; DON, deoxynivalenol; SEM, standard error of the mean.</italic>
</p><p><italic toggle="yes"><sup>1</sup>CON, control diet, without additive; GMOS, control diet + 0.05% GMOS</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Fermentation Parameters</title><p>The results of NH<sub>3</sub>-N concentration, total and individual VFA, and A/P ratio was presented in <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. The amounts of NH<sub>3</sub>-N, TVFA, and the molar proportions of butyric acid, isobutyric acid, valeric acid and isovaleric acid in the rumen or cecum did not differ (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.10) between CON and GMOS treatments. In the rumen, the molar proportion of propionic acid was greater (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in GMOS than that in CON, and the molar proportion of acetic acid tended to be lower (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.08) in GMOS than that in CON, thus leading to a tendency of lower (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.07) A/P ratio in GMOS. On the contrary, the molar proportion of acetic acid in the cecum did not differ between CON and GMOS treatments, but the molar proportion of propionic acid was lower (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in GMOS than in CON, resulting in a more significant (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01) A/P ratio in GMOS.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Effects of dietary supplementation of GMOS on ruminal and cecal fermentation parameters in goats.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Gastrointestinal</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Parameters</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>Treatments</bold>
<sup>
<bold>1</bold>
</sup>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SEM</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-Value</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CON</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>GMOS</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rumen</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TVFA (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.74</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetate (A) (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.64</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propionate (P) (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.67<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.32<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Butyrate (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.82</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iso-butyrate (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valerate (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iso-valerate (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.68</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion A:P</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.69</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NH<sub>3</sub>-N (mg/100 ml)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cecum</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TVFA (&#956;mol/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.95</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acetate (A) (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.86</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Propionate (P) (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.95<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.60<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Butyrate (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.74</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iso-butyrate (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valerate (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iso-valerate (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion A:P</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.72<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.45<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NH<sub>3</sub>-N(mg/g)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic toggle="yes"><sup>a, b</sup>Mean values within a row with different superscript letters were significantly different (P &lt; 0.05).</italic>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes"><sup>1</sup>CON, control diet, without additive; GMOS, control diet + 0.05% GMOS.</italic>
</p><p><italic toggle="yes">SEM, standard error of the mean; TVFA, total volatile fatty acid</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Hematology, Serum Biochemical and Enzyme Parameters</title><p>The serum antioxidant indexes including SOD, T-AOC and MDA were not (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.10) different between CON and GMOS treatments (<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). <xref rid="T6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref> shows the impact of GMOS supplementation on hematologic parameters and serum biochemical indexes of goats. Compared to CON, the percentage of MON, PDW and PCT and counting of PLT were greater (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the GMOS supplemented group; whereas, the other indexes did not differ between the two treatments. As for the biochemical parameters, the Albumin (ALB) and creatinine (CREA) levels were significantly lower (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the GMOS group compared to the CON group. In contrast, the serum creatine kinase (CK) concentrations were markedly higher (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in goats fed GMOS than those fed only a control diet.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Effects of dietary supplementation of GMOS on serum antioxidant indexes of goats.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Parameter</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>Treatments</bold>
<sup>
<bold>1</bold>
</sup>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SEM</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-Value</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CON</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>GMOS</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SOD (U/ml)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.741</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T-AOC (U/ml)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDA (nmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.95</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.89</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic toggle="yes">SOD, superoxide dismutase; T-AOC, total anti-oxidation competence; MDA, malonaldehyde; SEM, standard error of the mean.</italic>
</p><p><italic toggle="yes"><sup>1</sup>CON, control diet, without additive; GMOS, control diet + 0.05% GMOS</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Effect of dietary supplementation of GMOS on hematological and serum biochemical parameters in goats.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Item</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1">
<bold>Treatments</bold>
<sup>
<bold>1</bold>
</sup>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>SEM</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-Value</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CON</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>GMOS</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<bold>Hematological parameters</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBC (10<sup>9</sup>/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MON (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.86<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.06<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EOS (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BAS (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.53</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NEU (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.79</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.99</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LYM (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.88</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.84</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RBC (10<sup>12</sup>/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.64</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PLT (10<sup>9</sup>/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.56<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">224.00<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.74</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDW (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.38<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.69<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCT (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.074<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<bold>Biochemical parameters</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALB (g/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.22<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.53<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALT (U/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.62</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.91</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AST (U/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114.52</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.52</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALP (U/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CK (U/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">259.12<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">296.38<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BUN (mmol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CREA (&#956;mol/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.12<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.28<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic toggle="yes"><sup>a, b</sup>Mean values within a row with different superscript letters were significantly different (P &lt; 0.05).</italic>
</p><p>
<italic toggle="yes">WBC, white blood cell; MON(%), mononuclear cells percentage; EOS, eosinophil granulocyte counts; BAS, basophil granulocyte counts; NEU, neutrophils; LYM, lymphocyte; RBC, red blood cell counts; PLT, platelet count; PDW, platelet volume distribution width; PCT, platelet hematocrit; ALB, albumin; ALT, alanine amino transferase; AST, aspartate amino transferase; ALP, alkaline phosphatase; CK, creatine kinase; BUN, blood urea nitrogen; CREA, creatinine; SEM, standard error of the mean.</italic>
</p><p><italic toggle="yes"><sup>1</sup>CON, control diet, without additive; GMOS, control diet + 0.05% GMOS</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>In the current study, the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> test results indicated that 0.05% GMOS outperformed traditional adsorbents like YCW and MMT in the absorption of aflatoxins. However, there was no difference in DMI, F/G, or ADG between the GMOS and the CON treatments. Previous studies have reported that dietary supplementation of MOS has been proven to enhance the performance of monogastric animals, including BW gain and feed conversion efficiencies (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). However, investigations on MOS in ruminants have yielded inconsistent results. Hill et al. (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>) observed no differences in DMI and ADG when 3 g/day of a MOS was added to the diet of young Jersey calves. Similarly, Westland et al. (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>) reported that dietary supplementation of 2 g of MOS to each calf daily did not improve the performance of calves. However, some other studies demonstrated enhanced ADG, AFDI, and feed efficiency in calves when a greater amount of MOS (4 g/calf/day) was supplemented in the diet (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>) or milk replacer (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Therefore, the growth performance of goats was not well improved as expected in the present study, likely attributed to the low dose of GMOS.</p><p>The <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> test revealed that toxin concentrations in the GIT were much lower than those detected in the diet (refer to <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Suppplementary Table 1</xref>). These were likely due to two reasons: on the one hand, the toxins were adsorbed by mannan products (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>); on the other hand, the complex GIT bacteria can degrade mycotoxins to different degrees (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Although GMOS effectively adsorbed AFB1 in <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> test, the concentrations of AFB1 did not differ between CON and GMOS treatments either in ruminal or cecal digesta, suggesting the importance of carrying out <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> animal study. DON and AFB1 are metabolized into less toxic substances by rumen microorganisms (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>), while ZEN is commonly transferred to metabolites like &#945;-zearalenol (&#945;-ZEL) and &#946;-zearalenol (&#946;-ZEL), which are significantly more hazardous than ZEN (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Currently, it is challenging to separate ZEN and its metabolites using ELISA assay due to their similar structures. Moreover, rumen microbes can also selectively utilize oligosaccharides as fermentation substrates (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Fewer GMOS reached the cecum, which is insufficient to change the mycotoxin concentration in the cecum. Therefore, the greater concentration of ZEN in cecal digesta than that in ruminal digesta was reasonable. Better analysis methods are needed to determine ZEN and its metabolites in the future. Our results suggested that GMOS could decrease the concentration of ZEN in the rumen; however, an insufficient amount of GMOS could adsorb ZEN in the cecum.</p><p>Then we investigated how GMOS affects the animal's fermentation parameters. GMOS did not change the TVAF concentration and the ruminal ammonia concentration. It significantly enhanced the molar proportion of propionate in the rumen but decreased that in the cecum. Wang et al. (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>) have reported that mycotoxins negatively impact ruminal and intestinal fermentation. In contrast, MOS can attenuate the adverse effects of mycotoxins by promoting the growth of beneficial bacteria such as <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> in the rumen, and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> is essential for the production of butyric and propionic acids (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). So we speculate that GMOS could also repair the detrimental effects of mycotoxins by promoting the growth of beneficial rumen bacteria. Furthermore, the small amount of GMOS reached the cecum, and the accumulation of toxins, especially ZEN, inhibited the growth of beneficial bacteria in the cecum.</p><p>Mycotoxins cause liver lesions and kidney damage with subsequent changes of some enzymatic parameters in goats (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Previous studies have shown that MOS have antioxidative properties in sheep and chickens, including increasing the serum levels of SOD and T-AOC while lowing serum MDA levels (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). In the current study, dietary supplementation GMOS had no effect on antioxidant indices in goats, including SOD, T-AOC and MDA. This finding suggested that GMOS supplementation would not cause any oxidative stress to small ruminants. Unaffected serum EOS and BAS levels used as stress indicators could also be robust support (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>), suggesting that GMOS supplementation did not cause stress to goats. Similarly, dietary supplementation MOS did not affect the WBC count, EOS or BAS of dairy cows (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Zheng et al. (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) reported that MOS did not significantly influence basal hematological parameters because their effects on the animal body are slight. In the current study, dietary supplementation of GMOS significantly increased routine blood indicators like MON, PCT, PLT and PDW. Previous study has shown a decrease in PLT and PDW (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>), MON and PCT (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) in pigs exposed to mycotoxins such as ZEN and DON. Generally, an increase in MON indicates enhanced resistance to pathogens (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). In addition, platelet-related parameters such as PCT, PLT and PDW are associated with inflammatory reactions and immune responses (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). The rising level of PCT, PLT and PDW indicated the potential of GMOS to affect hematological parameters. We speculate that GMOS could prevent mycotoxin attacks on the goats' immune system to some extent.</p><p>In general, mycotoxins reduces the concentrations of CK and the decrease in serum levels of this substance may reflect renal cell damage with leakage of the contents into the blood (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). The current experiment showed an elevated CK level in the GMOS group, suggesting that GMOS may mitigate the damage caused by mycotoxins to the kidneys. Nargeskhani et al. (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>) indicated that animals challenged by mycotoxins showed lower ALB level, the dropping level of serum ALB content indicated liver damage in animals. Although the current experiment showed decreased ALB content in the GMOS group, the ALB level was within the normal range (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). This is the first time we have found similar results. Furthermore, the serum levels of ALT, AST, and ALP were widely used to evaluate liver functions (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). The serum levels of ALT, AST, and ALP showed no differences between two treatments. Our results suggested that the addition of GMOS did not impair the serum biochemistry of goats. The similar result showed that the addition of mannan in diets had no deleterious effects on serum biochemistry and hematological characteristics of laying hen (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). These facts suggested that addition GMOS to goats' diet had no negative effects on their liver function. The presence of an increase in serum CREA level indicates the damage of kidney function (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). In our study, CREA level was significantly decreased (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in the GMOS group, suggesting that feeding a naturally contaminated diet to goats might impair kidney function and supplementation of GMOS could mitigate the nephrotoxicity. The decreased CREA level observed in our study was similar to the result reported by Raja et al. (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>It was concluded that GMOS at 0.05% level was beneficial in promoting the proliferation of beneficial rumen bacteria. GMOS could also alleviate mycotoxin injury on the liver and kidney. Further research is needed to evaluate the degradation of mycotoxins by rumen microorganisms. And more <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> experiments should be conducted to adjust the amount of GMOS in the diet for the adsorption effect of various mycotoxins. However, we can affirm the ability of GMOS as a green mycotoxin adsorbent. GMOS could serve as an economical solution to mycotoxicosis and make livestock feeding more cost-effective.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Material</xref>, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding authors.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by Animal Care and Use Guidelines of the Animal Care and the Use Committee, Institute of Subtropical Agriculture, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Changsha, PR China (Approval Number: ISA-2019-0115).</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>YW, AR, CZ, and ZT designed the experiment. YW, AR, and XL conducted the experiment. YW, AR, XL, and GZ collected and analyzed data. YW prepared the tables, prepared the figures, and wrote the manuscript. CZ acquired funding. TR and CZ revised the manuscript. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="s9"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was jointly supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (U20A2057 and 31730092) and National Basic Research and Development Program of China (2018YFD0501903).</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s10"><title>Publisher's Note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We would like to thank Teketay Wassie (Institute of Subtropical Agriculture, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Changsha, China) for his linguistic assistance of this manuscript.</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s11"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2022.852251/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2022.852251/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Table_1.DOCX" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Worldwide occurrence of mycotoxins in cereals and cereal-derived food products: public health perspectives of their co-occurrence</article-title>. <source>J Agr Food Chem.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>7034</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jafc.6b04847</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27976878</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horky</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skalickova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baholet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skladanka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nanoparticles as a solution for eliminating the risk of mycotoxins</article-title>. <source>Nanomaterials.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>727</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>47</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nano8090727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30223519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6164963</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mgbeahuruike</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ejioffor</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Christian</surname><given-names>OC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shoyinka</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Detoxification of aflatoxin-contaminated poultry feeds by 3 adsorbents, bentonite, activated charcoal, and fuller's earth</article-title>. <source>J Appl Poult Res.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>461</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/japr/pfy054</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhatti</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ul Hassan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saleemi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saqib</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative efficacy of bentonite clay, activated charcoal and trichosporon mycotoxinivorans in regulating the feed-to-tissue transfer of mycotoxins</article-title>. <source>J Sci Food Agric.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>884</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.8533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28695994</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>UP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rasheed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dilger</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of oligosaccharides and polysaccharides of xylan and mannan in gut health of monogastric animals</article-title>. <source>J Nutr Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>E21</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/jns.2020.14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32595966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7303790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hang</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of mannan-oligosaccharide on bacterial community of piglet after weaning</article-title>. <source>J Agric Biotechnol.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>701</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Ministry of Agriculture of the People's Republic of China Announcement (No</collab></person-group>. <article-title>1126) [EB/OL]</article-title>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.moa.gov.cn/nybgb/2014/dyq/201712/t20171219_6104350.htm" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.moa.gov.cn/nybgb/2014/dyq/201712/t20171219_6104350.htm</ext-link> (accessed February 01, 2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baek</surname><given-names>JiSY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of commercially purified deoxynivalenol and zearalenone mycotoxins on microbial diversity of pig cecum contents</article-title>. <source>Anim Biosci.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>243</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5713/ajas.20.0137</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32777887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7876725</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehla</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of dietary supplementation of prebiotics (mannan oligosaccharide) on the performance of crossbred calves</article-title>. <source>Trop Anim Health Prod.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>617</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11250-011-9944-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21805307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinrichs</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinrichs</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of mannan oligosaccharide or antibiotics in neonatal diets on health and growth of dairy calves</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>4064</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(03)74018-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14740845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joannis-Cassan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tozlovanu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hadjeba-Medjdoub</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ballet</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfohl-Leszkowic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Binding of Zearalenone, Aflatoxin B1, and Ochratoxin A by yeast-based products: a method for quantification of adsorption performance</article-title>. <source>J Food Protect</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>1175</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-11-023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21740721</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saleemi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gul</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Naseem</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Toxicopathological effects of feeding aflatoxins B1 in broilers and its ameliosration with indigenous mycotoxin binder</article-title>. <source>Ecotox Environ Safe.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>187</volume>:<fpage>109712</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecoenv.2019.109712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31654867</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swelum</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashem</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abdelnour</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taha</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ei-hack</surname><given-names>MEA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of phytogenic feed additives on the reproductive performance of animals</article-title>. <source>Saudi J Biol Sci</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>5816</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sjbs.2021.06.045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34588896</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8459048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marroquin</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallmark</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. In vitro and <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> characterization of mycotoxin-binding additives used for animal feeds in Mexico. <source>Food Addit Contam A.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>733</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02652030802641872</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19680945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aazami</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nasri</surname><given-names>MHF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mojtahedi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Battacone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Preparation and characterization of yeast cell wall beta-glucan encapsulated humic acid nanoparticles as an enhanced aflatoxin B1 binder</article-title>. <source>Carbohyd Polym.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>203</volume>:<fpage>185</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2018.08.047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30318202</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Animal nutrition parameter and feeding standard</source>. <publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>China Agriculture Press (in Chinese)</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>AOAC</collab></person-group>. <source>Official Methods of Analysis</source>. 17th ed. <publisher-loc>Arlington, VA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Association of Official Analytical Chemists</publisher-name> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Soest</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Methods for dietary fiber, neutral detergent fiber, and nonstarch polysaccharides in relation to animal nutrition</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>1991</year>) <volume>74</volume>:<fpage>3583</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>97</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(91)78551-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1660498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kekana</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marume</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muya</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nherera-Chokuda</surname><given-names>FV</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Periparturient antioxidant enzymes, haematological profile and milk production of dairy cows supplemented with moringa oleifera leaf meal</article-title>. <source>Anim Feed Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>268</volume>:<fpage>114606</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anifeedsci.2020.114606</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>XT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>QG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zand</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Protective effects of <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> ANSB060, <italic toggle="yes">Bacillus subtilis</italic> ANSB01G, and <italic toggle="yes">Devosia</italic> sp. ANSB714-based mycotoxin biodegradation agent on mice fed with naturally moldy diets</article-title>. <source>Probiotics Antimicrob Proteins.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>994</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1001</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12602-019-09606-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31721071</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>ZL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of Lactobacillus acid ophilus supplementation for improving <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> rumen fermentation characteristics of cereal straws</article-title>. <source>Ital J Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1828051X.2016.1262753</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bafti</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mozaffari</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Normal hematological parameters in iranian cashmere (raini) goats</article-title>. <source>Comp Clin Pathol.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1653</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00580-011-1343-z</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>SPSS</collab></person-group>. <source>IBM SPSS Statistics for Windows, Version 19, 0</source>. <publisher-loc>Armonk, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IBM Corp</publisher-name> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khatke</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tyagi</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of the ability of Saccharomyces cerevisiae and mannan oliosaccharides to ameliorate the adverse effects of aflatoxin B1 in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Indian J Poul Sci.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>176</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soumeh</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohebodini</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toghyani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shabani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ashayerizadeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Synergistic effects of fermented soybean meal and mannan-oligosaccharide on growth performance, digestive functions, and hepatic gene expression in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Poul Sci.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>6797</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>807</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pez409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31347672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8913979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolt</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The addition of cottonseed hulls to the starter and supplementation of live yeast or mannan oligosaccharide in the milk for young calves</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>790</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2008-1320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19164693</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Westland</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mannan oligosaccharide prepartum supplementation: effects on dairy cow colostrum quality and quantity</article-title>. <source>Animal.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1779</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1751731117000672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28399957</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morgavi</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boudra</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jouany</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Graviou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevention of patulin toxicity on rumen microbial fermentation by SH-containing reducing agents</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>6906</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf034505v</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14582994</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#228;nicke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brezina</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Kinetics and metabolism of the Fusarium toxin deoxynivalenol in farm animals: consequences for diagnosis of exposure and intoxication and carry over</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>60</volume>:<fpage>58</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>75</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2013.07.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23872131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#228;nicke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valenta</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klobasa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#246;ll</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ganter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of graded levels of Fusarium toxin contaminated wheat in diets for fattening pigs on growth performance, nutrient digestibility, deoxynivalenol balance and clinical serum characteristics</article-title>. <source>Arch Anim Nutr.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0003942031000161045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15085961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Metagenomic analyses of microbial and carbohydrate-active enzymes in the rumen of Holstein cows fed different forage-to-concentrate ratios</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>649</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.00649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30984155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6449447</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of adding mannan oligosaccharides on digestibility and metabolism of nutrients, ruminal fermentation parameters, immunity, and antioxidant capacity of sheep</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>284</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jas/skx040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29385475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6140840</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of mannanoligosaccharide supplementation on the growth performance, immunity, and oxidative status of partridge shank chickens</article-title>. <source>Animals.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>817</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ani9100817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31623222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6827142</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akrami</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghobadi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmadifar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khoshroudi</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of prebiotic mannan oligosaccharide on hematological and blood serum biochemical parameters of cultured juvenile great sturgeon</article-title>. <source>J Appl Ichthyol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>1214</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jai.12245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meek</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Immune parameters of dry cows fed mannan oligosaccharide and subsequent transfer of immunity to calves</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>766</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>75</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.S0022-0302(05)72740-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15653543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7190086</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of mannan oligosaccharides on growth performance, nutrient digestibility, ruminal fermentation and hematological parameters in sheep</article-title>. <source>PeerJ.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e11631</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.11631</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34249497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8254473</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hyun</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Minseok</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bumseok</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of high levels of deoxynivalenol and zearalenone on growth performance, and hematological and immunological parameters in pigs</article-title>. <source>Toxins</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>114</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins10030114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29518941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5869402</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>LiS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Diagnostic method of pig blood routine index for pig health</article-title>. <source>J Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>54</volume>:<fpage>117</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>You</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of intrauterine growth retardation on blood routine indices of growing pigs</article-title>. <source>J Anim Nutr.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>417</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Andretta</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Meta-analysis of the relationship of mycotoxins with biochemical and hematological parameters in broilers</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2012</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.2011-01813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22252351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nargeskhani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dabiri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Esmaeilkhanian</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alipour</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bojarpour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of mannanoligosaccharide&#8211;&#946; glucan or antibiotics on health and performance of dairy calves</article-title>. <source>Anim Nutr Feed Tech.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>XG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Determination and analysis of partial blood physiological indexes of guizhou black female goat</article-title>. <source>Southwest China J Agri Sci.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>366</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maziar</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seyed</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Houshang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farid</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of probiotics, yeast, vitamin e and vitamin c supplements on performance and immune response of laying hen during high environmental temperature</article-title>. <source>Int J Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>895</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>900</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3923/ijps.2007.895.900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogunade</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Queiroz</surname><given-names>OCM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drouin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Silage review: mycotoxins in silage: occurrence, effects, prevention, and mitigation</article-title>. <source>J Dairy Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>101</volume>:<fpage>4034</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3168/jds.2017-13788</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29685276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raja</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saikumur</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ochratoxicosis in swine: clinical and pathological changes following prolonged exposure to ochratoxin A</article-title>. <source>Indian J Anim Sci.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>78</volume>:<fpage>922</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/gse:2008023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>