<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9685804</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC9685804.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">9685804</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">9685804</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36439358</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.998438</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Red blood cells morphology and morphometry in adult, senior, and geriatricians dogs by optical and scanning electron microscopy</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Montoya-Navarrete</surname><given-names initials="AL">Ana Luisa</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1376923/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guerrero-Barrera</surname><given-names initials="AL">Alma Lili&#225;n</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/95896/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quezada-Trist&#225;n</surname><given-names initials="T">Te&#243;dulo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valdivia-Flores</surname><given-names initials="AG">Arturo G.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cano-R&#225;bano</surname><given-names initials="MJ">Mar&#237;a J.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Morphology Department, Basic Sciences Center, Autonomous University of Aguascalientes</institution>, <addr-line>Aguascalientes</addr-line>, <country>Mexico</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Veterinary Sciences Department, Agricultural Sciences Center, Autonomous University of Aguascalientes</institution>, <addr-line>Aguascalientes</addr-line>, <country>Mexico</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Veterinary Medicine, Surgery and Anatomy, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Le&#243;n</institution>, <addr-line>Le&#243;n</addr-line>, <country>Spain</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Nianqiao Gong, Huazhong University of Science and Technology, China</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Katalin Pet&#246;, University of Debrecen, Hungary; Iren Miko, University of Debrecen, Hungary</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Alma Lili&#225;n Guerrero-Barrera <email>lilian.guerrero@edu.uaa.mx</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Comparative and Clinical Medicine, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">400313</issue-id><elocation-id>998438</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>7</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>25</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-05-10 18:25:36.247"><day>10</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2022 Montoya-Navarrete, Guerrero-Barrera, Quezada-Trist&#225;n, Valdivia-Flores and Cano-R&#225;bano.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Montoya-Navarrete, Guerrero-Barrera, Quezada-Trist&#225;n, Valdivia-Flores and Cano-R&#225;bano</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-09-998438.pdf"/><abstract><p>Red blood cells (RBC) morphologic evaluation through microscopy optical (OM) and SEM, provides information to forecast, evaluate, and monitor the functioning of many organs. Factors, such aging and diseases affect RBC morphology in both, human and animals. SEM is useful to evaluate RBC morphology, although its use in diagnosis and evaluation in dogs is limited, due to the availability and cost. The aim of this research was to assess the normal RBC morphology in adult, senior and geriatrician dogs, clinically healthy by OM and SEM. In addition to evaluating the age effect, sex, body size, and their interaction on erythrocyte morphometry. To carry out the research 152 blood samples were evaluated from dogs of different sexes and body sizes (small, medium, and large). Three groups were made based on dogs age: group I adults (1&#8211;7.9 years old), group II senior (8&#8211;11.9 years old), and group III geriatricians (&gt;12 years old). Erythrocyte parameters were evaluated by OM (diameter, height, and axial ratio). Per each dog, the parameters of 20 erythrocytes were measured. A total of 2,600 cells were scanned with the AmScope&#8482; Software scale. In addition, the RBC morphology was evaluated by SEM. Statistical analyses used analysis of variance and a general linear model, which allows the comparison of multiple factors at two or more levels (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). The results of this study showed that diameter and height were lower in adult dogs than in senior and geriatrician dogs (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Whereas, sex, body size, and the interaction did not show a significant effect (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &gt; 0.05). Additionally, some images of anisocytosis, polychromasia, and poikilocytosis (echinocytes, acanthocytes, codocytes, spherocytes, stomatocytes, dacryocytes quatrefoil, and elliptocytes) were obtained by OM and SEM. Our study provides information about the morphological and morphometry alterations of adult, senior, and geriatrician dogs RBC. This work contributes to future investigations and the diagnosing diseases, where it is necessary to evaluate the morphology of RBC.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>red blood cells morphology</kwd><kwd>optical microscopy</kwd><kwd>scanning electron microscopy</kwd><kwd>adult dogs</kwd><kwd>senior dogs</kwd><kwd>geriatric dogs</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001"><institution-wrap><institution>Universidad Aut&#243;noma de Aguascalientes</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100019357</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="12"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="65"/><page-count count="15"/><word-count count="7990"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Red blood cells (RBC) are the most abundant blood cells in the organism, delivering oxygen to body tissues. The count of these vital cells is often the first step done in analyzing a patient's pathological condition (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). RBC are anucleated, and in the shape of biconcave discs with central pallor called discocytes (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Poikilocytosis is the term used for abnormal shaped RBC in the blood (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Assessing alterations in red blood cell morphology provides important information that can help to establish a differential diagnosis of diseases in both humans and animals (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). In addition to diseases, other physiological factors can cause changes in erythrocyte morphology, such as aging (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p><p>The light microscope has been the most frequent method for the evaluation of the RBC morphology because is an important tool in the detection of diseases in geriatric patients, as well as a quality control measure for automated hematology equipment and as a rapid evaluation of patients in veterinary emergencies (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). However, the advancement of technology allows us to explore other tools that may be alternatives to assess the RBC morphology in a field of scientific research, as scanning electron microscopy (SEM) is widely used to evaluate the morphological properties of erythrocytes in different physiological conditions human (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>).</p><p>The morphological evaluation of RBC through SEM has been applied mainly in human medicine, in patients with inflammatory diseases, cardiovascular, related to aging, and diabetes (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Some of these diseases can also be present in dogs, especially in aging dogs (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Thus, over the years the dog has been used as an experimental model in the advancement of some diseases that also occur in humans (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>).</p><p>For this reason, it is important to explore other microscopy tools in the field of veterinary research that can assist in the diagnosis and monitoring of diseases in both animals and humans. Besides, to our knowledge, it has not been determined erythrocyte parameters in aging dogs. Therefore, this study aimed to evaluate RBC morphology in the adult dogs (1&#8211;7.9 years old), senior dogs (8&#8211;11.9 years old), and geriatrician dogs (&gt;12 years old) clinically healthy by OM and SEM. In addition to evaluating the effect of age, sex, body size, and their interaction on erythrocyte morphometry through parameters of RBC (diameter, height, and axial ratio).</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Population</title><p>This study was carried out in compliance with the provisions established in the Ethics Regulations for the Use of Animals in Teaching and Research at the Autonomous University of Aguascalientes (CEADI-UAA) Code: DI-PL-NO-37 (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). A non-experimental transverse design was used (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). We selected 152 healthy dogs of different sexes and sizes classified by age: group I 49 adults (1&#8211;7.9 years old), group II 51 seniors (8&#8211;11.9 years old), and group III 52 geriatricians (&gt;12 years old) (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). The breeds were grouped according to their body size: small-sized (&lt; 9.5 kg), medium-sized (9.5&#8211;22.7 kg), and large-sized dogs (&gt;22.7&#8211;54.5 kg) (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>).</p><p>Animals were assessed as healthy on the basis of a complete physical examination and history. The collection of the medical history and the physical examination were carried out by a veterinarian who specializes in clinical medicine of small species at the Parasitology Laboratory of the Center for Agricultural Sciences of the Autonomous University of Aguascalientes and private clinics. A questionnaire (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Appendix 1</xref>) related to health, living environment, activity, behavioral changes, nutrition, vaccination, parasite control, and medical history was administered (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). The questionnaire was reviewed with the owner, and additional questions were asked if required. During this time, the dog was allowed to freely explore the examination room. An animal information form in <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Appendix 2</xref> (documenting the date of birth, sex, breed, weight, body size, diet, reproductive status, and vital signs) was also obtained for each dog before inclusion in the study (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Moreover, a body condition score (BCS) was determined for each dog based on a 9-point scale (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>).</p><p>All dogs fasted for 8&#8211;12 h before blood sampling, and water was offered at libitum. Non-fasted dogs, dogs on medication at the time of blood sampling, or when a significant illness was suspected based on history and observation were excluded from the study. Dogs needed to be free of medication for at least 2 months before inclusion. Preventive medication (deworming, vaccination) was allowed until 2 weeks before the consultation. Females were not pregnant, not lactating, and not in oestrus. All dogs selected for this study were privately owned (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). All owners signed an informed consent form (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Appendix 1</xref>). No type of anesthesia or sedation was used when taking the blood sample.</p></sec><sec><title>Collection of blood samples</title><p>Samples of 500 &#956;l of blood were collected using venipuncture jugular with vacuum tubes BD Vacutainer<sup>&#174;</sup> with EDTA K2, applied by aspersion (BD Franklin Lakes NJ USA) to perform the blood smear analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Optical microscopy</title><p>We performed the blood smears immediately after blood collection in the Diagnostic Pathology Laboratory of the Agricultural Sciences Center of the Autonomous University of Aguascalientes. Smears were fixed with methanol and stained with Wright stain. Subsequently, a coverslip with Entellan (Merck<sup>&#174;</sup>, Darmstadt, Germany) and xylol (JT Baker<sup>&#174;</sup> Avantor, Matsonford Rd) was placed on them, and they were left to dry for 24 h (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). All smears were observed using a ZEISS optical microscope (Oberkochen, Germany). Images were obtained with an AmScope&#8482; camera and software (USA).</p><sec><title>Blood smear evaluation</title><p>The evaluation of the blood smear was divided into three parts: red series, white series, and platelets. A magnification of 100 &#215; was used to evaluate the morphology of erythrocytes, leukocytes, and platelets (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). In the analysis of the red series were evaluated the size (anisocytosis, macrocytosis, and microcytosis), the color (polychromatophilic and hypochromic), the shape (non-specific and specific morphological changes), the distribution (stacks of coins or agglutination), and the presence of inclusion bodies or erythrocyte parasites (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). The morphology of the leukocytes (white series) and platelets was evaluated (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Morphometry parameters of RBC</title><p>The erythrocyte parameters were determined from OM micrographs according to Loyola-Leyva et al. (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Per each dog of study, 20 erythrocytes were evaluated. The longest axis, called the major axis or diameter, was measured in all RBC; a perpendicular line was drawn at the center of the major axis to establish the length of the minor axis or height (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Then, the axial ratio was calculated by dividing the length of the major axis (diameter) by the length of the minor axis (height); a value of 1 represents a perfect circle (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Therefore, 2,600 cells were scanned to assess the morphological changes. All samples were viewed with the Measurement scaler of the main menu of the AmScope&#8482; software (USA).</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Blood smear from healthy dogs, showing positions for diameter and height calculations from optical micrographs using AmScope&#8482; software. The diameter or major axis was measured in the erythrocytes and a perpendicular line was drawn in the center of the diameter to establish the height. Scale bar = 7 &#956;m.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-998438-g0001.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Scanning electron microscopy</title><p>A total of 3 ml of whole blood obtained by jugular venipuncture was collected and deposited in tubes with K2EDTA BD Vacutainer<sup>&#174;</sup>, which contains the optimal amount of di-potassium EDTA applied by spray to anticoagulant the specified volume of blood (BD Franklin Lakes NJ USA). Once obtained the blood sample was centrifuged at 2,000 rpm for 10 min to separate the leukocyte layer that was deposited in a 1.5 ml Eppendorf tube, adding glutaraldehyde (JT Baker<sup>&#174;</sup> Avantor, Matsonford Rd), to fix them until further analysis. The sample, later, was centrifuged at 6,000 rpm for 1 min, obtaining only the precipitate by decanting the sample. Phosphate buffered saline (PBS) solution 1X (Merck<sup>&#174;</sup>, Darmstadt Germany) was added to the precipitate, mixed, and allowed to rest for 5 min. This process was carried out three times; then it was added alcohol at 60%, letting the precipitate rest for 10 min. The sample was centrifuged again at 6,000 rpm for 1 min; this process was repeated with alcohol at 70, 80, 90, 96, and 100%. Lastly, 100% of pure acetone was added and fixed in a dark-bottomed aluminum cylinder to later be coated with gold particles in Desk II Denton vacuum equipment (Lawrence, Kansas), and finally observed in the scanning electron microscope JEOL JSM-5900LV (JEOL Solutions for innovation, Mexico City) (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Micrographs of the erythrocytes were obtained by SEM. Some electron microscopy images were photoshopped to add color to the blood cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Statistical analysis was performed with Minitab 17 (Minitab Statistical Software, State College, PA); <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05 was considered significant. We evaluated the distribution of the variables by examining the histograms and using a goodness of fit test (Anderson&#8211;Darling) (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). To determine if the variance of two or more groups was significantly different, we used a test of equality of variances with multiple comparisons and Levene's test. These methods are valid in non-normal distributions, while in normal distributions, the Bartlett test is used. All tests of variance used a confidence level of 95% (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>).</p><p>Statistical analyses employed analysis of variance (ANOVA) with a general linear model (GLM), which allows the comparison of multiple factors at two or more levels (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05). Morphometric parameters of RBC: diameter, height, and axial ratio represent response variables (dependent), while age, sex, and body size represent factors (independent variables). The interaction between factors was also evaluated. When the data did not meet the normality assumptions and homoscedasticity, we performed a Box-Cox transformation using Minitab's optimal lambda (&#955;) with a confidence level of 95%. Subsequently, a multiple comparison method (Tukey) was performed with a confidence level of 95% (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>).</p><p>Reference intervals for each of the morphometric variables (diameter, height, and axial ratio) were calculated using the software Reference Value Advisor (RefValAdvV.2.1, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.biostat.envt.fr/reference-value-advisor/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.biostat.envt.fr/reference-value-advisor/</ext-link>) based on the recommendations of International Federation of Clinical Chemistry (IFCC) and the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI) (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). This software detected the outliers with Tukey and Dixon tests, showing the distribution (dot plot and histograms) and QQ plot for visual inspection (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 152 blood samples were collected from dogs of different ages: group I adults (1&#8211;7.9 years old), group II seniors (8&#8211;11.9 years old), and group III geriatricians (&gt;12 years old). Eighty-two dogs were female, and 66 dogs were male. All dogs were grouped according to their body size: 81 small dogs, 25 medium dogs, and 42 large dogs. A variety of small, medium and large dogs were represented in each age group. Nineteen blood samples were excluded: five samples due to the presence of clots, four samples with hemolysis and 10 samples from the statistical analysis because of underlying subclinical diseases. Therefore, only 129 blood samples from clinically healthy dogs were analyzed by light microscopy and 4 blood samples by scanning electron microscopy, as described in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Number of blood samples from clinically healthy dogs analyzed in this study by light microscopy and scanning electron microscopy.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Adult dogs</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Senior dogs</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Geriatric dogs</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Optical microscopy (OM)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 44</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 44</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 129</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scanning electron microscopy (SEM)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excluded samples</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 19</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 49</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 52</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 152</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec><title>Optical microscopy</title><p>In this research were obtained images of the blood smears by light microscopy. <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2A</xref>,<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">B</xref> show the normal RBC morphology and small platelets with pale gray to light blue cytoplasm with normal granule content. On evaluation regarding erythrocyte morphology, anisocytosis (size variation) was recorded in the 88% of samples (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>), polychromasia (polychromatophilic erythrocytes) y poikilocytosis (abnormal form). Abnormal forms of erythrocytes were specifically classified.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Light microscopy smears healthy dogs at 100 &#215;. <bold>(A)</bold> The normal morphology of red blood cells (RBC) shows a pale central area that represents 1/3 of their diameter approximately. <bold>(B)</bold> Platelets with a normal central cluster of small pink or purple granules in the cytoplasm (blue arrows).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-998438-g0002.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Light microscopy smears healthy dogs at 100 &#215;. The presence of red blood cells of the abnormal size called anisocytosis (size variation) is shown, and a microcyte is observed in the lower-left corner (yellow arrowhead) and macrocytes (blue arrows). Scale bars = 6 and 8 &#956;m.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-998438-g0003.jpg"/></fig><p><xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows the frequency of each of the variables such as the size, color, shape, and inclusion bodies of the erythrocytes that were observed in the blood smear by optical microscopy in each of the groups of dogs (adults, seniors, and geriatricians), where the absolute frequency, cumulative frequency, relative frequency, cumulative relative frequency, frequency in percentage, and cumulative frequency in percentage are described.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Frequency analysis of the variables evaluated in the blood smear of a population of dogs (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 129) of different ages: adults (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 44), seniors (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 41), and geriatrics (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 44).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Variable</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Finding</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Group</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Absolute frequency</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Accumulated frequency</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Relative frequency</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Cumulative relative frequency</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Percentage frequency %</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Cumulative percentage frequency %</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Size</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anisocytosis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senior</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geriatric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Macrocytosis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senior</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geriatric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Color</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Polychromatophilic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senior</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geriatric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shape</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Echinocytes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senior</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geriatric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acanthocytes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senior</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geriatric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Codocytes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senior</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geriatric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spherocytes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senior</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geriatric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stomatocytes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senior</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geriatric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dacryocytes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senior</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geriatric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Quatrefoil</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senior</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geriatric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Elliptocytes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senior</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geriatric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inclusion bodies</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Erythroblasts</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Senior</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geriatric</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>A presence of polychromasia (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A</xref>) was identified in geriatric dogs, accompanied by macrocytes (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>) and erythroblasts (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B</xref>). While in poikilocytosis the presence of abnormal erythrocyte forms was indistinct. However, three abnormal erythrocyte forms were observed most frequently (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>): acanthocytes (77%), codocytes (36%), and dacryocytes (34%). <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5A</xref> shows echinocytes with small spicules evenly spaced on their surface, a detail that differentiates them from acanthocytes (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figures 5B</xref>,<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">C</xref>) that have irregular projections. <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5C</xref> also shows target-shaped erythrocytes (target cells or codocytes). <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5D</xref> shows small erythrocytes, without central paleness and dense staining (spherocytes). Teardrop-shaped erythrocytes known as dacryocytes were observed in <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6A</xref>. Erythrocytes with oval or elongated central pallor are described as stomatocytes in <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6B</xref>. Quatrefoils are cells in the form of a cross (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6C</xref>). Elongated or elliptical red blood cells (elliptocytes) are shown in <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6D</xref>. Inclusion bodies indicative of erythropoiesis such as erythroblasts were detected in 7% of the samples analyzed (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B</xref>). No distribution abnormalities (pseudo phenomenon rouleaux) were observed, or erythrocyte parasites were found.</p><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Optical micrographs at 100 &#215; of senior and geriatric dogs. <bold>(A)</bold> Polychromatophilic erythrocytes have a bluish cytoplasm and are larger than a normal red blood cell (blue arrow). <bold>(B)</bold> Erythroblasts are nucleated precursor cells of erythrocytes (blue arrow).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-998438-g0004.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Optical micrographs at 100 &#215; of dogs, showing the poikilocytosis (abnormal forms of erythrocytes). <bold>(A)</bold> Echinocytes. <bold>(B)</bold> Acantocytes (blue arrows). <bold>(C)</bold> Codocytes or target cells (blue arrows) and acanthocytes (yellow arrowhead). <bold>(D)</bold> Spherocyte (blue arrow).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-998438-g0005.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Optical micrographs at 100 &#215; of dogs, showing the poikilocytosis (abnormal forms of erythrocytes). <bold>(A)</bold> Dacrocytes (blue arrow). <bold>(B)</bold> Stomatocytes (blue arrow). <bold>(C)</bold> Cross-shaped or quatrefoil erythrocyte (blue arrow) and acanthocytes (yellow arrowhead). <bold>(D)</bold> Elliptocytes (blue arrow).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-998438-g0006.jpg"/></fig><p>In <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7A</xref>, it can observe the morphology of a segmented neutrophil that shows a lobed nucleus and cytoplasm with slightly eosinophilic granulation, while <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7B</xref> shows a band neutrophil with a curved nucleus and slight strangulation, noticing that its cytoplasm shows a slightly eosinophilic granulation as well. Additionally, <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7C</xref> shows the morphology of a monocyte with the presence of vacuoles and gray-blue cytoplasm with an indented nucleus. The monocyte nucleus varies greatly and can take any shape from round, indented, coiled, or kidney-shaped. The presence of vacuoles of variable size in the cytoplasm is characteristic. On the other hand, in <xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7D</xref>, eosinophils were identified, presenting red-orange granules that are distinctive in a pale blue cytoplasm. No abnormalities were observed in leukocyte and platelet morphology.</p><fig position="float" id="F7" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Leukocytes in healthy dogs. <bold>(A)</bold> Segmented neutrophil with an elongated and irregularly lobed nucleus. <bold>(B)</bold> Band neutrophil with a curved nucleus and slight strangulation (blue arrow), codocytes (yellow arrowhead). <bold>(C)</bold> Monocyte with the presence of vacuoles in the cytoplasm (blue arrow), optical microscopy. <bold>(D)</bold> Eosinophil with orange-red granules (blue arrow) and a segmented nucleus (yellow arrowhead). Optical microscopy at 100 &#215;.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-998438-g0007.jpg"/></fig><p>Normal lymphocyte morphology was identified in the blood of dogs by light microscopy. <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8A</xref> shows a small lymphocyte, its nucleus can be round or oval, sometimes slightly indented, or strongly stained. Also, in <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8B</xref> the cytoplasm of the lymphocytes is sparse, and light blue in color. <xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8C</xref> shows a large lymphocyte, its cytoplasm is more abundant ranging from mild to moderate basophilia.</p><fig position="float" id="F8" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Leukocytes in healthy dogs. <bold>(A)</bold> Small lymphocyte with its round nucleus strongly dyed (blue arrow). <bold>(B)</bold> Small elongated and whitish area, close to the nucleus, typical of lymphocytes (blue arrow), codocyte (yellow arrowhead). <bold>(C)</bold> Large lymphocyte, with more abundant cytoplasm (blue arrow) and less dense nuclear chromatin. Optical microscopy at 100 &#215;.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-998438-g0008.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Morphometry parameters of RBC</title><p><xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> shows the mean, standard deviation, median, interquartile range, and the significant difference with a 95% confidence interval; the lower limit and upper limit were determined with a confidence interval of 90% from each of the morphometric parameters of RBC. The effect of age, sex, and body size on erythrocyte parameters (diameter, height, and axial ratio) were assessed. The following statistical data are reported in the results: the significance level (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>), mean (<italic toggle="yes">M</italic>), and standard deviation (<italic toggle="yes">SD</italic>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Parameters of red blood cells (RBC) evaluated by optical microscopy (OM).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>(I) Adults</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>(II) Senior</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>(III) Geriatric</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>1&#8211;7.9 year old</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>8&#8211;11.9 year old</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&gt;<bold>12 year old</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes"><bold>n</bold></italic> = <bold>44</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes"><bold>n</bold></italic> = <bold>41</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes"><bold>n</bold></italic> = <bold>44</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Variables</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mean (SD)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>LL (90% CI)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mean (SD)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>LL (90% CI)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mean (SD)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>LL (90% CI)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">p</italic> value</bold>
</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Median (IQR)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>UL (90% CI)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Median (IQR)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>UL (90% CI)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Median (IQR)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>UL (90% CI)</bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diameter (&#956;m)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.56 (0.44)<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.7 (6.7&#8211;6.8)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.67 (0.49)<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8 (6.7&#8211;6.9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.72 (0.45)<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.9 (6.8&#8211;6.9)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.54 (0.61)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 (8.4&#8211;8.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.65 (0.66)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7 (8.6&#8211;8.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.70 (0.63)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.7 (8.6&#8211;8.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height (&#956;m)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.18 (0.42)<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4 (6.3&#8211;6.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.29 (0.45)<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 (6.4&#8211;6.5)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.35 (0.44)<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 (6.5&#8211;6.6)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.16 (0.54)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0 (8.0&#8211;8.1)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.28 (0.58)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2 (8.1&#8211;8.3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.35 (0.62)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.2 (8.2&#8211;8.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Axial ratio</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.04)<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (1.0&#8211;1.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.04)<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (1.0&#8211;1.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 (0.04)<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0 (1.0&#8211;1.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.05)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (1.1&#8211;1.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (1.1&#8211;1.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04 (0.06)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2 (1.2&#8211;1.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>CI, Confidence interval; IQR, Interquartile rage; LL, Lower limit; SD, standard deviation; UL, Upper limit. <sup>a, b, c</sup>Groups that do not share the same letter are significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Age had a significant effect on the diameter (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.00). The average red cell diameter in adult dogs from 1 to 7.9 years old was 7.56 &#956;m (<italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 0.44), which was significantly lower than the diameter in seniors (<italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 7.67 &#956;m, <italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 0.49; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> =0.004), and geriatric dogs (<italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 7.72 &#956;m, <italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 0.45; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.00). Our research showed that diameter increased with age (<xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">Figure 9A</xref>). No significant effect of sex (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.069), body size (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.512), and interaction between age, sex, and body size (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.238) was observed on the diameter.</p><fig position="float" id="F9" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>The measures of erythrocyte morphometric parameters at different stages of the dog's life. Comparison of the means (red line) <bold>(A)</bold> diameter and <bold>(B)</bold> height between groups of clinically healthy dogs of different ages: adults (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 44 dogs of 1&#8211;7.9 years old), seniors (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 41 dogs of 8&#8211;11.9 years old), and geriatrics (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 44 dogs of &gt;12 years old). Horizontal blue dotted lines represent the RIs for adult dogs with a 90% CI (see <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Means that do not share a letter are significantly different (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-998438-g0009.jpg"/></fig><p>Age had a significant effect on height (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.00). <xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">Figure 9B</xref> shows that height in adult dogs (<italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 7.18 &#956;m, <italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 0.42) was significantly lower than the height of senior dogs (<italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 7.29 &#956;m, <italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 0.45; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.002) and geriatric dogs (<italic toggle="yes">M</italic> = 7.35 &#956;m, <italic toggle="yes">SD</italic> = 0.44, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.00). Furthermore, height in senior dogs was significantly lower than height in geriatric dogs (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.027). No effect of sex (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.867), body size (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.335), and interaction between age, sex, and body size (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.414) on height was identified. No statistically significant effect of age (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.56), sex (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.662), body size (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.078), and interaction between age, sex, and body size (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> = 0.298) on the axial relationship was identified.</p></sec><sec><title>Scanning electron microscopy</title><p>The following images were obtained through SEM and show the normal RBC morphology and leukocytes in adult, senior, and geriatric dogs. The Images of blood cells of adult dogs are shown in <xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">Figure 10</xref>, the normal RBC morphology is observed, with a characteristic smooth and concave surface (<xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">Figure 10A</xref>). In <xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">Figure 10B</xref>, the morphology of granulocytes (neutrophils) is seen which shows a rough surface. A comparison is also between the morphology and size of leukocytes and erythrocytes (<xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">Figures 10C</xref>,<xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">D</xref>). In addition, poikilocytosis was identified, as echinocytes, which are characterized by uniform protuberances (<xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">Figure 10E</xref>), smaller RBC known as spherocytes (<xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">Figure 10F</xref>), and codocytes, RBC with a densely dark center and surrounded by a pale halo around which an irregular dark band appears (<xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">Figures 10G</xref>,<xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">H</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F10" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>SEM images of normal and abnormal blood cells in adult dogs. <bold>(A)</bold> Erythrocyte. <bold>(B)</bold> Leukocyte. <bold>(C)</bold> Comparison of a leukocyte (left) and an erythrocyte (right). <bold>(D)</bold> Agglutination of erythrocytes and leukocytes. <bold>(E)</bold> Equinocyte. <bold>(F)</bold> Spherocyte (blue arrow). <bold>(G,H)</bold> Codocytes.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-998438-g0010.jpg"/></fig><p>As for the senior dogs, in <xref rid="F11" ref-type="fig">Figures 11A</xref>,<xref rid="F11" ref-type="fig">B</xref> the normal morphology of the erythrocytes is observed. The abnormalities identified in this group were leptocytes, these cells are thin, generally large in diameter, and displays often hypochromic-appearing erythrocytes with increased membrane-to-volume ratios (<xref rid="F11" ref-type="fig">Figures 11C</xref>,<xref rid="F11" ref-type="fig">F</xref>), knizocytes mature RBC showing three concavities with two lighter areas &#8220;Pinch cells&#8221; (<xref rid="F11" ref-type="fig">Figures 11C</xref>,<xref rid="F11" ref-type="fig">D</xref>), stomatocytes, cells with one or two cavities, that is, a mouth-shaped cleft (<xref rid="F11" ref-type="fig">Figures 11D</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="F11" ref-type="fig">F</xref>) and echinocytes (<xref rid="F11" ref-type="fig">Figure 11F</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F11" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>SEM images of normal and abnormal blood cells in senior dogs: <bold>(A,B)</bold> Normal erythrocyte morphology. <bold>(C)</bold> Leptocyte (blue arrow) and knizocyte (yellow arrowhead). <bold>(D)</bold> Stomatocyte (red pentagon arrow) and knizocytes (yellow arrowhead). <bold>(E)</bold> Stomatocyte (red pentagon arrow). <bold>(F)</bold> Leptocyte (blue arrow), equinocytes (yellow arrowhead), and stomatocyte (red pentagon arrow).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-998438-g0011.jpg"/></fig><p>Finally, <xref rid="F12" ref-type="fig">Figure 12</xref> shows the normal morphology of blood cells in geriatric dogs (<xref rid="F12" ref-type="fig">Figures 12A,B</xref>). Additionally, platelets adhered to erythrocytes are shown (<xref rid="F12" ref-type="fig">Figures 12B,C</xref>). In this group, the abnormalities identified in the erythrocytes were stomatocytes (<xref rid="F12" ref-type="fig">Figures 12C,D</xref>), echinocytes (<xref rid="F12" ref-type="fig">Figure 12E</xref>), and spherocytes (<xref rid="F12" ref-type="fig">Figure 12F</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F12" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 12</label><caption><p>SEM images of normal and abnormal blood cells in geriatric dogs: <bold>(A)</bold> Normal morphology of erythrocytes and leukocytes. <bold>(B,C)</bold> Platelets (blue arrow). <bold>(C,D)</bold> Stomatocytes (red pentagon arrow). <bold>(E,F)</bold> Equinocytes (yellow arrowhead) and spherocytes (blue arrow).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-998438-g0012.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Meanwhile, in the evaluation of the optical microscopy of the red series, in terms of size and color, anisocytosis and polychromatophilia were observed. This can be observed under normal conditions. In particular, polychromatophilia can be identified in Wright-stained smears, but this observation must be &lt; 1% (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). In addition, polychromasia was observed mainly in geriatric dogs in conjunction with macrocytes and erythroblasts. The loss of the nucleus of red blood cells (erythroblasts) gives rise to reticulocytes, larger red blood cells (macrocytes), and basophils (blue coloration) (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). Polychromatophilic erythrocytes are reticulocytes that stain bluish-red because of the combined presence of hemoglobin (red-staining) and ribosomes (blue-staining) (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Polychromatophilia, whenever moderate, is a physiological phenomenon in bone marrow erythrocyte regeneration, which is generally accompanied by a significant number of macrocytes. Its slightly purple or violaceous appearance is determined by the high concentration of RNA in the aggregated reticulocytes and when this concentration is low it is indicative of the presence of stippled reticulocytes (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>).</p><p>On the other hand, poikilocytosis like echinocytes, acanthocytes, codocytes, spherocytes, stomatocytes, dacryocytes, quatrefoil, elliptocytes, and leptocytes was observed in the OM and SEM micrographs. Three abnormal erythrocyte forms were observed most frequently: acanthocytes, codocytes, and dacryocytes. This is consistent with hematologic findings in dogs by other authors (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). Echinocytes are present in glomerulonephritis, uremia, lymphomas, alkalosis, and following the administration of furosemide and doxorubicin. Also, those may appear as artifacts if the collected blood volume is too low in relation to the EDTA content in the vial (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). Acanthocytes in dogs appear mainly in chronic liver diseases, portosystemic shunt, disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC), neoplasms, and nephropathies (glomerulonephritis) (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Codocytes are also known as target cells. They occur in association with liver damage, kidney disease, iron deficiency anemia, disorders of the bile ducts, and spleen (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Spherocytes, which are small cells without a central pallor, are characteristic of hereditary spherocytosis and autoimmune hemolytic anemia (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). Stomatocytes result from red blood cell membrane defects found in hemolytic diseases and hereditary diseases (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>, <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). Dacryocytes appear mainly in myeloproliferative disorders, hypersplenism, and glomerulonephritis. They are observed as tear-shaped red blood cells due to damage to the cell membrane, passing through the narrow medullary or splenic sinusoids (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). Quatrefoil is a cell in the form of a cross, associated with the aging of dogs as described in a 2014 study (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). However, in this study, the presence of quatrefoil erythrocytes was independent of age.</p><p>Another important finding is the presence of elliptocytes and leptocytes. A study conducted on humans with autistic disorder and non-autistic neurodevelopmental disorders (NA-NDD), In particular observed, that abnormally shaped erythrocytes in the blood samples from autistic subjects predominantly featured elliptocytes. While, the NA-NDDs group showed mixed abnormally shaped RBCs, without a predominant erythrocyte shape phenotype, although a slight prevalence of leptocytes was detectable (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). In parallel to the recent advances in canine behavior research, dogs have also been proposed as a model for many human neuropsychiatric conditions, including autism spectrum disorder (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Elliptocytes are erythrocytes elliptical or oval in shape, they are generally flat rather than biconcave (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Hereditary elliptocytosis has been reported in a dog due to a mutant &#946;-spectrin (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). Leptocytes are a thin, large diameter erythrocyte with increased surface area and normal cell volume (e.g., target cells and transverse folded cells) that readily distorts and gives a pinkish hue to the buffy coat layer. They are found in chronically diseased animals and in hepatic disease, obstructive jaundice, regenerative anemia, and iron deficiency anemia. Leptocytes tend to become knizocytes: a triconcave erythrocyte seen in hemolytic anemias in dogs and humans (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>).</p><p>Morphological changes in RBC have been associated with an increased risk of cardiovascular diseases in human medicine (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). In inflammatory conditions, in presence of hydroxyl radicals, some researchers have found that RBC lose their discoid form (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>). Some recent observations based on different types of microscopy concluded that iron has important effects on the morphology and deformability of RBC (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>). Nonetheless, these important contributions have been applied to human medicine while the information about the use of scanning electron microscopy as a diagnostic tool in veterinary medicine is quite limited, due to the availability and cost of the technique.</p><p>RBC diameter evaluated in this study from the OM micrographs obtained a mean in adult dogs of 7.56 &#956;m lower than of diameter of senior (7.67 &#956;m) and geriatric dogs (7.72 &#956;m). These results show an effect of age on the erythrocyte diameter. Some authors report that dogs' erythrocyte diameter varies from 6 to 8 &#956;m (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). An effect of age on erythrocyte height was also observed, increasing with age (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). These results can be related to the presence of polychromasia described in this study. Polychromasia, as mentioned above, appears in ~1% of healthy dogs. However, higher proportions may indicate increased erythropoiesis, blood loss, hemolytic disease, or remission phases of anemia (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). No statistically significant differences were observed in RBC axial ratio. An effect of sex, body size, and the interaction (age, sex, and body size) on diameter, height, and the axial ratio was also not observed. Other authors have shown that breed and age have a significant effect on RBC morphometry (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>It is important to evaluate the erythrocyte morphology and morphometry, especially in aged dogs, since this undoubtedly favors the diagnosis and prognosis of the aged patient. Optical microscopy is the tool par excellence to evaluate the blood smear, however, it is important to know other visual tools. Some diseases in humans also occur in dogs, therefore, the latter could be used in future research to help evaluate the morphology and RBC parameters by means of optical microscopy and scanning electron microscopy. It is well-known that the dog has contributed to some advances in applied medicine in humans. For this reason, this research encourages researchers in both veterinary medicine and human medicine to explore other diagnostic tools such as scanning electron microscopy.</p><p>SEM is a tool useful for determining morphological alterations in the membrane of the RBC as indicative of diseases but is not fully accessible in veterinary medicine for economic reasons and knowledge when interpreting the results because the blood circulation occurs in 3D and, it is how the cells look in SEM; whereas the evaluating a smear with MO, when &#8220;squashing&#8221; the cells change the dimension. Thus, the interpretation differs remarkably, the first exponent is that in SEM the nucleus is not seen and in the case of white blood cells (WBC), the interpretation is quite complicated by not having more than the morphological aspect of the membrane. Scanning electron microscopy has been shown to be a useful tool for detecting morphological changes in aged dogs. Therefore, this study lays the groundwork for continuing the use of electron microscopy as a diagnostic tool in veterinary medicine since it is important to know the effects of some illnesses and aging on the morphology of RBC. This would help clinicians to consolidate patients' reports and to detect diseases in time, as well as to improve their treatment.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/<xref rid="s11" ref-type="sec">Supplementary material</xref>, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by Ethics regulations for the use of animals in teaching and research at the Autonomous University of Aguascalientes Code: DI-PL-NO-37. Written informed consent was obtained from the owners for the participation of their animals in this study.</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Author contributions</title><p>AM-N and AG-B conceived this study, participated in its design, performed coordination, and helped draft the manuscript. TQ-T, AV-F, and MC-R made significant contributions to the conception, design, and analysis of the results. AM-N also carried out laboratory analysis and statistical analysis. All authors contributed to manuscript revision, read, and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="s9"><title>Funding</title><p>The Autonomous University of Aguascalientes approved and granted funding for TQ-T (Project PIP/SA15&#8211;3) for AG-B (PIB19-3, and Especial Resource UAA Research), which was used in the acquisition of materials and reagents necessary to obtain and process blood samples during the development of this study.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s10"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>Thanks to Biology Araceli Adabache Ort&#237;z, head of the Scanning Electron Microscopy Laboratory for her invaluable help in obtaining micrographs of red blood cells by SEM, and thanks also to AQB. Sonia Sof&#237;a Cruz Mu&#241;oz from the Laboratory of Histology and Embryology of the Autonomous University of Aguascalientes for her support in the staining and preservation techniques of blood smears. Juan Manuel Cruz Martinez Engineer Lean Six Sigma Green Belt certificated is gratefully acknowledged also, for his invaluable support in the statistical analysis of the data.</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s11"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2022.998438/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2022.998438/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.PDF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM2" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_2.PDF" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valenciano</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cowell</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rizzi</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Introduction: blood smear preparation and examination</article-title>. In: Valenciano AC, Cowell RL, Rizzi TE, Tyler R, editors. <source>Atlas of Canine and Feline Peripheral Blood Smears.</source><publisher-loc>Mosby</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>St. Louis</publisher-name> (<year>2014</year>). p. <fpage>2</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-323-04468-4.00001-X</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kulasekaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheeba</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mammen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saivigneshu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Morphology based detection of abnormal red blood cells in peripheral blood smear images</article-title>. In: Goh J, editor. <source>7th WACBE World Congress on Bioengineering.</source> Vol <volume>52</volume>. <publisher-loc>Springer</publisher-loc> (<year>2015</year>). p. <fpage>57</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-19452-3_16</pub-id>33279759</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The erythrocyte: physiology, metabolism and biochemical disorders</article-title>. In: Kaneko JJ, Harvey JW, editor. <source>Clinical Biochemistry of Domestic Animals</source>. 6th edition. <publisher-loc>San Diego, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name> (<year>2008</year>). p. <fpage>173</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>240</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-370491-7.00007-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wahed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Quesada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dasgupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chapter 3 - red blood cell disorders</article-title>. In: Wahed A, Quesada A, Dasgupta A, Second E, editors. <source>Hematology and Coagulation.</source><publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name> (<year>2020</year>). p. <fpage>31</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-814964-5.00003-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Red blood cell morphology</article-title>. <source>Int J Lab Hematol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>351</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ijlh.12082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23480230</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rishniw</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Behling-Kelly</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Reporting and interpreting red blood cell morphology: is there discordance between clinical pathologists and clinicians?</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin Pathol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>487</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vcp.12202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25280365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumiega</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Micha&#322;ek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kasztura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Noszczyk-Nowak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of red blood cell parameters in dogs with various stages of degenerative mitral valve disease</article-title>. <source>J Vet Res.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>64</volume>:<fpage>325</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2478/jvetres-2020-0043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32587922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7305654</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maksimov</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mamaeva</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Antonov</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munkhalova</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kononova</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sheikin</surname><given-names>IY</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Measuring erythrocyte morphology by electron microscopy to diagnose hematuria</article-title>. <source>Meas Tech.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>327</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11018-016-0966-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gavazza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brettoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gugliucci</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pasquini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rispoli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Retrospective and prospective investigations about &#8220;quatrefoil&#8221; erythrocytes in canine blood smears</article-title>. <source>Vet Med Int.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>2014</volume>:<fpage>409573</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/409573</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24511413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3913368</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Strijkova-Kenderova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Todinova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andreeva</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bogdanova</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danailova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Morphometry and stiffness of red blood cells&#8212;signatures of neurodegenerative diseases and aging</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>227</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms23010227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35008653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8745649</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Metzger</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rebar</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical pathology interpretation in geriatric veterinary patients</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin North Am Small Anim Pract.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>615</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cvsm.2012.04.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22720804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meinkoth</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hematology without the numbers: in-clinic blood film evaluation</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin North Am Small Anim Pract.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>245</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cvsm.2006.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17336674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lanaux</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rozanski</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Simoni</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Price</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stockman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Interpretation of canine and feline blood smears by emergency room personnel</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin Pathol.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-165X.2010.00280.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21204890</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loyola-Leyva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loyola-Rodr&#237;guez</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ter&#225;n Figueroa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atzori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barquera Cervera</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Altered erythrocyte morphology in Mexican adults with prediabetes and type 2 diabetes mellitus evaluated by scanning electron microscope</article-title>. <source>Microscopy.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>261</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jmicro/dfz011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30860262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loyola-Leyva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loyola-Rodr&#237;guez</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ter&#225;n-Figueroa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atzori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Camacho-Lopez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hypercholesterolemia associated with erythrocytes morphology assessed by scanning electron microscopy in metabolically unhealthy individuals with normal-weight and obesity</article-title>. <source>Obes Med.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>100292</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.obmed.2020.100292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loyola-Leyva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alc&#225;ntara-Quintana</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ter&#225;n-Figueroa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>In vitro effect of high glucose concentrations on erythrocyte morphology assessed by scanning electron microscopy</article-title>. <source>Micron.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>154</volume>:<fpage>103179</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micron.2021.103179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34895961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Detection of erythrocytes influenced by aging and type 2 diabetes using atomic force microscope</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>391</volume>:<fpage>1698</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>702</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2009.12.133</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20040363</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pretorius</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bester</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vermeulen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alummoottil</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soma</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buys</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Poorly controlled type 2 diabetes is accompanied by significant morphological and ultrastructural changes in both erythrocytes and in thrombin-generated fibrin: implications for diagnostics</article-title>. <source>Cardiovasc Diabetol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>30</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12933-015-0192-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25848817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4364097</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loyola-Leyva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loyola-Rodr&#237;guez</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atzori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Morphological changes in erythrocytes of people with type 2 diabetes mellitus evaluated with atomic force microscopy: a brief review</article-title>. <source>Micron.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>105</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micron.2017.11.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29145008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Greco</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chapter 37. Diabetes mellitus in animals: diagnosis and treatment of diabetes mellitus in dogs and cats</article-title>. In: Bagchi D, Nair S, editors. <source>Nutritional and Therapeutic Interventions for Diabetes and Metabolic Syndrome</source>. <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name> (<year>2018</year>). p. <fpage>507</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-812019-4.00037-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gates</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hinds</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dale</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Preliminary description of aging cats and dogs presented to a New Zealand first-opinion veterinary clinic at end-of-life</article-title>. <source>N Z Vet J.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>313</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00480169.2017.1360161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28747096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazzatenta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carluccio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robbe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giulio</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cellerino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The companion dog as a unique translational model for aging</article-title>. <source>Semin Cell Dev Biol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>141</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.semcdb.2017.08.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28803893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adin</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gilor</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The diabetic dog as a translational model for human islet transplantation</article-title>. <source>Yale J Biol Med</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>509</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28955189</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5612193</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Top&#225;l</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rom&#225;n</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turcs&#225;n</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The dog (Canis familiaris) as a translational model of autism: it is high time we move from promise to reality</article-title>. <source>Wiley Interdiscip Rev Cogn Sci.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e1495</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wcs.1495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30762306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Anesi</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abu-Seida</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>El Ashry</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahran</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abd-Elhamid</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of insulin on the healing of exposed dental pulp after pulp capping: an experimental study in a dog model</article-title>. <source>Spec Care Dentist.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>49</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/scd.12545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33197063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>UAA</collab></person-group>. <article-title>Regulations for the use of animals in teaching and research at the Autonomous University of Aguascalientes</article-title>. <source>Aguascalientes: University Legislation</source> (<year>2019</year>) <fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage> p.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chew</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Planning and conducting clinical research: the whole process</article-title>. <source>Cureus.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e4112</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.4112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31058006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6476607</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Radakovich</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pannone</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Truelove</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Olver</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santangelo</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hematology and biochemistry of aging-evidence of &#8220;anemia of the elderly&#8221; in old dogs</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin Pathol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>34</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vcp.12459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28195648</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Willems</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paepe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marynissen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smets</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van de Maele</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Picavet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Results of screening of apparently healthy senior and geriatric dogs</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>81</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.14587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27747924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5259637</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedrichs</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harr</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Szladovits</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnhart</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>ASVCP reference interval guidelines: determination of de novo reference intervals in veterinary species and other related topics</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin Pathol.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>441</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/vcp.12006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23240820</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Salvin</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McGreevy</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sachdev</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valenzuela</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The canine cognitive dysfunction rating scale (CCDR): a data-driven and ecologically relevant assessment tool</article-title>. <source>Vet J.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>188</volume>:<fpage>331</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tvjl.2010.05.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20542455</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellows</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Colitz</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Daristotle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lepine</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Defining healthy aging in older dogs and differentiating healthy aging from disease</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>246</volume>:<fpage>77</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>89</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/javma.246.1.77</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25517329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fortney</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Implementing a successful senior/geriatric health care program for veterinarians, veterinary technicians, and office managers</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin North Am Small Anim Pract.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>823</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cvsm.2012.04.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22720816</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Becvarova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cave</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacKay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rama</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>WSAVA nutritional assessment guidelines</article-title>. <source>J Small Anim Pract.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>385</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1748-5827.2011.01079.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21649660</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Valenciano</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cowell</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Diagnostic Cytology and Hematology of the Dog and Cat.</source> Fifth edition. <publisher-loc>St. Louis, MO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name> (<year>2019</year>) <fpage>438</fpage> p.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Paltrinieri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertazzolo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Patologia Clinica Del Cane e Del Gatto.</source><publisher-loc>Milan</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier-Masson</publisher-name> (<year>2010</year>) <fpage>22</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage> p.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thrall</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Erythrocyte morphology</article-title>. In:<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thrall</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Campbel</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group>, editors. <source>Veterinary Hematology and Clinical Chemistry</source>. <publisher-loc>Ames, IA</publisher-loc> (<year>2006</year>). p. <fpage>69</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Veterinary Hematology: A Diagnostic Guide and Color Atlas</source>. Vol. <volume>54</volume>. <publisher-loc>St. Louis, MO</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name> (<year>2012</year>) <fpage>675</fpage> p.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>JEOL</collab></person-group>. <source>Application Notes. Specimen Preparation Methods for Scanning Electron Microscopes.</source><publisher-loc>Mexico City</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>JEOL</publisher-name> (<year>2001</year>) <fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage> p.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoyt</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorward</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Scanning electron microscopy</article-title>. <source>Curr Protoc Microbiol.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>2B</fpage>.2. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/9780471729259.mc02b02s25</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22549162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3352184</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>RM</surname></name></person-group>. <source>Basic Statistics. In: Problem Solving and Data Analysis Using Minitab., Ed</source>. <publisher-loc>Chichester</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name> (<year>2013</year>). p. <fpage>50</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/9781118307502.ch3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lesik</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Applied Statistical Inference With MINITAB</source><sup>&#174;</sup>. Second edition. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>A Chapman and Hall/CRC Press</publisher-name> (<year>2018</year>) p. <fpage>496</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1201/9780429444951</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chapter 5 - analysis of variance</article-title>. In: <source>Problem Solving and Data Analysis Using Minitab.</source><publisher-loc>Chichester</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd</publisher-name> (<year>2013</year>). p. <fpage>150</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>208</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/9781118307502.ch5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Geffr&#233;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Concordet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trumel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Reference value advisor: a new freeware set of macroinstructions to calculate reference intervals with microsoft excel</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin Pathol.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>107</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-165X.2011.00287.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21366659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rizzi</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meinkoth</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Clinkenbeard</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Normal hematology of the dog</article-title>. In: Wardrop DJW, editor. <source>Schalm's Veterinary Hematology.</source><publisher-loc>Ames, IA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name> (<year>2010</year>). p. <fpage>799</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>810</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Veterinary Hemocytology Atlas.</source> 2nd edition. <publisher-loc>Zaragoza</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>SERVET</publisher-name> (<year>2009</year>) <fpage>4</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage> p.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Christian</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Erythrokinetics and erythrocyte destruction</article-title>. In:<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>, editor. <source>Schalm's Veterinary Hematology</source>. 6th edition. <publisher-loc>Ames, IA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name>. (<year>2010</year>). p. <fpage>136</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raiden</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Joel</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jes&#250;s</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melanie</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Willian</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Hallazgos hematol&#243;gicos en perros y gatos en Lima, Per&#250;</article-title>. <source>Rev Invest Vet.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>1395</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>413</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15381/rivep.v30i4.17154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daleke</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Regulation of transbilayer plasma membrane phospholipid asymmetry</article-title>. <source>J Lipid Res.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>233</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1194/jlr.R200019-JLR200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12576505</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stefanescu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vitalaru</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lippi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toader</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Alterations of echinocytes in dogs with acute renal injury undergoing hemodialysis</article-title>. <source>J Biotechnol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>280</volume>:<fpage>S76</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2018.06.249</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barger</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Erythrocyte morphology</article-title>. In:<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>, editor. <source>Schalm's Veterinary Hematology</source>. 6th edition. <publisher-loc>Ames, IA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley-Blackwell</publisher-name> (<year>2010</year>). p. <fpage>144</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>51</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parachini-Winter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carioto</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gara-Boivin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Retrospective evaluation of anemia and erythrocyte morphological anomalies in dogs with lymphoma or inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>254</volume>:<fpage>487</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/javma.254.4.487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30714871</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bexfield</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>N</surname></name></person-group>. <article-title>Canine inflammatory liver disease</article-title>. In: Bruyette DS, Bexfield N, Chretin JD, Kidd L, Kube S, Langston C, Owen TJ, Oyama MA, Peterson N, Reiter LV, Rozanski EA, Ruaux C, Wiley SM, editors. <source>Clinical Small Animal Internal Medicine</source>. <publisher-loc>Hoboken, NJ</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wiley Blackwell</publisher-name> (<year>2020</year>). p. <fpage>695</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>704</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Garden</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mexas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jeffery</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blois</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>ACVIM consensus statement on the diagnosis of immune-mediated hemolytic anemia in dogs and cats</article-title>. <source>J Vet Intern Med.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>313</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jvim.15441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30806491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6430921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zoia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerou-Ferriani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Drigo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caldin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Case-control study of plasma mean platelet component concentration and survival analysis for dogs with immune-mediated hemolytic anemia</article-title>. <source>J Am Vet Med Assoc.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>252</volume>:<fpage>1384</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2460/javma.252.11.1384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29772969</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonfanti</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Comazzi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paltrinieri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertazzolo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Stomatocytosis in 7 related standard schnauzers</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin Pathol.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>234</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-165X.2004.tb00379.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15570561</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Short communication: trypanosomosis in dog - a case report</article-title>. <source>Explor Anim Med Res.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>220</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2</lpage>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.animalmedicalresearch.org/Vol.7_Issue-2_December_2017/TRYPANOSOMOSIS%20IN%20DOG%20_%20A%20CASE%20REPORT.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.animalmedicalresearch.org/Vol.7_Issue-2_December_2017/TRYPANOSOMOSIS%20IN%20DOG%20_%20A%20CASE%20REPORT.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciccoli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Felice</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paccagnini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leoncini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pecorelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Signorini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Erythrocyte shape abnormalities, membrane oxidative damage, and &#946;-actin alterations: an unrecognized triad in classical autism</article-title>. <source>Mediators Inflamm.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>2013</volume>:<fpage>432616</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/432616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24453417</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3880759</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Terlizzi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohandas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolce</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Canine elliptocytosis due to a mutant &#946;-spectrin</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin Pathol.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-165X.2008.00092.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19228356</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whalan</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hematology glossary</article-title>. In: <source>A Toxicologist's Guide to Clinical Pathology in Animals</source>. <publisher-loc>Heidelberg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name> (<year>2015</year>). p. <fpage>109</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-15853-2_8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pretorius</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The adaptability of red blood cells</article-title>. <source>Cardiovasc Diabetol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>63</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2840-12-63</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23578325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3637111</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pretorius</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kell</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Diagnostic morphology: biophysical indicators for iron-driven inflammatory diseases</article-title>. <source>Integr Biol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>486</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>510</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C4IB00025K</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24714688</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adili</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Melizi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belabbas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Species determination using the red blood cells morphometry in domestic animals</article-title>. <source>Vet World.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>960</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14202/vetworld.2016.960-963</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27733796</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5057034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brun-Hansen</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kampen</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hematologic values in calves during the first 6 months of life</article-title>. <source>Vet Clin Pathol.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>182</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1939-165X.2006.tb00111.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16783710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anio&#322;ek</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barc</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jarosi&#324;ska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gajewski</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of frequency and intensity of asymptomatic anisocytosis in the Japanese dog breeds Shiba, Akita, and Hokkaido</article-title>. <source>Acta Vet Brno.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>385</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2754/avb201786040385</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>