<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9797813</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC9797813.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">9797813</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">9797813</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36590818</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.1025677</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Dietary <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus paracasei</italic> improve the intestinal health of broilers challenged with coccidia and <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="P">Peng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1590623/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names initials="L">Liyun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names initials="Y">Ya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhipeng</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names initials="E">Encun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1237771/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names initials="J">Jintao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhengfan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1984263/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names initials="S">Shuangshuang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn003" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8225;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/470447/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names initials="B">Binying</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c002" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn003" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8225;</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Hubei Key Laboratory of Animal Nutrition and Feed Science, Wuhan Polytechnic University, Wuhan</institution>, <addr-line>Hubei</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Key Laboratory of Animal Embryo Engineering and Molecular Breeding of Hubei Province, Institute of Animal Science and Veterinary Medicine, Hubei Academy of Agricultural Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Wuhan</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Bruno Solis-Cruz, Universidad Nacional Auton&#243;ma de M&#233;xico, Mexico</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Muhammad Zahoor Khan, University of Agriculture, Dera Ismail Khan, Pakistan; Victor Manuel Petrone-Garc&#237;a, National Autonomous University of Mexico, Mexico</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Shuangshuang Guo <email>guo1shuangshuang@163.com</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Binying Ding <email>dbying7471@126.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Animal Nutrition and Metabolism, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn002"><p>&#8224;These authors have contributed equally to this work and share first authorship</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn003"><p>&#8225;These authors have contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">400313</issue-id><elocation-id>1025677</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>8</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-06-13 13:25:14.730"><day>13</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2022 Li, Zheng, Qi, Liu, Du, Wei, Zhang, Guo and Ding.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Li, Zheng, Qi, Liu, Du, Wei, Zhang, Guo and Ding</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-09-1025677.pdf"/><abstract><p>Necrotic enteritis (NE) is a great threat to the intestinal health of broilers, resulting in decreased growth performance and significant economic losses. <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">LF</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus paracasei</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">LP</italic>) exert beneficial effects on intestinal health. The aim of the present study was to investigate the effects of dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> on the intestinal health and growth performance of broilers challenged with coccidia and <italic toggle="yes">Clostridium perfringens</italic> (CCP). The animal trial was carried out using 336 broilers (Ross 308) for 35 days with a completely randomized design. The broilers were divided into 4 groups based on treatment as follows: the control (CTR) group was fed the basal diet and without CCP challenge and the CCP group was fed the basal diet and with CCP challenge. The broilers in the CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> groups were challenged by CCP, and meanwhile, <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> (1 &#215; 10<sup>9</sup> CFU/g) and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> (1 &#215; 10<sup>9</sup> CFU/g) were supplemented into the basal diets, respectively. The results showed that the growth performance and the intestinal morphology were negatively affected by the CCP challenge. In addition, the number of coccidia in the intestinal digesta and the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> in the cecal digesta were increased. Besides, the mRNA level of <italic toggle="yes">IgA</italic> in the jejunum was downregulated, and the transcript level of <italic toggle="yes">IL-8</italic> was upregulated by the CCP challenge. Dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> failed to improve the growth performance of broilers with the CCP challenge. However, they were beneficial for intestinal barrier function. In addition, dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> was able to alleviate the downregulation of <italic toggle="yes">TGF-</italic>&#946; mRNA level in the spleen with CCP challenge and decreased the lesion scores compared with the CCP group. Furthermore, dietary <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> alleviated the upregulation of the <italic toggle="yes">IL-8</italic> mRNA level in the jejunum with CCP challenge and reduced the number of coccidia in the ileal digesta. In conclusion, dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> failed to mitigate the negative effects of CCP infection on growth performance; however, they were able to improve the intestinal health of broilers challenged with CCP by strengthening the intestinal barrier and alleviating inflammation.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic></kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus paracasei</italic></kwd><kwd>intestinal health</kwd><kwd>broiler</kwd><kwd>necrotic enteritis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001"><institution-wrap><institution>Natural Science Foundation of Hubei Province</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100003819</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="5"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="30"/><page-count count="11"/><word-count count="7150"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Necrotic enteritis (NE) in broilers caused by <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> is an enterotoxemic disease that shapes the impaired intestinal barrier, unstable intestinal flora, and weakened immunity of birds (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). In fact, NE results in significant economic losses. A study suggested that a loss of $0.05 per bird was caused by NE (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Previously, antibiotics were used to treat NE in poultry production. However, antibiotics are banned in feed in many countries, and in recent years, the incidence of NE has been increasing. At present, nutrition-based interventions to address this problem have attracted the attention of many scholars. Probiotics have great potential to improve intestinal health, and dietary probiotics continue to be a good antibiotic substitute to alleviate NE in broilers. It was reported that <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">LF</italic>) could produce short-chain fatty acids (SCFAs), which can inhibit the proliferation of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Some studies also suggested that dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> was beneficial to the intestinal barrier and immunity of weaned piglets (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Another study demonstrated that <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus paracasei</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">LP</italic>) improved intestinal flora, which contributed to the growth performance and immunity of birds (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>).</p><p>Although some biological effects of <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> had been investigated, they were not fully characterized in poultry. The reported beneficial effects of <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> on intestinal health suggest their potential to alleviate NE. Hence, it was necessary to study the effects of dietary <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> supplementation in NE broilers. However, the lack of a reliable NE model might leave us stranded. A stable NE model in broilers should be of great importance. In our previous study, <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> could be used in establishing the NE model (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). However, due to differences in individual birds or dietary factors, the infection of <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> was also not always successful to establish the NE model. A study suggested that the coinfection of coccidia and <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> might make a more stable NE model (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). In the present study, coccidia and <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> were used to establish a NE model, and dietary <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> were employed to prevent NE. This study aimed at investigating the effects of dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> on the intestinal health and growth performance of broilers infected with NE.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Animal and diet</title><p>The animal study was carried out at the Wuhan Polytechnic University (Hubei, China). A total of 336 1-day-old healthy Ross 308 broilers with uniform weight were randomly assigned to 4 treatments. There were 6 replicates in each group and 14 broilers (7 males and 7 females) in each replicate. The broilers in the control (CTR) group were fed the basal diet and without coccidia and were affected by the <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> (CCP) challenge. The basal diet was formulated according to the recommendation of the NRC (1994). The formula and nutrient levels of the basal diet are shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The broilers in the CCP group were fed the basal diet and challenged by CCP. The <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> (CVCC2030) was purchased from the China Veterinary Microbial Culture Collection and Management Center (Beijing, China), and the coccidia were purchased from Foshan Zhengdian Biotechnology Co., Ltd. (Guangdong, China). A quadrivalent anti-coccidiosis vaccine consisted of 5 &#215; 10<sup>4</sup> oocysts of <italic toggle="yes">E. tenella</italic> strain PTMZ, <italic toggle="yes">E. necatrix</italic> strain PNHZ, and <italic toggle="yes">E. maxima</italic> strain PMHY, as well as 1 &#215; 10<sup>5</sup> oocysts of <italic toggle="yes">E. acervuline</italic> strain PAHY. The recommended dose of the vaccine was 1,100 &#177; 110 sporulated oocysts per bird. In the present study, the number of coccidia oocysts inoculating each bird was 30 times the recommended dose. Birds in the CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> groups were also challenged with CCP, and the diets of the CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> groups were supplemented with 1 &#215; 10<sup>9</sup> CFU/g <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and 1 &#215; 10<sup>9</sup> CFU/g <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic>, respectively. The diet for each group was formulated one time a week. A 35-day trial was performed, and an overview of the trial is shown in <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>. On day 9 of the trial, the anti-coccidiosis vaccine was administered into the crop of broilers in the CCP, CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LF</italic>, and CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> groups. The birds in the CTR group were treated with an equal volume of saline. From days 13 to 18, the broilers in the CCP, CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LF</italic>, and CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> groups were challenged with <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>. Specifically, 64 ml of <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> broth (1 &#215; 10<sup>8</sup> CFU/mL) was well mixed into 1,200 g feed of each group, which was then equally distributed to each replicate. Importantly, these feeds should be consumed within 2 h, and the birds in the CTR group were fed a diet with an equal volume of sterile broth. On days 13 and 19, two birds in each replicate were selected to collect blood from the wing vein and slaughtered for sample collection. On days 1, 13, 19, and 35, all broilers and feed were weighed for the calculation of growth performance. All broilers were raised in wire cages with free access to water and feed. During the first 3 days of the trial, the room temperature was controlled at 35&#176;C, and then, the temperature was decreased by 1&#176;C per day until it was maintained at 25&#176;C. A 24-h light regime was implemented throughout the animal trial.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The feed ingredient composition and nutrient levels, air-dried basis.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Ingredient, %</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>d 0- 21</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>d 21- 35</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Nutrition level<xref rid="TN3" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>c</sup></xref></bold>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>d 0- 21</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>d 21- 35</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.69</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.78</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ME</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mc/kg</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.929</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.996</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">soybean meal</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.18</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Crude protein</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.606</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.739</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fish meal</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lysine</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.156</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soybean oil</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.20</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methionine</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.603</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.458</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CaHPO4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Methionine+ Cystine</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.914</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.760</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stone powder</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcium</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.131</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.061</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NaCl</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Available phosphorus</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.482</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.402</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DL-Met</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Threonine</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.747</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.658</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Choline chloride, 50%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mineral premix<xref rid="TN1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Lys HCl, 78%</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vitamin premix<xref rid="TN2" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1"><label>a</label><p>Trace element premix (provided per kilogram of feed) the following substances: Cu, 8 mg; Zn, 75 mg; Fe, 80 mg; Mn, 100 mg; selenium, 0.15 mg; iodine, 0.35 mg.</p></fn><fn id="TN2"><label>b</label><p>Vitamin premix (provided per kilogram of feed) the following substances: vitamin A, 12,500 IU; vitamin D3, 2,500 IU; vitamin E, 18.75 mg; vitamin K3, 2.65 mg; vitamin B1, 2 mg; vitamin B2, 6 mg; vitamin B12, 0.025 mg; biotin, 0.0325 mg; folic acid, 1.25 mg; nicotinic acid, 50 mg; pantothenic acid, 12 mg.</p></fn><fn id="TN3"><label>c</label><p>Calculated values.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The schematic diagram of the overview of the trial. All broilers were weighed to investigate the growth performance on days 1, 13, 19, and 35. Some broilers were selected to be slaughtered, and samples were collected for laboratory analysis. Among them, green circles indicate that all chickens were weighed and recorded on that day, and red triangles indicate the broiler chickens that were selected for slaughter and sampling on that day.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1025677-g0001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>The determination of growth performance and the immune organ index</title><p>The body weight of the broilers and the feed consumption were weighed on days 1, 13, 19, and 35. The average daily gain (ADG), average daily feed intake (ADFI), and the feed conversion ratio (FCR) from days 1&#8211;13, days 14&#8211;19, days 20&#8211;35, and days 1&#8211;35 were calculated. The indexes of the spleen, the bursa of Fabricius, and the thymus on days 13 and 19 were also analyzed. The formula for calculating the immune organ index is as follows: immune organ index = the weight of organ (g) /the body weight of broiler (kg).</p></sec><sec><title>The assay of immune and biochemical parameters in the serum</title><p>The blood was collected from the underwing vein and centrifuged at 3,000 r/min for 15 min at 4&#176;C, and the serum was separated from the supernatant. The kits purchased from Nanjing Jiancheng Biotechnology Co., Ltd. (Jiangsu, China) were used to determine the levels of lysozyme, inductible nitric oxide synthase (i-NOS), and lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) in the serum. An automatic biochemical analyzer (Unicel DXC800, Beckman Coulter, USA) was used to analyze the levels of glucose (GLU), calcium (Ca), and phosphorus (P) in the serum.</p></sec><sec><title>The measurement of intestinal morphology and lesion score</title><p>Approximately 1 cm of mid-segments of the duodenum, jejunum, and ileum were collected and fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde. Then, these intestinal segments were embedded in wax blocks and sectioned at 4 &#956;m, and the sections were stained with eosin-hematoxylin. Intestinal villus height (VH) and crypt depth (CD) were measured as described in the previous study (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Briefly, 10 straight and intact intestinal villi were randomly selected in each sample, and then the VH and CD were measured by an image analysis system using the Olympus BX-41TF microscope. The vertical distance from the tip of the villus to the crypt opening was considered as the villus height, and the vertical distance from the crypt opening to the ending was the crypt depth. The average values were calculated from the ten measurements, and the ratio of VH to CD was also calculated. In addition, the duodenum, jejunum, and ileum were cut lengthwise, and the digesta were rinsed. Then, a 6-point scoring system (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) was employed to score the intestinal lesion. The specific rules for this 6-point scoring were as follows: an intestine without any abnormalities should be a zero. The intestine marked 1 should be described as having a thin wall and diffuse fibrin attached to the mucosal surface of the intestine. There were 1&#8211;5 necrotic or ulcerated spots on the intestinal mucosa or deposits of fibrin that could not be removed, which should be marked as 2 points. The more severe the bowel lesion, the more spots there were. For example, 3 points for a number of lesions between 6 and 15, and 4 points for more than 16 lesions. The presence of a 2&#8211;3 cm patch of necrotic plaque on the intestine should be marked as 5 points. Beyond that, once the necrotic plaque penetrated from the intestinal mucosa into the lamina propria and muscle layers of the intestine, it was considered as 6 points.</p></sec><sec><title>Coccidia counts in digesta and feces</title><p>The digesta of the jejunum, ileum, and cecum as well as the feces were collected on days 13 and 19, and then stored in a refrigerator at &#8722;20&#176;C. A total of 2 g of samples were mixed with 10 ml of saline, and then 50 ml of saline was continuously added with stirring until there was no obvious fecal mass. A 60-mesh nylon was used to filter the mixture, and then the filtrate was collected and pipetted into the two counting chambers of the <italic toggle="yes">M. mcswelli</italic> counting plate. The chambers were filled with filtrate, and air bubbles should be removed. The counting plate was placed for 3 min before being counted using a microscope. The formula for calculating the data was as follows: number of coccidial oocysts per gram of feces (OPG) = [(n1 + n2)] &#215; 60 &#215; dilution factor/(2 &#215; 0.15) &#215; 2. Among them, n1 and n2 were the numbers of the coccidial oocysts in each chamber, and the volume of the counting chamber was 0.15 ml. The dilution factor was the number of times the mixture was diluted. The total volume of the mixture was 60 ml, and the weight of the digesta or feces was 2 g.</p></sec><sec><title>Gene expression</title><p>The jejunum and the spleen were collected and placed in an RNase-free centrifuge tube and then snap-frozen in liquid nitrogen before being transferred to a refrigerator at &#8722;80&#176;C. Extraction of total RNA, preparation of cDNA, and PCR were performed as previously described (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). The TRIzol reagent (Takara, Dalian, China) was used to obtain the total RNA, and the purity was checked with the following criteria: an OD<sub>260</sub>/OD<sub>280</sub> ratio of ~2.0 and a 28 S/18 S rRNA ratio of &gt; 1.8. Then, the gDNA Eraser (Takara, Dalian, China) was used to prepare the cDNA. An Applied Biosystems 7500 Fast Real-Time PCR System (Foster City, CA) was used to perform the qPCR. The 2<sup>&#8722;&#916;&#916;CT</sup> method (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) was used to analyze the relative expression of each gene, and the &#946;<italic toggle="yes">-actin</italic> was used as the reference gene. Primers of the genes in the present study are listed in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>List of gene primer sequences<xref rid="TN4" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Gene name</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Prime sequence (5<sup>&#8242;</sup>-3<sup>&#8242;</sup>)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>NCBI number</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">TNF-&#945;</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-GAGCGTTGACTTGGCTGTC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_204267">NM_204267</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R-AAGCAACAACCAGCTATGCAC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">IFN-&#947;</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-AGCTGACGGTGGACCTATTATT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="Y07922">Y07922</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R-GGCTTTGCGCTGGATTC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">IL-1&#946;</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-ACTGGGCATCAAGGGCTA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_204524">NM_204524</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R-GGTAGAAGATGAAGCGGGTC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">TGF-&#946;4</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-CGGGACGGATGAGAAGAAC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="M31160">M31160</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R-CGGCCCACGTAGTAAATGAT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">IL-8</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-ATGAACGGCAAGCTTGGA<break/> R-TCCAAGCACACCTCTCTTC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AJ009800">AJ009800</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">IgA</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-GTCACCGTCACCTGGACACCA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="S40610">S40610</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R-ACCGATGGTCTCCTTCACATC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">pIgR</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-GGATCTGGAAGCCAGCAAT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AY233381">AY233381</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R-GAGCCAGAGCTTTGCTCAG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Mucin-2</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-TTCATGATGCCTGCTCTTGTG</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="XM_421035">XM_421035</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R-CCTGAGCCTTGGTACATTCTTGT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Claudin-1</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-CATACTCCTGGGTCTGGTTGGT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="AY750897.1">AY750897.1</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R-GACAGCCATCCGCATCTTCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">ZO-1</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-CTTCAGGTGTTTCTCTTCCTCCTC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="XM_413773">XM_413773</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R-CTGTGGTTTCATGGCTGGATC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Occludin</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-ACGGCAGCACCTACCTCAA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="D21837.1">D21837.1</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R-GGGCGAAGAAGCAGATGAG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">&#946;-actin</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-GAGAAATTGTGCGTGACATCA</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_205518.1">NM_205518.1</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R-CCTGAACCTCTCATTGCCA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN4"><label>a</label><p>The primers were designed and synthesized by Shanghai Sangon Bioengineering Co., Ltd. Shanghai, China. TNF-&#945;, tumor necrosis factor &#945;; IFN-&#947;, interferon &#947;; IL-1&#946; and IL-8, interleukin 1&#946; and interleukin 8; TGF-&#946;4, transforming growth factor &#946;4; IgA, immunoglobulin A; pIgR, polymeric immunoglobulin receptor; ZO-1, zonula occludens protein 1.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Analysis of specific intestinal microflora</title><p>The cecal digesta was collected on day 19. QIAamp fast DNA stool mini kits (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) were used to extract the genomic DNA of the cecal microflora. A NanoDrop 2000 spectrophotometer (Thermo Scientific, USA) was used to measure the concentration of DNA. The steps of qPCR and the calculation method of genes were the same as described above. The total bacteria (16s rRNA) were used as the reference gene, and the specific 16S rRNA genes were targeted for <italic toggle="yes">E. coli, Lactobacillus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>. The primers of these bacteria were as follows: total bacteria: F-ACTCCTACGGGAGGCAGCAGT and R-GTATTACCGCGGCTGCTGGCAC; <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>: F-GTTAATACCTTTGCTCATTGA and R-ACCAGGGTATCTAATCCTGT; <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic>: F-AGCAGTAGGGAATCTTCCA and R-CACCGCTACACATGGAG; and <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>: F-AAAGATGGCATCATCATTCAAC and R-TACCGTCATTATCTTCCCCAAA.</p></sec><sec><title>Data analysis</title><p>A one-way ANOVA program in SPSS 23.0 software (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL) was used to analyze the data, and then, Tukey's multiple comparisons were used to investigate the differences between groups. The Kolmogorov-Smirnov test was used to analyze the data that did not comply with normal distribution, and a non-parameter test and pairwise comparisons were used to analyze the data. The Mann-Whitney U test was used to analyze lesion scores between treatments. The data of the lesion score was expressed in the median and interquartile range, and data other than the lesion score were presented as mean &#177; standard error. A <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value of &lt; 0.05 was considered to be significantly different between groups, and the Graphpad prism 8.0 software was used for creating graphs.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Growth performance and serum parameters</title><p>The FCR during days 1&#8211;13 and 14&#8211;19 was negatively affected by the CCP challenge, as well as the ADG and ADFI during days 14&#8211;19 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The growth performance in other periods was not significantly affected by CCP treatment. In addition, dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> failed to alleviate the negative effects of CCP on growth performance.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The growth performance of broilers during the trial, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Item</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CTR</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CCP</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LF</italic></bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LP</italic></bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">P-value</italic>
</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>d 1-13</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADFI, g</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.57 &#177; 0.65</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.97 &#177; 0.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.95 &#177; 0.61</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.60 &#177; 0.51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.631</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADG, g</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.65 &#177; 0.47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.71 &#177; 0.15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.60 &#177; 0.51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.14 &#177; 0.34</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.317</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FCR</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32 &#177; 0.01<xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 &#177; 0.01<xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34 &#177; 0.01<xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 &#177; 0.01<xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>d 14-19</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADFI, g</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.03 &#177; 1.53<xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.68 &#177; 0.68<xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.03 &#177; 0.90<xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.80 &#177; 0.95<xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADG, g</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.30 &#177; 1.07<xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.68 &#177; 0.41<xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.31 &#177; 0.65<xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.64 &#177; 0.59<xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FCR</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49 &#177; 0.01<xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58 &#177; 0.01<xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59 &#177; 0.02<xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60 &#177; 0.01<xref rid="TN5" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt; 0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>d 20-35</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADFI, g</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.54 &#177; 2.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.46 &#177; 1.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.30 &#177; 2.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.87 &#177; 2.59</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.660</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADG, g</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.44 &#177; 1.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.90 &#177; 1.55</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.39 &#177; 1.89</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.76 &#177; 1.62</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.643</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FCR</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73 &#177; 0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71 &#177; 0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71 &#177; 0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.72 &#177; 0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.790</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>d 1-35</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADFI, g</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.56 &#177; 1.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.82 &#177; 0.60</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.63 &#177; 0.74</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.08 &#177; 1.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.583</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADG, g</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.57 &#177; 0.71</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.88 &#177; 0.59</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.96 &#177; 0.63</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.80 &#177; 0.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.576</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FCR</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61 &#177; 0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62 &#177; 0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62 &#177; 0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63 &#177; 0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.722</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN5"><label>a,b</label><p>Means in the same row without common superscripts differ significantly (P &lt; 0.05). Data were presented as mean &#177; standard error. CTR, control group; CCP, the infection model group that was challenged with Clostridium perfringens and coccidia, CCP+ LF, the infection model group with Lactobacillus fermentum supplemented in the diet; and CCP+ LP, the infection model group with Lactobacillus paracasei supplemented in the diet.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The index of the thymus on day 13 tended to be reduced (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.091), and the spleen index on day 19 tended to be increased by CCP challenge (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.093) (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> were not able to improve immune organ indices. The content of serum glucose on day 13 was decreased (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), and serum lysozyme on day 19 tended to be increased by CCP challenge (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.059) (<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). Additionally, compared with the CCP group, the levels of serum i-NOS on day 13 were increased in the CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The contents of serum calcium on days 13 and 19 were elevated in the broilers of the CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.001).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>The immune organ indices, g/kg, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Item</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CTR</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CCP</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LF</italic></bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LP</italic></bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P-</italic>value</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d13</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spleen</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 &#177; 0.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 &#177; 0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 &#177; 0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 &#177; 0.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.438</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bursa of fabricius</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.18 &#177; 0.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.43 &#177; 0.18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.22 &#177; 0.15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.31 &#177; 0.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.562</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thymus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.74 &#177; 0.11<xref rid="TN6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.53 &#177; 0.10<xref rid="TN6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref rid="TN6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32 &#177; 0.07<xref rid="TN6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38 &#177; 0.06<xref rid="TN6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d19</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spleen</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 &#177; 0.05<xref rid="TN6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 &#177; 0.05<xref rid="TN6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref rid="TN6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 &#177; 0.06<xref rid="TN6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 &#177; 0.10<xref rid="TN6" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bursa of fabricius</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.40 &#177; 0.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14 &#177; 0.15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29 &#177; 0.18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.24 &#177; 0.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.701</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thymus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60 &#177; 0.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45 &#177; 0.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40 &#177; 0.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.59 &#177; 0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.371</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN6"><label>a,b</label><p>Means in the same row without common superscripts differ significantly (P &lt; 0.05). Data were presented as mean &#177; standard error. CTR, control group; CCP, the infection model group that was challenged with Clostridium perfringens and coccidia; CCP+ LF, the infection model group with Lactobacillus fermentum supplemented in the diet; and CCP+ LP, the infection model group with Lactobacillus paracasei supplemented in the diet.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>The levels of serum immune and biochemical parameters, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Item</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CTR</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CCP</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LF</italic></bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LP</italic></bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P-</italic>value</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d13</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lysozyme, U/mL</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.42 &#177; 1.58</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.47 &#177; 2.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.04 &#177; 1.62</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.65 &#177; 2.18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.766</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">iNOS, U/mL</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00 &#177; 0.51<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.55 &#177; 0.70<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.53 &#177; 0.87<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.62 &#177; 0.69<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GLU, mg/dL</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205.86 &#177; 2.88<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192.21 &#177; 2.90<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200.38 &#177; 3.57<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">198.52 &#177; 3.20<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>ab</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.033</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca, mg/dL</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.59 &#177; 0.17<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.81 &#177; 0.20<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.26 &#177; 0.23<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.25 &#177; 0.27<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P, mg/dL</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.15 &#177; 0.15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.14 &#177; 0.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.34 &#177; 0.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.61 &#177; 0.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.173</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDH, U/L</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">682.14 &#177; 30.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">638.57 &#177; 31.54</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">639.58 &#177; 23.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">663.82 &#177; 31.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.680</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d19</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lysozyme, U/mL</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.94 &#177; 1.21<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.57 &#177; 2.90<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.97 &#177; 1.82<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.18 &#177; 0.97<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">iNOS, U/mL</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.81 &#177; 0.21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.69 &#177; 0.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.47 &#177; 0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.78 &#177; 0.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GLU, mg/dL</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223.22 &#177; 6.18<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206.78 &#177; 4.67<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197.02 &#177; 6.75<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200.59 &#177; 7.05<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref><xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ca, mg/dL</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.58 &#177; 0.13<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.67 &#177; 0.19<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.31 &#177; 0.26<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.25 &#177; 0.17<xref rid="TN7" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P, mg/dL</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.80 &#177; 0.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.86 &#177; 0.25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.40 &#177; 0.18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.69 &#177; 0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.314</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDH, U/L</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">644.08 &#177; 37.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">746.15 &#177; 85.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">629.61 &#177; 33.96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">713.13 &#177; 34.67</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.350</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN7"><label>a,b</label><p>Means in the same row without common superscripts differ significantly (P &lt; 0.05). Data were presented as mean &#177; standard error. CTR, control group; CCP, the infection model group that was challenged with Clostridium perfringens and coccidia; CCP+ LF, the infection model group with Lactobacillus fermentum supplemented in the diet; and CCP+ LP, the infection model group with Lactobacillus paracasei supplemented in the diet.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>The measurement of the intestinal mucosa and cecal flora</title><p>The crypt depths of the duodenum, the jejunum, and the ileum on days 13 and 19 were increased by CCP challenge (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). In addition, the ratios of VH to CD in the duodenum, the jejunum, and the ileum on day 13 and in the jejunum and the ileum on day 19 decreased. Dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> elevated the ratios of VH to CD in the duodenum and the jejunum on day 13 and in the jejunum on day 19 of broilers with CCP challenge. Moreover, dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> increased the ratio of VH to CD in the ileum on day 13, and dietary <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> improved it in the duodenum on day 19 with the CCP challenge.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The intestinal villus height, crypt depth, and the ratio of villus height to crypt depth. <bold>(A)</bold> the data were collected on day 13, and <bold>(B)</bold> the data were collected on day 19. Among them, <sup>a,b</sup>, and <sup>c</sup> means in the different pillars without common superscripts differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). VH, villus height; CD, crypt depth; VH/CD, the ratio of VH to CD. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12. Data were presented as mean &#177; standard error. CTR, the control group; CCP, the group co-infected with coccidia and <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> (CCP), CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> denote the groups fed <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus paracasei</italic>-supplemented diets with <italic toggle="yes">CCP</italic> challenge.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1025677-g0002.jpg"/></fig><p>The CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> group had a lower lesion score in the jejunum than that of the CCP group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>). The relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> in the cecal digesta was upregulated by CCP challenge (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B</xref>), while dietary <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> decreased it. Although we did not observe a statistical difference in the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic>, it was numerically raised by the CCP challenge. Unexpectedly, dietary <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> upregulated the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> in the cecal digesta. Compared with the CCP group, the number of coccidial oocysts in the ileal digesta of the CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> group on day 13 was decreased (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C</xref>). It was concluded that dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> exerted beneficial effects in CCP-challenged birds.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The intestinal lesion score, the number of cecal bacteria, and intestinal coccidia. The data of the intestinal lesion score is arranged in <bold>(A)</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12), the levels of some bacteria in the cecal chyme are shown in <bold>(B)</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 10), and the numbers of coccidia in the chyme are arranged in <bold>(C)</bold> (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12 in the chyme of jejunum, ileum, and chyme. <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6 in the feces). The data in <bold>(A)</bold> were expressed in the median and interquartile range, and data in <bold>(B,C)</bold> were presented as mean &#177; standard error. CTR, the control group; CCP, the group coinfected with coccidia and <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> (CCP), CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> denote the groups fed <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus paracasei</italic>-supplemented diets with <italic toggle="yes">CCP</italic> challenge. In <bold>(A)</bold>, ** = 0.001 &lt; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.01, among <bold>(B,C)</bold>, <sup>a,b</sup>, and <sup>c</sup> indicate that the different pillars without common superscripts differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1025677-g0003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>The transcription levels of some genes in the jejunum and spleen</title><p>The mRNA levels of <italic toggle="yes">ZO-1, Mucin-2</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Occludin</italic> in the jejunum on day 13 were downregulated by CCP challenge, as well as the transcript level of <italic toggle="yes">Mucin-2</italic> in the jejunum on day 19 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figures 4A</xref>,<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">B</xref>). These results were logically consistent with the findings that CCP challenge weakened intestinal morphology. Dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> upregulated the mRNA levels of <italic toggle="yes">ZO-1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Mucin-2</italic> in the jejunum of broilers with CCP challenge on day 13 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Dietary <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> elevated the mRNA level of <italic toggle="yes">Claudin-1</italic> in the jejunum of broilers with CCP challenge on day 19 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Besides, the results of immune-related genes showed that the mRNA level of <italic toggle="yes">IL-8</italic> was upregulated on day 13, and the transcript level <italic toggle="yes">IgA</italic> in the jejunum was downregulated by CCP challenge (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), as well as the <italic toggle="yes">TGF-</italic>&#946; in the spleen (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.094) (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4C</xref>). Compared with the CCP group, the mRNA level of <italic toggle="yes">IL-8</italic> in the jejunum on day 13 was downregulated, and the mRNA level of <italic toggle="yes">IFN-</italic>&#947; in the spleen on day 19 was upregulated with <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> supplementation (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Additionally, dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> upregulated the transcript level of <italic toggle="yes">TGF-</italic>&#946; in the spleen of the birds with CCP challenge on day 13 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The mRNA transcript levels of some genes in the jejunum and spleen. <bold>(A)</bold> The data of the gene mRNA levels in the jejunum on day 13, <bold>(B)</bold> the data of the gene mRNA levels in the jejunum on day 19, and <bold>(C)</bold> the data of the gene mRNA levels in the spleen. Among them, <sup>a,b</sup>, and <sup>c</sup> means in the different pillars without common superscripts differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 12. Data were presented as mean &#177; standard error. CTR, the control group; CCP, the group coinfected with coccidia and <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> (CCP), CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and CCP+<italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> denote the groups fed <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic>- and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus paracasei</italic>-supplemented diets with <italic toggle="yes">CCP</italic> challenge.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1025677-g0004.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>A wheat-based diet was proven to help establish the NE model with coccidia and <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> challenge (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). We presented an undated report based on this idea in this study. Liu et al. (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) suggested that the growth performance of broilers with CCP challenge was negatively affected, and it might be recorded only during CCP infection. In the present study, we observed consistent outcomes. Specifically, combined infection with coccidia and <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> reduced the growth performance of broilers, which might only be observed during the infection period. There was no difference in growth performance between CCP-challenged and unchallenged broilers in the period after infection. A possible explanation was that the immune system of broilers was used to maintain immune homeostasis during the CCP challenge and that numerous nutrients needed to be ingested for immune responses. Since then, the compensatory growth mechanism (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) has been activated to eliminate the difference in growth performance. Some probiotics were found to be useful for the growth performance and immunity of broilers (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), which opened a new window for relieving the NE in broilers. Unexpectedly, we observed that <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> were ineffective in the growth performance of CCP-infected broilers in this study. It was speculated that <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> might not be able to colonize in the intestine of broilers, as we found in the present study that dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> failed to elevate the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic>. This transient probiotic might only be beneficial to the intestine, and this effect was not sufficient to improve the growth performance. To investigate our conjecture, we would conduct further studies on the intestines of broilers.</p><p>A healthy intestine should be equipped with a complete morphological structure and a stable microbial environment (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), and the tight junctions underlie the molecular basis of the intestinal barrier (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Additionally, the mucins secreted by goblet cells of the intestine are regarded as the first guardian of intestinal health (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). In the present study, the mRNA levels of <italic toggle="yes">Occludin, ZO-1</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Mucin-2</italic> were downregulated by the CCP challenge. It was demonstrated that the CCP challenge weakened the intestinal barrier, which was consistent with previous reports (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Besides, the ratio of villi height to crypt depth decreased with the CCP challenge. It was generally known that the longer the intestinal villi, the stronger the intestinal absorption function. Additionally, the intestinal crypts were rich in immature cells that were not capable of absorption, and the increase in crypt depth might be detrimental to the absorption function of the intestine. The ratio of intestinal VH to CD was considered a reliable indicator for assessing intestinal absorptive function (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). The negative effects of the CCP challenge on growth performance might be attributed to its disruption of the intestinal barrier. Interestingly, dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> contributed to improving the intestinal morphology of broilers with CCP challenge in the present study. This was demonstrated in a number of studies that short-chain fatty acids produced by <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> in the intestine were beneficial for intestinal development and immunity (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>), which might be the evidence that dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> improved the intestinal barrier function in this study. Although <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> did not improve the growth performance of CCP-challenged broilers, they strengthened the intestinal barrier. It showed that a combination of probiotics and other additives might improve the growth performance. This deserved an in-depth investigation.</p><p>The large quantity of microbes in the intestine is involved in shaping intestinal physiology (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), and a stable microflora is especially important. A study suggested that the stability of intestinal flora was perturbed by the CCP challenge and that some pathogenic bacteria might be active (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Pathogenic bacteria, such as <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, contain components of the cell wall like lipopolysaccharides that cause inflammation in the body by activating the toll-like receptor signaling pathways (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). In the present study, the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> in the cecal digesta was raised with CCP challenge, and <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> was also numerically increased. Additionally, the number of coccidial oocysts was elevated. Dietary <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> was able to alleviate the upregulation of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>. However, the relative abundance of <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> was upregulated with <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> supplementation. This was a somewhat surprising result since it was expected that dietary <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> might inhibit the proliferation of <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> in the intestine. A possible explanation was that, although dietary <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> inhibited the proliferation of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, in fact, it also disturbed the intestinal flora. The unstable flora structure provided an opportunity for the colonization of <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> in the intestine. However, it did not aggravate the negative effects of the CCP challenge on broilers. Dietary <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> decreased the number of coccidial oocysts with CCP challenge. It seemed that dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> might have the potential to improve the intestinal environment. A report demonstrated that almost 80% of the immune response was mediated by gut microbes (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Hence, it could be interesting to investigate the immunity in broilers.</p><p>It was accepted that calcium contributed to the performance and immunity of poultry (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). In the present study, dietary <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> elevated the level of calcium in the serum. Additionally, the level of serum i-NOS was also raised with <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> treatments. Based on those findings, it might be concluded that dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> were beneficial for the immunity of broilers. A study suggested that CCP challenge caused inflammatory responses in broilers (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), and IL-8 was considered a chemokine that was essential for angiogenesis and inflammation (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Additionally, IL-8 has attracted considerable attention as an immunomodulator in inflammatory responses (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). In the present study, the mRNA level of <italic toggle="yes">IL-8</italic> in the jejunum was upregulated with CCP challenge, and dietary <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> could alleviate its upregulation. In addition, the transcript level of <italic toggle="yes">TGF-</italic>&#946; in the spleen was downregulated with CCP challenge, and dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> also reversed this result. Pro-inflammatory and anti-inflammatory cytokines were involved in maintaining immune homeostasis. TGF-&#946; was a pivotal member of the anti-inflammatory factor family (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). The present findings demonstrated that the CCP challenge disrupted immune homeostasis and promoted inflammatory responses. This could be one of the reasons for the abnormal immune organ indices in broilers challenged by CCP.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Combined infection with coccidia and <italic toggle="yes">C. perfringens</italic> impaired the intestinal barrier function by disrupting the intestinal morphology and tight junctions. In addition, coinfection led to inflammation in broilers. All these adverse factors negatively affect the growth performance of broilers. Dietary <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> improved the intestinal health of broilers challenged with CCP by strengthening the intestinal barrier and alleviating inflammation. Dietary supplementation of <italic toggle="yes">LF</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">LP</italic> has great potential to alleviate NE in broilers. Here, a detailed investigation of the mechanisms of the regulatory effects of dietary LF and LP on intestinal barrier function and immunity needs to be implemented.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/supplementary material, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding authors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="s7"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Wuhan Polytechnic University.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s8"><title>Author contributions</title><p>BD and SG designed the study. PL wrote the manuscript. PL, LZ, YQ, ZL, ED, JW, and ZZ helped to collect and analyze experimental results. BD, SG, and PL participated in the writing and revision of the manuscript. All authors contributed to the data interpretation and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="s9"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was supported by the Hubei Provincial Key Project for Scientific and Technical Innovation (2020BBA054), the Natural Science Foundation of Hubei Province (2021CFB559), and the Open Project of Key Laboratory of Animal Embryo Engineering and Molecular Breeding of Hubei Province (KLAEMB-2021-04).</p></sec><ack><p>All authors would like to thank all volunteers for their commitment and patience during the study.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s10"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Daneshmand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kermanshahi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sekhavati</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Javadmanesh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmadian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Intestinal changes and immune responses during Clostridium perfringens-induced necrotic enteritis in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>101</volume>:<fpage>101652</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2021.101652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35038649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8762468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jayaraman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thangavel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukkalil</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chirakkal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bacillus subtilis PB6 improves intestinal health of broiler chickens challenged with Clostridium perfringens-induced necrotic enteritis</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>92</volume>:<fpage>370</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.2012-02528</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23300303</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blomberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henriksson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Inhibition of adhesion of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> K88 to piglet ileal mucus by <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus</italic> spp</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol.</source> (<year>1993</year>) <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>34</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aem.59.1.34-39.1993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8439162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC202051</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of Lactobacillus fermentum I5007 on the intestinal and systemic immune responses of healthy and <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> challenged piglets</article-title>. <source>Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>89</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>98</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10482-009-9339-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19347600</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary supplementation with the probiotic Lactobacillus fermentum I5007 and the antibiotic aureomycin differentially affects the small intestinal proteomes of weanling piglets</article-title>. <source>J NUTR.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>142</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3945/jn.111.147074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22113866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Lactobacillus paracasei subsp. paracasei LC01 positively modulates intestinal microflora in healthy young adults</article-title>. <source>J Microbiol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>777</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12275-013-3279-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24385355</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Probiotic Properties of Lactobacillus paracasei subsp. paracasei L1 and Its Growth Performance-Promotion in Chicken by Improving the Intestinal Microflora</article-title>. <source>Front Physiol</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>937</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2019.00937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31404251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6670285</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary lactobacillus fermentum and bacillus coagulans supplementation modulates intestinal immunity and microbiota of broiler chickens challenged by clostridium perfringens</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>680742</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2021.680742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34136557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8200825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary l-arginine inhibits intestinal Clostridium perfringens colonisation and attenuates intestinal mucosal injury in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Br J Nutr.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>118</volume>:<fpage>321</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0007114517002094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28901890</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Belote</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tujimoto-Silva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hummelgen</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanches</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wammes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Histological parameters to evaluate intestinal health on broilers challenged with Eimeria and Clostridium perfringens with or without enramycin as growth promoter</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>97</volume>:<fpage>2287</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pey064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29660058</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahmood</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dietary soya saponin improves the lipid metabolism and intestinal health of laying hens</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>101</volume>:<fpage>101663</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2021.101663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35172236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8851251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shojadoost</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vince</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prescott</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The successful experimental induction of necrotic enteritis in chickens by Clostridium perfringens: a critical review</article-title>. <source>Vet Res.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>74</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1297-9716-43-74</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23101966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3546943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Puerarin enhances intestinal function in piglets infected with porcine epidemic diarrhea virus</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>6552</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-85880-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33753826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7985190</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stromberg</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Viele</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Statistics and bioinformatics in nutritional sciences: analysis of complex data in the era of systems biology</article-title>. <source>J Nutr Biochem.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>561</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>72</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jnutbio.2009.11.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20233650</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2885517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Exogenous lysozyme influences Clostridium perfringens colonization and intestinal barrier function in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Avian Pathol.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03079450903447404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20390532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leeson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caston</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Summers</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Broiler response to energy or energy and protein dilution in the finisher diet</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>1996</year>) <volume>75</volume>:<fpage>522</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps.0750522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8786943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sandvang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Skjoet-Rasmussen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cantor</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mathis</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lumpkins</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of feed supplementation with 3 different probiotic Bacillus strains and their combination on the performance of broiler chickens challenged with Clostridium perfringens</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>100982</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2021.01.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33647715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7921869</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doranalli</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rinttila</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vienola</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jurgens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Apajalahti</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of Bacillus subtilis DSM 32315 on the pathology, performance, and intestinal microbiome of broiler chickens in a necrotic enteritis challenge</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>3450</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pey500</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30452717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6698186</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Fecal Microbiota Transplantation Reshapes the Physiological Function of the Intestine in Antibiotic-Treated Specific Pathogen-Free Birds</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>884615</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2022.884615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35812374</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9261465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Regulation of the intestinal barrier by nutrients: The role of tight junctions</article-title>. <source>Anim Sci J</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>91</volume>:<fpage>e13357</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/asj.13357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32219956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7187240</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Foxo1 controls gut homeostasis and commensalism by regulating mucus secretion</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>218</volume>:<fpage>e20210324</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20210324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34287641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8424467</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Csernus</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Czegledi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Physiological, antimicrobial, intestine morphological, and immunological effects of fructooligosaccharides in pigs</article-title>. <source>ARCH ANIM BREED.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>325</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/aab-63-325-2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32964103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7500070</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez-Nogales</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Algieri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garrido-Mesa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vezza</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Utrilla</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chueca</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Differential intestinal anti-inflammatory effects of <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus fermentum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Lactobacillus salivarius</italic> in DSS mouse colitis: impact on microRNAs expression and microbiota composition</article-title>. Mol Nutr Food Res. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>1700144</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mnfr.201700144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28752563</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tomova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bukovsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rembert</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yonas</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alwarith</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnard</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The effects of vegetarian and vegan diets on gut microbiota</article-title>. <source>Front Nutr.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>47</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnut.2019.00047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31058160</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6478664</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ohno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caballero-Flores</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alteri</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lawley</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Lipopolysaccharide O structure of adherent and invasive Escherichia coli regulates intestinal inflammation via complement C3</article-title>. <source>Plos Pathog</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>e1008928</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1008928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33027280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7571687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pop</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deboy</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eckburg</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Turnbaugh</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Metagenomic analysis of the human distal gut microbiome</article-title>. <source>Science.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>312</volume>:<fpage>1355</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1124234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16741115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3027896</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghasemi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toghyani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Landy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of dietary 1 alpha-hydroxycholecalciferol in calcium and phosphorous-deficient diets on growth performance, tibia related indices and immune responses in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Anim Nutr.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>134</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aninu.2018.04.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31193890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6544576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hakami</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sulaiman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alharthi</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Casserly</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouwhuis</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abudabos</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Growth performance, carcass and meat quality, bone strength, and immune response of broilers fed low-calcium diets supplemented with marine mineral complex and phytase</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>101</volume>:<fpage>101849</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psj.2022.101849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35390569</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8987615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Interleukin-8 in the tumor immune niche: lessons from comparative oncology</article-title>. <source>Adv Exp Med Biol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>1240</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-38315-2_2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32060885</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oronsky</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oronsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knox</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>TGF-beta: a master immune regulator</article-title>. <source>Expert Opin Ther Targets.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>427</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>38</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14728222.2020.1744568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32228232</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>