<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9171430</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC9171430.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">9171430</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">9171430</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35685341</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.898121</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Fumonisin B<sub>1</sub> Induces Immunotoxicity and Apoptosis of Chicken Splenic Lymphocytes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names initials="F">Fenghua</given-names></name><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1812280/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yang</given-names></name><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1197749/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff><institution>College of Animal Science and Technology, Qingdao Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Qingdao</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Ziwei Zhang, Northeast Agricultural University, China</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Adil Mehraj Khan, Sher-e-Kashmir University of Agricultural Sciences and Technology, India; Junliang Deng, Sichuan Agricultural University, China; Zhihua Ren, Sichuan Agricultural University, China; Flavia Girolami, University of Turin, Italy</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Yang Wang <email>yangwang@qau.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Veterinary Pharmacology and Toxicology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">400313</issue-id><elocation-id>898121</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>5</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>08</day><month>06</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-14 12:25:13.297"><day>14</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2022 Zhu and Wang.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Zhu and Wang</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-09-898121.pdf"/><abstract><p>Fumonisin B<sub>1</sub> (FB<sub>1</sub>), produced by <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium</italic>, is among the most abundant and toxic mycotoxin contaminations in feed, causing damages to the health of livestock. However, the mechanisms of FB<sub>1</sub> toxicity in chickens are less understood. As splenic lymphocytes play important roles in the immune system, the aim of this study was to investigate the immunotoxic effects and mechanisms of FB<sub>1</sub> on chicken splenic lymphocytes. In the present study, the chicken primary splenic lymphocytes were harvested and treated with 0, 2.5, 5, 10, 20 and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub>. Then, the cell proliferation, damage, ultrastructure, inflammation and apoptosis were evaluated. Results showed that the proliferation rate of splenic lymphocytes was decreased by FB<sub>1</sub> treatments. The activity of lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) was increased by FB<sub>1</sub> treatments in a dose-dependent manner, implying the induction of cell damage. Consistently, the ultrastructure of splenic lymphocytes showed that FB<sub>1</sub> at all the tested concentrations caused cell structure alterations, including nuclear vacuolation, mitochondrial swelling and mitochondrial crest fracture. Besides, immunosuppressive effects of FB<sub>1</sub> were observed by the decreased concentrations of interleukin-2 (IL-2), IL-4, IL-12 and interferon-&#947; (IFN-&#947;) in the cell culture supernatant. Furthermore, apoptosis was observed in FB<sub>1</sub>-treated cells by flow cytometry. The mRNA expressions of apoptosis-related genes showed that the expression of <italic toggle="yes">Bcl-2</italic> was decreased, while the expressions of the <italic toggle="yes">P53, Bax, Bak-1</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Caspase-3</italic> were increased with FB<sub>1</sub> treatment. Similar results were found in the concentrations of apoptosis-related proteins in the cell supernatant by ELISA assay. Moreover, regression analysis indicated that increasing FB<sub>1</sub> concentration increased LDH activity, concentrations of Bax, Bak-1 and mRNA expression of <italic toggle="yes">Bak-1</italic> linearly, increased M1 area percentage quadratically, decreased concentration of IFN-&#947;, mRNA expression of <italic toggle="yes">Bcl-2</italic> linearly, and decreased concentrations of IL-2 and IL-4 quadratically. Besides, regression analysis also showed reciprocal relationships between IL-12 concentration, <italic toggle="yes">Caspase-3</italic> mRNA expression and increasing FB<sub>1</sub> concentration. The increasing FB<sub>1</sub> concentration could decrease IL-12 concentration and increase <italic toggle="yes">Caspase-3</italic> mRNA expression. Altogether, this study reported that FB<sub>1</sub> induced the immunotoxicity of chicken splenic lymphocytes and caused splenic lymphocytes apoptosis by the Bcl-2 family-mediated mitochondrial pathway of caspase activation.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>fumonisin B<sub>1</sub></kwd><kwd>chicken</kwd><kwd>splenic lymphocytes</kwd><kwd>immunotoxicity</kwd><kwd>apoptosis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001"><institution-wrap><institution>National Natural Science Foundation of China</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001809</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="5"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="45"/><page-count count="9"/><word-count count="6158"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Mycotoxin fumonisins (FBs) are the secondary metabolites produced by <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium verticillioides</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Fusarium proliferatum</italic> (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Among the fumonisin homologs, fumonisin B<sub>1</sub> (FB<sub>1</sub>) is the most prevalent and abundant mycotoxin contamination in stale corn. It is reported that FB<sub>1</sub> has great potential health hazards to humans and animals (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). FB<sub>1</sub> can lead to intestinal damage (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>), neurotoxity (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) and various cancers (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). Moreover, in chickens, FB<sub>1</sub> exposure lead to reduced performance, nutrient digestibility, immune function, and increased diarrhea as well as mortality (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>).</p><p>The underlying cellular mechanisms of FB<sub>1</sub>-induced toxicity include the induction of oxidative stress, apoptosis and immunotoxicity (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). The immunotoxicity of FB<sub>1</sub> in chickens may partially be due to the impairment of lymphatic organs and lymphocyte (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Spleen, a secondary lymphoid organ, is the main filter for blood-borne pathogens and antigens, playing an important role in maintaining immune homeostasis. Circulating T and B cells often gain access to secondary lymphoid organs to search for their cognate antigens (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Harmful substances, such as cadmium and atrazine can impair chicken spleens (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). It is also reported that exposure to FB<sub>1</sub> reduced basal rate of splenic lymphocyte proliferation in female mice (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). In chickens, although Todorova et al. showed that FB<sub>1</sub> affected the immune function by damaging the ultrastructure of splenic lymphocyte (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), the detailed immunotoxicity and molecular mechanisms is still unclear. Thus, in this study, we investigated the immunotoxicity of FB<sub>1</sub> on splenic lymphocytes by evaluating the proliferation rate, cell damage, the expressions of cytokines, and further tried to examine the potential molecular mechanisms related to apoptosis to provide reference for further research on the toxicity of FB<sub>1</sub>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Materials</title><p>FB<sub>1</sub> and RPMI 1640 medium were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, Mo, USA). Fetal bovine serum (FBS) was purchased from Sijiqing Biological Engineering Materials Co. Ltd. (Hangzhou, China). The methyl thiazolyl tetrazolium (MTT) and lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) assay kits were obtained from Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute (Nanjing, China). The chicken interleukin-2 (IL-2), IL-4, IL-6, IL-12, and interferon-&#947; (IFN-&#947;) ELISA kits were obtained from Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute (Nanjing, China). The propidium iodide (PI) apoptosis detection kit was purchased from BD Pharmingen (Lexington, KY, USA). The chicken B cell CLL/lymphoma-2 (Bc1-2), P53, Bcl-2 associated X (Bax), Bcl-2 antagonist/killer 1 (Bak-1), and cysteinyl aspartate specific proteinase-3 (Caspase-3) ELISA kits were obtained from Qiyi Biological Technology Co. Ltd. (Shanghai, China). RNA extraction kit and the SYBR PremixScript RT-PCR Kit II were purchased from Takara (Shiga, Japan). All other reagents used were of analytical grade.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell Culture and Treatment</title><p>The 40-day-old healthy male specific pathogen free (SPF) White Leghorn chickens were obtained from Shandong Academy of Agricultural Sciences for splenic lymphocytes isolation and culture. The use of animals was approved and performed in accordance with the guidelines of Ethics and Animal Welfare Committee of Qingdao Agricultural University. Chickens were given intramuscular injections of ketamine-846 anesthesia mixture (Shengda Animal Medicine Co., Ltd., Dunhua, China) prior to splenic lymphocytes harvesting. Chicken splenic lymphocytes were prepared and cultured according to previous method (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Briefly, spleen samples were removed from the chickens, washed with sterile cooled phosphate buffered saline (PBS) and ground on ice. The mixture was filtered through a 200-mesh sieve into a Petri dish to collect spleen cell suspension. The lymphocytes were collected by centrifuging at 2,000 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic> for 15 min at room temperature in Histopaque 1077 (Sigma-Aldrich, USA). Then, lymphocytes were washed twice with cooled PBS and re-suspended in RPMI-1640 medium supplemented with 10% FBS, 100 U/mL penicillin, and 100 U/mL streptomycin, and counted using a hemocytometer. Based on trypan blue dye exclusion, when the lymphocytes viability was more than 95%, the cells could be used for the experiments.</p><p>In this study, the splenic lymphocytes were treated with 0, 2.5, 5, 10, 20, and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> according to previous studies (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>), in which 2.5&#8211;50 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> suppressed the proliferation of chicken primary cells, such as splenocytes and peripheral lymphocytes. The FB<sub>1</sub> was dissolved in deionized water to obtain a 40 mg/mL concentration solution. Then, various dilutions of the 40 mg/mL FB<sub>1</sub> solution were added to cell cultures with final concentrations of 0, 2.5, 5, 10, 20 and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub>. For MTT assay, splenic lymphocytes were cultured in 96-well microplates (1&#215; 10<sup>4</sup> cells/mL) under 5% CO<sub>2</sub> at 42&#176;C, and stimulated with 10 &#956;g/mL concanavalin A (ConA) to induce cell proliferation and treated with 0, 2.5, 5, 10, 20 and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> for 72 h, with 6 parallel holes in each treatment group. For other assays, splenic lymphocytes were cultured in 24-well microplates (1&#215; 10<sup>5</sup> cells/mL) under 5% CO<sub>2</sub> at 42&#176;C, and treated with 0, 2.5, 5, 10, 20, and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> for 48 h. Four parallel holes in each treatment group were set for quantitative real-time PCR (RT-PCR) and flow cytometry, and 6 parallel holes were set in each treatment group for the measurement of proliferation rate, inflammatory cytokine levels, LDH activity and apoptosis protein concentrations.</p></sec><sec><title>MTT Assay</title><p>After 72 h treatment with ConA and FB<sub>1</sub>, 10 &#956;L MTT solution (5 mg/mL) was added in each well and then incubated for 4 h. After incubated with 100 &#956;L of DMSO, the optical density (OD) was measured at 490 nm using a microplate reader (ThermoFisher MK<sub>3</sub>, USA). Proliferation rate (%) = (OD of cells treated with FB<sub>1</sub>-OD of cells without FB<sub>1</sub> treatment)/OD of cells without FB<sub>1</sub> treatment &#215; 100%.</p></sec><sec><title>Transmission Electron Microscopy (TEM)</title><p>Cells were fixed in a fresh solution of 0.1 M sodium cacodylate buffer containing 2.5% glutaraldehyde and 2% formaldehyde followed by a 2 h fixation at 4&#176;C with 2% osmium tetroxide in 50 mM sodium cacodylate (pH 7.2). Staining was performed overnight with 0.5% aqueous uranyl acetate. Specimens were dehydrated, embedded in Epon 812 and sectioned into ultrathin slices. The sections were examined on CCD camera system (AMT Corp., USA) (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Analysis of Inflammatory Cytokines and LDH</title><p>The concentrations of inflammatory cytokines, including IL-2, IL-4, IL-6, IL-12, IFN-&#947; and the activity of LDH were determined spectrophotometrically using commercial kits (Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute, China) according to manufacturer's protocol.</p></sec><sec><title>Apoptosis Assay by PI Staining</title><p>After adding pancreatin (HyClone, USA), the cells were harvested by centrifuging at 1,000 <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>. The cell pellet was fixed in 1.5 mL cold 75% ethanol at 4&#176;C for 8 h. Then, cells were centrifuged, washed in 1 mL PBS and re-suspended in 0.5 mL PBS. To a 0.5 mL cell sample, 0.5 mL RNase A (Sigma-Aldrich, USA) was added, followed by mixing by 1 mL PI (Sigma-Aldrich, USA) solution. The mixed cells were incubated in the dark at room temperature for 30 min and kept at 4&#176;C in the dark until measured. The PI fluorescence was measured using a FC500 flow cytometer (Beckman Coulter, Fullerton, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>RNA Extraction and RT-PCR</title><p>Total RNA extraction and reverse transcription were performed according to Mao et al. (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Primer and Oligo softwares were used for PCR primer sequences (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) design. RT-PCR was performed using Premix Ex TaqTM with SYBR Green (TaKaRa, Dalian, China) and ABI Stepone Real-Time PCR System 7500 Fast Real-Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, CA, USA). The thermocycle protocol was 30-s at 95&#176;C followed by 40 cycles of 5-s denaturation at 95&#176;C, 34-s annealing/extension at 60&#176;C, and then a final melting curve analysis to monitor purity of the PCR product. The mRNA abundances of <italic toggle="yes">Bcl-2, Bax, Bak-1, P53</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Caspase-3</italic> were determined by 2<sup>&#8722;&#916;&#916;Cq</sup> method. Relative gene expression concentrations were normalized by eukaryotic reference gene <italic toggle="yes">GAPDH</italic>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>RT-PCR primer sequences and products.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Gene</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Primer sequences (5<sup>&#8242;</sup> &#8594; 3<sup>&#8242;</sup>)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Product size (bp)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>GeneBank accession No</bold>.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">GAPDH</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCCTGGTATGACAATGAGTTTGGA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_204305">NM_204305</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGGGAGACAGAAGGGAACAGA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bcl-2</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCGTCGCCTTCTTCGAGTT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="Z11961.1">Z11961.1</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATCCCATCCTCCGTTGTCCT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bax</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTGATGGCATGGGACATAGCTC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="XM_422067.2">XM_422067.2</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGGCGTAGACCTTGCGGATAA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bak-1</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATGGATGCCTGTCTGTCCTGTTC</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_001030920.1">NM_001030920.1</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCAGAGCAGTCCAAAGACACTGA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">P53</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GAGATGCTGAAGGAGATCAATGAG</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="X13057.1">X13057.1</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GTGGTCAGTCCGAGCCTTTT</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Caspase-3</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACTCTGGAATTCTGCCTGATGACA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="NM_204725.1">NM_204725.1</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CATCTGCATCCGTGCCTGA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Analysis of Apoptosis-Related Proteins by ELISA</title><p>The concentrations of Bcl-2, Bax, Bak-1, P53 and Caspase-3 in the cell culture supernatant were measured by ELISA kits according to the manufacture instructions (Qiyi Biological Technology Co. Ltd., Shanghai, China). Briefly, standard solutions were prepared. Then, the specimens were thawed at room temperature and 50 &#956;L aliquots were added to the wells covered with a layer of monoclonal antibody, then incubated at 37&#176;C for 30 min together with the standard solutions. Subsequently, the wells were washed and 50 &#956;L of conjugate reagent was added. The wells were further incubated at 37&#176;C for 30 min at the end of which the wells were washed and 100 &#956;L of streptavidin&#8211;horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-tagged antibodies were added. The wells were incubated at 37&#176;C for 30 min. Following another round of washing, 100 &#956;L of tetramethylbenzidine was added to the wells. The wells were incubated at room temperature for 30 min in the dark. The reaction was stopped by adding 50 &#956;L stop solution to the wells. The absorbances of the solutions in the wells were measured by a spectrophotometer at 450 nm. A standard curve was plotted from the absorbance values of the standard solutions and the protein concentrations of the samples were calculated from the standard curve.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>One-way ANOVA was performed with the GLM procedure by SAS (SAS Institute Inc, USA, version 9.3), and multiple comparisons were performed with Duncan's test. Results were presented as the means &#177; standard deviation (SD). The Reg procedure of SAS (SAS Institute Inc, USA, version 9.3) was used for performing the regression of increasing FB<sub>1</sub> concentration on the measurements. One-dimensional linear equation, one-dimensional quadratic equation, and reciprocal equation were fit. The significant one with the largest <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sup>2</sup> was selected as the most appropriate equation. The differences were considered significant at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Effects of Different Concentrations of FB<sub>1</sub> on the Splenic Lymphocytes Proliferation Rate</title><p>According to <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, compared to the FB<sub>1</sub>-non-treated cells, the lymphocytes proliferation rate was significantly decreased by FB<sub>1</sub> at 2.5, 5, 10, 20 and 40 &#956;g/mL (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Moreover, compared to cells treated with 2.5 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub>, cells treated with 10 and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> had much lower lymphocytes proliferation rate (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Effects of different concentrations of FB<sub>1</sub> on the proliferation rate of splenic lymphocytes. Data are presented as the means &#177; SD for <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6. End-point means without a common letter are significantly different (a, b, or c, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-898121-g0001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Effects of Different Concentrations of FB<sub>1</sub> on the Activity of LDH</title><p>As for the LDH, we found that 2.5, 5, 10, 20, and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> significantly increased the LDH activity (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) in a dose-dependent manner, although there was no significant difference between the 10 and 20 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> treatment groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05) (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Effects of different concentrations of FB<sub>1</sub> on the LDH activity in the culture supernatant of splenic lymphocytes. Data are presented as the means &#177; SD for <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 6. End-point means without a common letter are significantly different (a, b, c, d, or e, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-898121-g0002.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Effects of Different Concentrations of FB<sub>1</sub> on the Ultrastructure of Splenic Lymphocytes</title><p>TEM results indicated that the non-treated cells had intact cell membrane and nucleus envelope. Moreover, mitochondria also had intact structure and were not swollen. However, 2.5, 5, 10, 20, and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> caused cell structure damage, including nuclear vacuolation, mitochondrial swelling and mitochondrial crest fracture (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Ultrastructure of splenic lymphocytes by TEM. Green arrows indicate the mitochondrial swelling and mitochondrial crest fracture. Red arrows indicate nuclear vacuolation.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-898121-g0003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Effects of Different Concentrations of FB<sub>1</sub> on the Concentrations of Inflammatory Cytokines</title><p>With the treatments of different concentrations of FB<sub>1</sub>, the concentration of IL-2 was significantly decreased compared to the non-treated group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Moreover, a dose-dependent effects of FB<sub>1</sub> were observed for the reduction of IL-2 concentration. In addition, 5, 10, 20, and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> also significantly down-regulated the concentration of IL-4 in a dose-dependent manner compared to the non-treated and 2.5 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub>-treated cells (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Furthermore, the concentration of IL-12 was also significantly reduced by 5, 10, 20, and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Compared to 5 and 10 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub>, 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> treatment led to a much lower IL-12 concentration (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Besides, the concentration of IFN-&#947; was significantly reduced by the FB<sub>1</sub> at all the tested concentrations (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> induced the lowest IFN-&#947; concentration compared to that of other FB<sub>1</sub> treatments (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). However, the concentration of IL-6 was not significantly affected by the treatments of FB<sub>1</sub> (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05) (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effects of different concentrations of FB<sub>1</sub> on the inflammatory cytokines.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>FB<sub><bold>1</bold></sub> concentrations (&#956;g/mL)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>IL-2 (ng/L)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>IL-4 (ng/L)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>IL-6 (ng/L)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>IL-12 (ng/L)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>IFN-&#947; (ng/L)</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.12 &#177; 2.13<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123.37 &#177; 14.24<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.35 &#177; 1.63</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140.24 &#177; 37.59<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.73 &#177; 2.84<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.25 &#177; 0.64<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116.77 &#177; 2.20<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.02 &#177; 4.39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123.52 &#177; 20.52<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.48 &#177; 7.15<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.04 &#177; 4.62<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105.31 &#177; 3.59<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.30 &#177; 5.58</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.17 &#177; 8.43<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.35 &#177; 3.13<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.96 &#177; 10.16<sup>d</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.91 &#177; 4.21<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.58 &#177; 2.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.10 &#177; 6.61<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.67 &#177; 2.05<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.76 &#177; 5.12<sup>e</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.60 &#177; 4.12<sup>d</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.23 &#177; 5.73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.39 &#177; 3.01<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.66 &#177; 5.30<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.54 &#177; 0.82<sup>e</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.47 &#177; 2.83<sup>e</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.02 &#177; 1.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.01 &#177; 2.43<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.05 &#177; 2.44<sup>c</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">Data are presented as the means &#177; SD for n = 6</italic>.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">a, b, c, d, e Mean value within a row with no common superscript differ significantly (P &lt; 0.05)</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Effects of Different Concentrations of FB<sub>1</sub> on the Apoptosis of Splenic Lymphocytes</title><p>Apoptotic cells were quantified by flow cytometry analysis. Early apoptotic cells appear in the cell cycle distribution as cells with a hypodiploid DNA. This alteration in DNA content results from degradation of cellular DNA by activation of endogenous endonucleases during apoptosis (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Thus, cells in the pre-G0/G1 phase (M1) were therefore defined as apoptotic cells (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). Results showed that the percentages of cells in M1 area of all the FB<sub>1</sub> treatment groups were significantly increased compared to the non-treated ones (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Moreover, compared to the 2.5 and 5 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> treatments, 10, 20, and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> treatments significantly increased the percentages of cells in M1 (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Effects of different concentrations of FB<sub>1</sub> on the apoptosis of splenic lymphocytes. <bold>(A)</bold> Cell apoptosis was analyzed by flow cytometry. M1 gate indicates the pre-G0/G1 (apoptotic) population, M2 gate indicates the G0/G1 phase, M3 gate indicates the S phase and M4 gate indicates the G2/M phase. <bold>(B)</bold> Percentage of cells in M1 gate. Data are presented as the means &#177; SD for <italic toggle="yes">n</italic> = 4. End-point means without a common letter are significantly different (a, b, or c, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-898121-g0004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Effects of Different Concentrations of FB<sub>1</sub> on the mRNA Expressions of Apoptosis-Related Genes</title><p>The expression of <italic toggle="yes">Bcl-2</italic> was significantly down-regulated by 5, 20, and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> compared to the cells treated with 0, 2.5 and 10 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). And 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> led to the lowest <italic toggle="yes">Bcl-2</italic> mRNA expression (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). The expression of <italic toggle="yes">P53</italic> was only up-regulated in the 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> treatment group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Besides, the expression of <italic toggle="yes">Bax</italic> was significantly up-regulated by 10 and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> compared to other groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). In addition, 10, 20 and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> significantly elevated the expression of <italic toggle="yes">Bak-1</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). And 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> induced the highest expression of <italic toggle="yes">Bak-1</italic> among groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Furthermore, 10 and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> significantly up-regulated the <italic toggle="yes">Caspase-3</italic> expression compared to the non-treated cells (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Effects of different concentrations of FB<sub>1</sub> on the relative expression of apoptosis-related genes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>FB<sub><bold>1</bold></sub> concentrations (&#956;g/mL)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Bcl-2</italic>
</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">P53</italic>
</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Bax</italic>
</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Bak-1</italic>
</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Caspase-3</italic>
</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 &#177; 0.06<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 &#177; 0.12<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 &#177; 0.03<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 &#177; 0.08<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 &#177; 0.18<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96 &#177; 0.04<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 &#177; 0.11<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98 &#177; 0.04<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 &#177; 0.12<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 &#177; 0.31<sup>ab</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 &#177; 0.07<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 &#177; 0.10<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 &#177; 0.04<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27 &#177; 0.18<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36 &#177; 0.29<sup>ab</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 &#177; 0.09<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 &#177; 0.08<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 &#177; 0.07<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 &#177; 0.22<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65 &#177; 0.21<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 &#177; 0.10<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 &#177; 0.02<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 &#177; 0.02<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 &#177; 0.03<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52 &#177; 0.45<sup>ab</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 &#177; 0.02<sup>d</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24 &#177; 0.13<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 &#177; 0.04<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54 &#177; 0.10<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70 &#177; 0.57<sup>a</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">Data are presented as the means &#177; SD for n = 4. mRNA expression was standardized to GAPDH expression</italic>.</p><p><italic toggle="yes"><sup>a, b, c</sup>Mean value within a row with no common superscript differ significantly (P &lt; 0.05)</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Effects of Different Concentrations of FB<sub>1</sub> on the Concentrations of Apoptosis-Related Proteins</title><p>ELISA results showed that the concentration of Bcl-2 in the cell supernatant was significantly decreased in 5 and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> treatment groups compared to the non-treated group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). But there was no significant difference for the Bcl-2 concentration among cells treated with FB<sub>1</sub> (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &gt; 0.05). Moreover, the concentration of P53 was significantly elevated by FB<sub>1</sub> at all the tested concentrations compared to the non-treated group (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), in addition, P53 concentration was much higher in 20 and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub>-treated groups than that of the 2.5 and 5 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub>-treated groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). FB<sub>1</sub> at all the tested concentrations also significantly increased the Bax concentration (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05), and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> induced the highest Bax concentration among the groups. Besides, the Bak-1 concentration in the 20 and 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub>-treated groups was much higher than that of the other groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05). Furthermore, 40 &#956;g/mL FB<sub>1</sub> significantly increased Caspase-3 concentration compared to other groups (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; 0.05) (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Effects of different concentrations of FB<sub>1</sub> on the apoptosis-related proteins.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>FB<sub><bold>1</bold></sub> concentrations (&#956;g/mL)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Bcl-2 (&#956;g/mL)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>P53 (&#956;g/mL)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Bax (&#956;g/mL)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Bak-1 (&#956;g/mL)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Caspase-3 (&#956;g/mL)</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50 &#177; 0.13<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">281.75 &#177; 10.68<sup>c</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.45 &#177; 0.17<sup>e</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.07 &#177; 1.19<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58 &#177; 0.15<sup>bc</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.39 &#177; 0.04<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">336.34 &#177; 29.56<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.74 &#177; 0.19<sup>d</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.98 &#177; 0.98<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70 &#177; 0.14<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.21 &#177; 0.23<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">379.58 &#177; 28.42<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.91 &#177; 0.14<sup>cd</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.29 &#177; 1.09<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51 &#177; 0.12<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35 &#177; 0.09<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">340.76 &#177; 30.42<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.23 &#177; 0.20<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.55 &#177; 0.96<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.72 &#177; 0.14<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35 &#177; 0.22<sup>ab</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">469.84 &#177; 17.63<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.11 &#177; 0.19<sup>bc</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.48 &#177; 0.40<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48 &#177; 0.05<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.16 &#177; 0.23<sup>b</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">445.86 &#177; 55.15<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.12 &#177; 0.29<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.52 &#177; 1.57<sup>a</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.94 &#177; 0.13<sup>a</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">Data are presented as the means &#177; SD for n = 6</italic>.</p><p><italic toggle="yes"><sup>a, b, c, d</sup>Mean value within a row with no common superscript differ significantly (P &lt; 0.05)</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Regression Analysis</title><p>Regression equations are presented in <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>. Results indicated that increasing FB<sub>1</sub> concentration increased the activity of LDH, the concentrations of Bax, Bak-1 and mRNA expression of <italic toggle="yes">Bak-1</italic> linearly, increased percentage of M1 area quadratically, decreased concentration of IFN-&#947;, mRNA expression of <italic toggle="yes">Bcl-2</italic> linearly, and decreased concentrations of IL-2 and IL-4 quadratically. Rregression analysis also showed reciprocal relationship between IL-12 concentration, <italic toggle="yes">Caspase-3</italic> mRNA expression and increasing FB<sub>1</sub> concentration. The increasing FB<sub>1</sub> concentration could decrease IL-12 concentration and increase <italic toggle="yes">Caspase-3</italic> expression. Proliferation rate tended to decrease with increasing FB<sub>1</sub> concentration (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.06).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Regression equations for FB<sub>1</sub> concentrations as a function for biochemical indices of splenic lymphocytes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Biochemical indices</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Equation</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">R</italic>
<sup>2</sup>
</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic toggle="yes">P-</italic>value</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proliferation Rate (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y = 50.47/x + 42.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL-2 (ng/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y = 0.10x<sup>2</sup>-5.71x + 108.49</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL-4 (ng/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y = 0.04x<sup>2</sup>-2.87x + 121.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IL-12 (ng/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y = 143.20/x + 66.84</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">INF-&#947; (ng/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y = &#8722;0.27x + 76.64</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LDH (U/L)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y = 0.94x + 57.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M1 (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y = &#8722;0.03x<sup>2</sup> + 1.50x + 20.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bax (&#956;g/mL)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y = 0.03x + 3.71</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bak-1 (&#956;g/mL)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y = 0.10x + 13.96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bcl-2</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y = &#8722;0.01x + 0.96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Bak-1</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y = 0.01x + 1.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Caspase-3</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y = &#8722;1.37/x + 1.70</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Fusarium mycotoxins such as FB<sub>1</sub> are the major contaminants in
animal feed and induce subclinical symptoms. The spleen of birds is a central immune organ for the proliferation of T and B cells.</p><p>In the present study, we aimed to determine the toxic effects and mechanisms of FB<sub>1</sub> on splenic lymphocytes. We found the proliferation rate of splenic lymphocytes was significantly decreased by treatments of FB<sub>1</sub> at 2.5, 5, 10, 20, and 40 &#956;g/mL. Similarly, Johnson and Sharma also reported that FB<sub>1</sub> exposure was able to reduce the lymphocyte proliferation (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). LDH, a key feature of cells undergoing cellular damage, is a stable cytoplasmic enzyme that is found in all cells (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). In the present study, FB<sub>1</sub> significantly increased the LDH activity in a dose-dependent manner. Regression</p><p>analysis also showed that the LDH activity was increased by increasing FB<sub>1</sub> concentrations. Consistent with this result, the ultrastructure of FB<sub>1</sub>-treated lymphocytes indicated cell impairments, including the mitochondrial swelling, mitochondrial crest fracture and nuclear vacuolation. Cell ultrastructure changes were also observed in a study by Todorova et al. (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). According to this study, the splenic lymphatic nodules were with pale centers, reduced cell number and contained large undifferentiated lymphoblasts or cells with pycnotic nuclei in chickens consuming FB<sub>1</sub> and deoxynivalenol.</p><p>The immunotoxicity of FB<sub>1</sub> has been associated with decreased immune responses (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Here, the concentrations of IL-2, IL-4, IL-12, and IFN-&#947; in the cell culture supernatant were decreased by FB<sub>1</sub> treatments, and the reductions of IL-2 and IL-4 were in a dose-dependent manner. However, the concentration of IL-6 was not significantly changed by FB<sub>1</sub>. Regression analysis further demonstrated that the concentrations of IL-2, IL-4, IL-12, and IFN-&#947; were reduced by increasing FB<sub>1</sub> concentrations. Studies demonstrated that splenocytes from female mice exposed to FB<sub>1</sub> had a reduced expression of <italic toggle="yes">IL-2</italic> mRNA (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> treatment of swine lymphocytes with FB<sub>1</sub> significantly decreased IL-4 production (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). Moreover, the secretions of IL-12 induced by LPS exposure of murine bone marrow-derived dendritic cells were suppressed by FB<sub>1</sub> in a dose dependent manner (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). The mRNA concentration of <italic toggle="yes">IFN-</italic>&#947; in macrophages was also reduced by supplementation of FB<sub>1</sub> in chickens (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Similar with our results, Bhandari et al. reported that the IL-6 concentration in the spleen of FB<sub>1</sub>-treated mice was not significantly altered (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Unfortunately, no other studies have shown related data on splenic lymphocytes to serve for comparison with our results.</p><p>The decrease of cell proliferation might not only be associated with the FB<sub>1</sub> direct cytotoxicity effects but also be due to apoptosis of lymphocytes (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Therefore, the pro-apoptotic role of FB<sub>1</sub> in splenic lymphocytes was further investigated. Previously, studies indicated that FB<sub>1</sub> induced apoptosis of porcine kidney cells (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>), human gastric epithelial cells (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>) and turkey peripheral blood lymphocytes (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Currently, we also observed splenic lymphocytes apoptosis with FB<sub>1</sub> treatment. Two major apoptotic pathways have been identified: (i) the extrinsic pathway, in which activation of a death receptor by a ligand leads to the activation of initiator Caspase-8; and (ii) the intrinsic pathway, which is caused by cellular stress and cytochrome c release from mitochondria, leading to Caspase-9 activation (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). Once active, Caspase-9 directly cleave and activate Caspase-3 (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). The apoptotic processes that occur before cytochrome c release require a variety of effector molecules, including Bcl-2 family proteins (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). The Bcl-2 family is composed of two subfamilies: one consisting of anti-apoptotic proteins (e.g., Bcl-2, Bcl-XL, Bcl-w, etc.) and the other of pro-apoptotic proteins (e.g., Bax, Bak, Bcl-XS, etc.) (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). In the current study, results of RT-PCR and ELISA demonstrated that the expression of Bcl-2 was decreased, while the expressions of the P53, Bax, Bak-1 and Caspase-3, which can promote apoptosis, were increased with FB<sub>1</sub> treatment. Regression analysis suggested that the M1 area percentage, concentrations of Bax, Bak-1 and mRNA expressions of <italic toggle="yes">Bak-1</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Caspase-3</italic> were increased, while the <italic toggle="yes">Bcl-2</italic> mRNA expression was reduced by increasing FB<sub>1</sub> concentrations. These results indicated that FB<sub>1</sub> can induce splenic lymphocytes apoptosis by the Bcl-2 family-mediated mitochondrial pathway.</p><p>In conclusion, data in this study imply that FB<sub>1</sub> strongly suppressed the chicken splenic lymphocytes proliferation and caused cell damage, especially the impairment of structure of mitochondria. The immunosuppressive effect of FB<sub>1</sub> was also found by the decreased concentrations of inflammatory cytokines. Moreover, FB<sub>1</sub> induced splenic lymphocytes apoptosis through the Bcl-2 family-mediated mitochondrial pathway of caspase activation. Overall, our data provide new evidence for the toxic effects and mechanisms of FB<sub>1</sub> on chicken and provide new targets for regulating the FB<sub>1</sub>-related subclinical symptoms with possible unfavorable economic outcome.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s5"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/supplementary material, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author/s.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The animal study was reviewed and approved by Ethics and Animal Welfare Committee of Qingdao Agricultural University.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>FZ designed the study. YW analyzed data and wrote the manuscript. FZ and YW performed the research and contributed to revision of the manuscript. Both authors read and approved the final manuscript, contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="s8"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the Public Sector Science and Technology Support Program of Qingdao (Grant No. 12-1-3-32-nsh), the National Modern Agricultural Industry Technology System Project of Shandong Province (SDAIT-11-07), National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant No. 32102586), the Shandong Provincial Natural Science Foundation (Grant No. ZR2020QC183), and the Talents of High Concentration Scientific Research Foundation of Qingdao Agricultural University (Grant No. 663/1119042).</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s9"><title>Publisher's Note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lumsangkul</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Developmental toxicity of mycotoxin fumonisin B1 in animal embryogenesis: an overview</article-title>. <source>Toxins.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>114</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins11020114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30781891</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6410136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schelstraete</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Devreese</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Croubels</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative toxicokinetics of Fusarium mycotoxins in pigs and humans</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>137</volume>:<fpage>111140</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2020.111140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32004578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ochieng</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scippo</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kemboi</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Croubels</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Okoth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang'ethe</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mycotoxins in poultry feed and feed ingredients from sub-Saharan Africa and their impact on the production of broiler and layer chickens: a review</article-title>. <source>Toxins</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>633</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins13090633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34564637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8473361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oswald</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desautels</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Laffitte</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fournout</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Odin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mycotoxin fumonisin B1 increases intestinal colonization by pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> in pigs</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>5870</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.69.10.5870-5874.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14532038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC201177</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouhet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hourcade</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Loiseau</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fikry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roselli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The mycotoxin fumonisin B1 alters the proliferation and the barrier function of porcine intestinal epithelial cells</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Sci.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/toxsci/kfh006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14600282</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uetsuka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanisms of mycotoxin-induced neurotoxicity through oxidative stress-associated pathways</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>5213</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>37</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms12085213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21954354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3179161</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Domijan</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fumonisin B(1): a neurotoxic mycotoxin</article-title>. <source>Arh Hig Rada Toksikol.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>531</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2478/10004-1254-63-2012-2239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23334049</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The fumonisin B1 content in corn from North China, a high-risk area of esophageal cancer</article-title>. <source>J Environ Pathol Toxicol Oncol.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>139</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/article/med/10905519" ext-link-type="uri">https://europepmc.org/article/med/10905519</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10905519</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alizadeh</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rohandel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roudbarmohammadi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roudbary</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sohanaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghiasian</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Fumonisin B1 contamination of cereals and risk of esophageal cancer in a high risk area in northeastern Iran</article-title>. <source>Asian Pac J Cancer Prev.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>2625</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7314/APJCP.2012.13.6.2625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22938431</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#252;ller</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dekant</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mally</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fumonisin B1 and the kidney: modes of action for renal tumor formation by fumonisin B1 in rodents</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>50</volume>:<fpage>3833</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2012.06.053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22771819</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sobrane Filho</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Junqueira</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Laurentiz</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>Filardi</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>da Silva Rubio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of mycotoxin adsorbents in aflatoxin B 1-and fumonisin B 1-contaminated broiler diet on performance and blood metabolite</article-title>. <source>R Bras Zootec.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>250</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>256</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1806-92902016000500007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wyatt</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fletchert</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The toxicity of purified fumonisin B1 in broiler chicks</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci</source>. (<year>2000</year>) <volume>79</volume>:<fpage>1378</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ps/79.10.1378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11055840</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grenier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dohnal</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shanmugasundaram</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eicher</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Selvaraj</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schatzmayr</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Susceptibility of broiler chickens to coccidiosis when fed subclinical doses of deoxynivalenol and fumonisins&#8212;special emphasis on the immunological response and the mycotoxin interaction</article-title>. <source>Toxins</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>231</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins8080231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27472362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4999847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doupovec</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schatzmayr</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murugesan</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bortoluzzi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Villegas</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of deoxynivalenol, fumonisins, and their combination on performance, nutrient, and energy digestibility in broiler chickens</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>272</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pez484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32416811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7587770</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stockmann-Juvala</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Savolainen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A review of the toxic effects and mechanisms of action of fumonisin B1</article-title>. <source>Hum. Exp. Toxicol.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>799</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>809</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0960327108099525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19244287</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhatti</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saleemi</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saqib</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>ul-Hassan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Protective role of bentonite against aflatoxin B1- and ochratoxin A-induced immunotoxicity in broilers</article-title>. <source>J Immunotoxicol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>66</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1547691X.2016.1264503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28094577</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mwanza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kametler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dutton</surname><given-names>KMF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The cytotoxic effect of fumonisin B1 and ochratoxin A on human and pig lymphocytes using the Methyl Thiazol Tetrazolium (MTT) assay</article-title>. <source>Mycotoxin Res.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>233</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12550-009-0033-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23605153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Todorova</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kril</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dimitrov</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardeva</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toshkova</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tasheva</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of fumonisin B1 on lymphatic organs in broiler chickens-pathomorphology</article-title>. <source>Bull Vet Inst Pulawy.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>801</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2376/0005-9366-124-83</pub-id>1627116</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bronte</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pittet</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The spleen in local and systemic regulation of immunity</article-title>. <source>Immunity.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>806</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>918</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2013.10.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24238338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3912742</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of atrazine and chlorpyrifos on oxidative stress-induced autophagy in the immune organs of common carp (Cyprinus carpio L</article-title>.). <source>Fish Shellfish Immun.</source> (<year>2015</year>). <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fsi.2015.01.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25652291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamid</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cadmium induces BNIP3- dependent autophagy in chicken spleen by modulating miR-33-AMPK axis</article-title>. <source>Chemosphere.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>194</volume>:<fpage>396</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>402</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2017.12.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29223809</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Gender-dependent immunosuppression following subacute exposure to fumonisin B1</article-title>. <source>Int Immunopharmacol.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>2023</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1567-5769(01)00131-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11606033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Protective effects of selenium against zearalenone-induced apoptosis in chicken spleen lymphocyte via an endoplasmic reticulum stress signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>Cell Stress Chaperon.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>77</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>89</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12192-018-0943-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30374880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6363622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vesonder</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comparative cytotoxicity of fumonisin B1 and moniliformin in chicken primary cell cultures</article-title>. <source>Mycopathologia.</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>132</volume>:<fpage>111</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01103783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8819833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ledoux</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bermudez</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fritsche</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rottinghaus</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of fumonisin B1 on selected immune responses in broiler chicks</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>78</volume>:<fpage>1275</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ps/78.9.1275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10515357</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keck</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bodine</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The effects of fumonisin B1 on viability and mitogenic response of avian immune cells</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>85</volume>:<fpage>1020</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ps/85.6.1020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16776470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hackenberg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friehs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Froelich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ginzkey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koehler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Nanosized titanium dioxide particles do not induce DNA damage in human peripheral blood lymphocytes</article-title>. <source>Environ Mol Mutagen.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>264</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/em.20615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20740634</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Glycyrrhizic acid promotes M1 macrophage polarization in murine bone marrow-derived macrophages associated with the activation of JNK and NF-kappaB</article-title>. <source>Mediators Inflamm.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>2015</volume>:<fpage>372931</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2015/372931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26664149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4668314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>KZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelsey</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Newland</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mantsch</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Quantitative determination of apoptosis on leukemia cells by infrared spectroscopy</article-title>. <source>Apoptosis.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>269</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>78</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1011383408381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11445669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagarajan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uchil</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of cell viability by the lactate dehydrogenase assay</article-title>. <source>Cold Spring Harb Protoc.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>2018</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/pdb.prot095497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29858337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Todorova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dimitrov</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Toshkova</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lazaroza</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gardeva</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yossifova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of fumonisin B1 and deoxynivalenol on the immune system of chickens after application in quantities, naturally presented in fodders</article-title>. <source>Medecine.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>67</volume>:<fpage>139</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. Available online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/281775009" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/281775009</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ledoux</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bermudez</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fritsche</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rottinghaus</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The individual and combined effects of fumonisin B1 and moniliformin on performance and selected immune parameters in turkey poults</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>79</volume>:<fpage>871</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ps/79.6.871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10875770</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taranu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marin</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouhet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pascale</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bailly</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mycotoxin fumonisin B1 alters the cytokine profile and decreases the vaccinal antibody titer in pigs</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Sci.</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>84</volume>:<fpage>301</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/toxsci/kfi086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15659571</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The immunosuppressive characteristics of FB1 by inhibition of maturation and function of BMDCs</article-title>. <source>Int Immunopharmacol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>206</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.intimp.2017.03.031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28432936</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of fumonisins on macrophage immune functions and gene expression of cytokines in broilers</article-title>. <source>Arch Anim Nutr.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>60</volume>:<fpage>267</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>76</lpage>. di: 10.1080/17450390600785079 <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17450390600785079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16921924</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bhandari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fumonisin B1-induced localized activation of cytokine network in mouse liver</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>1483</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0278-6915(02)00075-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12387313</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ciacci-Zanella</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Analysis of fumonisin B1-induced apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Environ Health Perspect.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>109</volume>(<issue>Suppl. 2</issue>):<fpage>315</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/ehp.01109s2315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11359701</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1240681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Transcriptome study reveals apoptosis of porcine kidney cells induced by fumonisin B1 via TNF signalling pathway</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>139</volume>:<fpage>111274</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2020.111274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32198028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Involvement of PERK-CHOP pathway in fumonisin B1-induced cytotoxicity in human gastric epithelial cells</article-title>. <source>Food Chem Toxicol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>136</volume>:<fpage>111080</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fct.2019.111080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31891755</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dombrink-Kurtzman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fumonisin and beauvericin induce apoptosis in turkey peripheral blood lymphocytes</article-title>. <source>Mycopathologia.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>156</volume>:<fpage>357</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:MYCO.0000003607.69016.d2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14682463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuchsluger</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jurkunas</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kazlauskas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dana</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Corneal endothelial cells are protected from apoptosis by gene therapy</article-title>. <source>Hum Gene Ther.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>549</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>58</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/hum.2010.079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21158568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3081440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brentnall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez-Menocal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Guevara</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cepero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boise</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Caspase-9, caspase-3 and caspase-7 have distinct roles during intrinsic apoptosis</article-title>. <source>BMC Cell Biol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>32</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2121-14-32</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23834359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3710246</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Scorrano</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Korsmeyer</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanisms of cytochrome c release by proapoptotic BCL-2 family members</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>304</volume>:<fpage>437</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-291X(03)00615-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12729577</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burlacu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Regulation of apoptosis by Bcl-2 family proteins</article-title>. <source>J Cell MolMed.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>249</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>57</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1582-4934.2003.tb00225.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14594549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6741335</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Study of anti-tumor and immunomodulatory activities of two annonaceous acetogenins: microcarpacin A and microcarpacin B</article-title>. [dissertation/doctoral thesis]. <publisher-loc>Hong Kong</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Chinese University of Hong Kong</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>