<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9880493</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC9880493.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">9880493</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">9880493</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36713863</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.1057977</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Diversity of RNA viruses of three dominant tick species in North China</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Qin</surname><given-names initials="T">Tong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names initials="M">Mingjie</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2049236/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names initials="M">Meina</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="Z">Zhitong</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names initials="H">Hao</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2015640/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>State Key Laboratory of Pathogen and Biosecurity, Beijing Institute of Microbiology and Epidemiology, Academy of Military Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Medical Corps, Naval Logistics Academy, PLA</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Daniel Oladimeji Oluwayelu, University of Ibadan, Nigeria</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Shahid Karim, University of Southern Mississippi, United States; Junzheng Du, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences (CAAS), China</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Yi Sun &#9993; <email>378176938@qq.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Veterinary Infectious Diseases, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">400313</issue-id><elocation-id>1057977</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>28</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-11-01 13:25:15.797"><day>01</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 Qin, Shi, Zhang, Liu, Feng and Sun.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Qin, Shi, Zhang, Liu, Feng and Sun</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-09-1057977.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>A wide range of bacterial pathogens have been identified in ticks, yet the diversity of viruses in ticks is largely unexplored.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Here, we used metagenomic sequencing to characterize the diverse viromes in three principal tick species associated with pathogens, <italic toggle="yes">Haemaphysalis concinna, Dermacentor silvarum</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes persulcatus</italic>, in North China.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>A total of 28 RNA viruses were identified and belonged to more than 12 viral families, including single-stranded positive-sense RNA viruses (<italic toggle="yes">Flaviviridae, Picornaviridae, Luteoviridae, Solemoviridae</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Tetraviridae</italic>), negative-sense RNA viruses (<italic toggle="yes">Mononegavirales, Bunyavirales</italic>, and others) and double-stranded RNA viruses (<italic toggle="yes">Totiviridae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Partitiviridae</italic>). Of these, Dermacentor pestivirus-likevirus, Chimay-like rhabdovirus, taiga tick nigecruvirus, and Mukawa virus are presented as novel viral species, while Nuomin virus, Scapularis ixovirus, Sara tick-borne phlebovirus, Tacheng uukuvirus, and Beiji orthonairovirus had been established as human pathogens with undetermined natural circulation and pathogenicity. Other viruses include Norway mononegavirus 1, Jilin partitivirus, tick-borne tetravirus, Pico-like virus, Luteo-like virus 2, Luteo-likevirus 3, Vovk virus, Levivirus, Toti-like virus, and Solemo-like virus as well as others with unknown pathogenicity to humans and wild animals.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, extensive virus diversity frequently occurs in <italic toggle="yes">Mononegavirales</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bunyavirales</italic> among the three tick species. Comparatively, <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> ticks had been demonstrated as such a kind of host with a significantly higher diversity of viral species than those of <italic toggle="yes">H. concinna</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> ticks. Our analysis supported that ticks are reservoirs for a wide range of viruses and suggested that the discovery and characterization of tick-borne viruses would have implications for viral taxonomy and provide insights into tick-transmitted viral zoonotic diseases.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>virome</kwd><kwd>diversity</kwd><kwd>high-throughput sequencing</kwd><kwd>Ixodidae</kwd><kwd>China</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by the National Key Program for Research and Development (2022YFC2305001), the Science &amp; Technology Fundamental Resource Investigation Program (2022FY100902), and the State Key Program of Infectious Diseases of China (2017ZX10303404).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="67"/><page-count count="16"/><word-count count="9359"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Ticks (Arachnida: Ixodida) are common hematophagous arthropods that have been implicated as vectors of human and animal diseases worldwide (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Approximately 900 species of ticks have been described and taxonomically classified into four families <italic toggle="yes">Argasidae</italic> (soft ticks), <italic toggle="yes">Ixodidae</italic> (hard ticks), <italic toggle="yes">Nuttalliae</italic>, and the newly proposed <italic toggle="yes">Deinotheriidae</italic> (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Their propensity for feeding on multiple hosts, expansive range, and long life cycle underlines the importance of active surveillance of ticks for the presence of potential pathogens threatening both human and animal health (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Argasid and ixodid ticks combined transmit a greater diversity of viral, bacterial, and protozoan pathogens than any other arthropod vectors (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). The increasing incidence of tick-borne disease worldwide is caused partly by the increased frequency of human exposure to ticks or their endemic habitats, burgeoning tick populations, and the discoveries of new tick-associated agents (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). The significance of tick-borne viral diseases (TBVDs) in human health has raised global health concerns in recent decades due to current suboptimal diagnostics, treatment options for emerging viruses, and a scarcity of vaccines (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Attention from clinicians and researchers had alerted the public to the frequent emergences of novel viral pathogens causing febrile human diseases, such as Dabie bandavirus, also known as severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome virus (SFTSV) (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), Alongshan virus (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), Bourbon virus (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), most recently Jingmen tick virus (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), Yezo virus (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), Toyo virus (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), and Songlin virus (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), which had been identified in China and neighboring countries. In addition, the re-emergence and continuous spread of known tick-borne viral diseases (TBVDs), such as Crimean&#8211;Congo hemorrhagic fever virus (CCHFV) (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), Heartland virus (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>), tick-borne encephalitis virus (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), Powassan virus (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>), and African swine fever virus (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), positively correlate with the increasing incidence of TBVDs in humans and animals. The emergence of some undefined TBVDs pathogens as well as the dearth of data on tick virome highlights an urgent requirement for active viral surveillance and discovery in ticks, which greatly promotes our knowledge of the biodiversity and evolution of viruses transmitted by ticks, although it seems plausible that traditional isolation <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> tissue culture in cell lines has been proven a prerequisite gold standard to characterize a novel virus or insight into a known one (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). However, not all tick-borne viruses are amenable to being isolated due to technological limitations, extensive culture-independent studies, such as transcriptomics analysis following the high-throughput sequences (HTSs), have been attempted to examine tick virome (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Such studies might not only identify viruses associated with acute diseases but also could provide insights into the pathogenesis of more controversial chronic illnesses associated with tick bites (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Therefore, profiling viruses in ticks and investigating the substantial contact between ticks and human or animal hosts are necessary to better understand the viral sphere harbored by ticks and identify the potential viral pathogens in China. In this study, the virome of tick pools was profiled <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> metagenomic sequencing aimed at identifying the baseline viruses carried by ticks and characterizing their biodiversity and evolution. Then, the viral transmission patterns between ticks and humans were discussed based on the active surveillance results of molecular prevalence and potential exposure of humans to these ticks. These findings may shed light on the tick virome endemic to China and reveal the potential risks of TBVDs in the human population, which helps to guide tick-borne disease prevention and control in China.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Tick collection, visual assignment, and DNA/RNA preparation</title><p>Questing <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes persulcatus, Haemaphysalis concinna</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor silvarum</italic> were collected by sweeping flags on the vegetation in Zhalantun county, Inner Mongolia Autonomous Region, and Mudanjiang city, Heilongjiang province, respectively (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>). Morphological identification of ticks was conducted using the standard key for Chinese ticks (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) under stereomicroscopes. We further assigned these ticks into eight pools by species, sex/nymph, and origin location, each with 30 individuals (the nymphal pool of <italic toggle="yes">H. concinna</italic> was abandoned for inadequate individuals). All tick specimens were thoroughly surface sterilized to remove the possible contaminants before DNA/RNA isolation. Surface sterilization included sequential 1 mL washes with a vortex for 1 min in 3% hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>), two 30 s washes in 70% ethanol (w/v), 2 min in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS, pH = 7.4), and finally drying on clean tissue paper to avoid cross contaminations. Extraction of total DNA and RNA from ticks was performed using E.Z.N.A. DNA/RNA Isolation Kit (OMEGA) with modifications. In brief, ticks were homogenized in RLT solution under liquid nitrogen and then incubated at 55&#176;C for 10 min with proteinase K (Qiagen) and centrifuged for 30 s at 15,000 &#215; <italic toggle="yes">g</italic>. We took a proportion (~30 &#956;L) of the homogenates for genomic DNA extraction with RNAase A treatment (15 min) for later DNA purification. Simultaneously, another 300 &#956;L of tick homogenates was utilized to enrich viral particles and total RNA extraction. Before RNA extraction, the homogenates were filtered (0.45 &#956;M) at room temperature and then treated with RNase A (15 min), followed by Turbo DNase and Benzonase (MilliporeSigma, Burlington, MA, USA) (30 min) (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). The enrichment of viral particles had been achieved due to the degradations of unprotected nucleic acid absence of a viral capsid (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Validation of tick identifications</title><p>To verify tick species identification, genomic DNA was extracted from each specimen pool using E.Z.N.A. DNA/RNA Isolation Kit (OMEGA). Two genes were used for tick identification: the partial 18S rRNA gene (~1,100 nt) which was amplified using primer pairs 18S-1 (5&#8242;-CTGGTGCCAGCGAGCCGCGGYAA-3&#8242;) and 18S-2 (5&#8242;-TCCGTCAATTYCTTTAAGTT-3&#8242;) and partial COI gene (~680 nt) using primer pairs LCO1490 (5&#8242;-GGTCAACAAATCATAAAGATA TTGG-3&#8242;) and HCO2198 (5&#8242;-TAAACTTCAGGGTGACCAAAAAATCA-3&#8242;). PCRs were performed as previously described (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). For taxonomic determination, the resulting sequences were compared against the non-redundant nucleotide (nt) database and with all COI barcode records on the Barcode of Life Data (BOLD) Systems.</p></sec><sec><title>Library preparation and sequencing</title><p>The enriched total nucleic acid (11 &#956;L) from each tick pool was then subjected to first- and second-strand cDNA synthesis with Super Script IV reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen, Waltham, MA, USA) and exo-Klenow fragment (New England Biolabs, Ipswich, MA, USA), respectively. For all libraries, the Ribo-Zero Gold Kit (Illumina) was used to remove ribosomal RNA under the manufacturer's guidance. Subsequently, all rRNA-depleted RNA samples were resuspended to construct libraries using the KAPA Stranded RNA-Seq Kit (KAPA biosystems, Roche) with TruSeq Index PCR Primer barcodes (Illumina, SanDiego, CA, USA) following the manufacturer's instructions. Qubit high-sensitive RNA assays (Thermo Fisher Scientific) were performed to quantify cDNA levels before, during, and after library preparation, and the fragment sizes were simultaneously determined with an Agilent Bioanalyzer. Subsequently, equimolar amounts of nucleic acids were pooled and submitted for sequencing in each library. All libraries were sequenced on a single lane (paired-end, 125 bp read-length) on an Illumina HiSeq 2,500 platform at the BGI Sequencing Center (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.genomics.cn" ext-link-type="uri">www.genomics.cn</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec><title>Quality checking, trimming, and <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> assembly</title><p>Raw sequencing reads were first subjected to adapter removal and quality trimmed with TrimGalore (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/trim_galore/" ext-link-type="uri">www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/trim_galore/</ext-link>) (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Clean reads were <italic toggle="yes">de novo</italic> assembled using the Trinity v2.8.5 program (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Virus discovery and genome annotation</title><p>Trinity assemblies with a length above 200 bp were subjected to BLASTN against all nt databases using a local BLAST tool and BLASTX against all non-redundant protein (nr) databases (available as early as May 2022) of reference RNA viruses as well as those recently published, with hits at an e-value of 1 &#215; 10<sup>&#8722;5</sup> or better collated. All potential virus assemblies were screened against the Conserved Doman Database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Structure/cdd/wrpsb.cgi" ext-link-type="uri">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Structure/cdd/wrpsb.cgi</ext-link>) with an expected value threshold of 1 &#215; 10<sup>&#8722;3</sup> to identify viral gene segments. Putative viral contigs were further merged by high-identity overlaps with a threshold value of 95% similarity using the SeqMan program of the Lasergene package v7.1 (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). To complete the remaining gaps, original reads were aligned to the viral contigs again using the Bowtie2 program (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>), and the resultant assembly was verified in the Integrated Genomics Viewer (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). A novel viral species should be satisfied with one of the following conditions described before (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>), namely (i) &lt;80% nucleotides identity across the complete genome or (ii) &lt;90% amino acids identity of RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp) domain with the known viruses. To eliminate possible endogenous viruses, all viral assemblies were blasted against the reference genomes of <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> (GCA_013339685.1), <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> (GCA_013339745.1), and whole-genome shotgun database of Ixodida (Taxonomy ID: 6935, accession data:1/1/2022), respectively. If aligned bases of the query contigs covered more than 50% and the nucleotide similarity exhibited higher than 85% from any comparison with the earlier databases, they were discarded from the downstream analysis. Transcript abundance containing RNA-Seq fragment counts for each transcript (or gene) across each sample was estimated using the alignment-based abundance estimation method RSEM (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). The trimmed mean of M-values normalization method (TMM) was employed to normalize the transcript abundance.</p></sec><sec><title>Viral PCR confirmation and full-length genome walking</title><p>Reverse transcription-PCR and nested PCR were performed to confirm the existence of virus on RNA samples from the tick pools which were originally subjected to RNA-seq with primer sets (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 2</xref>) targeting the RdRp contigs of virus hit. Then, these primers were utilized to really exclude the presence of endogenous viral elements by PCR amplifications on genomic DNA templates from the same tick pools. Only positively detected potential virus would undergo a further epidemiological survey. The contigs which hit the viral genome were used as templates for overlapping primers design. The overlapping primers for amplifying the complete genome of the representative viruses (Taiga tick Nigecruvirus and Mukawa virus) were provided for the nested RT-PCR, genome walking, and rapid amplification of complementary DNA ends (5&#8242;-, 3&#8242;-RACE) with a commercial kit (Takara) according to the manufacturer's protocol (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Tables 3</xref>, <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">4</xref>). All the PCR products were separated on 0.8% agarose gel and purified through an agarose gel DNA extraction kit for Sanger sequencing.</p></sec><sec><title>Multiple sequence alignments and evolutionary analysis</title><p>To infer the evolutionary relationships of the viruses discovered, the protein-translated RdRp open reading frame segments produced in this study were combined with representative complete proteomes and (or) RdRp-segments of the <italic toggle="yes">Bunyavirales, Mononegavirales, Flaviviridae, Luteoviridae, Partitiviridae, Totiviridae</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Picornaviridae</italic> were retrieved from NCBI GenBank (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank" ext-link-type="uri">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank</ext-link>) and aligned using MAFFT v.7.266, employing the E-INS-i algorithm (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Ambiguous regions in the alignments were removed with TrimAl v.1.2 (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Following sequence alignment, ProtTest v.3.4 was employed to select the best-fit model of amino acid substitution (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). Finally, maximum likelihood trees for all alignments were inferred using the best-fit model of amino acid substitution (LG + I + &#915; + F for all alignments) with 1,000 bootstrap replicates with the PhyML v.3 program (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). Phylogenetic trees were edited and visualized with FigTree v.1.4.2 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree" ext-link-type="uri">http://tree.bio.ed.ac.uk/software/figtree</ext-link>). All phylogenetic trees were mid-point rooted for purposes of clarity only. The flowchart of the study design diagram was illustrated with different types of treatment and analysis (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>After morphological classification, there were 216 <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> (129 females, 52 males, and 35 nymphs) and 147 <italic toggle="yes">H. concinna</italic> (87 females, 49 males, and 11 nymphs) achieved alive from Mudanjiang city, Heilongjiang province, which were then randomly assigned into five groups of 30 individuals each species, sexes, and development stage. Among them, <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> groups included female, male, and nymphal ones, respectively, while only two groups (female and male) of <italic toggle="yes">H. concinna</italic> were arranged for inadequate nymphs. An average of 10.96 Gb data, including 7.1&#8211;7.6 &#215; 10<sup>7</sup> or so 150-base paired-end reads, were generated from male, female, and nymph groups of <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic>, while the male and female groups of <italic toggle="yes">H. concinna</italic> generated ~11.18 Gb of data on average, including 6.8 &#215; 10<sup>7</sup> and 8.0 &#215; 10<sup>7</sup> or so 150-base paired-end reads. While in Zhalantun city, Hulunbuir, Inner Mongolia, a total of 274 <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> (58 females, 170 males, and 46 nymphs) and 40 <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> (28 females and 12 males) were harvested alive. The <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> ticks were also divided into three groups (female, male, and nymphal ones), each with 30 individuals, which generated ~12.30 Gb data on average. After quality filtration and host subtraction, a total of 614,213,814 reads remained which were assembled into 815,457 contigs. Assembled contigs were compared to the NCBI Viral Genomes database, resulting in 1,311, 1,033, and 709 viral contigs from <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus, D. silvarum</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">H. concinna</italic> as viral origin through BLASTN and BLASTX, which were kept for a subsequent manual inspection (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). A prediction of ORFs was also implemented and compared to the viral protein database through BLASTP. As a result, sequences of 28 putative viruses were identified (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), with five representing novel species. Seventeen viruses were identified within the <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> pool, 11 in <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic>, while only six were discovered in <italic toggle="yes">H. concinna</italic>. Of them, single-stranded positive-sense RNA viruses (<italic toggle="yes">Flaviviridae, Luteoviridae, Picornaviridae, Solemoviridae</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Tetraviridae</italic>), negative-stranded RNA viruses (<italic toggle="yes">Mononegavirales</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bunyavirales</italic>), and double-stranded RNA viruses (<italic toggle="yes">Totiviridae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Partitiviridae</italic>) were involved (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The presence of the representative viral strains in the corresponding pool was further verified by nested RT-PCR and Sanger sequencing (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Tables 2</xref>, <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">3</xref>, <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figures 3</xref>, <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">4</xref>). In total, 41 viral sequences from the 28 identified RNA viruses were verified and submitted to NCBI under the accession numbers <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="OP863261" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">OP863261</ext-link>&#8211;<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="OP863295" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">OP863295</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="OP863301" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">OP863301</ext-link>&#8211;<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="OP863305" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">OP863305</ext-link>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Virus identified in three dominant tick species in North China.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="border-right: thin solid #000000;background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Voucher species</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Genus</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>No. unique contigs</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>contig length</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Encoded fragments</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>mean seq. depth</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>relative abundance (RdRp%)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>RdRp Identity</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Top hit (RdRp accession no)</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Ixodes persulcatus</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mivirus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,853</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N, L, G, VP4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,107&#8211;3,210</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01&#8211;0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.95</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nuomin virus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="UKS70436.1">UKS70436.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nigecruvirus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,436</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N, L, G, VP4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,103&#8211;3,309</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.70</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blacklegged tick Chuvirus 2 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AUW34382.1">AUW34382.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleorhabdovirus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,033&#8211;5,986</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L, G</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">650&#8211;1,645</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01&#8211;0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.44</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chimay rhabdovirus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AVM86063.1">AVM86063.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alphanemrha virus-like</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,717&#8211;6,663</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L, N</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,905&#8211;2,221</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.46</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Norway mononegavirus 1 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="ASY03261.1">ASY03261.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ixovirus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,650&#8211;6,680</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L, N</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,105&#8211;4,732</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25&#8211;0.47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.67</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sara tick phlebovirus 1 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QPD01621.1">QPD01621.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ixovirus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,380&#8211;6,630</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">277&#8211;22,219</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02&#8211;0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scapularis ixovirus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="YP_010086238.1">YP_010086238.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Orthonairovirus</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,840&#8211;12,869</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L, S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105&#8211;4,732</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.04</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beiji nairovirus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="UFP37779.1">UFP37779.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Orthonairovirus</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,842&#8211;11,076</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L, N</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,137&#8211;4,326</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.25</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Bay virus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="ANT80542.1">ANT80542.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Orthobunyavirus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,780&#8211;5,800</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L, G</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,237&#8211;2,938</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.25</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ixodes scapularis bunyavirus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="BBD75425.1">BBD75425.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">unclassified Bunyavirales</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,295&#8211;9,080</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,231&#8211;3,091</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.78</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ubmeje virus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QKK82912.1">QKK82912.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Deltapartitivir us-like</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,510&#8211;1,628</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#8211;521</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01&#8211;0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jilin partiti-like virus 1 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QTZ97684.1">QTZ97684.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Luteoviridae</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,419&#8211;1,628</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">427&#8211;469</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01&#8211;0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Norway luteo-like virus 2 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="ASY03255.1">ASY03255.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Luteoviridae</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,398&#8211;1,610</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178&#8211;506</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01&#8211;2.62</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.04</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Norway luteo-like virus 3 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="ASY03257.1">ASY03257.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Riboviria</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,389&#8211;5,427</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L, N</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,793&#8211;1,797</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25&#8211;0.47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.24</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vovk virus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QKK82915.1">QKK82915.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Levivirus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">620&#8211;1,899</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L, H4bulk, coat</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206&#8211;632</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.27</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Levivirus <italic toggle="yes">sp</italic>. (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QDH88856.1">QDH88856.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Totivirus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,100&#8211;1,330</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">509</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01&#8211;0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.17</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hubei toti-like virus 24 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="YP_009336908.1">YP_009336908.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sobemovirus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,621</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">872</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01&#8211;0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.62</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hubei sobemo-like virus 15 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="YP_009330030.1">YP_009330030.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Dermacenor silvarum</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pestivirus-like viruses</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,481&#8211;15,100</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L. S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,827</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.81</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bole tick virus 4 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QUJ17979.1">QUJ17979.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alphanemrha virus-like</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,610&#8211;6,701</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L, N</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,241&#8211;3,305</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.51</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rhipicephalus associated rhabdo-like virus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QYW06859.1">QYW06859.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alphanemrha virus-like</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,659&#8211;6,700</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,893&#8211;2,215</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.42</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">America dog tick rhabdovirus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AUX13124.1">AUX13124.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ixovirus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6,650</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L, S</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,732</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.41</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sara tick phlebovirus 1 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QPD01621.1">QPD01621.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phlebovirus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,890&#8211;3,300</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L, N, Ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,079</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.53</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mukawa virus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="YP_009666332.1">YP_009666332.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Uukuvirus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4,537&#8211;4,550</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,513</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.61</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tacheng uukuvirus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AWK68110.1">AWK68110.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Orthonairovirus</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,842&#8211;11,076</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L, N</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,137&#8211;4,326</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.25</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South Bay virus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="ANT80542.1">ANT80542.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Solemoviridae</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">722&#8211;1,440</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">orf1, orf2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">522&#8211;1,328</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xinjiang tick associated virus 1 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QBQ65134.1">QBQ65134.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Picornavirus</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">648&#8211;684</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">316&#8211;328</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01&#8211;0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.79</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xiangshan picorna-like virus 7 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="UDL13977.1">UDL13977.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Totivirus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,008&#8211;4,566</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L, orf1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">774&#8211;1,052</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.10</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lonestar tick totivirus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AUX13136.1">AUX13136.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Totivirus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">572&#8211;881</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">235</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.31</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Xinjiang tick totivirus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QBQ65052">QBQ65052</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclassified Tetravirus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,310&#8211;5,514</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,345&#8211;1,737</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.53</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">tick borne tetravirus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QTE18640.1">QTE18640.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Haemaphyaslis concinna</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alphanemrha virus-like</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7,238</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,170</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01&#8211;0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.69</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tahe rhabdovirus 2 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="UXX19014.1">UXX19014.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleorhabdovirus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,350&#8211;1,568</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L, N</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">537</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.53</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">blacklegged tick rhabdovirus-1 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AUW34390.1">AUW34390.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alphanemrha virus-like</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,489&#8211;6,500</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,133&#8211;2,169</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01&#8211;0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.29</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tacheng Tick Virus 3 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="YP_009304331.1">YP_009304331.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alphanemrha virus-like</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,227&#8211;2,415</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L, N</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">775&#8211;804</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.40</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bole tick virus 2 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="YP_009287864.1">YP_009287864.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sobemovirus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,700&#8211;5,092</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,228&#8211;1,678</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hubei sobemo-like virus 15 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="YP_009330029.1">YP_009330029.1</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Totivirus</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,008&#8211;4,566</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L, orf1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">774&#8211;1,052</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.01</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lonestar tick totivirus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AUX13136.1">AUX13136.1</ext-link>)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec><title>SsRNA (+) viruses</title><p>Sequences for a novel viral species belonging to the family Flaviviridae, tentatively named <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor silvarum</italic> pestivirus-like virus 1 (DSPV), were identified in all the three <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> pools (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figures 1A</xref>, <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">B</xref>). DSPV comprises a single polyprotein that shares the closest homology within the NS3 and NS5 of viruses within the genus <italic toggle="yes">Pestivirus</italic> (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>), which clustered DSPV with other recently identified <italic toggle="yes">Pestivirus</italic>-like viruses, Bole tick virus 4 and Trinbago virus (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Additional segmented <italic toggle="yes">Flavivirus</italic>, Jingmen tick virus, was also discovered in <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> with 97.16 and 96.90% amino acid similarities with RdRp (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QFR36159.1">QFR36159.1</ext-link>) and VP3 protein (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QHW66956.1">QHW66956.1</ext-link>), respectively (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). These contigs were shown positioned on corresponding sites in our phylogenetic tree of these Flavivirus-associated viruses (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>) constructed based on their RdRp genes (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figures 1A</xref>, <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">C</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic analysis of representative branches in the family <italic toggle="yes">Flaviviridae</italic> based on the RdRp sequences. <bold>(A)</bold> Enhanced region showing the relationship of the unclassified <italic toggle="yes">Pestivirus</italic>-like group in relation to <italic toggle="yes">Pestivirus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Flavivirus</italic>. <bold>(B)</bold> Enhanced region showing the relationship of Jingmen tick virus in relation to the family <italic toggle="yes">Flaviviridae</italic>. <bold>(C)</bold> Enhanced region showing the relationship of Dermacentor pestivirus-like virus in relation to genus <italic toggle="yes">Pestivirus</italic>. Red dot marked with 1 represents Jingmen tick virus from <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes persulcatus</italic>, and green dot marked with 1 represents Dermacentor pestivirus-like virus from <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor silvarum</italic>. Maximum likelihood tree inferred using the best-fit model of amino acid substitution (LG + I + &#915; + F for all alignments) with 1,000 bootstrap replicates.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1057977-g0001.jpg"/></fig><sec><title>Luteovirus, Solemovirus, Picornavirus, and Tetravirus</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Luteovirus, Picornavirus, Tetravirus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Solemovirus</italic> are single-stranded positive-sense RNA viruses that are endowed with important and potential viral pathogen parasites on humans and animals (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). In the present study, taiga tick luteo-like virus was identified with shared amino acid sequences of Norway luteo-virus 2 (93.80%, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="ASY03255.1">ASY03255.1</ext-link>) and Norway luteo-virus 3 (84.04%, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="ASY03257.1">ASY03257.1</ext-link>), respectively, across 99% RdRp gene (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The two luteo-like viruses grouped with <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes scapularis</italic>-associated viruses in our ML phylogeny tree, although low abundant Norway luteo-virus 2 was present in one library (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 7</xref>). Moreover, a total of three Solemoviruses were discovered in the present study as well (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure S8</xref>). Of which, a novel <italic toggle="yes">Solemoviridae</italic> member, Xinjiang tick-associated virus 1 from <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic>, was shown 100% identical to those sequences on orf1 and orf2, respectively (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Sobemovirus-like viruses from <italic toggle="yes">H. concinna</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> were found to be identical to Hubei sobemo-like virus 15 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="YP_009330030.1">YP_009330030.1</ext-link>) with 75.65 and 39.62% identities on RdRp coverage over 2,620 amino acid sequences, respectively (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In addition, another positive-sense ssRNA viruses, tick-borne tetravirus and Picorna-like virus from <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic>, exhibited 71.53 and 33.79% amino acid identities of RNA polymerase genes with tick-borne tetravirus-like virus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QTE18640.1">QTE18640.1</ext-link>) (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 9</xref>) and Xiangshan picorna-like virus 7 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="UDL13977.1">UDL13977.1</ext-link>) over 95% coverage spaced across L segments, respectively (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 10</xref>). Further classification of the two ss (+) RNA viruses was challenging due to high sequence divergence in combination with a limited number of available <italic toggle="yes">Tetravirus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Picornavirus</italic> sequences.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>SsRNA (-) viruses</title><sec><title>Mononegavirales</title><sec><title>Chuviridae</title><p>Assembly of the viral contigs from <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> yields two viruses belonging to <italic toggle="yes">Chuviridae</italic> (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2A</xref>, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">B</xref>). Among them, a <italic toggle="yes">Mivirus</italic> was discovered from <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> with shared viral RdRp amino acid (aa) sequences at 99.95% on the 100% query coverage of Nuomin virus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="UKS70432.1">UKS70432.1</ext-link>) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Nuomin virus was reported as a negative-strand circular RNA virus, whose genome at a length of 10,863 nucleotides, coding open reading frames (ORFs) of RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp), glycoprotein (G), nucleoprotein (NP), and VP4 protein (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 11</xref>, left), shows high similarity to RdRp of Lesone mivirus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QPD01622.1">QPD01622.1</ext-link>) and Suffolk virus (YP 009177218.1) with distinct amino acids sequences on VP4. Nuomin virus had been recognized as pathogenic to humans in Tahe, Heilongjiang province, China (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>), and then assigned to the recently proposed <italic toggle="yes">Mivirus</italic> genus of <italic toggle="yes">Chuviridae</italic> (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Fortunately, we also achieved a novel <italic toggle="yes">Nigecruvirus</italic>, tentatively named Taiga tick nigecruvirus, which was shown at a length of 11,436 nucleotides and identical to blacklegged tick chuvirus 2 in L (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AUW34382.1">AUW34382.1</ext-link>), G (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AUW34383.1">AUW34383.1</ext-link>), NP (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AUW34384.1">AUW34384.1</ext-link>), and VP4 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AUW34385.1">AUW34385.1</ext-link>) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 11</xref>, right) based on the amino acids' similarities at 83.07, 79.94, 66.22, and 67.31%, respectively, over the 100% coverage. Homology searches revealed this virus to be very distant from genus <italic toggle="yes">Mivirus</italic>. The similarities of the four ORFs of the novel taiga tick nigecruvirus and Nuomin virus ensure the prevalence of these two <italic toggle="yes">Chuviridae</italic> members in <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> in China (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic analysis of representative branches in the order <italic toggle="yes">Mononegavirales</italic>. <bold>(A)</bold> Alignment of all branches belonging to the order <italic toggle="yes">Mononegavirales</italic>. <bold>(B)</bold> Enhanced region showing the genera relationship of <italic toggle="yes">Mivirus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Nigecruvirus</italic>. <bold>(C)</bold> Enhanced region showing the relationships of <italic toggle="yes">Mononegavirus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Rhabdovirus</italic>. Red dots marked with 1 to 4 represent Nuomin chuvirus, taiga tick <italic toggle="yes">nigecruvirus</italic>, Chimay rhabdovirus, and Norway <italic toggle="yes">mononegavirus</italic>-like virus 1 from <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes persulcatus</italic>, respectively. Green dots marked with 1 and 2 represent <italic toggle="yes">Rhipicephalus</italic>-associated rhabdo-like virus and America dog tick rhabdovirus from <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor silvarum</italic>, respectively. Blue dots marked with 1 to 3 represents blacklegged tick rhabdovirus-1, Bole tick virus 2, and Manly virus from <italic toggle="yes">Haemaphysalis concinna</italic>, respectively. Maximum likelihood tree inferred using the best-fit model of amino acid substitution (LG + I + &#915; + F for all alignments) with 1,000 bootstrap replicates.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1057977-g0002.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Mononegaviridae-like virus</title><p>Except for <italic toggle="yes">Chuviridae</italic>, we also identified several viral contigs belonging to <italic toggle="yes">Mononegavirales</italic> (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>), among which one <italic toggle="yes">Nucleorhabdovirus</italic> and two <italic toggle="yes">Alphanemrhavirus</italic>-like viruses (Tacheng tick virus 3 and Norway mononegavirus 1) were discovered from <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> with 88.44, 47.32, and 49.46% identities to those aligned RdRp sequences of Chimay-like rhabdovirus (62.52% <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AVM86063.1">AVM86063.1</ext-link>), Tacheng tick virus 3 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="YP_009304331.1">YP_009304331.1</ext-link>), and Norway mononegavirus 1 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="ASY03261.1">ASY03261.1</ext-link>) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2A</xref>, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">C</xref>, <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 5</xref>). Moreover, similar glycoprotein (G) and nucleoprotein (NP) sequences were also obtained from <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> and assigned as glycoprotein of Chimay rhabdovirus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AVM86062.1">AVM86062.1</ext-link>) and nucleoprotein of Tacheng tick virus 3 (62.17%, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AJG39137.1">AJG39137.1</ext-link>) and Norway mononegavirus 1 (57.43%, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="KAG0427517.1">KAG0427517.1</ext-link>), respectively (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). As a case of <italic toggle="yes">H. concinna</italic>, assembly contigs obtained were shown with a high degree of diversity in <italic toggle="yes">Mononegavirales</italic> involving three <italic toggle="yes">Alphanemrhavirus</italic>-like rhabdoviruses and one <italic toggle="yes">Nucleorhabdovirus</italic>. Of <italic toggle="yes">Alphanemrhavirus</italic>-like rhabdovirus, Bole tick virus 2, Tacheng tick virus 3, and Tahe rhabdovirus 2 were involved, and their RdRp sequence accession numbers of reference strains as <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="YP_009287864.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">YP_009287864.1</ext-link> (51.40%, 804 aa), <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="YP_009304331.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">YP_009304331.1</ext-link> (48.29%, 2,179aa), and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="UXX19014.1" ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank">UXX19014.1</ext-link> (99.69%, 2,168aa) in L segments, respectively (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2A</xref>, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">C</xref>, <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 5</xref>). Bole tick virus 2 was also identified with nucleoprotein segment (73.02%, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="YP_009287860.1">YP_009287860.1</ext-link>) over 100% coverage. The nucleorhabdovirus shared 73.53% similarities as (1,568aa) in RdRp genes of blacklegged tick rhabdovirus-1 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AUW34390.1">AUW34390.1</ext-link>), whereas <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> from Zhaluntun, Inner Monogolia, yield two <italic toggle="yes">Alphanemrhavirus</italic>-like viruses identical to <italic toggle="yes">Rhipicephalus</italic> associated rhabdo-like virus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QYW06859.1">QYW06859.1</ext-link>) and American dog tick rhabdovirus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AUX13124.1">AUX13124.1</ext-link>) with 94.51% and 48.42% similarities over the 99.0% coverage, respectively (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figures 2A</xref>, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">C</xref>). The details of other related protein fragments in the viruses described earlier are shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Bunyavirales</title><p>Bunyaviruses are segmented negative-stranded viruses that include at least nine families and 13 genera, many of which were involved as pathogens to humans and animals (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). In our study, 11 species in five genera of three families in the order <italic toggle="yes">Bunyavirales</italic> were detected. Assembly of these contigs revealed the presence of two <italic toggle="yes">Orthonairovirus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Nairoviridae</italic>), three <italic toggle="yes">Phlebovirus</italic>, two <italic toggle="yes">Ixovirus</italic>, and one <italic toggle="yes">Uukuvirus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Phenuiviridae</italic>), one <italic toggle="yes">Orthobunyavirus</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Peribunyaviridae</italic>), and two unclassified Bunyaviruses from <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic>, whereas no <italic toggle="yes">Bunyavirales</italic> contigs detected in <italic toggle="yes">H. concinna</italic> (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The phylogenetic tree of <italic toggle="yes">Bunyavirales</italic> constructed based on the RdRp genes indicated that these phleboviruses, orthonairoviruses, and unclassified bunyaviruses clustered with referenced strains and formed well-supported monophyletic groups as the &#8220;classic&#8221; schematic diagram involved with <italic toggle="yes">Orthohantanviridae, Nairoviridae, Phenuiviridae, Peribunyaviridae</italic>, and others (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic analysis of representative branches in the order <italic toggle="yes">Bunyavirales</italic>. <bold>(A)</bold> Alignment of all branches belonging to the order <italic toggle="yes">Bunyavirales</italic>. <bold>(B)</bold> Enhanced region showing <italic toggle="yes">Phenuiviridae</italic> members. <bold>(C)</bold> Enhanced region showing <italic toggle="yes">Orthonairoviridae</italic> members. Red dots marked with 1 to 6 represent <italic toggle="yes">Scapularis ixovirus</italic>, Sara tick phlebovirus 1, Beiji <italic toggle="yes">orthonairovirus</italic>, unclassified <italic toggle="yes">Bunyavirales</italic> 1, unclassified <italic toggle="yes">Bunyavirales</italic> 2, and <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes scapularis</italic> orthobunyavirus viruses from <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes persulcatus</italic>, respectively. Green dots marked with 1 to 4 represent Tacheng uukuvirus, Sara tick phlebovirus 2, Mukawa virus, and South Bay virus from <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor silvarum</italic>, respectively. Maximum likelihood tree inferred using the best-fit model of amino acid substitution (LG + I + &#915; + F for all alignments) with 1,000 bootstrap replicates.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-1057977-g0003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Orthonairoviridae</title><p>Assembly of multiple contigs from <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> pools contained with coding sequences is similar to viruses in the genus <italic toggle="yes">Orthonairovirus</italic> by BLASTx. With CCHFV as a reference genome, assembly of these <italic toggle="yes">Orthonairovirus</italic>-like contigs provided 100% coverage of L and S segments. The assembled sequences from <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> showed high identity (99.81%) to Beiji <italic toggle="yes">orthonairovirus</italic> (BJNV) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3A</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">B</xref>), a novel species initially discovered from <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>) and human patients (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). BJNV reads were the dominant viral reads obtained from all <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> pools and accounted for 5&#8211;7% of filtered reads. Moreover, South Bay virus was also revealed from <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> with 97.12% similarity in RdRp (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AII01810.1">AII01810.1</ext-link>) and 77.61% in nucleocapsid protein (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AII01798.1">AII01798.1</ext-link>) over the 100% coverage (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3A</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">B</xref>). However, despite an exhaustive bioinformatics analysis, we were unable to identify any contigs or reads with any similarity to M segments of <italic toggle="yes">Orthonairovirus</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Phenuiviridae</title><p>In the present study, a total of six species of three genera in the family <italic toggle="yes">Phenuiviridae</italic> are present in <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic>. The most diversity appeared in genus <italic toggle="yes">Phlebovirus</italic>, which is currently comprised of over 70 phleboviruses isolated from ticks, mosquitoes, and sand flies (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). We identified multiple contigs with homology to phleboviruses by BLASTx in pools of <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3A</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">C</xref>). The contigs derived from the pools of each tick species were assembled separately to a reference phlebovirus genome. We obtained phlebovirus contigs from <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic>, which were identical to Mukawa virus with shared amino acids similarities in L segments (98.60%, YP 009666332.1) and non-structural protein (93.53%, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="YP_009666334.1">YP_009666334.1</ext-link>) and nucleoprotein (99.60%, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="YP_009666333.1">YP_009666333.1</ext-link>) over the 98% coverage (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3A</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">C</xref>). Moreover, an unclassified <italic toggle="yes">Phlebovirus</italic>, Changping tick virus 2 (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AJG39235.1">AJG39235.1</ext-link>), was harvested from <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> with 85.46% similarity on the 100% sequence coverage of RdRp gene (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3A</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">B</xref>). In addition, two members in genus <italic toggle="yes">Ixovirus</italic> were also achieved, one is Sara tick phlebovirus from both <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> with their RdRp identities up to 99.32 and 99.41%, respectively, across the 2,210 amino acids sequences (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3A</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">C</xref>). Another <italic toggle="yes">Ixovirus</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">Phenuiviridae, Scapularis ixovirus</italic> (previously cited as blacklegged tick Phlebovirus 3, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="YP_010086238.1">YP_010086238.1</ext-link>), was also documented in <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> with 74.1% identity in L segments (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3A</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">C</xref>). Fortunately, the third genus <italic toggle="yes">Uukuvirus</italic> in the family <italic toggle="yes">Phenuiviridae</italic> was harvested from <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> and identical to Tacheng <italic toggle="yes">Uukuvirus</italic> (Tacheng tick virus 2, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AWK68110.1">AWK68110.1</ext-link>) with 92.61% similarity on the amino acids' sequences on polymerase gene (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3A</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">C</xref>). All sequences assigned to the <italic toggle="yes">Phenuiviridae</italic> family were presented with missed M segment coding for the viral glycoprotein.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Other <italic toggle="yes">bunyavirales</italic></title><p>Except for <italic toggle="yes">Nairoviridae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Phenuiviridae</italic>, we also obtained another viral contig belonging to <italic toggle="yes">Bunyavirales</italic> from <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>, <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 6</xref>), which exhibited a relatively lower identity with Volzhskoe tick virus 1 (72.41%, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QPD01626.1">QPD01626.1</ext-link>) (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>) and <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes scapularis</italic> bunyavirus (38.25%, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="BBD75425.1">BBD75425.1</ext-link>) (<italic toggle="yes">Orthobunyavirus, Peribunyaviridae</italic>) based on over 90% sequence coverage of RdRp gene (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Moreover, Ubmeje-like virus (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QKK82912.1">QKK82912.1</ext-link>) from <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> was presented with a lower RdRp identity of 46.78%, which was also known as an unclassified <italic toggle="yes">Bunyavirales</italic> (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Double-stranded RNA viruses</title><p>Both <italic toggle="yes">Partitiviridae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Totiviridae</italic> are double-stranded RNA viruses mostly known as abundant and diverse in arthropods, some of which are pathogens to animals and humans. Notably, several lineages of <italic toggle="yes">Partitivirus</italic> appear related to endogenous virus elements in the genomes of these arthropod hosts (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). We identified three highly divergent <italic toggle="yes">Partiti</italic>-like viruses, Jilin partiti-like virus 1 from three <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes persulcatus</italic> pools (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 12</xref>). Interestingly, this virus formed a cluster with other arthropod-associated partiti-like viruses, which shared a close relationship with those found in host animals associated with arthropods. Whether Jilin partiti-like virus 1 is a truly tick-borne virus will need to be examined in detail. In addition to partiti-like virus, another dsRNA virus close to the family <italic toggle="yes">Totiviridae</italic> was also discovered from <italic toggle="yes">H. concinna</italic> with relatively lower amino acid identities with over 95% coverages of RdRp genes (50.01%, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AUX13136.1">AUX13136.1</ext-link>) and ORF1 (67.01%, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="AUX13135.1">AUX13135.1</ext-link>) of Lonestar tick totivirus (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Meanwhile, <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> yields contigs similar to Hubei toti-like virus 24 based on over 95% sequences L segment (38.17%, <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="YP_009336908.1">YP_009336908.1</ext-link>) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). As a case of <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic>, both Lonestar tick totivirus and Hubei toti-like virus 24 were found with RdRp genes (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 13</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Others</title><p>Other more distantly related viruses including unclassified Vovk virus (44.24% RdRp aa identity with <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QKK82915.1">QKK82915.1</ext-link>) and Levivirus (42.27% RdRp aa identity <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QDH88856.1">QDH88856.1</ext-link>, 31.75% H4bulk (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="QDH87337.1">QDH87337.1</ext-link>) and 35.34% coat (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-protein" xlink:href="UJQ85258.1">UJQ85258.1</ext-link>) in the family of <italic toggle="yes">Leviviridae</italic> were also detected from <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study focused on the characterization of virome diversity of questing <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum, I. persulcatus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">H. concinna</italic> ticks from North China. The outcome from our sampling efforts supports the results throughout various Chinese regions, showing that <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus, D. silvarum</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">H. concinna</italic> are three of the most abundant questing ticks within the regions (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). All three tick species have been heavily implicated in the transmission of TBDs throughout the regions. <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> is the principal vector of the agents of Lyme borreliosis, Rickettsioses, and Babesioses along with <italic toggle="yes">A. phagocytophilum</italic> and clinically relevant human pathogen Jingmen tick virus (Alongshan virus) and Far-Eastern strain of TBEV (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">H. concinna</italic> had also been linked with several tick-borne pathogens found throughout China, including <italic toggle="yes">Francisella tularensis, Coxiella burnetii, Rickettsia</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">Babesia</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">Anaplasma</italic> spp., TBEV, and SFTSV/Dabie bandavirus (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). Despite examining more pools of <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">H. concinna</italic>, we identified a greater number of viral contigs in <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic>, while no <italic toggle="yes">Bunyavirales</italic> viral sequences were detected within <italic toggle="yes">H. concinna</italic> pools. Combined, these studies support a hypothesis that different tick species can harbor diverse viruses at different levels. Interestingly, no viral sequence of TBEV was identified in the known endemic region, in addition to a low abundance of Jingmen tick virus identified. This most likely is attributed to the low prevalence of these viruses within the tick populations along with sampling bias. For example, data show that the prevalence of TBEV maintained within <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> populations in China is &lt;0.1% (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). Since we only examined 90 <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> ticks, it is unlikely we would identify a positive tick.</p><sec><title>Diverse <italic toggle="yes">Bunyavirus</italic> predominated in our HTS data</title><p>More than 350 viruses are classified in the order <italic toggle="yes">Bunyavirales</italic>, which were assigned as nine families and over 13 genera, with various species only recently discovered and characterized (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). Our studies have demonstrated molecular evidence of the emergence of over 10 bunyaviruses present in ixodid ticks in China. Based on the phylogenetic analysis of the polymerase coding regions, Beiji <italic toggle="yes">orthonairovirus</italic> and South Bay virus form a distinct phylogenetic lineage within currently described orthonairoviruses, which indicate that the genus <italic toggle="yes">Orthonairovirus</italic> is significantly more diverse than previously appreciated. Based on a very short sequence fragment, the earlier phylogenetic analysis of tick-associated <italic toggle="yes">orthonairoviruses</italic> yielded two main phylogenetic clades, with which one clade being isolated exclusively from ixodid ticks and the other from argasid ticks (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). The phylogeny has been proven complex and confounded as some previously unidentified genetically distinct or emerged <italic toggle="yes">Nairovirus</italic> presents. A more accurate <italic toggle="yes">Orthonairovirus</italic> classification scheme is urgent to be updated with oncoming contributions from genome sequencing of unclassified <italic toggle="yes">Nairovirus</italic>, especially those isolated from ticks of Argasid or Ixodid. In addition to the genus <italic toggle="yes">Orthonairovirus</italic>, we also identified several <italic toggle="yes">Phenuiviridae</italic> viruses from <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">Phenuiviridae</italic> was the latest update representing the newly combined <italic toggle="yes">Phlebovirus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Tenuivirus</italic> along with the newly erected genera <italic toggle="yes">Goukovirus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Phasivirus</italic> (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Historically, phleboviruses were classified into at least three phylogenetic clusters, each comprised of several potential species: the Uukuniemi group, the Bhanja group, and the STFS group based on vector, genomic, and serological relationships (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Of them, Tacheng uukuvirus in <italic toggle="yes">D. reticulatus</italic> has been proven phylogenetically close to a human clinical isolate with a history of tick bite in northwestern China (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>), which raised widespread concerns about the health risk of <italic toggle="yes">Dermacetor</italic> ticks to transmit <italic toggle="yes">Uukuvirus</italic> in China. As one of the predominant human-bitten species, the potential transmission ability of <italic toggle="yes">Uukuvirus</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> remains to be determined in detail. Furthermore, the Mukawa virus, another novel <italic toggle="yes">Phlebovirus</italic> outsides the described three clades earlier, was first detected from <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic>. Together with the evidence of Mukawa virus proliferation in the Huh-7 cell line and the innate immune responses caused by the viral NSs during mice infection (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>), the immense medical significance of <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> to human victims should be addressed and more detailed surveys on the epidemiological characters of Mukawa virus should not be ignored (<xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>). Similarly, although no clinical manifestations were documented to elucidate the pathogenicity of some phleboviruses in humans and animals, the discovery of Sara tick phlebovirus, <italic toggle="yes">Scapularis ixovirus</italic>, and Changping tick virus 2 in our studies has deepened our knowledge about diverse <italic toggle="yes">Phenuiviridae</italic> viruses widely prevalent in China and adjacent areas. However, the relative abundance of these <italic toggle="yes">Bunyavirales</italic> viruses was shown as quite lower among the viral transcripts obtained. The expansive infectious ticks, for example, up to 3% infection rate of Beiji <italic toggle="yes">orthonairovirus</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), might cause a series of human victims suffering from bunyavirus infections. Considering the unknown pathogenicity of Volzhskoe tick virus, Ubmeje virus, and <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes scapularis</italic>-orthobunyavirus discovered in the present article, the findings of <italic toggle="yes">Bunyavirus</italic>-like contigs from <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> suggest that these viruses may have much medical relevance and broader geographical distributions, perhaps throughout the range of the two tick species, comparable to bacterial and protozoan pathogens transmitted by them. Enhanced by the spreading of ticks through the movements of the viremic host reservoir, the real geographical ranges should be further extended. We do not know whether these bunyaviruses are specific to their vector tick species. As a matter of fact, some tick-borne viruses can usually be isolated from more than one tick species. CCHFV, for example, has been isolated from over 30 tick species and multiple genera throughout Europe, Africa, and Asia, and it is unlikely that all of the 30 species represent competent vectors (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>). Although the HTS analysis suggests vector specificity for tick species, we cannot rule out the possibility that other tick species may serve as vectors of these viruses.</p><p>One particularly notable characteristic of these Bunyaviruses is the lack of a recognizable glycoprotein-coding segment. Although we recovered ~90% of the L and S segments for Sara tick phlebovirus, Mukava virus, and other Bunyavirus by HTS and dispelled the possibility of viral integration, we were unable to identify any scenario with similarity to <italic toggle="yes">Bunyavirales</italic> M segments. We have considered various explanations for this confounding result. First, these viruses encode a more complicated secondary structure of the M segments, which may inhibit efficient cDNA synthesis, subsequently resulting in the failure to detect by amplifications (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Alternatively, these viruses may employ special pathways in the process of cellular attachment and entry other than the well-known glycoprotein precursor (GPC) depending manner (<xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>). Finally, we also cannot exclude the possibility that an episome-like form is coded by S and L segments of these viruses. As such, they may not assemble an infectious virion but instead use other vehicles, for instance, extracellular vesicles, for their dissemination to new hosts (<xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>High diversity <italic toggle="yes">Mononegavirales</italic> contigs predominated in our HTS data</title><p>In our analysis, a novel <italic toggle="yes">Chuvirus</italic>, Taiga tick nigecruvirus, was also revealed in <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> other than Nuomin virus. Phylogenic analysis based on L, G, NP, and VP4 fragments suggested that Taiga tick nigecruvirus and blacklegged tick chuvirus 2 formed a separate monophyletic clade outside genus <italic toggle="yes">Mivirus</italic> under the <italic toggle="yes">Chuviridae</italic> branch of <italic toggle="yes">Jingchuvirales</italic> in the order <italic toggle="yes">Mononegavirales</italic>, although a complete genetic characterization will be required to fully determine its taxonomy. The taiga tick nigecruvirus was found to have high identity in RdRp and relatively lower identities in N and G genes with blacklegged tick chuvirus 2, with no pathogenicity in humans and other animals. However, the reported human pathogenicity of Nuomin virus in genus <italic toggle="yes">Mivirus</italic> from Tahe, Heilongjiang province, suggested the potential threats of the Taiga tick nigecruvirus on humans and animals <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> tick bites or other transmission routes. Based on the phylogeny relationship, we considered the virus closely related to blacklegged tick chuvirus 2 as a novel Chuvirus named Taiga tick nigecruvirus tentative, while Nuomin virus as a member of <italic toggle="yes">Mivirus</italic>, called <italic toggle="yes">Mivirus nuomin</italic>.</p><p>Rhabdoviridae are another diverse set of single-stranded negative-sense RNA viruses with frequent host-switching features during their evolution history (<xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>) and widely found to naturally infect both animals and plants. In the present study, almost all the pools of the three tick species yield the positive contains of <italic toggle="yes">Rhabdovirus</italic>-like contigs, which demonstrates relatively high divergence of RdRp sequences of the rhabdoviruses. Among these rhabdoviruses, only two <italic toggle="yes">Nucleorhabdovirus</italic>, Chimay-like rhabdovirus and blacklegged tick rhabdovirus-1, were harvested from <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">H. concinna</italic>, respectively. While, in the <italic toggle="yes">Alphanemrha</italic> virus-like group, extensive diversity was observed with three virus species in <italic toggle="yes">H. concinna</italic>, two species in <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic>, and one species in <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus</italic>. Together with two <italic toggle="yes">Nucleorhabdovirus</italic> detected, diverse <italic toggle="yes">Rhabdovirus</italic> in the three tick species might be associated with high frequencies of host switches within their comparable broader host spectrums. It should be noted that more diversity of <italic toggle="yes">Rhabdovirus</italic> is still unexplored due to limited tick samples or geographical sites.</p><p>Although our surveys have demonstrated a wide array of highly diverse viruses harbored in the three tick species sampled, however, the limitations of the study were also prominent due to our sample bias. One constraint of our study was caused by the limited geographical regions and aggregated distributions of these ticks, as our HTS analysis merely focused on specimens collected from limited locations. We could not determine the pathogenicity and transmission capability of the viruses carried by these ticks. Necessary investigations should be carried out in detail to characterize their epidemiological features and determine their potential threats to public health. Meanwhile, in our sequence-based query strategies, the presence of &#8220;dark contigs&#8221; which had no BLAST hits, may include novel, highly divergent viruses that are unrecognizable (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). We still anticipate that many of the viruses uncovered by our HTS analysis would be along the distribution ranges of their presumed natural cycle between vector ticks and host animals, and we also speculate that analysis of ticks from diverse geographical areas would reveal greater viral diversity with more emerged agents to be discovered in future. Thus, accurate viral taxonomy would allow more precise elucidation of tick-associated virus evolutionary relationships (<xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In summary, we metagenomically analyzed the virome of <italic toggle="yes">I. persulcatus, D. silvarum</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">H. concinna</italic>, three predominant tick species associated with pathogens transmitted in China. In addition to the exploration of viral diversity, our study also identified several tick-borne viruses with potential relevance for diseases of humans and livestock, for example, Tacheng uukuvirus, Sara tick-borne phlebovirus, Beiji <italic toggle="yes">orthonairovirus</italic>, Nuomin virus, and Jingmen tick virus. The novel viruses found in the present study, such as <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor</italic> pestivirus-like virus, taiga tick nigecruvirus, Mukawa virus, South Bay virus, and <italic toggle="yes">Scapularis ixovirus</italic>, do not allow reliable conclusions on the transmissibility issues merely depending on available genetic similarities to human pathogens. Our discoveries have paved a cornerstone for more detailed investigations and rational control strategies for tick-borne viral diseases in China.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The datasets presented in this study can be found in online repositories. The names of the repository/repositories and accession number(s) can be found in the article/<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s7"><title>Author contributions</title><p>YS contributed to the concept, design, and statistical analysis of the manuscript. TQ and MS were involved in the field survey. YS and HF were involved in the taxonomic identification of ticks. TQ and ZL were involved in the sequencing and molecular analysis of viruses. YS, TQ, MS, and MZ were involved in the analysis, interpretation, and drafting of the manuscript. All authors contributed to revising it critically for important intellectual content, final approval of the version to be published, and agreement to be accountable for all aspects of the manuscript in ensuring that questions related to the accuracy or integrity of any part of the manuscript are appropriately investigated and resolved.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank all the staff in the tick-borne disease department at Mudanjiang Forestry Central Hospital and Balin town Clinics of Zhanlantun City for their help with sample collections.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s9"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s10"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2022.1057977/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fvets.2022.1057977/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.docx" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guglielmone</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Apanaskevitch</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petney</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Estrada-Pena</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horak</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>The hard ticks of the world (Acari: Ixodida: Ixodidae)</source>. <publisher-loc>Heidelberg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name> (<year>2014</year>). p. <fpage>xiii</fpage> + 738. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-94-007-7497-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guglielmone</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Apanaskevich</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petney</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Estrada-Pe&#241;a</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horak</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The <italic toggle="yes">Argasidae, Ixodidae</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Nuttalliellidae</italic> (Acari: Ixodida) of the world: a list of valid species names</article-title>. <source>Zootaxa.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>2528</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11646/zootaxa.2528.1.1</pub-id>14570115</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pe&#241;alver</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Arillo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Delcl&#242;s</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Peris</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimaldi</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>And De La Fuente RP</article-title>. <source>Ticks parasitised feathered dinosaurs as revealed by Cretaceous amber assemblages Nat Commun.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1924</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-01550-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29233973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5727220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jongejan</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>F</surname></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Uilenberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The global importance of ticks</article-title>. <source>Parasitology</source>. (<year>2004</year>) <volume>129</volume>:<fpage>S3</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182004005967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15938502</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madison-Antenucci</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gebhardt</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kauffman</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Emerging tick-borne diseases</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>e00083</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00083-18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31896541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6941843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>LQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X-L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>H-W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Emerging tick-borne infections in mainland China: an increasing public health threat</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1467</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>79</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(15)00177-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26453241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4870934</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Piche-Ovares</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romero-Vega</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wagman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Troyo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of deforestation, urbanization, and changing land use patterns on the ecology of mosquito and tick-borne diseases in central America</article-title>. <source>J Med Entomol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>1546</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/insects13010020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35055864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8781098</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Fever with thrombocytopenia associated with a novel bunyavirus in China</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>364</volume>:<fpage>1523</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1010095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21410387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3113718</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Severe fever with thrombocytopenia syndrome, an emerging tick-borne zoonosis</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>148</volume>:<fpage>763</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>72</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(14)70718-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24837566</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A new segmented virus associated with human febrile illness in China</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>380</volume>:<fpage>2116</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1805068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31141633</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ejiri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murota</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of a novel thogotovirus isolated from <italic toggle="yes">Amblyomma testudinarium</italic> ticks in Ehime, Japan: a significant phylogenetic relationship to Bourbon virus</article-title>. <source>Virus Res.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>249</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2018.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29548745</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>WQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Large-scale comparative analyses of tick genomes elucidate their genetic diversity and vector capacities</article-title>. <source>Cell.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>182</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.07.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32814014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kodama</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tatemoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sashika</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A novel nairovirus associated with acute febrile illness in Hokkaido, Japan</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>5539</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-25857-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34545081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8452618</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuwata</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faizah</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Higa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Toyo virus, a novel member of the Kaisodi group in the genus <italic toggle="yes">Uukuvirus</italic> (family Phenuiviridae) found in <italic toggle="yes">Haemaphysalis formosensis</italic> ticks in Japan</article-title>. <source>Arch Virol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>166</volume>:<fpage>2751</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00705-021-05193-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34341873</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of a new <italic toggle="yes">orthonairovirus</italic> associated with human febrile illness in China</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>434</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>39</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-020-01228-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33603240</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monsalve-Arteagaid</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alonso-Sardon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bellido</surname><given-names>JLM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santiago</surname><given-names>MBV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lista</surname><given-names>MCV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aban</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Seroprevalence of Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever in humans in the world health organization European region: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>e0008094</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0008094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32119682</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7067482</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McMullan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Folk</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>MacNeil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Metcalfe</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A new phlebovirus associated with severe febrile illness in Missouri</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>367</volume>:<fpage>834</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1203378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22931317</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moureau</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charrel</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemasson</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gallian</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic characterization of tick-borne Flaviviruses: new insights into evolution, pathogenetic determinants and taxonomy</article-title>. <source>Virology</source>. (<year>2007</year>) <volume>361</volume>:<fpage>80</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2006.09.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17169393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cozens</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brackney</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Vector competence of human-biting ticks <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes scapularis, Amblyomma americanum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor variabilis</italic> for Powassan virus</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>466</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-021-04974-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34503550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8427896</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gaudreault</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Trujillo</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richt</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>African swine fever virus: an emerging DNA arbovirus</article-title>. <source>Front Vet Sci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>215</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2020.00215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32478103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7237725</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Unprecedented genomic diversity of RNA viruses in arthropods reveals the ancestry of negative-sense RNA viruses</article-title>. <source>Elife.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e05378</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.05378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25633976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4384744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pettersson</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bohlin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Eldholm</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brynildsrud</surname><given-names>OB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Characterizing the virome of <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes ricinus</italic> ticks from northern Europe</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-11439-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28883464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5589870</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Houldcroft</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beale</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breuer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical and biological insights from viral genome sequencing</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>183</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro.2016.182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28090077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7097211</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Economic insect fauna of China. Fasc 39. Acarina: Ixodidae.</source><publisher-loc>Beijing</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Science Press, Academia Sinica.</publisher-name> (<year>1991</year>). p. <fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>359</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loens</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ursi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Goossens</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ieven</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of NucliSens easyMAG for automated nucleic acid extraction from various clinical specimens</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>421</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.00894-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17166966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1829055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Folmer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hoeh</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vrijenhoek</surname><given-names>RDNA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>primers for amplification of mitochondrial cytochrome c oxidase subunit I from diverse metazoan invertebrates</article-title>. <source>Mol Mar Biol Biotechnol.</source> (<year>1994</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>294</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7881515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Machida</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Knowlton</surname><given-names>NPCR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>primers for metazoan nuclear 18S and 28S ribosomal DNA sequences</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e46180</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0046180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23049971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3458000</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolger</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Usadel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Trimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for Illumina sequence data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatic.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>2114</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24695404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4103590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>FO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ewels</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Afyounian</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schuster-Boeckler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>FelixKrueger /TrimGalore: v0, 6.7.</source> (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grabherr</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yassour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amit</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-Seq data without a reference genome</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol.</source> (<year>1883</year>) <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>644</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.1883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3571712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Papanicolaou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yassour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grabherr</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blood</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>De novo transcript sequence reconstruction from RNA-seq using the Trinity platform for reference generation and analysis</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1494</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>512</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2013.084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23845962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3875132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burland</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>DNASTAR's Lasergene sequence analysis software</article-title>. <source>Methods Mol Biol.</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>132</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1385/1-59259-192-2:71</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10547832</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>357</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3322381</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thorvaldsd&#243;ttir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mesirov</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Integrative Genomics Viewer (IGV): high-performance genomics data visualization and exploration</article-title>. <source>Briefings Bioinform</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>178</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bib/bbs017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22517427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3603213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>LX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Tick virome diversity in Hubei Province, China, and the influence of host ecology</article-title>. <source>Virus Evolut</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ve/veab089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34804590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8599308</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cram</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fuhrman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Accurate genome relative abundance estimation based on shotgun metagenomic reads</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e2799</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0027992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22162995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3232206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Standley</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>MAFFT multiple sequence alignment software version 7: Improvements in performance and usability</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>E30</volume>:<fpage>772</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mst010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23329690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3603318</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Capella-Gutierrez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silla-Martinez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gabaldon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>trimAl: a tool for automated alignment trimming in large-scale phylogenetic analyses</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1972</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2712344</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Darriba</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taboada</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Doallo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>ProtTest 3: fast selection of best-fit models of protein evolution</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1164</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21335321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5215816</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dufayard</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lefort</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anisimova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hordijk</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>New algorithms and methods to estimate maximum-likelihood phylogenies: assessing the performance of PhyML 3.0</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>307</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sysbio/syq010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20525638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sameroff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tokarz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vucelja</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oleynik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boljfeti&#263; M&#8222; et</surname><given-names>al</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Virome of <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes ricinus, Dermacentor reticulatus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Haemaphysalis concinna</italic> ticks from Croatia</article-title>. <source>Viruses.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>929</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v14050929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35632671</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9146755</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sameroff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tokarz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oleynik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Che</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Viral diversity of tick species parasitizing cattle and dogs in Trinidad and Tobago</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>10421</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-46914-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31320705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6639388</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vasilakis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Divergent viruses discovered in arthropods and vertebrates revise the evolutionary history of the <italic toggle="yes">Flaviviridae</italic> and related viruses</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>90</volume>:<fpage>659</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>69</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.02036-15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26491167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4702705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hameed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tahir</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Luteovirus: insights into pathogenicity</article-title>. <source>Arch Virol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>159</volume>:<fpage>2853</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00705-014-2172-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25091739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tokarz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sameroff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez Leon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lipkin</surname><given-names>WI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Virome analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Amblyomma americanum, Dermacentor variabilis</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes scapularis</italic> ticks reveals novel highly divergent vertebrate and invertebrate viruses</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source>. <volume>88</volume>:<fpage>11480</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.01858-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25056893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4178814</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of a new chuvirus associated with febrile illness in China</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>434</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21203/rs.3.rs-104938/v1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33603240</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Metagenomic profiling of viruses associated with <italic toggle="yes">Rhipicephalus microplus</italic> ticks in Yunnan province, <italic toggle="yes">China</italic></article-title>. <source>Virol Sin</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>623</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>35</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12250-020-00319-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33400089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8379324</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Afonso</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amarasinghe</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>B&#225;nyai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>B&#224;o</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Basler</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bavari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Taxonomy of the order <italic toggle="yes">Mononegavirales</italic>: update 2016</article-title>. <source>Arch Virol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>161</volume>:<fpage>2351</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00705-016-2880-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27216929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4947412</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adkins</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alioto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alkhovsky</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Amarasinghe</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Anthony</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Taxonomic update of phylum Negarnaviricota (Riboviria: Orthornavirae), including the large orders <italic toggle="yes">Bunyavirales</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Mononegavirales</italic></article-title>. <source>Arch Virol</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>166</volume>:<fpage>3513</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00705-021-05143-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34463877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8627462</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Virome analysis of tick-borne viruses in Heilongjiang province, China</article-title>. <source>Ticks Tick Borne Dis.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>412</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ttbdis.2018.12.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30583876</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A new nairo-like virus associated with human febrile illness in China</article-title>. <source>Emerg Microbes Infect</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1200</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>08</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/22221751.2021.1936197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34044749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8212832</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Emerging phleboviruses</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion Virol</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coviro.2014.01.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24607799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4031632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pettersson</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ellstr&#246;m</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergstr&#246;m</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez-Acu&#241;a</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Circumpolar diversification of the Ixodes uriae tick virome</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>e1008759</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1008759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32745135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7425989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nibert</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ghabrial</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maiss</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lesker</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vainio</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ji&#257;ng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Taxonomic reorganization of family <italic toggle="yes">Partitiviridae</italic> and other recent progress in Partitivirus research</article-title>. <source>Virus Res.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>188</volume>:<fpage>128</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2014.04.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24768846</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bell-Sakyi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Emergence of human infection with Jingmen tick virus in China: A retrospective study</article-title>. <source>EBioMedicine</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>317</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ebiom.2019.04.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31003930</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6557783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>NZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Virome and blood meal-associated host responses in <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes persulcatus</italic> naturally fed on patients</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>728996</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.728996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35250897</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8891964</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Extensive diversity of RNA viruses in ticks revealed by metagenomics in northeastern China</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>e0011017</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.04.27.489762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36542659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9836300</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of tick-borne pathogens by metagenomic next-generation sequencing in <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor nuttalli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes persulcatus</italic> in Inner Mongolia, China</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>287</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-021-04740-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34044867</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8161991</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiley</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>B&#224;o</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Travassos da Rosa</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genomic characterization of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Nairovirus</italic> (Family <italic toggle="yes">Bunyaviridae</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Viruses</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>164</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v8060164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27294949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4926184</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang Y&#8222; et</surname><given-names>al</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Human Tacheng tick virus 2 infection, China, 2019</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>. 27:594. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid3201/191486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33496245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7853585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kajihara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nao</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mori-Kajihara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Muramatsu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>The unique phylogenetic position of a novel tick-borne phlebovirus ensures an ixodid origin of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Phlebovirus</italic></article-title>. <source>mSphere</source>. <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e00239</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSphere.00239-18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29898985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6001614</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>First Detection of Mukawa Virus in <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes persulcatus</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Haemaphysalis concinna</italic> in China</article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>791563</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.791563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35308357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8930188</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bente</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Forrester</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McAuley</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Whitehouse</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever: history, epidemiology, pathogenesis, clinical syndrome and genetic diversity</article-title>. <source>Antiviral Res.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>100</volume>:<fpage>159</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>89</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.antiviral.2013.07.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23906741</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Scholte</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Spengler</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ritter</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman-McCray</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harmon</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever virus nsm protein is dispensable for growth in vitro and disease in Ifnar-/- mice</article-title>. <source>Microorganisms</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>775</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms8050775</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32455700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7285326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woodson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neupane</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Exosomes serve as novel modes of tick-borne flavivirus transmission from arthropod to human cells and facilitates dissemination of viral RNA and proteins to the vertebrate neuronal cells</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>e1006764</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1006764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29300779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5754134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Longdon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The evolution, diversity, and host associations of rhabdoviruses</article-title>. <source>Virus Evolut.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ve/vev014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27774286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5014481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Redefining the invertebrate RNA virosphere</article-title>. <source>Nature.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>540</volume>:<fpage>539</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature20167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27880757</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>