<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9998488</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC9998488.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">9998488</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">9998488</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">36908514</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2023.1126266</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The life cycle of <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor nuttalli</italic> from the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau under laboratory conditions and detection of spotted fever group <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> spp.</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names initials="H">Hejia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1978538/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ai</surname><given-names initials="J">Jingkai</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names initials="M">Ming</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="J">Jixu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1075302/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yali</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/545649/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>State Key Laboratory of Plateau Ecology and Agriculture, Qinghai University</institution>, <addr-line>Xining</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>College of Agriculture and Animal Husbandry, Qinghai University</institution>, <addr-line>Xining</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Qinghai Provincial Key Laboratory of Pathogen Diagnosis for Animal Diseases and Green Technical Research for Prevention and Control, Qinghai University</institution>, <addr-line>Xining</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Calin Mircea Gherman, University of Agricultural Sciences and Veterinary Medicine of Cluj-Napoca, Romania</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Abdulaziz Alouffi, King Abdulaziz City for Science and Technology, Saudi Arabia; Remil Galay, University of the Philippines Los Ba&#241;os, Philippines</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Yali Sun &#9993; <email>yalisun@qhu.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Parasitology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">427755</issue-id><elocation-id>1126266</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>2</month><year>2023</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>11</day><month>03</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2024-05-02 20:25:24.007"><day>02</day><month>05</month><year>2024</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2023 Ma, Ai, Kang, Li and Sun.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Ma, Ai, Kang, Li and Sun</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-10-1126266.pdf"/><abstract><p><italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor nuttalli</italic> has been a focus of study because tick-borne pathogens have been widely identified in this tick from northern and southwestern China. The aim of this study was to characterize the life cycle of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> under laboratory conditions and to detect spotted fever group (SFG) <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> in the midgut and salivary glands of both field-collected and first laboratory generation adults. <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> ticks were collected in the field on the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau from March to April 2021 and their life cycle was studied under laboratory conditions. Tick identify was molecularly confirmed, and SFG <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> were detected in the midgut and salivary glands of males and females by PCR targeting different rickettsial genes. The results showed that the life cycle of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> under laboratory conditions was completed in an average of 86.1 days. High positivity of <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> spp. was detected in the midgut and salivary glands of both males (92.0%) and females (93.0%) of field-collected <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> ticks. However, a relatively lower positivity (4.0&#8211;6.0%) was detected in first laboratory generation adults. Furthermore, sequencing analysis showed that the <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> sequences obtained in this study shared 98.6 to 100% nucleotide identity with <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia slovaca</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia raoultii</italic> isolated from <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor</italic> spp. in China. Phylogenetic analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> spp. based on the <italic toggle="yes">gltA, ompA, ompB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sca4</italic> genes revealed that the <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> sequences obtained could be classified as belonging to <italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">R. raoultii</italic> clades. This study described for the first time the life cycle of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> from the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau under laboratory conditions. Two species of SFG <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> were detected in the midgut and salivary glands of males and females in both field-collected and first laboratory-generation adults of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic>. Our study provides new insights into pathogen detection in ticks in the Qinghai-Tibet Plateau, and the relationships among hosts, ticks, and pathogens.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor nuttalli</italic></kwd><kwd>life cycle</kwd><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic></kwd><kwd>molecular identification</kwd><kwd>Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by the Natural Science Foundation of Qinghai Province of China (Grant Number 2022-ZJ-940Q).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="6"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="61"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="6624"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Ticks are vectors transmitting a large number of pathogenic bacteria, protozoa, and viruses to humans and animals that cause serious diseases (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Species belonging to the genus <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor</italic> (Acari: Ixodidae), including <italic toggle="yes">D. marginatus, D. nuttalli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> are well known as vectors for a great variety of infectious pathogens (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Among <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> are widely distributed in northern China, Mongolia, and Russia (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> as a major vector for transmitting various diseases including tick-borne rickettsiosis, Q fever, anaplasmosis, and tick-borne encephalitis virus, has been reported in Europe and some countries in Asia (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). In China, it was highlighted because the genus <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> has been widely identified in <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> in northern and southwestern regions of the country (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>).</p><p>Tick-borne rickettsiosis, which is caused by species of spotted fever group (SFG) <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic>, poses a serious threat to the health of humans and animals (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). The SFG <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> species, including <italic toggle="yes">R. raoultii, R. slovaca, R. sibirica, R. conorii, R. rickettsii, R. heilongjiangensis, R. aeschlimannii, R. felis, R. massilia</italic>e, and <italic toggle="yes">R. monacensis</italic>, have been identified in ticks, humans, and animals in China (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Among them, <italic toggle="yes">R. raoultii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">R. heilongjiangensis</italic> were identified in tick vectors and humans, and are pathogenic factors of human rickettsiosis in China (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>).</p><p>The salivary glands and midgut in ticks, as specific and major barriers to efficient pathogen transmission, are the main factors influencing the acquisition, maintenance, colonization, and transmission of pathogens by ticks (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). The tick's salivary glands can transmit pathogens to the host during blood-feeding along with salivary secretions, and the midgut determines pathogen colonization and survival in ticks (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). The influences of salivary glands and the midgut on pathogen transmission and survival is not independent, rather there is a pathogenic life cycle: the salivary glands are infected by the ingestion of the infected host blood, the pathogens colonize and multiply after they are transported into the midgut along with the blood, pathogens are exchanged between the midgut and salivary glands, and the salivary glands transmit the pathogens to another host when the ticks blood-feed again (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Studies of the genus <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> in both the midgut and salivary glands of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> are limited. The aim of this study was to characterize the life cycle of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> under laboratory conditions, and to detect SFG <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> in the midgut and salivary glands of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> males and females in both field-collected and first laboratory-generation adults.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Sample collection of ticks</title><p>Adult ticks were collected on vegetation from 8 counties in Haidong city (102&#176;09&#8242;-102&#176;47&#8242; E and 36&#176;16&#8242;-36&#176;40&#8242; N, average elevation of more than 2,500 m above sea level) of Qinghai Province (89&#176;35&#8211;103&#176;04&#8242; E and 31&#176;36&#8242;-39&#176;19&#8242;N) on the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau (73&#176;19&#8242;-104&#176;47&#8242; E and 26&#176;00&#8242;-39&#176;47&#8242; N) in northwestern China from March to April 2021 (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). All ticks were placed in sterile glass bottles, sent to Qinghai University within one day, and reared in an incubator at 25&#8211;30&#176;C and 60&#8211;90% humidity.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Map of the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau area and Qinghai Province showing the sampling area in this study.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1126266-g0001.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Morphological identification of tick species and laboratory-rearing of ticks</title><p>Microscopy identification of tick species and sex was performed at Qinghai University. After morphological identification (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>), 200 males and 200 females of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> were selected for laboratory rearing.</p><p>To characterize the life-cycle of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic>, New Zealand white rabbits (specific-pathogen-free, female, 9-weeks-old, purchased from Yifengda, Xi'an, China) housed in the animal facility of Qinghai University at a temperature of 25 &#177; 2&#176;C and humidity of 40% under controlled lighting (i.e., period of light from 6:00 to 19:00 h) were used to feed the adult ticks. After a few days, engorged ticks were weighed, placed in a sterile glass bottle, and reared in an incubator at 25 &#177; 2&#176;C and 80% humidity. After tick eggs were laid and hatched, a total of 500 larvae were allowed to refeed on the ears of rabbits within 3&#8211;4 days after hatching all eggs. The engorged ticks were collected for incubation until molting as nymphs and then allowed to feed on the rabbit ears again within 12&#8211;14 days after molting all larvae. During these periods, the processes of egg laying, hatching, and molting and the viability of the ticks were regularly observed. All animal procedures were carried out according to the ethical guidelines of Qinghai University (2020017 and SL-2022007).</p></sec><sec><title>DNA extraction and molecular characterization of ticks</title><p>In this study, after morphological identification of the field-collected <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic>, we randomly selected five females and males to extract DNA for molecular identification of ticks. And for the first-laboratory generation, we also randomly selected five males and five females for molecular identification. DNA from the field-collected and first-laboratory generation adult males and females was extracted using the QIAamp DNA Mini Kit (QIAGEN, Germany) according to the manufacturer's manual. The DNA concentration was determined using a NanoDrop 2000 (Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA), and the DNA was stored at&#8722;80&#176;C until further use. To further confirm the tick species, PCRs based on the 12S ribosomal RNA (12S rRNA), 16S ribosomal RNA (16S rRNA), cytochrome c oxidase subunit I (<italic toggle="yes">COI</italic>), and internal transcribed spacer 2 (<italic toggle="yes">ITS2</italic>) genes were conducted, respectively. All primers are listed in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The PCR assay volume was 10 &#956;l including 2 &#956;l of DNA, 0.5 &#956;l of each forward and reverse primer (100 &#956;M), 0.2 &#956;l of deoxyribonucleotide triphosphate (200 &#956;M, New England BioLab, USA), 1 &#956;l of 10&#215; ThermoPol Reaction Buffer (New England BioLab, USA), 0.1 &#956;l of Taq polymerase (0.5 U, New England BioLab, USA) and enough double-distilled water to reach a final volume of 10 &#956;l. Double-distilled water was used as a negative control and <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> DNA stored in our laboratory was used as a positive control.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Oligonucleotide primers used in this study.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Organism</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Target gene</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Primer sequence (5<sup>&#8242;</sup>-3<sup>&#8242;</sup>)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Amplification size (bp)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Annealing temperature(&#176;C)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Reference</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="8" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor</italic>. spp</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">12S rRNA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAACTAGGATTAGATACCCT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">386</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AATGAGAGCGACGGGCGATGT</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">16S rRNA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATGAAAATCTTTAAATTGCTG</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">475</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCTCATTCTC ATCGGTCT</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">COI</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGAATAGAACTTAGCCAACCT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,210</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AATAACGACGGGGTATTCCT</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">ITS2</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TCCGTCGACTCGTTTTGACC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,042</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GGATAC ATCGCTTTCGCCCAT</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="8" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic>. spp</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">ompA</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCTTTATTCACCACCTCAAC</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209/212</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRATCACCACCGTAAGTAAAT</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">ompB</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAACAATAATCAAGGTACTGT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">812</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TACTTCCGGTTACAGCAAAGT</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">gltA</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCAAGTATCGGTGAGGATGTAAT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">401</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GCTTCCTTAAAATTCAATAAATCAGGAT</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">sca4</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CGATGGTAGCATTAAAAGCT</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">623</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTTGCTTTTCAGCAATATCAC</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Detection and identification of SFG <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic></title><p>To identify SFG <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> in the midgut and salivary glands in both field-collected and first-laboratory generation males and females of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> in the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau area, organ DNA from 100 original males, 100 original females, 100 first-laboratory generation males and 116 first-laboratory generation females chosen randomly was extracted and screened using previously established PCR assays based on the citrate synthase gene (<italic toggle="yes">gltA</italic>). To further confirm SFG <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> species, all samples positive for the <italic toggle="yes">gltA</italic> gene were tested for the outer membrane protein A (<italic toggle="yes">ompA</italic>) gene, outer membrane protein B (<italic toggle="yes">ompB</italic>) gene, and surface cell antigen 4 (<italic toggle="yes">sca4</italic>) gene. All primers for the four genes are listed in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The PCRs were performed as described above.</p></sec><sec><title>Sequence analysis</title><p>For the confirmation of ticks and detected pathogens, at least one positive sample of each tissue per sex was selected for sequencing and molecular characterization. PCR products of the positive samples were purified using a QIAquick Gel Extraction Kit (QIAGEN, Germany). Purified PCR products was cloned into <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> DH5&#945; using the PMDTM 19-T Vector Cloning Kit (TaKaRa, Japan). At least three positive clones were sequenced by Sangon Biotech (Shanghai) Co., Ltd. The obtained sequences were confirmed by a BLASTn search in GenBank.</p></sec><sec><title>Phylogenetic analyses</title><p>Phylogenetic trees were constructed using the maximum likelihood statistical method and bootstrap analysis with 500 replications in MEGA7: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis version 7.0 for larger datasets (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The chi-squared test was used to compare proportions of detected sample positivity in different regions and among different animals <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> Prism 8 software. Observed differences were considered to be statistically significant when the resulting <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-values were &lt;0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Morphological identification and molecular characterization of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic></title><p>In this study, <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> ticks were preliminarily morphologically identified. As shown in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>, the dorsal view of the female <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> is about 5.1 &#215; 3.0 mm with an elliptical scutum of the specimen, which only occupies a small part of the front of the body (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>). And the genital pore of the female has a wing-like protrusion (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>). The male <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> is about 5.8 &#215; 4.0 mm. Its scutum on the back almost covers the entire back of the body and has a lighter enamel color on its back (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C</xref>). In the ventral view of male <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic>, the paraproct is very obvious (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2D</xref>). Moreover, the capitulum of the male and female <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> is rectangular and the overall color is dark brown. The anal groove presents an inverted &#8220;U&#8221; shape in front of the anus.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Morphological characterization of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic>. The dorsal view and ventral view of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic>. All figures used the same ruler (1 mm). <bold>(A)</bold> Dorsal view of female. <bold>(B)</bold> Ventral view of female. <bold>(C)</bold> Dorsal view of male. <bold>(D)</bold> Ventral view of male.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1126266-g0002.jpg"/></fig><p>Furthermore, the species identify was confirmed by molecular analysis of the PCR assay based on the 12S rRNA, 16S rRNA, <italic toggle="yes">COI</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">ITS2</italic> genes. The sequencing of positive samples showed that the length of the obtained tick sequences varied from 386 to 1,210 bp (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The BLASTn analysis of two <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> 12S rRNA sequences in this study showed identities ranging from 98.7 to 99.5% with reference sequences in China from GenBank (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The 16S rRNA sequences of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> obtained in this study showed 99.8% identity with each other and 98.2&#8211;99.0% identity with the sequences from <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor</italic> spp. in China. Sequence analysis revealed that the nucleotide sequence of <italic toggle="yes">COI</italic> in this study shared 99.0 to 99.7% identity with <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor</italic> spp. sequences from China and 99.0&#8211;99.7% identity with <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor</italic> spp. sequences from other countries from GenBank. Moreover, the BLASTn analysis of the <italic toggle="yes">ITS2</italic> gene revealed that the three sequences obtained in this study had 98.7 to 99.2% identity with each other, and 97.5&#8211;99.2% identity with the sequences of <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor</italic> spp. from China. Additionally, the phylogenetic analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor</italic> spp. based on the 12S rRNA, 16S rRNA, <italic toggle="yes">COI</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">ITS2</italic> genes revealed that tick sequences obtained from this study grouped with the <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> clades (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor</italic> spp. sequences obtained in this study.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Obtained sequences</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<bold>The closest BLASTn match</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Organism</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Target gene</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Accession number</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Length (bp)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Identity (%)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Species</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Accession number (host, country)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="8" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor</italic> spp.</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">12S rRNA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP376735">OP376735</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">386</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.2</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MF002575.1">MF002575.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor nuttalli</italic>, China)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP376736">OP376736</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">386</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MF002575.1">MF002575.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor nuttalli</italic>, China)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">16S rRNA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP376732">OP376732</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">475</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="KT764942.1">KT764942.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor nuttalli</italic>, China)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP376733">OP376733</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">475</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="KT764942.1">KT764942.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor nuttalli</italic>, China)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">COI</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP394118">OP394118</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.210</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OM368307.1">OM368307.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor nuttalli</italic>, China)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">ITS2</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP376722">OP376722</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,042</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.6</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MK027319.1">MK027319.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor nuttalli</italic>, China)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP376723">OP376723</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,039</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.5</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MW477811.1">MW477811.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor nuttalli</italic>, China)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP376724">OP376724</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,045</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="KF241877.1">KF241877.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor nuttalli</italic>, Russia)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Molecular phylogenetic analysis by the maximum likelihood method based on the 12S rRNA, 16S rRNA, <italic toggle="yes">COI</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">ITS2</italic> genes of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic>. The sequences obtained in this study are shown in bold font. The numbers at the nodes represent bootstrap support values.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1126266-g0003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Laboratory-rearing of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic></title><p>For laboratory-rearing of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> and detection of <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> colonization in first-laboratory generation <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic>, 200 <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> males and 200 females were randomly chosen to generate next-generation adults by blood-biting in rabbits and rearing in an incubator at 25 &#177; 2&#176;C and 80% humidity. The results showed that the first laboratory-generation of adults was completed within an average of 86.1 days (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>; <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The average weight of engorged females was 656.0 mg, which was 74.5 times the weight of unfed females (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). No significant difference in average weight was found between field-collected and first-laboratory generation female adults, while the first-generation males produced in the laboratory weighed 2 mg more than the original male adults (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The laboratory-rearing of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic>. All figures used the same ruler (1 mm). <bold>(A)</bold> Prophase of eggs. <bold>(B)</bold> Metaphase of eggs. <bold>(C)</bold> Anaphase of eggs. <bold>(D)</bold> Larva. <bold>(E)</bold> Nymphs. <bold>(F)</bold> Female and male adults.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1126266-g0004.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T3" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The durations of various developmental stages of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic>.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Developmental stage</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Period</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Number of ticks tested</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>Duration (days)</bold>
</th></tr><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Range</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mean &#177;SD</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Egg</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incubation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#8211;14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.40 &#177; 2.76</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Larva</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-feeding</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#8211;4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.71 &#177; 0.45</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feeding</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#8211;7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.40 &#177; 0.99</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-molting</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#8211;8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.29 &#177; 0.45</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Nymph</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-feeding</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#8211;6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.43 &#177; 0.86</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feeding</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#8211;10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.14 &#177; 1.25</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-molting</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#8211;8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.40 &#177; 0.66</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Adult female</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-feeding</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8&#8211;11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.16 &#177; 0.88</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feeding</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11&#8211;12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.36 &#177; 0.48</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-oviposition</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#8211;9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.96 &#177; 2.41</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oviposition</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9&#8211;18</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.80 &#177; 2.07</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>SD, standard deviation.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T4" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Changes of body weight of larva, nymph, and adult <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> before and after feeding.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Developmental stage</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Number of ticks</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Unfed (mg) (Mean &#177;SD)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Engorged (mg) (Mean &#177;SD)</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Weight ratio (engorge/unfed)</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" style="background-color:#dee1e1" rowspan="1">
<bold>Original</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult male</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.48 &#177; 0.37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.12 &#177; 0.41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult female</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.80 &#177; 0.62</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">656.00 &#177; 29.77</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.50</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="5" style="background-color:#dee1e1" rowspan="1">
<bold>First generation under laboratory conditions</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Larva</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05 &#177; 0.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 &#177; 0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nymph</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38 &#177; 0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.83 &#177; 2.39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.34</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult male</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.48 &#177; 0.45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.05 &#177; 0.66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adult female</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.68 &#177; 0.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">283.28 &#177; 89.79</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.97</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>SD, standard deviation.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Identification of SFG <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> in the midgut and salivary glands in field-collected and first-laboratory generation <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> males and females</title><p>In this study, 100 field-collected <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> males and 100 females collected were chosen randomly to determine <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> colonization. For first laboratory-generation ticks, 100 males and 116 females were screened by randomly selecting one or two males or females for each female mother tick. SFG <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> in the midgut and salivary glands of the adult <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> males and females was determined using a PCR assay based on the <italic toggle="yes">gltA</italic> gene. As shown in <xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>, high colonization rates of <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> were found in both the midgut and the salivary glands of both field-collected <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> males and females, and no positivity was found in single tissue colonization. However, low rates (4.0&#8211;6.0%) of <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> colonization in the midgut or salivary glands of first-laboratory generation <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> were detected (<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). The positivity rates of SFG <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> in the same generation of ticks showed no significant difference depending on either sex and organ.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Infection rate (%) of SFG <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> spp. in field-collected and first-laboratory generation adults of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> in the QTPA.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic>
</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="12" rowspan="1"><bold>Infection rate (%, 95% CI) in field-collected and first-laboratory generation of</bold>
<italic toggle="yes"><bold>D. nuttalli</bold></italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>Field-collected</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="6" rowspan="1">
<bold>First-laboratory generation</bold>
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>Male (</bold><italic toggle="yes"><bold>n</bold></italic> = <bold>100)</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>Female (</bold><italic toggle="yes"><bold>n</bold></italic> = <bold>100)</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>Male (</bold><italic toggle="yes"><bold>n</bold></italic> = <bold>100)</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>Female (</bold><italic toggle="yes"><bold>n</bold></italic> = <bold>116)</bold></td></tr><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Single SG</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Single MG</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SG</bold> + <bold>MG</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Single SG</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Single MG</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SG</bold> + <bold>MG</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Single SG</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Single MG</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SG</bold> + <bold>MG</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Single SG</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Single MG</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SG</bold> + <bold>MG</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (92.0, 86.7&#8211;97.3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (93.0, 88.0&#8211;98.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (4.0, 0.2&#8211;7.8)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (6.0, 1.3&#8211;10.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (4.3, 0.6&#8211;8.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (4.3, 0.6&#8211;8.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (8.0, 2.7&#8211;13.3)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (7.0, 2.0&#8211;12.0)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 (96.0, 92.2&#8211;99.8)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (94.0, 89.3&#8211;98.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111 (95.7, 92.0&#8211;99.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111 (95.7, 92.0&#8211;99.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">/</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>SG, salivary gland. MG, midgut. 95% CI, 95% confidence interval. /, no analysis.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>All positive samples for the <italic toggle="yes">gltA</italic> gene were confirmed by PCR of the <italic toggle="yes">ompA, ompB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sca4</italic> genes, and the GenBank numbers of these sequences with lengths ranging from 209 to 813 bp are listed in <xref rid="T6" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>. BLASTn analysis of the four genes showed that the <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> spp. detected in this study had 98.6 to 100% identities with either <italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">R. raoultii</italic> sequences from <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor</italic> spp. from China. The phylogenetic analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> sequences based on the <italic toggle="yes">gltA, ompA, ompB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sca4</italic> genes revealed that the sequences obtained from <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> in this study grouped with the <italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">R. raoultii</italic> clades of isolates from <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor</italic> spp., <italic toggle="yes">Homo sapiens</italic>, animals and other tick species from China, Russia, France, Pakistan, the United States, the Netherlands, Turkey, Romania, Austria, and Italy (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T6" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> spp. sequences obtained in this study.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Obtained sequences</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">
<bold>The closest BLASTn match</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Organism</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Target gene</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Accession number</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Length (bp)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Identity (%)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Species</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Accession number (host, country)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="19" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">ompA</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP375089">OP375089</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. raoultii</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MN394801.1">MN394801.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">yak</italic>, China)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP375090">OP375090</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MN394806.1">MN394806.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">yak</italic>, China)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP375091">OP375091</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MN388785.1">MN388785.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Pipistrellus pipistrellus</italic>, China)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="7" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">gltA</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP375098">OP375098</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">401</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. raoultii</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MK304547.1">MK304547.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor reticulatus</italic>, Russia)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP375099">OP375099</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">401</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MK304547.1">MK304547.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor reticulatus</italic>, Russia)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP375100">OP375100</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">401</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MK304547.1">MK304547.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor reticulatus</italic>, Russia)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP375101">OP375101</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">401</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MK304547.1">MK304547.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor reticulatus</italic>, Russia)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP375102">OP375102</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">401</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MK304547.1">MK304547.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor reticulatus</italic>, Russia)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP375103">OP375103</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">401</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MF002529.1">MF002529.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor marginatus</italic>, China)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP375104">OP375104</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">401</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MF002529.1">MF002529.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor marginatus</italic>, China)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">ompB</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP375092">OP375092</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">812</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. raoultii</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MF002526.1">MF002526.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor nuttalli</italic>, China)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP375093">OP375093</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">812</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. raoultii</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MF002526.1">MF002526.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor nuttalli</italic>, China)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP375094">OP375094</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">812</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MF002539.1">MF002539.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor marginatus</italic>, China)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP375095">OP375095</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">813</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MF002539.1">MF002539.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor marginatus</italic>, China)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP375096">OP375096</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">812</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.9</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MF002539.1">MF002539.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor marginatus</italic>, China)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP375097">OP375097</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">812</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MF002539.1">MF002539.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor marginatus</italic>, China)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">sca4</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP375105">OP375105</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">624</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. raoultii</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="KP768191.1">KP768191.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor reticulatus</italic>, Ukraine)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP375106">OP375106</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">624</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. raoultii</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="CP098324.1">CP098324.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor silvarum</italic>, China)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="OP375107">OP375107</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">624</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MN581997.1">MN581997.1</ext-link> (<italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor</italic> sp., Pakistan)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F5" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Molecular Phylogenetic analysis by maximum likelihood method based on the <italic toggle="yes">gltA, ompA, ompB</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">sca4</italic> genes of spotted fever group <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic>. The sequences obtained in this study are shown in bold font. The numbers at the nodes represent bootstrap support values.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-10-1126266-g0005.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The current sampling sites located in Qinghai Province on the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau are over 2,500 m above sea level and have a unique natural ecosystem with a cold climate and oxygen deficiency. Some organisms, such as the yak (<italic toggle="yes">Bos grunniens</italic>) and tick vectors, can survive under the extreme environmental conditions of Qinghai Province. Chen et al. (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>) reported that at least 25 species of six tick genera have been recorded in Qinghai Province, and the most common species were <italic toggle="yes">Haemaphysalis qinghaiensis, D. nuttalli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum</italic> (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). In this study, the collected <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> ticks in this province were molecularly confirmed, and found to have a life cycle with an average of 86.1 days under laboratory conditions. Furthermore, the present study detected two species of SFG <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> that grouped with <italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">R. raoultii</italic> in both the salivary glands and midgut of field-collected and first-laboratory generation males and females.</p><p>The life-cycle of several tick species including <italic toggle="yes">D. everestianus, Ha. qinghaiensis, Hyalomma scupense, Hy. asiaticum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Hy. rufipes</italic> under laboratory conditions and <italic toggle="yes">D. silvarum, Ha. tibetensis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Ha. concinna</italic> under field conditions, has been characterized in China (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). These studies showed that the average period of one female tick life-cycle of under laboratory conditions was ranged from 110.2 to 179.0 days, while it ranged from 121.0 to 177.8 days under field conditions (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). However, the average periods showed seasonal differences (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> is widely distributed in northern China, including the sampling sites in Qinghai Province in this study (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Here, an average life cycle of 86.1 days (ranging from 65.0 to 107.0 days) of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> under laboratory conditions was found, indicating a shorter length of time than previously reported (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). This may be because the ticks were collected in March and April which is the blood-feeding period in the natural cycle, and ticks may retain wild habits during the first cycle in the laboratory. These results suggest the specificity of the life cycle of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> compared with other hard ticks, especially in terms of the duration and the morphology of different life stages.</p><p>The ubiquity and high proportions of pathogens in the salivary glands and midgut of ticks collected in the field were determined by the species of pathogens and the presence of infectious host blood. The present study detected SFG <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> in both the salivary glands and midgut of males and females, with high infection rates in the original <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> adults. This suggests that this tick-borne pathogen could be well adapted to the different environmental conditions of both the salivary glands and the midgut in <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> males and females, which is consistent with the finding of previous studies that SFG <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> was most frequent in <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> ticks in Qinghai Province, northwestern China (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Subsequently, the identification of <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> was performed in the first-laboratory generation adults of <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic>. However, the result in contrast with that in the original ticks, in which SFG <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> was detected in either the salivary glands or the midgut in males and females, with low positivity rates. This indicates that the acquisition, maintenance, colonization, and transmission of SFG <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> by <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> ticks cannot be separated from the blood contributions of an effective host. Moreover, although our study simulated the natural environment of ticks, it is possible that subtle environmental changes could influence the life-cycle of ticks, as well as the colonization and exchange of pathogens in tick salivary glands or midguts (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>). Furthermore, the positivity rates of SFG <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> in the same generation of ticks showed no significant difference between sexes or organs, suggesting that this pathogen strongly colonizes in both the salivary glands and the midgut in <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> males and females.</p><p>Furthermore, our study provides new evidence of DNA-based detection of SFG <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> pathogens in <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> ticks in the sampling areas. The sequencing and phylogenetic analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> spp. based on the <italic toggle="yes">gltA, ompA, ompB</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">sca4</italic> genes revealed that the sequences obtained could be classified into two groups, representing two different rickettsial species, <italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">R. raoultii</italic>. Previous studies reported that SFG rickettsiae including <italic toggle="yes">R. aeschlimannii, R. conorii, R. sibirica, R. massiliae</italic>, Candidatus <italic toggle="yes">R. barbariae, R. raoultii</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic>, were detected in field-collected <italic toggle="yes">Ha. qinghaiensis, D. marginatus, D. abaensis, D. silvarum, Ixodes crenulatus, Rhipicephalus turanicus</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> in northwestern China (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Consistent with our findings in this study, it is common to detect <italic toggle="yes">R. raoultii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">R. slovaca</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> ticks in previous studies (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). The two <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> species were identified as pathogenic factors of human rickettsiosis in tick vectors and humans (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>, <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>), and importantly, <italic toggle="yes">R. raoultii</italic> has been detected in humans in China (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). These results suggest that humans and animals are susceptible to the pathogens due to exposure to <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> tick vectors in the sampling areas.</p><p>In conclusion, this study is the first to characterize the life cycle of collected <italic toggle="yes">D. nuttalli</italic> in the field from the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau under laboratory conditions, and two species of SFG <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> were identified in the midgut and salivary glands of males and females of both field-collected and first-laboratory generation adults. However, there are differences between laboratory conditions and natural conditions that impact tick survival and may influence the life cycle of laboratory-reared ticks. Moreover, the seasonal diapause of ticks must be considered because it may affect their life cycle and pathogen colonization under laboratory conditions. Our study provides new insights into the pathogen colonization of ticks on the Qinghai-Tibetan Plateau, and the relationships among hosts, ticks and pathogens.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s5"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The datasets presented in this study can be found in online repositories. The names of the repository/repositories and accession number(s) can be found in the article/supplementary material.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s6"><title>Author contributions</title><p>YS: conceptualization, data curation, formal analysis, funding acquisition, resources, writing-original draft, and writing-review and editing. HM and JA: data curation, formal analysis, and investigation. MK: resources and writing-review and editing. JL: conceptualization, writing-original draft, and writing-review and editing. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s8"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madison-Antenucci</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gebhardt</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kauffman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Emerging tick-borne diseases</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>e00083</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00083-18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31896541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6941843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan ZW Ji</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mapping ticks and tick-borne pathogens in China</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1075</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-21375-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33597544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7889899</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kulakova</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khasnatinov</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sidorova</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adel'shin</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belikov</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular identification and phylogeny of Dermacentor nuttalli (Acari: Ixodidae)</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>113</volume>:<fpage>1787</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-014-3824-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24604384</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Species delimitation of the <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor</italic> ticks based on phylogenetic clustering and niche modeling</article-title>. <source>PeerJ.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e6911</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.6911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31123639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6512763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia raoultii</italic>-like bacteria in <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor</italic> spp. ticks, Tibet, China</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1532</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid1809.120644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22931966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3437703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui YF Li</surname><given-names>BX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Investigation of <italic toggle="yes">Borrelia</italic> spp. in ticks (Acari: Ixodidae) at the border crossings between China and Russia in Heilongjiang province</article-title>. <source>China Asian Pac J Trop Med.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>459</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1995-7645(12)60078-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22575978</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Igolkina</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vysochina</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tikunov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pukhovskaya</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic variability of <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> spp. in dermacentor and haemaphysalis ticks from the Russian far east ticks</article-title>. <source>Tick Borne Dis.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1594</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>603</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ttbdis.2018.07.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30121164</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moumouni</surname><given-names>PFA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galon</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular detection of tick-borne pathogens harbored by ticks collected from livestock in the Xinjiang Uygur Autonomous Region, China</article-title>. <source>Ticks Tick Borne Dis.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>101478</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ttbdis.2020.101478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32723638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>von Fricken</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qurollo</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boldbaatar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lkhagvatseren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic diversity of <italic toggle="yes">Anaplasma</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Ehrlichia</italic> bacteria found in <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes</italic> ticks in Mongolia</article-title>. <source>Ticks Tick Borne Dis.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>101316</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ttbdis.2019.101316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31677968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yaxue</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hongtao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiuyue</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhixin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hongwei</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pengpeng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular detection of <italic toggle="yes">Anaplasma phagocytophilum</italic> in Ixodid ticks in Hebei province, China</article-title>. <source>Vector Borne Zoonotic Dis.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1323</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/vbz.2010.0253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21923254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khasnatinov</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liapunov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Manzarova</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kulakova</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrova</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Danchinova</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The diversity and prevalence of hard ticks attacking human hosts in Eastern Siberia (Russian Federation) with first description of invasion of non-endemic tick species</article-title>. <source>Parasitol Res.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>115</volume>:<fpage>501</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-015-4766-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26443685</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pukhovskaya</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morozova</surname><given-names>OV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vysochina</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belozerova</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bakhmetyeva</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zdanovskaya</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Tick-borne encephalitis virus in arthropod vectors in the Far East of Russia</article-title>. <source>Ticks Tick Borne Dis.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>824</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ttbdis.2018.01.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29555424</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kholodilov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Belova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Burenkova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Korotkov</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Romanova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Morozova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Ixodid ticks and tick-borne encephalitis virus prevalence in the South Asian part of Russia (Republic of Tuva)</article-title>. <source>Ticks Tick Borne Dis.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>959</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>69</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ttbdis.2019.04.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31103456</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cern&#253;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buyannemekh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Needham</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gankhuyag</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oyuntsetseg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Hard ticks and tick-borne pathogens in Mongolia-A review</article-title>. <source>Ticks Tick Borne Dis.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>101268</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ttbdis.2019.101268</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31471272</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aizezi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Coxiella burnetii</italic> is widespread in ticks (Ixodidae) in the Xinjiang areas of China</article-title>. <source>BMC Vet Res.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>317</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12917-020-02538-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32859190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7455992</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Identification of tick-borne pathogens by metagenomic next-generation sequencing in <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor nuttalli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes persulcatus</italic> in Inner Mongolia, China</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>287</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-021-04740-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34044867</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8161991</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zong</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lenz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Isolation of a spotted fever group rickettsia from a patient and related ecologic investigations in Xinjiang Uygur Autonomous Region of China</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol.</source> (<year>1987</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>628</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jcm.25.4.628-632.1987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3571471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC266048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>QH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Rickettsial and serologic evidence for prevalent spotted fever rickettsiosis in inner Mongolia</article-title>. <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg.</source> (<year>1987</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>615</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.1987.36.615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3578658</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Detection of spotted fever group <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">Haemaphysalis longicornis</italic> from Hebei province, China</article-title>. <source>J Parasitol.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>97</volume>:<fpage>960</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1645/GE-2751.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21506802</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diao</surname><given-names>XN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Extensive diversity of Rickettsiales bacteria in two species of ticks from China and the evolution of the Rickettsiales</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12862-014-0167-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25073875</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4236549</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of rickettsiae in ticks in northeastern China</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>498</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-016-1764-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27623998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5022169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kawabata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Spotted Fever Group Rickettsiae in Inner Mongolia, China, 2015-2016</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>2105</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2411.162094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30334715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6200000</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hornok</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Diversity of <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> species in border regions of northwestern China</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>634</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-018-3233-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30545379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6293579</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular prevalence of spotted fever group rickettsiae in ticks from Qinghai province, northwestern China</article-title>. <source>Infect Genet Evol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2017.10.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29107656</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular detection of spotted fever group rickettsiae in hard ticks, northern China</article-title>. <source>Transbound Emerg Dis.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>1587</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tbed.13184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30920159</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular evidence of the spotted fever group Rickettsiae in ticks from Yunnan province, southwest China</article-title>. <source>Exp Appl Acarol.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>80</volume>:<fpage>339</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>48</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-020-00467-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31925589</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang XL Li</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Distribution and molecular characterization of rickettsiae in ticks in Harbin area of northeastern China</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>e0008342</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0008342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32497120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7272007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>QC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>HZ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence of multiple tick-borne pathogens in various tick vectors in northeastern China</article-title>. <source>Vector Borne Zoonotic Dis.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>162</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/vbz.2020.2712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33347789</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gui</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu SY Yu</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Identification and genetic diversity analysis of <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor nuttalli</italic> within inner Mongolia, China</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>286</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-022-05387-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35934699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9358909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parola</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raoult</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ticks and tickborne bacterial diseases in humans: an emerging infectious threat</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>897</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>928</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/319347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11247714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parola</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paddock</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Socolovschi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Labruna</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mediannikov</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kernif</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Update on tick-borne rickettsioses around the world: a geographic approach</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>657</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>702</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00032-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24092850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3811236</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Satjanadumrong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stenos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Blacksell</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Diagnosis of spotted fever group <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> infections: the Asian perspective</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Infect.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>147</volume>:<fpage>e286</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0950268819001390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31587667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6805790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>First report of <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia felis</italic> in China</article-title>. <source>BMC Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>682</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-014-0682-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25510419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4297373</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Detection of spotted fever group <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsiae</italic> in ticks from Zhejiang province, China</article-title>. <source>Exp Appl Acarol.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>403</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-015-9880-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25633265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4322220</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>QQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The first detection of <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia aeschlimannii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia massiliae</italic> in <italic toggle="yes">Rhipicephalus turanicus</italic> ticks, in northwest China</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>631</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-015-1242-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26652857</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4675064</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>John Kelly</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cruz-Martinez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> in mosquitoes, Yangzhou, China</article-title>. <source>Emerg Microbes Infect.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e108</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emi.2016.107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27729642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5117729</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Human-pathogenic Anaplasma spp, and Rickettsia spp in animals in Xi'an, China</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e0006916</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0006916</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30419024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6258427</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia raoultii</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia sibirica</italic> in ticks from the long-tailed ground squirrel near the China-Kazakhstan border</article-title>. <source>Exp Appl Acarol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>425</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-019-00349-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30805816</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huo QB Ni</surname><given-names>XB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Human infections with <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia raoultii</italic>, China</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>866</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2005.130995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24750663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4012798</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ZD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Isolation and identification of <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia raoultii</italic> in human cases: a surveillance study in 3 medical centers in China</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>1109</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/cix917</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29069294</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Complete genome sequence of <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia heilongjiangensis</italic>, an emerging tick-transmitted human pathogen</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>193</volume>:<fpage>5564</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.05852-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21914880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3187448</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lejal</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moutailler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>&#352;imo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vayssier-Taussat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pollet</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Tick-borne pathogen detection in midgut and salivary glands of adult <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes ricinus</italic></article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>152</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-019-3418-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30940200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6444572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bacellar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos-Silva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Formosinho</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gr&#225;cio</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Franca</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ultrastructural study of the infection process of <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia conorii</italic> in the salivary glands of the vector tick <italic toggle="yes">Rhipicephalus sanguineus</italic></article-title>. <source>Vector Borne Zoonotic Dis</source>. (<year>2002</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>77</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/15303660260613738</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12737546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Popov</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Korenberg</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nefedova</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kovalevskii</surname><given-names>YV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Ultrastructural evidence of the ehrlichial developmental cycle in naturally infected <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes persulcatus</italic> ticks in the course of coinfection with <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic>, Borrelia, and a flavivirus</article-title>. <source>Vector Borne Zoonotic Dis.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>699</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>716</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/vbz.2007.0148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18171109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Narasimhan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rajeevan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>YO</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Heisig</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Gut microbiota of the tick vector <italic toggle="yes">Ixodes scapularis</italic> modulate colonization of the Lyme disease spirochete</article-title>. <source>Cell Host Microbe.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>58</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2013.12.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24439898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3905459</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Economic insect fauna of China</source>. Fasc 39 Acari: Ixodidae. Science Press, Beijing. (<year>1991</year>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Adjou Moumouni</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thekisoe</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic characterization of tick-borne pathogens in ticks infesting cattle and sheep from three south African provinces</article-title>. <source>Ticks Tick Borne Dis.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>875</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ttbdis.2019.04.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31010732</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maggi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Diniz</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hegarty</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Breitschwerdt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of conventional and real-time PCR assays for detection and differentiation of spotted fever group <italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia</italic> in dog blood</article-title>. <source>Vet Microbiol.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>129</volume>:<fpage>294</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>303</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2007.11.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18226476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hazihan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rizabek</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Askar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gulzhan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular detection of spotted fever group rickettsiae in ticks parasitizing pet dogs in Shihezi city, northwestern China</article-title>. <source>Exp Appl Acarol.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>77</volume>:<fpage>73</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-018-00337-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30649634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6341051</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moumouni</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Efstratiou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>First molecular detection of tick-borne pathogens in dogs from Jiangxi, China</article-title>. <source>J Vet Med Sci.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>79</volume>:<fpage>248</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>54</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.16-0484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27890889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5326926</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Tamura K. MEGA7: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 70 for bigger datasets</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>33</volume>:<fpage>1870</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msw054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27004904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8210823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Ticks (acari: ixodoidea: argasidae, ixodidae) of China</article-title>. <source>Exp Appl Acarol.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>393</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>404</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-010-9335-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20101443</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The life cycle of <italic toggle="yes">Hyalomma asiaticum</italic> kozlovi Olenev, 1931 (Acari: Ixodidae) under laboratory conditions</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol.</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>160</volume>:<fpage>134</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2008.10.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19062189</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The life cycle and biological characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor silvarum</italic> Olenev (Acari: Ixodidae) under field conditions</article-title>. <source>Vet Parasitol.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>168</volume>:<fpage>323</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetpar.2009.11.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20006442</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Life cycle of <italic toggle="yes">Dermacentor everestianus</italic> hirst, 1926 (Acari: Ixodidae) under laboratory conditions</article-title>. <source>Korean J Parasitol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>193</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3347/kjp.2017.55.2.193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28506042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5450962</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The life cycle of <italic toggle="yes">Hyalomma rufipes</italic> (Acari: Ixodidae) under laboratory conditions</article-title>. <source>Exp Appl Acarol.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>85</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-011-9490-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21913002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The life cycle and occurrence of <italic toggle="yes">Haemaphysalis concinna</italic> (Acari: Ixodidae) under field conditions</article-title>. <source>Ticks Tick Borne Dis.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>887</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ttbdis.2014.07.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25113978</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of the life cycle of the tick <italic toggle="yes">Haemaphysalis tibetensis</italic> under field conditions in Qinghai-Tibet plateau</article-title>. <source>Exp Appl Acarol.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>107</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-016-0020-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26873779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The life cycle of <italic toggle="yes">Haemaphysalis qinghaiensis</italic> (Acari: Ixodidae) ticks under laboratory conditions</article-title>. <source>Exp Appl Acarol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>493</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>500</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-012-9617-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23111808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chuai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The life cycle of <italic toggle="yes">Hyalomma scupense</italic> (Acari: Ixodidae) under laboratory conditions</article-title>. <source>Ticks Tick Borne Dis.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>102019</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ttbdis.2022.102019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35963189</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rehacek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Rickettsia slovaca</italic>, the organism and its ecology</article-title>. <source>Acta SC Nat Brno.</source> (<year>1984</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>