<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Vet Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2864</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">fvets</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Vet. Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Veterinary Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2297-1769</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media SA</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9234663</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC9234663.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">9234663</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">9234663</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35769322</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fvets.2022.906973</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Veterinary Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Characterization of the Lytic Phage Flora With a Broad Host Range Against Multidrug-Resistant <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> and Evaluation of Its Efficacy Against <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> Biofilm Formation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names initials="L">Liming</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/992613/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names initials="Y">Yaxian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names initials="W">Wen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#8224;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names initials="R">Rui</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names initials="C">Chenghua</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/305124/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>State Key Laboratory for Quality and Safety of Agro-products, Ningbo University</institution>, <addr-line>Ningbo</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Collaborative Innovation Center for Zhejiang Marine High-Efficiency and Healthy Aquaculture, Ningbo University</institution>, <addr-line>Ningbo</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Clinical Laboratory, The First People's Hospital of Yunnan Province</institution>, <addr-line>Kunming</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Department of Clinical Laboratory, The Affiliated Hospital of Kunming University of Science and Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Kunming</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Department of Rheumatology Immunology, The First People's Hospital of Hefei</institution>, <addr-line>Hefei</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><sup>6</sup><institution>Laboratory for Marine Fisheries Science and Food Production Processes, Qingdao National Laboratory for Marine Science and Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Qingdao</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Lixing Huang, Jimei University, China</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Xu-Jie Zhang, Huazhong Agricultural University, China; Yinnan Mu, Fujian Agriculture and Forestry University, China</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Chenghua Li <email>lichenghua@nbu.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Veterinary Infectious Diseases, a section of the journal Frontiers in Veterinary Science</p></fn><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn002"><p>&#8224;These authors have contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>6</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">400313</issue-id><elocation-id>906973</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>3</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>4</month><year>2022</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>28</day><month>06</month><year>2022</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2022-06-30 15:16:48.030"><day>30</day><month>06</month><year>2022</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2022 Jiang, Jiang, Liu, Zheng and Li.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Jiang, Jiang, Liu, Zheng and Li</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="fvets-09-906973.pdf"/><abstract><p><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> is a gram-negative bacterium that is distributed widely throughout the world; it is mainly found in contaminated food, the poultry industry, and animal feces. The emergence of antibiotic-resistant <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> poses a threat to human and animal health, which has led to renewed interest in phage-based therapy. <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> biofilm control and prevention are of great importance. In this study, the isolated phages Flora and KM18 were found to belong to the family <italic toggle="yes">Myoviridae</italic>; the optimal preservation buffer was pH = 6~7, and the phage genome sizes were 168,909 (Flora) and 168,903 (KM18) bp. Phage Flora had a broader lytic spectrum than KM18. Phage Flora had a better antibiofilm effect than kanamycin sulfate in high-concentration <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> cultures. A combination of the phage Flora and kanamycin sulfate showed better antibiofilm effects than Flora or kanamycin sulfate alone in low-concentration <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> cultures. These characteristics can serve as a guideline for the selection of effective candidates for phage therapy, in this case antibiotic-resistant <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> control in the poultry industry.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></kwd><kwd>phage</kwd><kwd>host range</kwd><kwd>biofilm</kwd><kwd>antibiotic</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="10"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="39"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="6308"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> is a gram-negative bacterium that is distributed widely worldwide; it is mainly found in contaminated food, the poultry industry, and animal feces, and some strains cause intestinal disease (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Moreover, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> O157:H7 is an important human pathogen causing abdominal pain, hemorrhagic colitis, gastroenteritis, diarrhea, and potentially fatal hemolytic-uraemic syndrome (HUS), hemorrhagic colitis, and death (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). The overuse of vancomycin, methicillin, trimethoprim, and sulfamethoxazole has led to the generation of many antibiotic-resistant <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Furthermore, with the emergence of an increasing number of multidrug-resistant (MDR) bacteria, antibiotic substitutes are urgently needed (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p><p><italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> adhere and internalizes in epithelial cells. <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> persistence in cattle mammary glands causes mastitis and biofilms formation related to recurrence (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). In addition, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> biofilms are related to antibiotic resistance and cattle mastitis. Bacterial biofilms are multicellular communities of microorganisms that embed within a self-produced extracellular matrix attached to non-biological, biological, and highly hydrated extracellular matrices on surfaces (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). The extracellular polymeric substances in the matrix of biofilms act as a barrier, reducing the penetration of antimicrobial agents into the interior of the biofilms (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Biofilms are highly resistant to desiccation, antibiotics, acidic conditions, and heat (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Bacteria in biofilms are ~10&#8211;1,000 times less susceptible to antimicrobial agents than planktonic bacteria because the extracellular polymeric substances of the biofilm prevent contact with antimicrobial agents (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). This makes the complete elimination of biofilms in animal husbandry, the food industry, and the clinic nearly impossible (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>).</p><p>The abuse of antibiotics results in the problem of multiple resistant bacteria (MRB). In 2003, annually, 80,000 deaths were reported to be caused by the abuse of antibiotics in China (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Phages and their derivatives are ideal candidates for replacing or compensating for antibiotic problems in the future (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Phages have the ability to sterilize bacteria (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Phages appear to be a good alternative to antimicrobials and disinfectants for their ability to kill bacteria. Above all, phages only infect bacteria and are not harmful to humans, making them safe for application in the clinic and food products (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). A recent study found that phages have high efficiency in reducing and controlling bacterial biofilms on various surfaces, such as those produced by <italic toggle="yes">Pseudomanas aeruginosa, Salmonella, E. coli</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">Listeria monocytogenes</italic> (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p><p>Gram-negative phages first attach to the surface receptor lipopolysaccharide via phage tail fiber proteins before they begin to infect bacteria (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). The narrow lytic spectrum restricts the application of phages. In this study, we isolated and characterized two lytic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> phages, flora and KM18. This study aimed to characterize the gene characteristics of the tail fiber of two different lytic spectrum phages. In addition, prevention and control of E. coli biofilm contamination are of great importance. The authors aimed to provide direction and a theoretical basis for the development and modification of broad-spectrum phages.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Bacterial Strains and Growth Conditions</title><p><italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains were isolated from a hennery in Yunnan, China, and were used as host bacteria for phage isolation. The host strain and phage host range determination strains were grown aerobically on LB plates or in LB broth (Difco, Detroit, MI, USA) and incubated at 37&#176;C. Soft top agar containing 0.5% (w/w) agar in LB broth was used for phage plaque confirmation, and LB agar plates containing 1.8% (w/w) agar were used for bacterial growth. All <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains were stored at &#8722;80&#176;C (Difco, Detroit, MI, USA) in 20% (v/v) glycerol.</p></sec><sec><title>Phage Isolation and Purification</title><p><italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>-targeting phages were isolated from a hennery and a foul water sewer. The phage isolation method was modified as follows (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Briefly, 10 g of the hennery or foul water sewer sample was mixed with 30 ml of sterile normal saline (0.9% NaCl) buffered in a 50 ml sterile centrifuge tube and then shocked in an incubator at 180 rpm for 3 h at room temperature. Then, the samples were centrifuged at 4,500 &#215; g for 10 min and filtered with a 0.22 &#956;m filter membrane. A total of 15 ml of each filtered medium was added to 35 ml of LB broth containing 1% (v/v) of an <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> overnight culture and then incubated for 2 d. After that, the cultures were centrifuged at 7, 000 &#215; g for 10 min, and the supernatant was filtered with a 0.22 &#956;m filter membrane. The filtrate was diluted by 10-fold serial dilutions, mixed with 6 ml of molten LB soft agar containing 200 &#956;l <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (2 &#215; 10<sup>8</sup> cfu/ml), and immediately added to an LB plate. After overnight culture, plaque formation was observed. A single phage plaque was selected for phage purification, which was repeated three times.</p></sec><sec><title>pH, Thermotolerance, MOI, and Growth Curve of the Isolated Phage</title><p>The phage flora stock was diluted to 1 &#215; 10<sup>8</sup> pfu/ml with LB broth. Liquid buffer (0.99 ml) with pH values of 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, and 11 (50 mmol/L citrate buffer for pH 3, 4, and 5; 50 mmol/L phosphate buffer for pH 6, 7, and 8; 50 mmol/L Tris-HCl buffer for pH 9; 50 mmol/L sodium carbonate buffer for pH 10 and 11) was placed in a 2 ml sterile centrifuge tube, and 0.01 ml of diluted phage Flora with a titer of 1 &#215; 10<sup>6</sup> pfu/ml was added to each tube. The mixture was placed at room temperature for 1.5 h, and then the titer of phage Flora was assessed in different pH buffers. The experiments were repeated three times. Thermotolerance assessment was performed by placing 1.5 mL diluted phage Flora in temperature controllers at 4, 25, 37, 42, 50, 60, and 90&#176;C for 1.5 h, respectively. The multiplicity of infection (MOI) is the ratio of phages to host bacteria used for the initial infection. Phage Flora stocks were added to the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> culture at MOIs of 0.0001, 0.001, 0.01, 0.1 1, 10, and 100, followed by incubation at 37&#176;C for 10 h. The culture was centrifuged at 12, 000 &#215; g for 15 min at 4&#176;C, the supernatant was filtered with a 0.22 &#956;m filter, and the titers of the phage Flora solutions were determined through the double plate method. The experiment was repeated three times. For growth curve measurements, 1 &#215; 10<sup>8</sup> pfu/ml phage Flora was added to an LB culture containing 1/250 of an <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> seed culture based on the optimum MOI, and the culture was shaken at 37&#176;C. Intermittent sampling was performed to determine the titer of phage Flora.</p></sec><sec><title>Transmission Electron Microscopy</title><p>The morphology of the phage Flora particles was observed by transmission electron microscopy (TEM). Briefly, each phage stock dilution (~3 &#215; 10<sup>8</sup> to 3 &#215; 10<sup>9</sup> pfu/ml) was deposited on copper grids with carbon-coated Formvar films and stained with 2% uranyl acetate (pH 4.0). Phage Flora samples were imaged using a Philips EM 300 electron microscope operated at 80 kV at Ningbo University (Ningbo, China). Phage Flora was classified and identified according to the International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses.</p></sec><sec><title>Phage Genome DNA Extraction, Sequencing, and Bioinformatics Analysis</title><p>First, phage Flora was purified by concentrating on a high titer stock with a 10 kDa filter (~10<sup>9</sup> to 10<sup>10</sup> pfu/ml). Purified phage Flora was treated with DNase and RNase at 37&#176;C for 1.5 h. Then, a Takara Minibest Viral RNA/DNA Extraction Kit (Cat# 9766) was used to obtain purified phage Flora genomic DNA. The restriction endonucleases <italic toggle="yes">Eco</italic>rI, <italic toggle="yes">Not</italic> I, <italic toggle="yes">Hin</italic>d III, and <italic toggle="yes">Xho</italic>l I were used for phage Flora genome digestion. Extracted phage Flora genomic DNA was sequenced using an Illumina HiSeq (Sangon Biotech, China). The original sequencing data were evaluated by FastQC and assembled with SPAdes assembler software. The NCBI Blast comparison with multiple databases of COG, KOG, CDD, NR, NT, PFAM, SwissProt, and TrEMBL were used for functional annotation information of the gene protein sequences.</p></sec><sec><title>Phage Lytic Spectrum and Antimicrobial Susceptibility of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic></title><p>The host ranges of phages flora and KM18 were determined by the spot test method (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). The reference strains were tested for susceptibility to phages Flora and KM18. Generally, 250 &#956;l reference strains (10<sup>9</sup> cfu/ml) was added to 6 ml liquified LB soft agar (LB broth with 0.5% (w/w) agar) and poured over an LB 1.8% (w/w) agar plate. Four minutes later, single drops of the Flora and KM18 phage suspensions were added and incubated at 37 &#176;C for 24 h. The antibiotic susceptibility of the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains was tested against 17 antibiotics by the minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC) method. The antimicrobials tested were penicillin, streptomycin, kanamycin sulfate, cefoxitin, ampicillin, ceftriaxone, gentamicin, ertapenem, aztreonam, amoxicillin, ciprofloxacin, imipenem, levofloxacin, cefepime, macrodantin, and amikacin.</p></sec><sec><title>Structure and Molecular Diversity of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> Phage Tail Fibers</title><p>The amino acid sequences of the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> phages Flora and KM18 tail fibers were obtained by genomic sequencing. <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> phage tail fiber tertiary structure homology modeling was performed using the SWISS-MODEL online suite. Phage tail fiber gene specificity was studied with BioEdit software.</p></sec><sec><title>Assessment of the Effects of Phage Flora and Kanamycin Sulfate on Biofilm Formation</title><p>First, the phage preparations were made, and a 48-well-cell slide was placed into a 24-well-plate. The seed solution was inoculated into 100 ml of LB culture solution at a concentration of 4&#8240;. About 1 ml of bacterial solution was inoculated into a 24-well-plate. In one group, phage Flora, kanamycin sulfate, or mixtures of kanamycin sulfate and phage Flora were added, with no addition used as a control (the phage was added at an MOI = 0.1; the final concentration of kanamycin sulfate was 10 &#956;g/ml), followed by incubation (37 &#176;C, 24 h). In the other group, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> were cultured first for 12 h, after which phage Flora, kanamycin sulfate, or mixtures of kanamycin sulfate and phage Flora were added, with no addition used as a control (the phage Flora was added at a MOI = 0.1; the final concentration of kanamycin sulfate was 10 &#956;g/ml), followed by incubation (37&#176;C, 12 h). The cfu count of each sample was measured through the plate counting method. Next, the recovered culture was washed twice with PBS buffer and fixed with 2.5% pre-cooled glutaraldehyde at room temperature for 2 h in the dark. The samples were washed twice with PBS buffer and then dehydrated with an increasing ethyl alcohol gradient (15, 30, 40, 50, 70, 100% v/v) for 15 min for each step. Afterward, the samples were dried overnight and gilt and the results were obtained through scanning electron microscopy with an accelerating voltage of 20 kV. The <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> seed solution was inoculated in LB at a concentration of 4&#8240; for overnight culture. Then, a 200 times dilution with LB was performed in the 96-well-plate (200 &#956;l/well), and each sample had three replicate wells. For one group, phage Flora, kanamycin sulfate, or mixtures of kanamycin sulfate and phage Flora were added, with no addition used as a control (the phage Flora was added at an MOI = 0.1; the final concentration of kanamycin sulfate was 10 &#956;g/ml), followed by incubation (37 &#176;C, 24 h). In the other group, <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> was first cultured for 12 h, after which phage Flora, kanamycin sulfate, or mixtures of kanamycin sulfate and phage Flora were added, with no addition used as a control (the phage Flora was added at an MOI = 0.1; the final concentration of kanamycin sulfate was 10 &#956;g/ml), followed by incubation (37&#176;C, 12 h). The <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> population density (OD<sub>600</sub>) was measured using an ELISA (Thermo Scientific, EUA), and the bacterial solution was discarded. Each well was washed twice with PBS to remove unattached <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, which was repeated three times. Then, 99% methanol was added, and the cells were fixed for 10 min. Then, the methanol was discarded, and the well was dried at room temperature, followed by the addition of 2% crystal violet for 10 min. The culture plate was rinsed with running water until the water was colorless. After drying, the absorbance was measured at a wavelength of 570 nm with a microplate reader. The experiment was repeated three times.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Characteristics and Morphology of the Isolated Phages</title><p>Virulent <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> phage Flora and KM18 were isolated from a hennery and a foul water sewer in Yunnan, China. The plaques of phages Flora and KM18 appeared 6&#8211;8 and 5&#8211;7 mm in diameter, respectively, after overnight incubation at 37&#176;C (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Negative staining of purified <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> phages Flora and KM18 was observed using an electron microscope. TEM revealed the phages Flora and KM18 virions to have an icosahedral head of 60 &#177; 2 nm in diameter and a contractile tail of 150 &#177; 5 nm in length (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). The morphology of phages Flora and KM18 indicated that they belong to the family <italic toggle="yes">Myoviridae</italic>. A one-step growth curve of the phages KM18 and Flora was obtained by inoculation of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> at an MOI of 1 at 37 &#176;C (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). The latent period for the phages KM18 and Flora was 55 min. The titers of phages KM18 and Flora reached peaks very quickly in 20 h and appeared to decrease after 20 h. The burst size of phages KM18 and Flora was ~2000.</p><fig position="float" id="F1" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Plaques formed by <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> phages KM18 and Flora; the host strain was <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> BL21 incubated overnight at 37&#176;C. The scale was 1 cm.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-906973-g0001.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Morphological features of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> phages KM18 and Flora as demonstrated by transmission electron microscopy (TEM).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-906973-g0002.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Population dynamics of phages KM18 and Flora incubated with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> BL21.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-906973-g0003.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Optimum Temperature, pH, and MOI of the Isolated Phages</title><p>Phages KM18 and Flora had the highest viability after treatment for 1 h at 37&#176;C, with a noticeable decline at 60 &#176;C and complete inactivation at 90 &#176;C (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). The results showed that phages KM18 and Flora were viable at low temperatures, which is consistent with the optimum survival temperature of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>. Phages KM18 and Flora showed the most plaques at pH = 7; furthermore, phages KM18 and Flora had a high activity at pH = 11 and pH = 3 (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). These results indicated that phages KM18 and Flora have good tolerance to alkali and acids. MOI refers to the ratio of the number of phages to bacterial cells. The optimum MOI of phages KM18 and Flora was 0.0001; among the MOIs tested, plaques of Flora and KM18 decreased significantly starting at MOI = 0.0001 and reaching a minimum at MOI = 100 (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F4" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Optimum temperature, pH, and MOI of the isolated phages KM18 and Flora.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-906973-g0004.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Characterization and Analysis of the Phage Genomes</title><p>The complete genome sizes of phages Flora and KM18 were 161,903 and 161,909 bp, respectively. We identified 263 protein-coding genes [open reading frames (ORFs)] in Flora. Genome analysis revealed that phages Flora and KM18 are virulent phages (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>). The complete genomic sequences of phage Flora and KM18 were deposited into the NCBI GenBank database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore</ext-link>) (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MT787017">MT787017</ext-link> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmc:entrez-nucleotide" xlink:href="MT787018">MT787018</ext-link>).</p><fig position="float" id="F5" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Line map of the phage Flora genome. In the Flora map, genes colored red represent lysozymes, genes colored purple represent endonucleases, and genes colored yellow represent tail structure genes. The arrows represent the ORFs and indicate the direction of transcription.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-906973-g0005.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Phage Lytic Spectrum and Antibiotic Resistance of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic></title><p><italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains were isolated from a hennery in Yunnan, China. Unfortunately, they showed a broad spectrum of resistance (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), but fortunately, some of them could be removed by phages Flora and KM18 (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). All the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains possessed resistance to penicillin, streptomycin, kanamycin sulfate, ertapenem, amoxicillin, imipenem, cefepime, macrodantin, and amikacin but were susceptible to ampicillin and ceftriaxone. Lytic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> phage Flora was able to infect 4/10 <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains that were isolated from the hennery in Yunnan, China (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). This analysis demonstrated the wide host range of the isolated phage Flora.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Antibiotic resistance of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> isolates used in this study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="12" rowspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">
<bold>Escherichia coli</bold>
</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antibiotic</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">J</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DH5&#945;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BL21</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Penicillin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Streptomycin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">kanamycin sulfate</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefoxitin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ampicillin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gentamicin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aztreonam</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ciprofloxacin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Levofloxacin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Macrodantin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amikacin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefepime</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Imipenem</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amoxicillin</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ertapenem</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ceftriaxone</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">S, susceptible; R, resistant</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Host range analysis of phages KM18 and Flora.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Strain</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>KM18</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Flora</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>-A</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>-B</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>-</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>-C</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>-</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>-</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>-D</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>-</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>-</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>-E</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>-</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>-F</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>-</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>-G</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>-</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>-</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>-H</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>-</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>-</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>-I</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>-</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>-</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>-J</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>-</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic>-DH5&#945;</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>-</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli-</italic>BL21</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>+</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic toggle="yes">clear lysis zone <bold>(+)</bold>, no lysis zone <bold>(&#8722;)</bold></italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Structure and Molecular Diversity of the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> Phage Tail Fibers</title><p>Tail fiber adsorption to bacteria is the first step in phage infection. The <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> phage tail fiber sequences and sizes have significantly different numbers of amino acids and homologies. Genome sequencing revealed that Flora has 10 different tail fiber genes of 8711-9262, 9290-12370, 12374-13044, 14234-18100, 67787-68278, 68395-70374, 72725-73543, 76778-78361, 92957-93487, and 94262-94504 bp in its genome. The identity and homology of the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> phage tail fiber genes were analyzed through BioEdit software. Amino acid differences between Flora and KM18 were located at positions 33 (Q-H), 60 (L-I), 61 (A-P), 220 (A-S), 289 (H-Q), 439 (K-I), and 457 (S-L) of 76,778-78,361 bp in the genome. Compared with the KM18 genome, the Flora Gly amino acid deletion was located at position 322 of 14,234-18,100 bp in the genome (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>). The <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> phage tail fiber tertiary structure was predicted by SWISS-MODEL (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://swissmodel.expasy.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://swissmodel.expasy.org/</ext-link>). The tail fiber tertiary structures were highly similar between Flora and KM18 and had the same modeling template (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://swissmodel.expasy.org/templates/5iv5.15.A" ext-link-type="uri">https://swissmodel.expasy.org/templates/5iv5.15.A</ext-link>). Compared with KM18 tail fiber homologous modeling, Flora has special &#946;-strands (<xref rid="F7" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F6" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Location of mutated bases and amino acids in the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> phage tail fiber proteins of the Flora and KM18 genomes. There are eight base mutations in the whole genome tail fiber; these positions are 322(-/G) of the fourth tail fiber and 33(G/A), 60(A/G), 61(A/G), 220(A/G), 289(A/G), 439(A/G), and 457(A/G) of the eighth tail fiber.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-906973-g0006.jpg"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F7" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Predicted tertiary structure of the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> phage eighth tail fiber protein. Compared with the KM18 eighth tail fiber, Flora has special &#946; strands in the eighth tail fiber.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-906973-g0007.jpg"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Comparison of the Effects of Phage Flora and Kanamycin Sulfate on Host Biofilm Formation</title><p>SEM was used to assess <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> biofilm formation on round coverslips treated with phage Flora (MOI = 0.1) and kanamycin sulfate (10 &#956;g/ml). After <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> inoculation at a concentration of 4&#8240;, phage Flora (MOI = 0.1) and kanamycin sulfate (10 &#956;g/ml) were added immediately and cultured for 24 h. Kanamycin sulfate showed a better eradication effect than phage Flora according to the results of the microplate reader OD<sub>570</sub> of the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> biofilm, the scanning electron micrograph, and the OD<sub>600</sub> of the bacterial culture solution (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figures 8</xref>&#8211;<bold>10</bold>). Nevertheless, when <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> was inoculated at a concentration of 4&#8240; and cultured for 12 h, followed by the addition of phage Flora (MOI = 0.1) and kanamycin sulfate (10 &#956;g/ml) and culturing for 12 h, phage Flora showed a better eradication effect than kanamycin sulfate according to the results of the microplate reader OD<sub>570</sub> of the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> biofilm, the scanning electron micrograph and the OD<sub>600</sub> of the bacterial culture solution (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figures 8</xref>&#8211;<bold>10</bold>). In addition, when <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> was inoculated at a concentration of 4&#8240; and cultured for 12 h, followed by phage Flora (MOI = 0.1) and kanamycin sulfate (10 &#956;g/ml) addition and culturing for 12 h, the combination of phage Flora and kanamycin sulfate showed a better eradication effect than phage Flora or kanamycin sulfate alone according to the results of the microplate reader OD<sub>570</sub> of the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> biofilm, the scanning electron micrograph and the OD<sub>600</sub> of the bacterial culture solution (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figures 8</xref>&#8211;<bold>10</bold>). The results of the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> colony-forming units indicated that the combination of phage Flora and kanamycin sulfate showed a better eradication effect than phage Flora or kanamycin sulfate alone (<bold>Figure 10</bold>).</p><fig position="float" id="F8" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Scanning electron micrographs (SEM) of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> colonization before and after phage Flora (MOI = 1) and kanamycin sulfate (10 &#956;g/ml) application to the biofilms formed on round coverslips. <bold>(A)</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> was inoculated at a concentration of 4&#8240; and cultured for 24 h, followed by <bold>(B)</bold> addition of phage Flora (MOI = 1) or <bold>(C)</bold> addition of kanamycin sulfate (10 &#956;g/ml). <bold>(D)</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> was inoculated at a concentration of 4&#8240; and cultured for 12 h, after which phage Flora (MOI=1) was added and cultured for 12 h. <bold>(E)</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> was inoculated at a concentration of 4&#8240; and cultured for 12 h, after which kanamycin sulfate (10 &#956;g/ml) was added and cultured for 12 h. <bold>(F)</bold>
<italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> was inoculated at a concentration of 4&#8240; and cultured for 12 h, after which phage Flora (MOI = 1) and kanamycin sulfate (10 &#956;g/ml) was added and cultured for 12 h (5, 000&#215; magnification).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-906973-g0008.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains used in this study were isolated from a hennery in Yunnan, China; unfortunately, they were resistant to penicillin, streptomycin, kanamycin sulfate, ertapenem, amoxicillin, imipenem, cefepime, macrodantin, and amikacin. The emergence of MDR strains urgently requires new measures to inhibit pathogens. With the overuse of antibiotics, multi-drug-resistant bacteria and superbacteria have led to public health problems (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). The isolated <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> phage Flora was identified as an ideal substitute for antibiotics due to its strong lytic activity and wide lytic spectrum. Moreover, phage Flora showed a better eradication effect than kanamycin sulfate in a high-concentration culture, and the combination of phage Flora and kanamycin sulfate showed a better eradication effect than phage Flora or kanamycin sulfate alone in a low-concentration culture (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figures 8</xref>&#8211;<bold>10</bold>) (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>).</p><p>The isolated <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> phages Flora and KM18 belong to the family <italic toggle="yes">Myoviridae</italic>, and the genome sizes were 168,909 and 168,903 bp, respectively. In comparison, the <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> phage phiLLS genome size is 107,263 bp, and the genome sizes of phage vB_EcoM-Ro111lw, vB_EcoS-Ro145lw, and vB_EcoM-Ro157lw are between 42 kb and 149 kb; moreover, they all belong to the family <italic toggle="yes">Myoviridae</italic> (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Washizaki et al. constructed a phage T4 mutant strain Arl and identified that the amino acid changes at V941E, A955E, and G943S in the DT region of the phage tail fiber played an important role in the interaction with lipopolysaccharide, indicating that the terminal head domain of T4 tail fiber was interacting with lipopolysaccharide (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). The genome characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> phages Flora and KM18 revealed that Flora encodes a special endonuclease and a more unique exonuclease. The extra endonuclease and exonuclease in Flora may be the reason why it has a wider lytic spectrum. Another reason for the wider lytic spectrum of Flora could be its greater resistance than KM18 to restriction enzymes.</p><p>The ability to form biofilms on different food surfaces increases the risk of microorganism cross-contamination, particularly in poultry products, which is a serious problem for food industries, clinics, and public health (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). However, the significant problem of pathogen biofilm elimination is still challenging (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Until now, there has been no ideal technology for biofilm control; hence, new control strategies for biofilms are constantly recommended (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). In this study, we demonstrated that phage Flora has better properties than antibiotics for reducing the biofilm formation of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figures 8</xref>, <xref rid="F9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F9" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Effects of phages and kanamycin sulfate (10 &#956;g/ml) on biofilms. <bold>(A,B)</bold> Effects of phage Flora and kanamycin sulfate (10 &#956;g/ml) on <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (inoculated at a concentration of 4&#8240;) growth after 12 and 24 h of culture (OD<sub>600</sub>). <bold>(E,F)</bold> Effects of phage Flora and kanamycin sulfate (10 &#956;g/ml) on <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (inoculated at a concentration of 4&#8240;) biofilms cultured for 12 and 24 h (OD<sub>570</sub>). <bold>(C,D)</bold> Effects of phage Flora and kanamycin sulfate (10 &#956;g/ml) on <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (inoculated at a concentration of 4&#8240;) growth after first being cultured for 12 h, followed by phage Flora and kanamycin sulfate (10 &#956;g/ml) addition and culturing for 12 and 24 h (OD<sub>600</sub>). <bold>(G,H)</bold> Effects of phage Flora and kanamycin sulfate (10 &#956;g/ml) on <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (inoculated at a concentration of 4&#8240;) biofilms after first being cultured for 12 h, followed by phage Flora and kanamycin sulfate (10 &#956;g/ml) addition and culturing for 12 and 24 h (OD<sub>570</sub>). *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-906973-g0009.jpg"/></fig><p>The results showed that phage Flora and kanamycin sulfate have the ability to reduce <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> biofilms. Kanamycin sulfate showed a better antibiofilm effect than phage Flora in low-concentration <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> cultures (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figures 8</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>). Nonetheless, phage Flora showed a better antibiofilm effect than kanamycin sulfate in high-concentration <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> cultures (<xref rid="F8" ref-type="fig">Figures 8</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="F10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>). The data of this study provide strong evidence that the application of phage Flora could reduce the growth of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> biofilms, which is important for maintaining public health.</p><fig position="float" id="F10" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Effects of phage and kanamycin sulfate (10 &#956;g/ml) on <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> colony-forming units. <bold>(A)</bold> Effects of phage Flora and kanamycin sulfate (10 &#956;g/ml) on <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (inoculated at a concentration of 4&#8240;) cultured for 24 h. <bold>(B)</bold> Effects of phage Flora and kanamycin sulfate (10 &#956;g/ml) on <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> (inoculated at rate of 4&#8240;) after first being cultured for 12 h, followed by phage Flora and kanamycin sulfate (10 &#956;g/ml) addition and culturing for 12 h. ***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="fvets-09-906973-g0010.jpg"/></fig><p>In conclusion, we first isolated and characterized lytic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> phages and found that the combination of phage and antibiotics shows significantly better antibiofilm and bactericidal properties than either antibiotics or phages alone. The data of this study provide strong evidence that phage application could reduce <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> biofilm growth, which is important for maintaining public health.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s5"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/supplementary material, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>CL and RZ conceived and designed the experiments. LJ performed the experiments, analyzed the data, and wrote the paper. WL, YJ, and LJ contributed reagents, materials, and analysis tools. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="s7"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the General project of Education Department of Zhejiang Province (Y202043742), the Research Fund Program of Guangdong Provincial Key Lab of Pathogenic Biology and Epidemiology for Aquatic Economic Animals (No. PBEA2020ZD01), the Natural Science Foundation of Ningbo (2021J118 and 2021J113), the National Natural Science Foundation of China (82160403), and the K.C. Wong Magna Fund at Ningbo University.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s8"><title>Publisher's Note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shimamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Isolation and molecular characterization of <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enterica, Escherichia coli</italic> O157:H7 and <italic toggle="yes">Shigella spp</italic>. from meat and dairy products in Egypt</article-title>. <source>Int J Food Microbiol</source>. (<year>2014</year>) 168&#8211;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2013.10.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24239976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Croxen</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Finlay</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Molecular mechanisms of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> pathogenicity</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>26</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>38</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro2265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19966814</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Balcomb</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagaraja</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Evidence of non-O157 Shiga toxin-producing <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> in the feces of meat goats at a U. S slaughter plant</article-title>. <source>J Food Prot.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>76</volume>:<fpage>1626</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-13-064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23992509</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abnavi</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alradaan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Munther</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kothapalli</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Modeling of free chlorine consumption and <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> O157:H7 cross-contamination during fresh-cut produce wash cycles</article-title>. <source>J Food Sci.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>84</volume>:<fpage>2736</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1750-3841.14774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31573690</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karmali</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Petric</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sporadic cases of haemolytic-uraemic syndrome associated with faecal cytotoxin and cytotoxin-producing <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia col</italic>i in stools</article-title>. <source>Lancet.</source> (<year>1983</year>) <volume>1</volume>:<fpage>619</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(83)91795-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6131302</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verstraete</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Denys</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Minnebruggen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hertel&#233;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>De Waele</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Determination of CTOD resistance curves in side-grooved single-edge notched tensile specimens using fullfeld deformation measurements</article-title>. <source>Eng Fract Mech.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>110</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.engfracmech.2013.07.015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kemper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Outbreak of hemolytic uremic syndrome caused by <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>. coli O104:H4 in Germany: a pediatric perspective</article-title>. <source>Pediat Nephrol.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00467-011-2067-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22160440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamasaki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Watahiki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isobe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kurazono</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Quantitative detection of Shiga toxins directly from stool specimens of patients associated with an outbreak of enterohemorrhagic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> in Japan-quantitative Shiga toxin detection from stool during EHEC outbreak</article-title>. <source>Toxins</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>4381</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/toxins7104381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26516915</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4626740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tarr</surname><given-names>PI</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> O157:H7: clinical, diagnostic, and epidemiological aspects of human infection</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis.</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/clinids/20.1.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7727633</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ansari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nepal</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gautam</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shrestha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Neopane</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gurung</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Community acquired multi- drug resistant clinical isolates of Escherichia coli in a tertiary care center of Nepal</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Resist Infect Control</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>15</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13756-015-0059-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25937923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4416386</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Branda</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Biofilms: the matrix revisited</article-title>. <source>Trends Microbiol.</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>20</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2004.11.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15639628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Flemming</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wingender</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The biofilm matrix</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol.</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>623</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro2415</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20676145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall-Stoodley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costerton</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoodley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bacterial biofilms: from the natural environment to infectious diseases</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>108</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15040259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Donlan</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Costerton</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Biofilms: survival mechanisms of clinically relevant microorganisms</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>167</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.15.2.167-193.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11932229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC118068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effect of biofilm on the survival of <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolated from raw milk in high temperature and drying environment</article-title>. <source>Food Res Int.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>149</volume>:<fpage>110672</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2021.110672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34600674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Understanding biofilm resistance to antibacterial agents</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Drug Discov</source>. (<year>2003</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>114</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrd1008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12563302</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luppens</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reij</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Heijden</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rombouts</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Abee</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Development of a standard test to assess the resistance of <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> biofilm cells to disinfectants</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>4194</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>200</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.68.9.4194-4200.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12200265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC124130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bacillus cereus hazard and control in industrial dairy processing environment</article-title>. <source>Food Control.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>20</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2016.04.012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jaiswal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sodhi</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Antibiotics bioremediation: perspectives on its ecotoxicity and resistance</article-title>. <source>Environ Int.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>124</volume>:<fpage>448</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2018.12.065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30684803</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Local food systems food safety concerns</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Spectr.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>10</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/microbiolspec.PFS-0020-2017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29651980</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11633565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Endersen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Mahony</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McAuliffe</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Phage therapy in the food industry</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Food Sci Technol.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>327</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>49</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-food-030713-092415</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24422588</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Paik SY Ryu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Isolation and genome characterization of the virulent <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic> bacteriophage SA97</article-title>. <source>Viruses.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>5225</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v7102870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26437428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4632378</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Bacteriophages and its applications: an overview</article-title>. <source>Folia Microbiol.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>62</volume>:<fpage>17</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12223-016-0471-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27718043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCallin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alam Sarker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barretto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sultana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huq</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Safety analysis of a Russian phage cocktail: from metagenomic analysis to oral application in healthy human subjects</article-title>. <source>Virology.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>443</volume>:<fpage>187</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virol.2013.05.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23755967</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Biswas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">In vitro</italic> assessment of the susceptibility of planktonic and attached cells of foodborne pathogens to bacteriophage p22-mediated salmonella lysates</article-title>. <source>J Food Prot.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>76</volume>:<fpage>2057</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>62</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4315/0362-028X.JFP-13-183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24290682</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Magri</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Philippi</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vinner&#229;s</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Inactivation of pathogens in feces by desiccation and urea treatment for application in urine-diverting dry toilets</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>79</volume>:<fpage>2156</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.03920-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23335764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3623211</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Ornellas Dutka Garcia</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Oliveira Corr&#234;a</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>LQ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Souza Ribeiro Mioni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>de Moraes Izidoro</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Bacteriophage use to control Salmonella biofilm on surfaces present in chicken slaughterhouses</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>3392</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pex124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28595324</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Application of bacteriophages to reduce <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> attachment and biofilms on hard surfaces</article-title>. <source>Poult Sci.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>96</volume>:<fpage>1838</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>48</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3382/ps/pew463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28339743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Veesler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cambillau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A common evolutionary origin for tailed-bacteriophage functional modules and bacterial machineries</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>75</volume>:<fpage>423</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MMBR.00014-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21885679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3165541</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization and comparative genomic analysis of a novel bacteriophage, SFP10, simultaneously inhibiting both <italic toggle="yes">Salmonella enteric</italic>a and <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> O157:H7</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>78</volume>:<fpage>58</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>69</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.06231-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22020516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3255626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chopin</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chopin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Definition of bacteriophage groups according to their lytic action on mesophilic lactic streptococci</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol.</source> (<year>1976</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>741</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aem.32.6.741-746.1976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16345180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC170454</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amarillas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rub&#237;-Rangel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaidez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#225;lez-Robles</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lightbourn-Rojas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le&#243;n-F&#233;lix</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Isolation and characterization of phiLLS, a novel phage with potential biocontrol agent against multidrug-resistant <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1355</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.01355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28785246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5519627</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Am&#233;zquita-L&#243;pez</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qui&#241;ones</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soto-Beltr&#225;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yambao</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lugo-Melchor</surname><given-names>OY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial resistance profiles of Shiga toxin-producing <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> O157 and non-O157 recovered from domestic farm animals in rural communities in Northwestern Mexico</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Resist Infect Control.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13756-015-0100-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26734130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4700648</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Washizaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yonesaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Otsuka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterization of the interactions between <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> receptors, LPS and OmpC, and bacteriophage T4 long tail fibers</article-title>. <source>Microbiologyopen.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1003</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mbo3.384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27273222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5221442</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>AI-Shabib</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Husain</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Rutin inhibits mono and multi-species biofilm formation by foodborne drug resistant <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title>. <source>Food Control</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>79</volume>:<fpage>325</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodcont.2017.03.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hashem</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parveen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title><italic toggle="yes">Salmonella</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter</italic>: antimicrobial resistance and bacteriophage control in poultry</article-title>. <source>Food Microbiol</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>104</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fm.2015.09.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26678136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lianou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nychas</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koutsoumanis</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Strain variability in biofilm formation: a food safety and quality perspective</article-title>. <source>Food Res Int.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>137</volume>:<fpage>109424</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodres.2020.109424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33233106</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>M&#248;retr&#248;</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hermansen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holck</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sidhu</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langsrud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Biofilm formation and the presence of the intercellular adhesion locus ica among staphylococci from food and food processing environments</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol.</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>5648</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.69.9.5648-5655.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12957956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC194930</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunawan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>We are one: multispecies metabolism of a biofilm consortium and their treatment strategies</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>635432</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2021.635432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33584635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7876221</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article></pmc-articleset>